<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rdf:RDF
 xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
 xmlns="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/"
 xmlns:taxo="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/taxonomy/"
 xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:syn="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
 xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
>

<channel rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/">
<title>Allakhazam.com News (full)</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/</link>
<description>allakhazam gaming news rss feed</description>
<items>
 <rdf:Seq>
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12758" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12754" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12753" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12751" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12748" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12747" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12746" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12745" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12743" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12742" />
 </rdf:Seq>
</items>
</channel>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12758">
<title>The Mog House [Final Fantasy XI]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12758</link>
<description>Howdy! This is a pleasant reminder to you all that tomorrow we will not be having another saucy episode of &quot;The Mog House&quot; since it&#39;s Easter Sunday (hope you all are having a good one!)&lt;br />&lt;br />This doesn&#39;t mean you still can&#39;t download our podcasts! Feel free to download them at your leisure! &lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;a href="http://www.onlinegamingradio.com/podcasts/podcasts-the-mog-house" target="_blank">Click here to go to our podcast download page!&lt;/a></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12754">
<title>The Springy Grab Bag [Dark Age of Camelot]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12754</link>
<description>Time for Joanne&#39;s weekly &lt;a href="http://www.camelotherald.com/more/3488.shtml" target="_blank">grab bag&lt;/a> of info:&lt;br />&lt;blockquote>&lt;strong>Q. I have a question regarding the celerity tincture that can be imbued onto crafted armor.&lt;br />&lt;br />Is it possible to recharge the item once you have used up all the original charges? When I delve my crafted item (circlet) it now reads 0 of 7 charges remaining. When I go to a Recharger and give him/her the item I get a pop-up saying that it will cost 0g to recharge, then a message saying that the Recharger cannot recharge the item. How can I recharge my item?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />&lt;br />A. After pondering in deep thought for a moment, the Lady of the Jewels responds: &lt;em>If it is a crafted item, and therefore has a player-made charge applied to it, only an Alchemist can recharge it for you. It does not have to be the same Alchemist thankfully. The NPC Rechargers are only able to recharge items that did not have their charge imbued by a player Alchemist.&lt;/em>&lt;br />&lt;/blockquote>&lt;a name="pause" title="pause">&lt;/a>&lt;blockquote>&lt;strong>Q. I have never seen my Heretic&#39;s increasing damage spells ever crit.&#160; Is it possible for it to crit and if it isn&#39;t then why does the class get Wild Power?&lt;br />&lt;/strong>&lt;br />A. The Balancinator went to the testing dungeon to verify: &lt;em>The Heretic increasing damage spells can achieve critical hits. The class starts out with a 0% chance of a critical hit. The only way to achieve critical hits is to buy the realm ability &#8220;Wild Power&#8221; and it will take you above the 0% chance to do critical damage. &lt;/em>&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;strong>Q. Is there a set amount of damage that the Dissonance Trap does when it detonates? If so, what is the damage value?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />&lt;br />A. Diving straight into facts and figures, the Balancinator says: &lt;em>The Dissonance Trap does 40% of the target&#39;s total health in damage. It is not a true 40% because it is affected by resists.&lt;br />&lt;/em>&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;strong>Q. I recently killed Dorawm about 10 times on my Bondedancer. He didn&#8217;t drop any loot. Is this a bug?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />&lt;br />A. Fresh from the open seas of Atlantis our Lady of the Jewels answers: &lt;em>All Master Level and artifact encounter monsters will now only drop their normal loot again if someone in the group killing them needs credit for the encounter. If no one in the group needs credit, they will drop nothing of significance. This does not include Celestius.&lt;br />&lt;br />New encounters have been added which will drop random loot taken from the Master Level and artifact encounters. As well, players can turn in essences that drop from these encounters for a roll on a specific master level or artifact encounter loot table.&lt;/em>&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;strong>&lt;br />Q. I have discussed this with many people whether or not there is a &quot;hidden&quot; weapon skill for the Berserker, Blademaster and Mercenary associated with their dual wield lines. Is there a different weapon skill value for the main weapon spec that is shown in game vs. a dual wield weapon skill?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />&lt;br />A. The Balancinator also known as the time traveler reports: &lt;em>The easiest way to answer this question is by going back in time. From a Grab Bag in 2007:&lt;br />&lt;br />What does weaponskill have to do with damage?&lt;br />&lt;br />Weaponskill is a tricky beast. Technically, it has nothing to do with damage, as the displayed value of weaponskill on your character sheet is not actually used in any calculations. It does, however, use a lot of the same factors that are used to determine damage. So in most cases, a higher weaponskill will mean you&#39;re doing more damage.&lt;br />&lt;br />Why doesn&#39;t your weapon skill increase with dual wielding skills?&lt;br />&lt;br />You&#39;re using two weapon types that have two different weapon skills. Only one can be displayed on the paper doll, and that one happens to be the base weapon type for what you have equipped in your main hand. Your weaponskill is actually increasing; you just don&#8217;t see it reflected in the number displayed on your paper doll.&lt;/em>&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;strong>Q. Does a caster&#39;s spec in the line affect the effectiveness of debuff spells in a base spec line? For example will a Sorcerer with 1 matter spec have variance on the baseline dexterity debuff while a sorcerer with 50 Matter spec would not?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />&lt;br />A. Specializing in his specialization, The Balancinator explains: &lt;em>The debuff does not have a variance like damage spells do. The debuff gains in effectiveness as you gain power in that specialization line.&lt;/em>&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;strong>Q. My question is about Tyr&#39;s Fury. The proc on this style seems to be resisted way too often. After doing a small test of 100 swings, about 30% of them were out right resisted. At the moment, I get less resist rates out of Thyrm&#39;s Strength and Raider which are levels 8 and 25 respectively. In my opinion, a level 50 style should not be resisted more often than these lower level styles. Is this supposed to happen?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />&lt;br />A. I asked the Balancinator to open the book of Thanes: &lt;em>I looked at all of the Thane direct damage styles for discrepancies. The direct damage effects on the styles are all the same level spell just varying damages. The resist percentage of the direct damage effects should all be the same. While the 100 swings using Tyr&#39;s Fury may not alleviate the probability of random deviation. I would be interested in the results of the 100 swings with the other two styles. If you have the log of the tests still, we would be more than happy to look them over. &lt;/em>&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;strong>ANNOUNCEMENTS&lt;/strong>&lt;br />&lt;br />The house repossession countdown has begun. Some house lots could become available as soon as Monday evening, so if you are thinking of renewing your subscription, do not wait until the last minute. For those of you who want to see which house lots might become available, head on over to housing and click on houses which are marked as condemned to see how much time they have left.&lt;br />&lt;br />This week we announced our new Mauler and Valkyrie Team Leads. We still have a couple of Team Lead Positions to fill, including those for Gaheris (PvE), Wizard, Valewalker and Bonedancer. If you think you have what it takes, &lt;a href="http://www.camelotherald.com/teamleads/tl_available.php" target="_blank">Apply Today&lt;/a>!&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;a href="http://www.camelotherald.com/more/3487.shtml" target="_blank">Load It Up!&lt;/a> Today we announced an exciting and absolutely fun contest called Load It Up, where we want you to submit your ideas for new loading screen tips/hints/myths or anything you come up with. We&#39;ve already received a couple of entries and they are keeping us smiling over here! Be creative, helpful and funny.&lt;br />&lt;br />It&#39;s the first weekend of spring and it sure is windy out here in Northern Virginia. I think it is the perfect time to head to the frontiers and see what&#39;s sieging. Stay safe all.&lt;br />&lt;/blockquote></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12753">
<title>Load It Up Contest! [Dark Age of Camelot]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12753</link>
<description>Ooo, a fun new contest is underway over on the Herald, &lt;a href="http://www.camelotherald.com/more/3487.shtml" target="_blank">check it out&lt;/a> and enter!&lt;br />&lt;blockquote>Have you ever been zoning your character to a new area and wished that you could write one of the tips/hints that you see? Enter our Load It Up contest and you will have a chance at having your very words immortalized on the loading screen between zones! Sound fun? Here are the details:&lt;br />&lt;br />Load It Up Contest Rules&lt;br />&lt;br />Send us your best loading screen tips/hints/funny sayings and your entry might be seen in game in the near future! Be helpful, funny or just crazy!&lt;br />&lt;br />&#160;&#160;&#160; * All submissions must have a PG rating. Please keep it clean.&lt;br />&#160;&#160;&#160; * Enter as many times as you wish.&lt;br />&#160;&#160;&#160; * All entries must be received no later then March 31st at midnight eastern time to qualify.&lt;br />&#160;&#160;&#160; * All entries must be 100 characters or less (this includes spaces).&lt;br />&#160;&#160;&#160; * All winners must have an active Dark Age of Camelot account.&lt;br />&#160;&#160;&#160; * Entries must be Dark Age of Camelot related.&lt;br />&lt;/blockquote>&lt;a name="pause" title="pause">&lt;/a>&lt;blockquote>Prizes:&lt;br />&lt;br />All winning entries (The number of winning entries will depend on how many winning entries are sent in, so send in as many as you can for more chances to win!) will be added to the loading screen shortly after they have been announced.&lt;br />&lt;br />All winning entries will be announced here on the Herald.&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;br />How To Enter:&lt;br />&lt;br />All entries must include the following:&lt;br />&#160;- Your name.&lt;br />&#160;- Your character name/server.&lt;br />&#160;- Loading Screen tip/hints that you have come up with. &lt;br />&lt;br />Once you have your loading screen tip/hint created, send it in an e-mail to: daoc-contests@mythic.ea.com&lt;br />&lt;br />All entries must be received no later then Midnight EST on March 31st.&#160; There is no time to spare, so Submit your entry today!&lt;br />&lt;br />Please note: All contest entries will become property of EA Mythic.&lt;br />&lt;/blockquote></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12751">
<title>Shard of Hate on Test! [EverQuest II]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12751</link>
<description>The long-anticipated zone Shard of Hate is on Test!  Akil &quot;Lyndro&quot; Hoooper, Lead Designer, has &lt;a href="http://forums.station.sony.com/eq2/posts/list.m?start=0&amp;topic_id=412231" target="_blank">requested your feedback:&lt;/a>&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;blockquote>&lt;span class="postbody">Shard of Hate is up and ready for testing.  The entrances are in Neriak and in Nektulos.  Please put any feedback on the encounters and items here.  Thanks and have fun!&lt;/span>&lt;br />&lt;/blockquote>&lt;span class="postbody">&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;/span></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12748">
<title>Why, Yes.  I Do Have a Death Wish. [EverQuest II]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12748</link>
<description>It&#39;s late in the day, I know. But I present your Friday (and maybe weekend reading just in case you need something to read while coming down off the Easter candy sugar high) reading. &lt;br /> &lt;br />I&#39;ve decided that it&#39;s time to run a little experiment. &lt;br /> &lt;br />Sides, who doesn&#39;t wanna &lt;a rel="external" href="http://eq2.allakhazam.com/db/guides.html?guide=1152" target="_blank" title="eq2.allakhazam.com/db/guides.html?guide=1152">see me die&lt;/a>?  ;)</description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12747">
<title>Bristlebane Day! [EverQuest II]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12747</link>
<description>&lt;a href="http://eq2.allakhazam.com/forum.html?forum=19;mid=1204768297222195163" target="_blank">As you may recall&lt;/a>, Bristlebane Day is slated for April 1.  But you can get your sneak peak now.  &lt;a href="http://forums.station.sony.com/eq2/posts/list.m?topic_id=412196" target="_blank">According to Gnobrin&lt;/a>, Bristlebane Day is on Test!&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;blockquote>&lt;span class="postbody">&lt;p>FYI to all! &lt;/p>&lt;ul>&lt;li>Jesters, thieves, bards and fans of mischief are invited to enjoy the festivities that surround Bristlebane Day! You never know what laughs and pranks are to be found, during this enjoyable time of year. Celebrators have been spotted in every home city!&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>&lt;p>&#160;&lt;/p>&lt;p>Have at &#39;em!&lt;/p>&lt;p>~Gnobrin!&lt;/p>&lt;/span>&lt;/blockquote></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12746">
<title>Celebrate Easter in All Outspark Games [Fiesta Online]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12746</link>
<description>&lt;p>Spring is finally here, and we&#8217;re excited to announce a bunch of Easter goodies in Fiesta, Secret of the Solstice and Bread &#8216;n Butter!&lt;/p>&lt;p align="left">&#160;&lt;/p>&lt;p>Check out a few of the great premium items now available in each of the games:&lt;/p>&lt;a name="pause" title="pause">&lt;/a>&lt;blockquote>&lt;div class="body">&lt;br />&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://www.outspark.com/forums/showthread.php?t=55771" target="_blank">&lt;img src="http://cdn2.outspark.com/blog/images/fiesta/events/2008/EasterDress_girl.jpg" border="0" width="62" height="150" align="right" />&lt;/a>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://www.outspark.com/fiesta" target="_blank">Fiesta&lt;/a> - Happy Easter Pack:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>&lt;blockquote>&lt;p>&lt;em>-Easter Sunday Outfit (gives +7% critical strike)&lt;br />-Mini Chick Pet (+7 to STR/DEX/END/INT/SPR)&lt;br />-Rabbit Ears (+5% critical strike)&lt;br />-A Rabbit House&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>&lt;p>Each time you purchase a Happy Easter Pack, you are entered in our contest to win an iPod Shuffle! &lt;a href="http://www.outspark.com/forums/showthread.php?t=55771" target="_blank">Click here&lt;/a> to learn more about Fiesta&#8217;s Easter update&lt;/p>&lt;p align="left">&#160;&lt;/p>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://solstice.outspark.com/" target="_blank">&lt;img src="http://cdn2.outspark.com/blog/images/solstice/events/2008/Easter_BunnySuit.jpg" border="0" width="83" height="153" align="right" />&lt;/a>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://solstice.outspark.com/" target="_blank">Secret of the Solstice&lt;/a> - Rabbit Costume and EXP Boosters&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>&lt;blockquote>&lt;p>&lt;em>-Rabbit Helmet (+75 HP, Shield 10, Weight 10)&lt;br />-Rabbit Suit (+100 HP, Shield 12, Weight 12)&lt;br />-Easter Set (30-day Rabbit Helmet, Rabbit Suit &amp; 100% EXP Boost Card)&lt;br />-50% and 100% EXP boosters for 7 and 30 days&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>&lt;p>GM Break is playing the Easter Bunny this holiday weekend and he will be roaming around the continent of Xen with his pet parrot. If you see the parrot and are wearing the Rabbit Suit, say &#8220;Happy Easter&#8221; to receive a special prize!&lt;/p>&lt;p align="left">&#160;&lt;/p>&lt;p>GM Break will also be at Tramis Mansion in Brynhilld on March 23 at 3pm PDT. Players with either Bunny Ears or a Rabbit Helmet will be warped to a special party area. Picture-taking, storytelling and games are all part of the celebration.&lt;/p>&lt;p align="left">&#160;&lt;/p>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://breadnbutter.outspark.com/" target="_blank">&lt;img src="http://cdn2.outspark.com/blog/images/bnb/events/2008/BenjiBunny.gif" border="0" width="100" height="100" align="right" />&lt;/a>&lt;a href="http://breadnbutter.outspark.com/" target="_blank">&lt;strong>Bread &#8216;n Butter&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>&lt;strong> - 15% Sale on All Premium Items!&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>&lt;blockquote>&lt;p>&lt;em>-Holiday Benji (Gives 100 bonus chocoballs each time you play the Rainin&#8217; Chocoballs game)&lt;br />-Sale lasts until March 26!&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>&lt;p align="left">&#160;&lt;/p>&lt;p>All of us from Outspark wish you a Happy Easter!&lt;/p>&lt;/div>&lt;/blockquote></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12745">
<title>Game Update 44 Preview! [EverQuest II]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12745</link>
<description>&lt;blockquote>&lt;span class="newsContent">The Shard of Hate has appeared, sending some of the inhabitants of Norrath into a blind fury! Fights are breaking out in some of the major cities due to the overspill of hate-energy, and you can choose to either help cleanse the hearts of those that are affected by assisting Priests of Love or you can choose to further deepen the hate by assisting the members of the group named &quot;&lt;em>The Dead&lt;/em>&quot;.&lt;/span>&lt;br />&lt;/blockquote>&lt;span class="newsContent">&lt;br />&lt;/span>&lt;div align="justify">&lt;a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive_content.vm?id=1619&amp;section=News&amp;locale=en_US" target="_blank">&lt;span class="newsContent">Read more at EQ2Players!&lt;/span>&lt;/a>&lt;br />&lt;/div></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12743">
<title>Fabled Planes of Power Lore, Part 7 [EverQuest]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12743</link>
<description>From &lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50861">EQLive&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>, Part 7 of the Fabled Planes of Power Lore series focuses on the Plane of Nightmares:&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;strong>The Plane of Nighmares&lt;/strong> &lt;br />&lt;br />The Plane of Nightmares is ruled over by Terris Thule, the Dream Scorcher. &lt;br />&lt;br />The western region of Terris-Thule&#39;s domain is a dense forest with many small clearings. A river dissects the forest above and the barrows below, eventually becoming a water fall that drops into a lake. To the northwest, there&#39;s a small cottage that lies in the disrepair. Behind the cottage, a modest graveyard services the mortal victors of this realm.&lt;a name="pause" title="pause">&lt;/a>&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;div style="text-align: center">&lt;img src="http://everquest.allakhazam.com/mediabox/2008-0321-pon1.jpg" border="2" hspace="5" vspace="5" width="600" height="375" />&lt;/div>&lt;br />Great gnarly trees with foul twisted visages formed in the patterns of the bark compose much of the dark woodlands. The trees are sentient, powerful, and malevolent beyond comprehension; they will often spring to life as mortal trespassers enter their domain. The entire forest, like the maddening nightmares sent by the plane&#39;s horrific mistress, is unpredictable and unquenchable in its hunger. Reports come to New Tanaan with regularity regarding the disappearance of the foolishly brave that travel to this realm. &lt;br />&lt;br />Terris-Thule&#39;s most treasured minions lurk in the southwest caverns, living a dual existence in both astral space and upon the primal world. These include terrifying goblins that infect the minds of all, for none are beyond Terris-Thule&#39;s reach. &lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;strong>Mujaki the Devourer&lt;/strong>&lt;br />Chronicled by Sage Unimvariea of the Gatecallers of Erudin &lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;a href="http://everquest.allakhazam.com/mediabox/2008-0321-pon2.jpg">&lt;img src="http://everquest.allakhazam.com/mediabox/2008-0321-pon2_tn.jpg" border="2" hspace="5" vspace="5" width="300" height="188" align="right" />&lt;/a>Mujaki was born the first child to the Erudite couple of Tevrai, a mage, and Etumara, a cleric. His father, Tevrai, had high hopes for a son to follow in his footsteps and become a powerful wielder of magic. However, Mujaki seemed to lack the spark for magical pursuits early on. Much to his father&#39;s chagrin, little Mujaki liked to play more and had a physical affinity for the world around him, not a magical one. &lt;br />&lt;br />The couple, Tevrai and Etumara, looked forward to bringing another child into the world, but met with little success. Whatever ailed Etumara after her first birth did not allow her to conceive again. This was a serious point of consternation for Tevrai who desired another heir who might carry on his magical research. It was a notable point of shame for Etumara. She found comfort in the church of Prexus, focusing on helping those she could when she could not please her husband. A rift grew between the couple and for several years they existed in a somewhat detached, distant relationship. &lt;br />&lt;br />All of this was lost on young Mujaki though he knew that for some reason he did not please his father and his mother was often less than happy. This weighed heavily on the young mind, planting seeds of gilt and inadequacy. As he grew in his childhood, Mujaki was often found at his mother&#39;s side in the church of Prexus and was a source of comfort and solace for her as she delighted in his advancement in the &quot;lesser&quot; arts, as his father would say. &lt;br />&lt;br />As Mujaki approached the age of seven, his parents rejoiced as Etumara was again with child. Tevrai was nearly obsessed with the possibility of a magically adept heir. Young Mujaki simply looked forward to the promise of another playmate. However, as the pregnancy progressed, it was clear that it would not be a smooth one. Etumara was not carrying the child well and complications developed late in the term. As fate would have it, Etumara would deliver to Tevrai a beautiful baby boy adept in magic, but at the cost of her own life. &lt;br />&lt;br />Tevrai&#39;s sorrow knew no bounds and his anguish turned to self blame for it was he who had so desired another child. It was only the responsibility of caring for his new son that saved Tevrai from destroying himself with profound sadness. The infant was named Etumer in memory of his mother. &lt;br />&lt;br />Mujaki was crushed nearly as much as Tevrai. However, with little love coming from his father, he found solace in the support of the clerics of Prexus and his mother&#39;s many friends there. Despite his best understanding of what happened, Mujaki could not help but blame his infant brother for taking his mother from him. &lt;br />&lt;br />As the years passed, Etumer would greatly please his father with his aptitude for the magical arts and further alienate Mujaki from the family. Despite this rift, Mujaki still looked to his father for acceptance and worked exceedingly hard to prove his worth to Tevrai. He would devote his life to the ways of Prexus and became a devout paladin of the Ocean Lord. &lt;br />&lt;br />As Mujaki entered into manhood, he became attracted to the young Lady Yuntair, a magician who had gained an early reputation of being exceedingly skilled in magic. &lt;br />&lt;br />At the same time that a relationship was developing between Yuntair and Mujaki, Etumer was discovering something wonderful, powerful and innately sinister -- the ways of necromancy. Initially introduced as something innocent and an outgrowth of his regular magical studies, Etumer was seduced by the power that necromancy offered. He could not hold these discoveries from his father. With a charming tongue, and milking his father&#39;s pride, Etumer drew his father to the study of necromancy also. &lt;br />&lt;br />Even when the principles of The Faceless, Cazic-Thule, were revealed by Etumer&#39;s dark friends, it was sufficiently clouded in righteous logical posturing to not sway the son or his overly ambitious father from delving deeper into the possibilities of this dark art. &lt;br />&lt;br />Heady with newfound power and possibilities, Etumer was introduced to Mujaki&#39;s acquaintance, the lovely Lady Yuntair. Smitten by her radiant beauty, Etumer began to pursue Yuntair, having little to no respect for his brother. Playing out the same seduction that he had with his father, Etumer swayed Yuntair by appealing to her thirst for knowledge. &lt;br />&lt;br />Mujaki was tormented by his position and languished in indecision. He was pulled by the iron grip of the principles of Prexus and pushed by his deep-seeded inadequacy enforced by the actions of his own family. At first he was plagued by dreams that tormented him with possibilities of what may happen should he not find a way to repair his failings in his father&#39;s eyes. &lt;br />&lt;br />By the time Mujaki moved to salvage his relationship with Yuntair, he was too late. Initially, he uncovered his brother&#39;s treachery by stumbling upon Etumer and Lady Yuntair in a very loving embrace and this was further compounded when he learned of his brother&#39;s involvement with necromancy. Dumbstruck, Mujaki could only flee the scene, battling with his feelings and duty-bound heart to reveal the necromancy to the Erudin authorities. Mujaki approached his father for guidance, only to be spurned with statements alluding to Etumer&#39;s superiority in ability, despite the deficit of his age. Tevrai reasoned that Etumer should rightfully win the Lady Yuntair over Mujaki. &lt;br />&lt;br />This, coupled with his father&#39;s casual dismissal of necromancy, crushed Mujaki&#39;s ego and caused him to further question himself for many days. Throughout this time, his sleep was wracked by the nightmares of Terris-Thule who delighted in twisting the knives of his situation deeper into his psyche. &lt;br />&lt;br />Finally, he chose to cast Prexus aside and seek his family&#39;s acceptance at the cost of his own principles. He returned to his father seeking the teachings of necromancy. He hoped if he could find favor with his father and use his new knowledge to impress Yuntair, she would fall in love with him. And his situation improved for some time. &lt;br />&lt;br />The reality of the situation he led himself into became all too apparent one night as he Mujaki discovered his father, brother and Lady Yuntair, along with several of Etumer&#39;s friends, practicing the most foul and evil necromantic experiments. Suddenly gripped with an overwhelming loathing for his father, a deep-rooted disdain for his brother for the loss of his mother and his beloved, Mujaki swept into action, drew his once-holy blade and bloodily killed them all. &lt;br />&lt;br />His mind wracked with what he had committed, Mujaki ran from his house into the streets of Erudin, his mind lost in a frenzy of emotion. As he ran, Mujaki fell headlong into a side ally, his own blade bloody with gore of his family goring his midsection. It took a long time for Mujaki&#39;s life force to ebb and as he succumbed to death, his thoughts were wracked by calamity and insanity. &lt;br />&lt;br />Mujaki&#39;s essence was trapped by The Dream Scorcher, Terris-Thule. She played upon Mujaki&#39;s feelings of inadequacy and his need for acceptance to bring this essence of terror to her own plane of Nightmares. Terris-Thule continues her manipulation of Mujaki even now; driving him to reap the essences of others he holds so much contempt for -- those like his father and brother.&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;br /></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12742">
<title>Exploring Middle-earth: Sarnur [Lord of the Rings Online]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=12742</link>
<description>The web team for the Lord of the Rings Online has published another of their Exploring Middle-earth articles. The focus of this installment is the abandoned delving, &quot;Sarnur&quot;: &lt;blockquote>In the long-abandoned delving named &lt;a href="http://www.lotro-europe.com/news.php?search=yes&amp;keyword=&amp;pagename=news&amp;type=news&amp;id=5867&amp;type=News&amp;pagename=gameinformation">Sarn&#250;r&lt;/a>, the Dourhand dwarves and their evil allies are mustering forces to begin a final assault upon the Longbeards of Thorin&#8217;s Hall and the Elves of Duillond. Adventurers may want to see if they can assist the Blue Stone Garrison in their goal to remove the threat from Sarn&#250;r.&lt;/blockquote>You can read the article &lt;a href="http://www.lotro.com/" target="_blank" title="Exploring Middle-earth: Scary">here&lt;/a>, or &lt;a href="http://www.lotro-europe.com/news.php?id=5868&amp;pagename=news&amp;type=news" target="_blank">here&lt;/a> from the European site.</description>
</item>

</rdf:RDF>

