<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/" />
<modified>2004-11-30T15:28:03Z</modified>
<tagline>Everquest news, editorials, and commentary.</tagline>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2</id>
<generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="3.01D">Movable Type</generator>
<copyright>Copyright (c) 2004, Loral</copyright>
<entry>
<title>Everquest 2 Review</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000041.html" />
<modified>2004-11-30T15:28:03Z</modified>
<issued>2004-11-20T16:14:46Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.41</id>
<created>2004-11-20T16:14:46Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today Mobhunter offers a double-sized article: a full review of the first two weeks of Everquest 2.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Note: I wrote this review for both Mobhunter and EQ2 Caster's Realm. For bonus points, find four pop culture references!</p>

<p>Since the days I began playing Everquest I heard about the development of Everquest 2. It took form over the years becoming less of a dream and more of a reality. I've bought games for the last twenty years now and I learned not to pay attention to previews. Ever since the days the glossy game mags touted Sewer Shark as a revolutionary step towards interactive entertainment, I learned to ignore the hype and pay attention to the game itself when released.</p>

<p>I felt different about Everquest 2 than most new games. I looked forward to its release, but I felt trepidation instead of giddy excitement. I still love Everquest. I still want to play it. I don't want my friends to leave; I don't want my guild to fall apart. SOE doesn't want players switching games either, they prefer to drag in a whole new pack of angry wizards, but that doesn't mean it won't happen. While I knew I would buy EQ2 and I was pretty sure I'd play it for a long while, part of me didn't WANT to like it. So it was with this trepidation that I opened up the beautifully packaged EQ2 box and installed the two DVDs filled with Norrath's new world.</p>

<p>For the past two weeks, young Pavlen, my half-elf rogue, reached level 15. What I've seen impresses me a lot. So today I write a review of Everquest 2 from the eyes of a long-time Everquest player.</p>

<p>Character generation alone shows the depth of this game. What impressed me most was how different two characters of the same race can look. The variations between two half-elves were as extreme as the difference between high elf, half elf, and wood elf. The wide range of hair styles, hair color, skin color, and even physical size helps create a truly unique character. The details of cheek hight, chin size, eye slant, and mouth width probably went too far; few people will see your big goofy Bruce Campbell chin as you race around the city, but more detail is always better. (That's two pop-culture references so far, Moorgard.)</p>

<p>While graphics in a game like Everquest get people to ooh and ahh at magazines, demonstrations, and videos, they matter little when compared to gameplay. Massive online games have to pay close attention to steady yet limitless progression, class desirability, class interdependence, social connectivity, and encounter variance. Graphics are important but people pay less and less attention to them the longer they play. But yes, the graphics are stunningly beautiful.</p>

<p>EQ2 includes graphic settings so advanced that EQ2 will push machines to their limits five years from now. I had to set my machine, which screams through Doom 3's most advanced settings, to performance-level to achieve a reliable framerate. This thread on <a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=tech_support&message.id=3265&amp;jump=true">setting graphic performances</a> has a lot of good advise. One thing that will drastically increase your framerate is to set "complex shader distance" to "-1", all the way to the left, in your "Performance" menu under display options. It removes the pretty bumps from things but will result in sometimes a 20 FPS increase. It appears, however, that Everquest 2 graphics will scale well into the future. As hardware gets better, so will EQ2's appearance.</p>

<p>The quest journal is the core of Everquest 2. As I grew from a young adventurer on the Isle of Refuge to the seasoned hunter of Antonican Gnolls, I constantly added new quests into my quest journal. I didn't push to progress in levels or equipment. I pushed to find quests and complete them.</p>

<p>The quests in Everquest 2 follow a very wide range of tasks including delivery, collection, slaughter, exploration, completing tradeskills, and mini-zone clearing. Quests arrive from anywhere. Poke a wooden boat on the beach and find a strange rune inside that leads to a whole new quest. Get a brass key from a rat and discover a quest to unlock a room full of dark elf spies. Buy books in the library to learn of long lost treasures.</p>

<p>Quests follow every path of the game; whether you want to explore, hunt, tradeskill, or travel around a city. Quests drive you to find new zones and new places. Each quest is a small story for you to follow. The game doesn't force you down any one path; you choose which of these quests you wish to pursue; but there is little reason to hunt without having a quest to drive you.</p>

<p>The low-level quests from level 5 to 7, especially the collection and delivery quests, help you learn the layout of the huge cities of Qeynos and Freeport. These delivery quests frustrate people at first but once finished, it is far easier to find one's way around.</p>

<p>Quests lead you through all forms of progression. I spend little time worrying about my equipment or level. Instead, I watch my quest journal. What quests can I accomplish fast? Which ones are too old? Are there quests that other people have? One great feature lets you peek into your group member's quest books. If they have a quest you don't, you can learn where this quest starts and get it yourself.</p>

<p>It's far too early to tell if this will continue throughout Everquest 2. Much of what I describe is also true for Everquest 1 at this level. I do not know if quests become far fewer and less rewarding at the higher levels, forcing us to go back to camping in one spot and grinding experience.</p>

<p>So far it appears that Everquest 2 embraced its title. We may very well quest forever.</p>

<p>Now lets talk a little about the cities. After taking Pavlen up to level 15, I rolled up a dark elf enchanter and took him through level 7 in Freeport. The vast difference in atmosphere between Freeport and Qeynos astounded me. While Qeynos feels like Minis Tirith or Camelot, Freeport feels like H.P Lovecraft's version of planet Gidi Prime in Dune. Huge red tendrils of power hold a vast tower floating above the torn city. What horrors lie in that tower? What power could lift such a thing? Freeport is vast and scary. I love it.</p>

<p><br />
EQ2's combat system is another big change from Everquest. Efficient combat requires a lot of interaction. Combinations of moves, a wide range of skills, and situational requirements require that a player constantly pay attention to the battle and press the right attack at the right time.</p>

<p>As a 15 rogue, nearly all of my damage comes from my variety of bending and twisting stabs and slashes. If I were to set on auto-attack and go get a pop-tart, my efficiency in group would drop to less than 10%. I have to pay attention.</p>

<p>Heroic opportunities, a mix of fighting-game style combinations and the most graphically advanced version of Simon Says, offer a collaborative dimension to combat. Some groups seem to ignore them completely, but when they work they're very exciting.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 based class dependence around archetypes. Each player decides on an archetype in two steps before picking a particular class. Each class has the basic abilities of the archetype. All scouts can improve run speed, track creatures, and hide in shadows. All priests can heal and resurrect. This breakout of four archetypes should help keep each class useful in any group. We cannot yet tell how this will work out at the higher levels, but it seems to work fine at the low.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 focuses on trying to give people more content at each level. Leveling too quickly robs the player of a lot of opportunities. Some players will always drive as high as they can go as far as they can go, like Icarus trying to reach the sun, but the best way to play this game is to enjoy it at your own pace and let leveling and gear come as they come.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 built in a lot of tools to improve social interaction. Players can invite other players into a group anywhere in a zone. Players can directly invite others from the "Looking for Group" tool. Players can target other players in a group and see their name highlighted across the zone no matter how far away. There are world-wide channels for new players, classes, and cities.</p>

<p>SOE streamlined the actions of getting into a group, finding your group, following your group, hunting in your group, and leaving your group. Every class, upon achieving citizenship in the citizenship quest, receives a daily gate to your home city helping players leave the game quickly when real life rears its ugly head and demands a sacrifice.</p>

<p>It is too early to poke big holes in a game this big but a couple of things stick out as potential problems. While raiding doesn't require more than 24 people, a limit that may radically change the forming of the dreaded uberguild, a level system for guilds promising a new path for content could alienate guilds of lower power or lower membership. This may not be a problem as long as it doesn't become the only form of progression available. EQ1 seemed to drive players into uberguilds once they reached a certain level. At the high levels joining a raiding guild became the only way to increase one's power. Still, a guild-based level system seems to stretch outside of simple social interaction and into the realm of cliques and elitism; something I detest in massive online games.</p>

<p>Everquest 2's biggest problem is time. I don't plan on quitting Everquest 1. I already filled my day with work, writing, the dreaded Tivo, and my nightly hunts in Everquest. I have yet to successfully play two massive online games at the same time. Whichever game I happen to be in, I feel like I'm missing something going on in the other.</p>

<p>Everquest 1's numbers certainly dropped in the last two weeks. However, I hear other guild leaders say that Halo 2, Half Life 2, Grand Theft Auto: San Andraes, and the holidays in general take more players away from EQ than World of Warcraft or Everquest 2. While it looks like EQ numbers dropped in the last couple of weeks, we won't know its real impact until the worlds settle and we see where everyone ends up. I wouldn't count anything as fact until early next year.</p>

<p>It is easy to look at the release of Everqust 2 as an earth-shaking event. We play in a community where the decisions of a sword or a bow bring hundreds of angry rangers to the doors of SOE. From some of the passion we read on the EQ forums and even on the comments on previous Mobhunter articles, it would seem we traveled far outside the realm of a simple game.</p>

<p>But Everquest and Everquest 2 are games. We buy them, we install them, we play them, and we talk about them. Sure, these aren't like any other games before them. No couple ever met and got married over Ratchet and Clank. Everquest 2 is one of the best games I have ever seen. If my dollar is my vote, I bought two copies of the game, one as a gift, and signed up for a year-long subscription including all of the web features. The total price was over $200 but I expect a high entertainment reward for my investment. Everquest 2 is an amazing game and I look forward to watching young Pavlen progress through this vast world.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
22 November 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>November News Roundup</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000040.html" />
<modified>2004-11-11T14:51:09Z</modified>
<issued>2004-11-11T14:44:53Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.40</id>
<created>2004-11-11T14:44:53Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we take a look at some community news including the release of EQ2, some code changes, Caster&apos;s Realms&apos;s new administrator, and a few other odds and ends from around the net.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Everquest 2 hit the shelves on Tuesday and the world didn't end.  Few people know exactly what will happen over the next six months but numbers in EQ will no doubt be low throughout the next few weeks.  For the raiding guilds that require 54 people all night every night, this might end up causing a bit of trouble but for the single-group pickup hunters, life shouldn't be so bad.  There will be less groups overall but each group still needs six members.  Spots that were once over camped may open up.  The great hoards of treasure falling out of the  lands of Kuua should distribute to fewer people, giving each one a greater chance for a nice item or rune of power.</p>

<p>Not all communication methods are up and running yet between EQ and EQ2 but cross-game tells and EQ2 channel joining from EQ1 works.  From within EQ you can send a tell to your EQ2 friend by typing "[tell eq2.antonia_bayle.pavlen hail" where antonia_bayle is the servername he or she is on and pavlen is his or her character name.  You can send a tell from EQ2 to Everquest by typing "/tell eq.quellious.loral hello".  I hoped that this would be a little easier.  With all of the various / ; [ ways to send tells it is easy to get confused.  One would think, with the various server names, that we wouldn't have to put the game title in front to send a tell.  "/tell antonia_bayle.pavlen" has enough information to tell the vast self-aware machine farm at SOE that I want to send a tell to EQ2.  "[tell eq2.antonia_bayle.pavlen" makes me feel like I'm writing my own email headers.</p>

<p>Moorgard announced that you can also send tells to Star Wars Galaxies characters using the same method: "/tell swg.servername.charname message".  I don't know anyone playing SWG so I couldn't test it out.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 players cannot yet subscribe to EQ1 channels but you can subscribe to EQ2 channels within EQ1 by typing "[join eq2.servername.channel" (there's that stupid bracket again).  Hopefully we'll see EQ1 channel subscribing from within EQ2 soon.</p>

<p>I plan to write a full review and comparison of Everquest 2 during a slow news week but I love it so far.  It won't drag me off of EQLive any time soon, but the quest system is very rewarding and I hope we see a system like it in EQLive sometime soon.</p>

<p>SOE released the details of the backflagging solution this week.  Some mobs, like those in Plane of Time, drop items that let previously unflagged players become flagged.  Some zones require a single-group quest once an unflagged player acquired a quest piece from a raid-level mob inside the zone they wish to enter.  Most zones will soon have an 85-15 rule, allowing 15% of a raid to enter a zone without needing a flag.  There will be a variety of other quests to backflag people for lower-tier Planes of Power zones.  Read the full <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=7049">backflagging report</a> from my summit friend, Emil.</p>

<p>This is a fine solution for backflagging.  It will not help unflagged groups get flags, however.  At this point in the game's life, I don't know that that matters.  Unflagged raiding organizations now have a wide range of unflagged raids to conquer.  Gates and Omens offer a lot of unflagged raid-level content with rewards higher than Plane of Time.  I still see many guilds or raiding groups banging their heads on the walls of Time and losing members in the process.  With the probable drop in members due to EQ2, Grand Theft Auto, Halo 2, WoW, and the holidays in general, an enterprising raid force would be wise to try new targets with greater rewards.  It is also a good time to open your doors a little bit and let some typical non-raiders into your raids.</p>

<p>Grumbuk, SOE's resident coder at the Fan Faire, wrote a <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=development&message.id=1987#M1987">lengthy report on some current collision changes</a>.  We can expect a few performance tweaks in areas that previously gave us a bit of trouble and getting out of that chilly water should finally come a bit easier.</p>

<p>A series of strange new spells, all available to level 20 priests and casters, hit the dark pages of Lucy on the 9th.  These spells, called "blessings" each correspond to one of the known gods.  When cast, these spells summon a strange unknown item.  If I had to guess, and it is probably wishful thinking on my part, I would say they could summon a single-charge, no-rent gate device usable by typical non-gaters.  If it isn't, well, it should be.</p>

<p><a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/">Caster's Realm</a>, one of the more popular EQ websites, underwent a change of command.  Baelish, the previous administrator, moved on to help SOE develop the Station Players website for EQ2.  My friend Gemdiver, the previous administrator of the wizard community forum, Graffe's, now maintains Caster's Realm and <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=6885">plans</a> to take it to all new levels.  He recruited a few community writers to write content for the site including your favorite cleric who started with a <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=6966">Raidleader's Guide to Raiding</a> posted late last week.  Now if I can just convince Gemdiver not to burn Plane of Knowledge to the ground, I could make real progress.</p>

<p>It's been a slow couple of weeks since the Fan Faire but in December we can expect a patch or two with some exciting changes.  In the mean time, help save the Dragorns from the plight of their Muramite overlords and get some fine armor in the process.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight <br />
11 November 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>October 2004 Fan Faire Report</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000039.html" />
<modified>2004-11-02T12:29:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-11-02T12:21:27Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.39</id>
<created>2004-11-02T12:21:27Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">We return from New Orleans full of strange visions and fine tales to tell.  Pull up a chair and listen to the stories of the future of Norrath.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>The following article was written for both Mobhunter and Caster's Realm.</p>

<p>I return from the Bayou, black notebook laden with facts, details, rumors and the philosophies from the silver temple of the west.  SOE put on a fine event, as entertaining as it was informative.  SOE developers and staff made themselves available throughout the three-night event, happy to discuss anything the fans could bring up.</p>

<p>If you care not to hear of the festivities, skip down right into the juicy morsels of goodness below.  If you have not been to a Fan Faire, however, it is quite a treat.  There's always a bit of nervousness going to such an event.  We all know each other in-game but to meet face to face can be a bit daunting.  Non stop contests, presentations, late-night gatherings, and panels filled out three days perfectly.  It wasn't uncommon to see three fellows walking down Burbon Street, hurricanes high, shouting "hail" at everyone they saw.  "Train to Zone" they'd shout as a pack of bikers drives by with grim looks on their bearded faces.</p>

<p>Your head swims with after-images as you fly back home.  Brenlo hurls sharp-edged boxes at the heads of players in the manifestation of his ultimate Community Relations dream.  Vannoth teaches players how to train zones ("OMGZ RUN") and Cyb3r barbarian females in Everquest 2 ("OMGZ YUO USED ME!").  The costumes, the contests, the dialog, the tales of adventure, the personalities; they all add up to a weekend packed with enough memories to last six months.  If you ever get a chance to go to a Fan Faire, take it.</p>

<p>Ok, now on to the juicy morsels of goodness.</p>

<p>A large amount of the Fan Faire focused on Everquest 2.  By now most people have heard of the November 8 release date.  SOE had planned on this date for some time; it was not a knee jerk reaction to the rumored simultaneous release date of World of Warcraft.  Who really believes those EBGames dates anyway? Shame on you.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 showed up everywhere.  A 24 hour Everquest 2 contest awarded an Alienware PC to the player with the highest level and experience.  Over 30 machines were open for Fan Faire attendees to play.  Every Fan Faire attendee earned an EQ2 beta account upon registration.  I will leave it to other reviewers to discuss the details of Everquest 2 but I will discuss a few interesting tidbits.</p>

<p>I finally met my predecessor, Moorgard.  During our discussion he mentioned that EQ2 went through a series of focus tests and usability tests for both new and veteran players.  I hope Everquest goes through such tests if it has not done so already.  Making the game easy to start and play is a key to bringing in new customers.</p>

<p>SOE demonstrated the new Station Players website for Everquest 2 players.  The website offers a wide range of excellent features including guild website tools, Magelo-like player profiles, web-based guild chat, and server community forums.  There's a lot to like and demonstrations are available on the EQ2 website.  SOE intends to implement these features for all SOE games including EQLive in the next six to eight months.</p>

<p>Now let us dig into EQLive news.</p>

<p>In the next patch or two, the task system will gain over one thousand new tasks including tasks up to level 70.  Tasks will include a variety of new actions such as foraging and fishing on top of the existing kill 10, collect 4, talk to an NPC, or visit a location.  SOE plans to balance many old tasks as well.  Kaikachi, the task developer, reinforced that he uses bug reports and feedback to balance tasks so make sure to /bug or /feedback them if you find a task that doesn't work.</p>

<p>Backflagging came up more than once this event and SOE appears to have a viable solution in the works.  SOE will extend the 85-15 flagging rule, the rule that allows 15% of a raid to enter a flagged zone without the flag, to Time and many Gates zones.  Raid mobs within flagged zones will drop one or two quest items that let unflagged members begin a quest to receive a permanent flag for that zone.  Flags achieved this way will not backflag characters for previous zones.  A Time flag quest, for example, will not award a Fire flag.</p>

<p>Rashere, the primary Alternate Ability developer, has a list of AAs to review.  He already wrote a spreadsheet of point cost reductions for Gates AAs.  A piece of code will soon let players receive AA refunds without losing AAs over 30 should they zone.  It will not let players store more than 30 new AAs, however.  Players who already purchased AAs at the higher cost will receive the difference; they will not get a full refund for abilities unless the ability itself changes.</p>

<p>During the "Maintain a Living World" panel a pompous jackass of a moderator brought up the Everquest's Economy. According to Lyndro, tributes helped take money out of the economy but targeted the wrong players.  High-end players hold most of the money in Norrath but rarely use tributes.  Items like horses only take money out of the economy once.  SOE designed systems like trade skills to take money out of the economy but SOE always considers new solutions.</p>

<p>SOE does not plan to add new LDON loot.  Like Kunark and Velious, SOE intends players who get through the content of LDON to travel onwards to expansions like Omens and Gates.  LDON is not intended to offer progression through the entire range of the game.  Now that Omens offers fine equipment to single-group hunters, I agree with their assessment.</p>

<p>SOE plans to continue changing hot-zones to get players traveling out to old world zones.  From time to time they may add Fabled-like items to old-world content like they did with the fifth anniversary.  These changes, on top of epic quests and tasks, help get new players to older world zones.</p>

<p>Rogue's Hour, the first in a series of four planned Everquest-based novels, hit the shelves a couple of weeks ago and Scott Ciencin signed books and discussed future publishing plans.  Each of the next three books will come out every three months including one by Elane Cunningham, the author of many fine Forgotten Realms books.  These books help add new depth to our world and I look forward to their continued release.</p>

<p>Class tuning came up many times and SOE has plans to address class issues.  SOE will release class descriptions, not full class definitions, which contain a lot of SOE internal statistics.  SOE community relations folk meet often with developers to help make sure the class issues get discussed and to make sure each class has a clear group role and is fun to play.</p>

<p>I spent a time far shorter than I would have liked speaking with Vahlar regarding lore and story progression.  I mentioned my desire to see the Muramites invading Norrath and she assured me that some big changes would hit Norrath in coming weeks.  SOE heard the player's cry for a more cohesive storyline, one built from original EQ lore and plans to improve this.  The return of Firiona Vie and the Lifeguide to the storyline begins this return to older lore.</p>

<p>SOE already began the design of a new EQLive expansion but details are scarce.  Lyndro stated clearly that expansions will follow the Kunark, Velious, and Omens trend for one single locked zone, not a series of progressive locked zones such as those we faced in Planes of Power and Gates of Discord.  SOE rebuilt much of Omens, far more than I expected, after the guild summit in June.  SOE hears what players ask for and they heard us very well with Omens.  I have high hopes and look forward to January's announcement.</p>

<p>The future looks bright.  We see many exciting changes on the way and every SOE employee I spoke to said many of the things I wanted to hear.  EQ2 presents a huge unknown variable but it is clear that no SOE employee on either team wants EQ players quitting one for the other.  I do not see EQ2 affecting EQLive's future in any way but for the better.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
2 November 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Loral&apos;s Evil Halloween Agenda</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000038.html" />
<modified>2004-10-21T12:01:41Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-21T11:59:15Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.38</id>
<created>2004-10-21T11:59:15Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Next week Loral travels to the strange lands of New Orleans.  He travels with a satchel full of this Evil Agenda in the hopes of helping to manipulate Everquest to his own evil lands of darkness and horror.  Read on...if you dare!</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Next week I travel to New Orleans and join in the fun at this year's EQ Fan Faire.  As I did with the guild summit in March, I write the direction I would like to see EQ travel.  This article describes five areas for SOE to focus on and improve in the future.</p>

<h2>Add and Improve Quests</h2>

<p>Quests should be the cornerstone of Everquest.  Currently, however, most progression comes from killing beasts and getting occasional rare drops.  Many different types of events could spawn from quests, whether they are group hunts, raids, tasks, tradeskills, or soloing.</p>

<p>Add and update quests.  Consider developing a new quest system similar to the task system.  Update the Ro armor quests with valuable pieces.  Add level 30 and 40 armor quests.  Add a mid-level epic quests.</p>

<p>Everquest should include fun, powerful, and progressive quests at all levels.  Quest completion should offer significant experience bonuses, character flags, equipment upgrades, augments, new spells, and new disciplines.</p>

<p>Build a new quest interface that uses the "find" trail, compass marking, and a log-book to keep track of quests players currently follow.</p>

<p>Quests should return to the center of the game, especially a game titled "Everquest".</p>

<h2>Improve Grouping Options</h2>

<p>Add a /groupinvite keyboard command to invite players from outside the zone into a group.  Add "invite player" to the LFG window so one can send invites across the game.  Allow players to invite another by pressing the "invite" box on the group window and typing in a name.</p>

<p>Improve the "Friends" window.  Add a notes field for each friend.  Add a way to track alternate characters of a single player.  Add a way to forward tells from one character to another.  Make the "Friends" window more like the guild tool so we can track friends online, view notes, send tells, and perhaps send messages to off line characters.</p>

<p>Add short-duration tasks for groups of two or more people working on a single task.  Use the task system of Omens to give groups a short-duration quest tracking down evil bosses or hunting packs of loosed werewolves.  Tie it in with an improved quest system so groups can get together, pick a quest, and accomplish it within 90 minutes for experience and progress towards new gear.</p>

<p>Find a way for high level and low level players to work together.  Both should be challenged and both should receive an appropriate reward.  With the large amount of both high level and low level players, if methods can be found for these groups to work together, far more groups will gather together, run off, and have fun.  Gandalf and Frodo both grouped together and Frodo was totally g1mp.</p>

<h2>Focus on 90 minute events.</h2>

<p>While many Everquest players play for long periods of time, many cannot.  Everquest should focus around 90 minute game sessions.  Players should be able to progress in levels, AAs, and equipment in 90 minute intervals.  Camping for extended periods of time should not be the only way to progress in equipment at higher levels.</p>

<p>LDON offers a 90 minute point-based loot system that lets players earn new gear in smaller play-sessions but longer periods of time.  Use systems like this one to let players with limited time earn new equipment in other areas of Norrath.</p>

<p>Not every area or encounter should focus on 90 minutes, but many of them should.  Everquest needs to fit in better with our busy lives.</p>

<h2>Improve Encounter Variety</h2>

<p>Add more variety to single-group encounters.  Use instanced expeditions to tailor scripted encounters around groups.  Find new challenges for players other than straight damage.  Consider a lich that has very few hitpoints but many spells of protection that must be defeated before damaging the lich.  Consider beasts that only cast spells instead of melee, but with devastating effects!  Keep it fun, not frustrating.  No more chain complete healing mobs or mobs that gate only to earn back 30% of their hitpoints.</p>

<p>Use the experience gained from building excellent raid encounters to build fun new single-group events.  I understand the Muramite Provinground trials include events like this.  Continue this great work and build it for players of all levels, not just the highest high-end players.</p>

<h2>Make the Game Easier for New Players</h2>

<p>Everquest is a very difficult game to learn for new players.  Systems like the tutorial help but further refinements could help new players learn how to play and become slobbering addicts posting general substance-free negativity on the ranger forum in a few short months.  Here are a few suggestions:</p>

<p>Add a newbie chat channel autojoined at character creation.  Make it very easy for players to learn how to chat.  Give them a message that tells them how to send information and what the chat is for.</p>

<p>Streamline the interface for skills, disciplines, AAs, and other hotbutton effects.  Create a single window with all possible effects that we can drag over to our hotboxes. Auto-learn skills or notify players of new possible skills when they become available.</p>

<p>Add in an alternative to corpse recovery.  Add an NPC that summons bodies to Shadowrest for a high level-based cost.  Make the bodies he summons unressable to account for the easier corpse recovery.  As an alternative, add it as a necromancer and shadowknight spell.</p>

<h2>In Conclusion...</h2>

<p>Flexibility is the strength of Everquest.  Every year our world changes and every year it gets better.  The requests above will help Everquest continue to grow into an enjoyable and ground-breaking game for both old and new players.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
21 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Warts Under the Emperor&apos;s Clothes</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000037.html" />
<modified>2004-10-20T00:04:43Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-18T16:32:45Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.37</id>
<created>2004-10-18T16:32:45Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">It is a month after the release of Omens of War and the world of Norrath changed forever.  While this expansion has many strengths, it also has a few weaknesses.  This week we peek underneath the beautiful and ornate exterior to examine a few of the expansion&apos;s weaknesses.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>A month passed since the release of Omens of War and there is much to love.  Excellent graphics, useful and fun zones, great hunting, and many new directions to progress all build one of the best expansions we've ever seen.</p>

<p>In previous articles we talked about the strengths of Omens.  This week we look at some of its problems in hope that SOE considers them for change in Omens itself or considers them in the design of future expansions.  Let us begin.</p>

<p>The Hollows, Sewers, and Catacombs expeditions in Omens include instanced content between levels 45 and 70 filled with experience mobs and the occasional rare beast holding a bag of shiny loot.</p>

<p>One thing lacking in these expeditions is any sort of plot, story, quest, or purpose aside from general hunting.  These dungeons could have included plots and story lines, boss mobs, point-based loot systems, or even Kael-like armor quests instead of simply being more experience content.  Add a quest, add a story or purpose, or add a new loot system and these dungeons become a lot more fun.  And please, no more rats, bats and spiders.</p>

<p>The Omens task system could be the future of quests in Everquest.  All of the tools are there to help players accomplish quests and travel across Norrath.  While the current quest options are limited, scripted encounters and continuing story lines could take players through exciting quests far different from what we're used to.  Add scripted and locked encounters, add an overarching story line, add more rewards than just cash and experience, and you will create a strong new quest system in Everquest for all levels.  Include quests for level 68 and above.  All players should have the option to perform tasks.</p>

<p>Omens brings a much improved spell system over Gates of Discord and Planes of Power.  The Muramite Rune system ensures players never receive duplicate spells.  Players may trade and sell level 66, 67, and 68 spell runes and already the obnoxious prices in the bazaar plummet.  I predict rune prices will hit the reasonable10k mark by the end of November.</p>

<p>While players can reach level 70 in dozens of areas, they must now travel to either Muramite Proving Grounds or Riftseekers, two very difficult zones for non-raid equipped players, and hope they get lucky on a drop and lucky again on a roll.</p>

<p>SOE can improve this in two ways.  Add in a quest that lets players receive their first rune at each level.  Make the quest more than just rare drops on rare mobs.  Remove the no-drop flag on 69 and 70 runes so players can sell these runes in the bazaar like the others.</p>

<p>When the whole focus-item quagmire hit a couple of months ago, we heard that Focus 5 items would be more available than the focus items we saw in Planes of Power.  While decent focus gear seems to drop regularly in Wall of Slaughter, the drops in Ruined City of Dranik and Muramite Provingrounds, both harder zones than the Wall of Slaughter, drop few items with focus or combat effects.  Add more focus and combat effects to equipment in Ruined City of Dranik, Muramite Provingground, and the Ruined City expeditions.</p>

<p>Now lets talk about a larger problem: Everquest's time requirements.</p>

<p>Lost Dungeons of Norrath changed the face of Everquest.  Instead of spending four to six hours at a time sitting in one place pulling the same mobs over and over, we now had adventures that forced us to crawl, gave us a goal to accomplish, and a time limit to accomplish it in.  It was not uncommon to get a group together, start an adventure, finish it, and camp out within a two-hour period.  The game went from camping the same spot for six hours to a game of fast and furious adventure.</p>

<p>With Omens  I hoped to see an improvement on this.  More quests, more adventure types, perhaps a new point based loot system that doesn't remind us of a cigarette vending machine ("Innoruuk curse it! My +40 hitpoint augment is stuck again!" *bang bang*).  Omens had the potential to combine our favorite overland hunting from expansions like Velious and Luclin with the powerful dungeon and loot system of Lost Dungeons.</p>

<p>Instead we took a step backwards.  We have expeditions but they are simply instanced hunting zones.  We sit, we pull mobs, we kill them, they respawn, and we repeat until we fall over into our own four hour old bowl of mulchy Coco Puffs.</p>

<p>In order to have any shot at new spells or gear in Omens, you have to hunt for at least four hours.  In that time you may see two to three named mobs and may have a 50% shot at winning something.  If you don't win, you are no closer to a new item or spell than you were when you started.  There is no loot or spell progression option other than random luck or spending cash in the bazaar.</p>

<p>More important than the loot system, however, is a sense of an urgent adventure, one that requires us to fight fast and hard towards a single goal.  These exist deeper in Omens with the Muramite Provinground trials, but few will see these Ikkinz level expeditions any time soon.</p>

<p>Omens is a great expansion with a lot of excellent content and features.  With a little more focus towards quests, events, and goals, and a 90 minute duration per adventure this expansion or future expansions will step outside the traditional Everquest four hour camp and into a more time-friendly and exciting game.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
18 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Myths of Class Balancing</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000036.html" />
<modified>2004-10-12T04:41:05Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-12T04:09:52Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.36</id>
<created>2004-10-12T04:09:52Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we get away from some of the controversy surrounding our beloved game and go into the green pastures of a topic we can all enjoy and agree upon.  I kid, of course.  Lets roll up our sleeves and dig into the myths of class balance.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>A couple of weeks ago I wrote about five meaningless terms of Everquest.  One of these, Class Balance, is so overused that it now defines just about any problem one has with one's class.  There is no such thing as class balance and if there were, we'd have no defined classes.  There are nuggets of truth within this chaotic topic, however, and once we know what to ask for we can learn how to ask for it.</p>

<p>While there is no class balance, there is class tuning. Many of us focus on a particular class and with the time we've put in, we know bits and pieces of our class that under-perform.</p>

<p>Every class has advantages and disadvantages when compared to other classes.  This should always be true.  Adventurers depend on each other and always should.  If we could all solo our way to 70 with greater efficiency than in a group, we would.  Dependency forces us to group to progress and grouping is what makes Everquest different than any other single-player role playing game.</p>

<p>There are four main archetypes that current Everquest classes fall into.  Powerful efficient groups require each of these four archetypes in order to battle at the best of their ability.  These archetypes include healers, crowd controllers, tanks, and damage dealers.  </p>

<p>Groups should not depend on any one of the sixteen classes.  At worst, they should only require one from each of the four archetypes in order to group well.  For the most part, this exists today.  A group can earn excellent experience and a shot at some nice loot without any dependency on one class.</p>

<p>Now it is possible to have an ideal group.  It is possible to have a perfect combination of classes that outperform a group of a different makeup.  Again, this will probably always be true and even after extensive class tuning, will end up being true in some other configuration. Even if some sort of widespread class evaluation took place, equipment, AAs, and the skills of the players will always create imbalance between two different groups.</p>

<p>Here is one of Loral's Key to Happiness:  Forget about the numbers.  Throw away your damage per second parser.  Ignore the experience per hour you hear people acquiring in Fire.  Enjoy your class and your skills and go where you desire to hunt.  Constantly worrying about the damage per second of your character and only hunting in the most profitable zones leads to boredom and anger.  </p>

<p>This Key to Happiness is superseded by Loral's First Rule of Happiness: Have Fun.  If you like delving into the numbers, go ahead.  If they lead you to believe your class is worthless and weak and you end up spending days arguing with monks on the class boards, best to leave them aside.</p>

<p>When I brought up the topic of class balance with my editor, we decided we'd take a look at rangers.  He plays a wizard and I play a cleric so we had to go to his wife, the only one we know personally who plays a ranger.  When we asked what her top five ranger issues were, this is what she came back with:</p>

<p>- Rangers aren't big enough.<br />
- The starting city is too hard.<br />
- Rangers are a mishmosh class.<br />
- After years of playing she is only level 24.<br />
- Rangers get no respect.</p>

<p>I bring these up to show how perception changes our focus.  You may think you're the voice of all rangers when you argue that the Epic 1.5 should be a bow, but you really only focus on high-level rangers capable of accomplishing the quest.  The more narrow your view, the fewer people you help.  While focus is fine, we should not lose sight of the bigger picture.</p>

<p>For the class correspondents I have one piece of advise.  Always consider the class at all levels.  Don't focus on only the highest level of the game.  Classes have problems throughout their life and problems between level 30 and 50 effect more players than those at 65 and above.</p>

<p>So how can we help SOE improve our classes?  First, consider what we ask for.  If it bleeds into another class consider what impact it may have on them.  If the impact is little, perhaps it is a reasonable request.  If it impacts a lot, best to think about it further.  The best chance for change is to focus on skills that do not dramatically effect the class.</p>

<p>Second, use your class correspondent.  Find out who they are and what their issues are.  They work with SOE directly to make sure top class issues are known.  If your change is really as important as you think it is, you shouldn't have a hard time convincing them about it.</p>

<p>Third, speak in detail.  Don't complain about your classes overall grouping benefit.  Pick the abilities that require improvement and focus on them.  When I read over the class requests on the EQLive forums, I see mixes of specific requests (Turn Undead needs to work better) with general ones (Clerics need a secondary role).  Guess which one I'd fix first?</p>

<p>Like every other topic we bring up with SOE, avoid constant negativity, avoid threats, avoid woe-is-me statements about how your class is dead.  No class is dead.  Every class is still well represented on every server.  Every class has use.  Every class has advantages over others.</p>

<p>Above all, we should keep the whole game in mind when we consider changes.  Vast ranges of players, classes, levels, and zones remind us that we have a huge world.  SOE should always consider focusing on big changes first and smaller changes second.  While SOE cannot ignore class changes, it is the large changes that improve the game the most.  I would sacrifice Turn Undead in a minute if it meant we would see a new corpse recovery option.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Interview with Scott Adams</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000035.html" />
<modified>2004-10-19T18:21:22Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-08T05:27:26Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.35</id>
<created>2004-10-08T05:27:26Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week it is my pleasure to interview Scott Adams.  Scott and Pasty Loral dicuss Scott&apos;s mark on the computer game world, Scott&apos;s Everquest career, and Scott&apos;s EQ Wishlist.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>This week I am honored to introduce Scott Adams.  Scott agreed to sit down with Mobhunter for a short interview.  Scott is a long-time Everquest player and a major icon in the computer gaming community.  Let us begin the questions:</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  For those who have yet to figure out the gnomish technology of "Google" could you please introduce yourself and your background?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I am credited with starting the Personal Computer Gaming industry in 1978 with the publication of Adventureland. I am also called the father of computer gaming. (Should be grandfather now, hehe) My company Adenture International was in business til aprox 1985 publishing primarily computer games for the micro computers of that era.</p>

<p>I had actually been writing computer games before this. I remember writing computer games at a radar station I worked at and using the radar monitors to play the games on. I later had a homebrew system my brother build from CPU bit slices that I wrote a simple arcade style shooter for. I had to entirely hand assemble and link it. Later I had a Sphere computer (kit computer) which I wrote an elaborate arcade tank war game complete with home made controllers. It won Sphere's first annual "What do I use my Sphere Computer for" contest. With the advent of "appliance" computers  (that is what we homebrewers called them back then) such as TRS-80 and Apple I saw my chance to write for a larger audience.</p>

<p>I understand I have inspired many of today's game designers and programmers. I still get allot of fan mail from the nice folks who tell me that my games were the reason they got into computers as a career. I am always happy to hear from folks like that and have made many new friends over the years because of it.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  How do you feel about the direction computer games took since you started the field?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I am actually very happy with modern day computer games. One of the reasons I started my writing computer games was there were none around to play. Now there is a wonderful surfeit of great games. I watch them evolve over the years from the simple single man generated effort to the small team built games to the industrial strength mega efforts of today.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  How long have you played EQ?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I started playing EQ in April 2001. I had heard about the game before when it launched but had the impression it was some sort of glorified chat room with folks pretending they were medieval people. Sort of like a Medieval reenactment world. Certainly nothing a real computer game player would ever be interested in.</p>

<p>Then a friend of mine told me he played and what it was really about. I decided to give a try and rolled up a halfling druid. I was instantly hooked.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong> What characters, classes, and levels do you play?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I have played almost all the classes and characters. My highest char is only 48 and is a druid. I have allot of 30-40 level characters as I would roll them up and play them to see how well they fit into my hydra.</p>

<p>You can see my current set and my others here:<br />
<a href="http://www.msadams.com/magelo.htm">http://www.msadams.com/magelo.htm</a></p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong> Could you explain your Hydra?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I play 5 chars at one time. I use 5 discreet computers to do this. My center machine I run my Paladin. On my left is my enchanter, to my right is my druid. These machines are all on the same desktop. On a rolling cart to my left is my Bard and another cart on my right has my cleric.</p>

<p>I have many in game macros setup to assist me. For example when I bring in a mob I hit the 5 key on my setups. This will then do the assist the puller and start whatever normal attack its. The cleric will do a celestial heal and the bard will auto follow the puller to get in place then assist and melee attack.</p>

<p>My bard uses a keyboard macro to allow him twist 3-4 songs at time, normally he is using amplify and a manna song.</p>

<p>I remapped the F1-F8 keys to be the spell gems, so I can instantly fire off spells as needed on any of my characters. My 1-0 keys are all mapped to the normal hotkeys. I have an emergency bail out on the 8 key on all my chars. The druid has a Crucible of Escape and this on the 8 key, the other casters all have gate on 8.</p>

<p>I also use a 4rd party utility called EQ Watcher www.eqwatcher.com which reads the log files out loud. I have my own custom scripts I have written for it so I can be kept informed at all times what is going on my other chars. This one utility more than anything else makes my hydra MX5 possible!</p>

<p>http://www.msadams.com/EQWatcher/</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  What other MMOGs do you play and what do you think of them?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong>  I have played all the major MOGS and many of the minors ones too. Dark Age of Camelot, Anarchy Online, Neocron, Eve, Underlight, A Tale in the Desert are some examples of the MOGs I have played. Right now the only two I am playing are EQ and City of Heroes.</p>

<p>CoH is a MOG lite. Basically a pure fighting game with nothing added to get in the way of the fast furious battles. I have currently been in CoH since its launch this April.</p>

<p>Of all the MOGs I play EQ is the only one that I keep coming back to, I usually play a MOG for 2 to 4 months then return to EQ.</p>

<p>I am also beta testing EQ2 and will be in that big time when it launches. I won't play a hydra there. I also do not play a hydra in CoH, the game is way to fast and furious to really allow it.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  What are some of the things you like about EQ?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> Big world and lots of utility spells. The co-operative aspect of the game where it is you and friends against a hostile environment. The abilities you get at higher levels to teleport around quickly. The excitement of the drops and not knowing what may turn up.</p>

<p>I love the bazaar system and all the updates they did recently to improve it. No other game has anything even close to this. A one stop shopping mall is SO much better than tiny shops scattered over the whole game world.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  What sorts of things would you like to see improved in the existing EQ world?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> Quests. You really have no way to know if a quest is doable or not, what the reward might be and if it is worth even trying, maybe times the reward is simply not even usable. I, like many others, use the 3rd party web sites to determine which quests are even worth bothering with. This really stinks.</p>

<p>Content for non raiders. I don't raid and don't want to, but I want to see interesting sites and fight interesting mobs.</p>

<p>In game email. Some way to communicate with EQ only friends. My other mogs have this feature and it makes a big difference.</p>

<p>Sidekicking. This feature in City of Heroes allows one to play their friends no matter their levels. You can either choose to raise some else level to you or decrease yours to theirs. This alone would make an incredible difference in EQ to allow folks to join up.</p>

<p>Improved graphics. The current Luclin era character models certainly need work as do most of the old world zones.</p>

<p>Group oriented task system. The OOW task system should be expanded to allow groups to get them together and all reap the rewards. This is then like an outdoor LDoN spread across Norrath. Would be great fun. Currently I do tasks with my hydra but not all members of the hydra can always get the same tasks.</p>

<p>The ability to do LFG across zones. CoH just put that in and its a phenomenal idea. This way folks can invite others no matter where they are currently looking for group!</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  Thank you for your time Scott!  You can read more about Scott Adams at <a href="http://www.msadams.com/">his website</a> and download some of <a href="http://www.msadams.com/downloads.htm">Scott's Grand Adventures</a>.</p>

<p>Interview conducted by Loral Ciriclight<br />
7 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Early October News</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000034.html" />
<modified>2004-10-06T03:50:36Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-04T05:17:32Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.34</id>
<created>2004-10-04T05:17:32Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we relax from the onslaught of Lorals editorials for a more traditional look at the news.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>This week we take a look at some of the news appearing throughout the Everquest community.</p>

<p>On Halloween SOE hosts the <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/fanfaire/index.jsp">New Orleans Fan Faire</a>.  SOE posted the  <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/fanfaire/event_schedule.jsp">schedule</a> for this year's Fan Faire last week.  Your favorite cleric (that's me in case you forgot) will be in attendance armed with an all new agenda to stuff into the pockets of anyone with an SOE badge.  Like the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000016.html">summit agenda</a>, I will post this agenda here a week or two before the Fan Faire.</p>

<p>This week SOE announced <a href="http://soeworlds.station.sony.com/">SOE Worlds</a> a print magazine devoted to Everquest, Everquest 2, Everquest Online Adventures, Star Wars Galaxies, and the rest of SOE's army of massive online games.  The magazine includes strategy articles, general reviews, fiction, and interviews.  I expected something like this to come out eventually; I'm surprised it took as long as it did.</p>

<p>The largest buzz and attention in the last couple of weeks appears to focus on Epic 1.5s.  Every class board, hundreds of discussions on the EQ Live forums, and most of the developer and community feedback follows the progression of these quests.  Epic raids pour into most chat channels and even the non-raiders seem to have epic fever.  Why people seem to be more interested in epics than levels, AAs, spells, or other gear seems beyond me.  It may be the most popular Omens feature for high-level players.</p>

<p>A bit of nastiness hit quite a few people last week.  People's Omens accounts shut off without warning and sent level 66+ players back to their level 65 self.  At first rumors spoke of credit transaction problems but reports came in from people who bought their copy in the store.  Sony jumped on it and posted <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=63626">this statement</a>.  I heard of nearly half a dozen people losing their level in this manner but all of them seemed to get it back without too much of a hassle.  This seems to be the only major bug in an otherwise smooth expansion release; certainly smoother than Gates of Discord which suffered from random linkdeaths for nearly a week.</p>

<p>A new <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=testing&message.id=4617">feature on test</a> has bards cheering.  Bards will soon have the ability to auto-twist songs using a new "/melody" command.  Typing "/melody 1 2 3" will play each of the three songs in sequence.  The change helps bards become more social creatures, giving them the time to chat with friends and watch Tivo until their friends shout "Heal Me, Dolt!".  Some bard purists complain that it removes one of the great tests of skills for bards but most bards agree that the loss of challenge is worth the reduction in repetitive motion stress.</p>

<p>66+ spell costs dropped from 140,000 plat on the first few days to 60,000 plat today on Quellious.  I expect to see them drop to 10k before they meet the balance of supply and demand.  This should probably happen in a month or two.  I still know little about the location of 69 and 70 spells.  The no-drop requirement worries me.  Instead of living the twilight of my levels where I choose, I will probably have to hunt in Muramite Provingrounds and Riftseeker's in order to receive 69 and 70 spells.</p>

<p>People continue to migrate in long lines to the Wall of Slaughter.  Though better experience and loot awaits discovery in Ruined City of Dranik and its two sets of instances, people prefer the easier hunting ground and higher drop-rate of the Wall.  I cannot blame them and it is better to have one zone like the Wall than none at all, but it will be nice to see people spread out a bit more into the other lands.  In the mean time, for great fun and high adventure, travel to the Ruined City of Dranik through the Bloodfields.  If you are truly a band of hearty adventurers, attempt the Sewers and Catacombs expeditions.</p>

<p>One thing that definitely appears to be missing are random rare drops on normal mobs.  Instead of spending hours camping the same two spawn areas in the Hollows, I'd prefer to have a low chance (1/100) of receiving a rune drop or a loot item off of a normal beast.  Perhaps they haven't been found and reported yet, but so far I have seen none.</p>

<p>Expect a new system for the loading screens between zones.  People in beta had problems with the original one looking too much like a system hanging forever so they put in the loading screen.  The loading screen, however, breaks the flow of the game too much.  Sony builds a new system as we speak.  Perhaps we will see it in the mid-October patch.</p>

<p>I look with narrowed eyes to find problems for the single-group hunter in Omens and I find few.  Spell drops seem reasonable.  I received a piece of loot in a single-group battle I could immediately use, something that hasn't happened to me in a long while.  High level players can reach high level loot without required raiding.  We have so many useful zones that some excellent hunting areas like the Ruined City of Draniks sit empty.  Most of the problems I find and report are little more than nitpicks.  Overall I still give Omens a big thumbs-up.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
4 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>After Omens</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000033.html" />
<modified>2004-10-06T03:51:32Z</modified>
<issued>2004-09-28T23:13:39Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.33</id>
<created>2004-09-28T23:13:39Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today we take a look at the chaotic news of the last couple of weeks and we take a harder look at the Omens of War expeditions.  If you look closely, you will see Loral flip flop again.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Every new expansion changes the face of Everquest.  Omens is no different.  I had a conversation with a guild leader today who said he had great trouble bringing his guild together to defeat raid targets in Planes of Power. Their guild focuses on reaching the Plane of Time but each day he finds it more and more difficult to gather his forces.  When I asked what they were doing instead, he said they hunted in Omens.  I see little surprise there.</p>

<p>There seem to be two attitudes towards Omens.  One all but ignores it and continues progression down the same path they followed two years ago.  People seek the same flags, people hunt in the same experience zones, people all but completely avoid the new worlds.</p>

<p>The other takes the opposite approach.  They seek to tear through all of the content in Omens as fast as possible.  They hunt in the most lucrative experience zones in the game until they reach level 70 twenty hours later.  They earn AAs and buy the best abilities as soon as they can.  The random drops of spells and equipment hold them back, so instead they switch to Epic 1.5s.  I remember being asked to help with all new epic raids within three days of entering the lands of Kuua.</p>

<p>A healthy balance exists between these two extremes.  The world of Norrath changed with the opening of the portals of Discord.  Powerful equipment becomes easier to acquire.  We find new levels, spells, AAs, quests, and zones.  We should seek out and learn more of these new paths.  We should enjoy our journeys and adventures without feeling like someone pokes a spear in our back.  The journey is more rewarding than the goal.</p>

<p>Most of the epic 1.5 quests have already been completed.  The puzzle solvers worked day and night to solve the quests and epic 1.5 spoilers now sit on almost every class forum.  I didn't receive my happy clicky stick until almost a year and a half after Kunark came out.  I am in no hurry now.  Instead, I'll pick short term goals and begin working on my quest when my own power and the power of my friends grows.</p>

<p>Spells in Omens so far prove difficult to obtain.  All spells except teleports come from dropped runes.  While the runes ensure that no class gets duplicate spells and all spell casting classes can use these runes, they drop perhaps half the time on rare mobs.  </p>

<p>There are two things I would have liked to have seen with spells in Omens.  I would like to see one spell given out at each level off of a vendor or a short quest.  A single spell at each level gives players a bit more motivation to level than just new aas.  I would also like to see a more progressive, less random, quest to receive new spells.</p>

<p>Again, I fall back to the point system in LDON.  It took 11 adventures to receive a new spell but I knew I made progress with each successful adventure.  I did not compete with my group to receive it; we all earned equal rewards for our adventures.  Instead of only dropping muramite runes off of random rare mobs, why not drop pieces of runes randomly off of every mob.  Collect 10 pieces, build yourself a rune.</p>

<p>Speaking of LDON, prepare for a flip flop.  Four months ago I asked SOE to add new LDON equipment to the  LDON vendors.  At the time it would help non-raiders access more Gates content and give high-level LDON adventurers a few more trinkets to seek.  I was told at the Summit that these items would be added.  Later I was told they would be added, but not until after Omens.</p>

<p>At this point in the game, most of the "after Omens" fixes are obsolete.  Like instancing the Plane of Time, new content overshadows the desire for such a large fix.  If we want higher end items than the LDON vendors, we can go to one of three instanced expeditions and earn better loot.  We can hunt named in the Wall of Slaughter and Ruins of Dranik.  Like the gear in Kunark, Velious, and Luclin, LDON gear becomes obsolete with age.  LDON equipment works well up to 65 but when one outgrows it, one should head head to Omens.</p>

<p>I could be a pain in the arse and demand that SOE follow through with new LDON loot.  I know many high-end raiders will still demand a Time instance even though instanced zones in Gates and Omens offer better loot without any guild-based competition.  Instead, SOE should focus their resources on the problems that matter most and the features that help the game grow further.</p>

<p>I'd rather see them work on new LDON-style adventures with new themes, new adventure types, new beasts, and new loot than rehash the loot on the adventures in which many people have already fought.  Even if they did put focus 5 items on LDON vendors, I'd probably stay over in Omens for awhile.</p>

<p>I would prefer SOE look at the expeditions in Omens and add more LDON-like features to them than rebuild LDON.  I would like to see an incremental quest for spells in addition to random drops.  I would like to see a in-game goal and a two-hour duration for each expedition.  I would like to see the removal of spawns so groups crawl from the beginning to the end.  I would like to see boss-mobs spawn after the party kills a number of normal beasts.</p>

<p>Expeditions have a lot more potential than instanced group hunting content.  Expeditions are controlled environments for the developers to build fun and interesting scripts.  They use some of these scripts for the Muramite Proving Grounds trials, but few will see those powerful events and far fewer will survive them.</p>

<p>I asked for new LDON items and better LDON adventures, but now I would rather focus on the future.  I would prefer to see Omens filling in the gaps left open with LDON.  Omens includes enough content to keep almost any player busy for a long time regardless of the amount of time they play or the style of play they enjoy.  A few changes to the expeditions would help bring the best parts of Lost Dungeons to new and more flexible expeditions.  After that, all we must fear are the sharp teeth of the Dragorns and the green gasses of the umbrella people.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
28 September 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Omens of War Review</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000032.html" />
<modified>2004-09-25T00:02:56Z</modified>
<issued>2004-09-21T04:38:56Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.32</id>
<created>2004-09-21T04:38:56Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">In this week&apos;s article we review the first week of Omens of War.  We take a look at zones, levels, aas, gear, graphics, and the extra features Omens of War has to offer.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Last week SOE released Everquest's eighth expansion in five years, Omens of War.  There is no way to fully review an expansion after only one week, so consider this the first of at least two reviews of the expansion.  In later weeks we will discuss whether the expansion filled in all of the gaps it intended to fill.  For now we focus on what we know so far.  Omens of War is a very strong expansion and well worth $30.</p>

<p>Omens includes a lot of new, useful, and fun zones to hunt in.  There are eight over-land zones starting at level 45 and quickly reaching into level 65 and 70.  There are three sets of instanced expeditions, the sewers, catacombs, and hollows.  One locked zone awaits the arrival of big fancy people, and a set of Justice-like instanced group and raid trials await the corpses of level 70s.</p>

<p>The zones in this expansion look great.  The wide open wastelands of the Wall of Slaughter stretch to the crushed walls of the Dragorn keeps. Ancient bridges cross the canyons of the Ruins of Dranik.  All of these zones resemble lands at war, with scorched earth and skies of smoke.</p>

<p>Unlike Planes of Power, the better hunting zones of Omens are unlocked.  The instanced expeditions guarentee that any player above 45 can find a place to earn good experience with little competition.</p>

<p>Omens has only one locked zone and none are expected to see it right away.  Already we see treasures coming from the furthest reaches of the Muramite Provingrounds (sic) and Riftseeker's Sanctum.  Flags prevented this sort of  gold rush in Planes of Power and Gates of Discord, but the advantages of unflagged zones outweigh the disadvantages.</p>

<p>It is no surprise that characters began reaching level 70 two days after release.  Characters have been at level 65 for a long time and not being at the top level seems unnatural.  Many seek to reach that top end not because they want it but because they feel they deserve to have it.</p>

<p>More troubling is where they go to get it.  Instead of joining five friends and exploring these new lands, fast-track hunters head to the Plane of Fire. Message threads string across the net with discussions of the Plane of Fire and the experience within.  Some report waiting in lines to kite at the tables, the single best place to earn experience in the game.  If ever a place needed to be modified to increase the risk vs reward, that is it.</p>

<p>The alternate advanced abilities in Omens appear far more useful than the ones we saw in Gates.  Most continue the progression of previous AAs such as critical damage increases, healing increases, and stat increases.  Some offer a lot of utility such as a ninth spell-gem and five more buff slots.  For 25 AA points, one can up their mana regeneration cap from 15 to 20.  Each class has a few unique and interesting abilities as well.</p>

<p>The shiny loot of Omens appears to fill in the power gap between level 65 single-group hunters and high-end professional raiders.  We now reached a point where a character can level from 1 to 70, gear up with bazaar, Ornate, and LDON loot, and then earn gear in the high-end of Omens without ever needing to raid to get better gear.  Raiding always offers greater rewards, as it should, but single-group progression now has a bridge deep into Gates of Discord and the high-end of Omens of War without requiring raiding.</p>

<p>The task system improved a lot since the early days of beta.  Tasks break up into a set of four sub-tasks involving exploration of places best left alone, shady meetings with Wayfarer agents, collecting four shiny things, and killing ten evildoers.  Tasks range from level 5 to level 65 with more tasks on the way in coming weeks.  Their difficulty varies but I completed two or three different ones by myself at level 65, not bad for a weak and pasty cleric.</p>

<p>The greatest improvement to the task system is the scaling reward.  While some classes solo much better than others, players earn rewards based on class.  Clerics, paladins, and warriors who generally have more trouble hunting alone receive a higher reward than necromancers, bards, and wizards who can complete tasks much faster.  The rewards of the task system make it useful without ruining the rewards of grouping.  Triggered beasts and events locked for the triggering player would add a lot of excitement to the tasks.  Perhaps that is a feature we will see later on.</p>

<p>The graphics in Omens are astounding.  Detailed carvings and erosion on walls look good enough to run a hand over.  Torchlight shines on the scaly skin of a Dragorn as it rushes down a hallway.  Red eyes shine bright from the six eyes of a Chimera.  Moonlight shines off of the water over the Abysmal Seas.  Breath frosts out of the mouths of the hunters of Halas.  Everquest's look improved much in the last five years and its visuals never cease to amaze me.</p>

<p>The lack of description and options for graphic performance makes these new graphics inconsistent from user to user.  A new "advanced" tab in display options offers shadows, reflective waters, pixel shader 1.0, pixel shader 2.0, vertex shaders, reflective waters, and a few other options.  It doesn't include Hardware TnL (don't ask me what it stands for) and Vsync, the option that tells the game not to run faster than your monitor can display. Vsync may be the most important feature to make Everquest look solid on faster machines and the only way to enable it is to put a "Vsync=1" variable under "Defaults" in one's eqclient.ini file.</p>

<p>Everquest needs a better interface for display settings with better auto-detection, a simple slider bar or check box for the features to enable.  Most important are descriptions of what each feature does and what types of systems should enable it.  Few people know what a pixel shader 2.0 is and no one should need to.</p>

<p>In the mean time, players must work hard to understand all of the available settings and figure out which they should use.</p>

<p>SOE released a lot of smaller features in Omens as well.  The voice macro system lets tanks shout "Heal me, dolt!" when my eyes stray over to my Tivo too much.  Guild tributes let officers donate junky gear so other members can have an extra point of mana regen.  Custom titles ensure you can pick the title you liked the best.  I always preferred Venerable to Exarch.</p>

<p>Omens is a great expansion.  Excellent unflagged and unrestricted zones, new levels and AAs, new shiny loot for both single-group hunters and raiders, top-notch graphics, and a lot of fun new features make Omens one of the best Everquest expansions.  It takes time to find all of the nooks and crannies in such a game, no one can write a complete review after only one week of play, but so far Omens is a lot of fun.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
20 September 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Meaningless Words of Everquest</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000031.html" />
<modified>2004-09-13T13:02:01Z</modified>
<issued>2004-09-13T12:49:57Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.31</id>
<created>2004-09-13T12:49:57Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we discuss five meaningless and overused terms in the Everquest community.  These five terms muddy the clear waters of communication and hide our true intent from the eyes of SOE.  Remove them from your communications, replace them with detail, and we can finally express our true desires.
</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Jargon plagues Everquest.  We find meaningless words or phrases everywhere. Everyone has an idea, everyone has a complaint, and everyone has something about the game they want to talk about.  Instead of finding ways to properly communicate what our problem is, we fall back to generalizations and buzzwords that may have meaning to us but lose that meaning the more they are used and misused.  These words don't help us communicate with SOE.  Instead of articulating a problem, they muddy the conversation and cloud the real problems.</p>

<p>Five terms in particular get used dozens of times each week on the various forums.  These words add nothing to our conversations and don't help SOE find and fix the problems we gloss over.  If we eliminate them from our vocabulary and speak in detail, we increase SOE's ability to respond.  Lets take a look at these meaningless words:</p>

<p>Uber:  The German word for Over describes high end characters, guilds, equipment, or abilities.  We hear about uberguilds and ubermobs.  We use the word as insult or praise when a friend acquires a new shiny item.  Uber is anything more powerful than you.  Some 65 paladins with 300 AA points don't consider themselves uber.  Level 25 rangers tear through Crushbone like a tornado and everyone in the zone considers them uber.  There is no specific use of the word that helps describe a particular state of the game, guilds, or players.  In almost every Mobhunter article I wrote for my first three months, my editor, the uber wizard Azile Ciricbane, had to edit out my use of uberguild and told me to replace it with something more specific.</p>

<p>Casual:  Casual is the most misunderstood and misused phrase in the Everquest community.  There are casual guilds who raid the Elemental Planes.  Some casual players have hundreds of AA points and play 40 hours a week.  Everyone has a different definition of a casual gamer.  Sometimes it means low level.  Other times it means non-raiders.  Instead of asking for changes for the casual gamer, we need to describe exactly what it is we desire.  Do we need more short-duration events?  Do we need less locked content?  Do we need higher power equipment available to single LDON / Ornate equipped level 65 groups?  Avoid the word casual, speak in detail.</p>

<p>Mudflation:  This ancient term gets used any time someone sees the game progress and doesn't like it.  Mudflation means little but has a built-in wrapper of negativity that lets us label progression like a package of spoiled meat.   Few describe exactly what they mean when they use the term and fewer can describe how to fix it.  The game gets larger.  The high-end zones get higher.  Level limits increase.  Equipment grows in power.  That isn't mudflation, that's progress.</p>

<p>Timesink:  This is one of my favorites.  Timesinks describe any action in Everquest that someone doesn't enjoy.  Everquest is a timesink.  Reading a book is a timesink.  I know one perfect way to avoid timesinks.  If you aren't enjoying what you do, do something else.  Before you begin telling me that you HAVE to camp shards to get intoVex Thal or you HAVE to get your Ring of Scale faction up, remember that this entire game is voluntary and the world is big enough to find a million other and often more enjoyable things to do.  If you find a particular event or hunt that bores you to tears, instead of labeling it a timesink, just tell SOE what you don't like about it.  Speak in details, not overused and meaningless generalities.</p>

<p>Class Balance:  Classes, by definition, cannot be balanced.  Every class is good at some things and bad in others.  There is no way to balance the wide variety of skills from one class to another.  How does one compare the blasts of a wizard to the slows of a shaman to the healing of a cleric?  With limited combat interaction it becomes difficult to make every one of the sixteen classes unique yet not required for a group.  SOE can tweak class abilities and help support those unique roles.  SOE can also tune encounters so they work well with particular class archetypes as they did with knights and the Ikkinz trials.  There is never a clear solution for class balance and there is no conclusion.  Classes cannot be balanced without ruining the unique skills that each class has to offer.</p>

<p>Every day players interact with SOE and every day players use these terms to gloss over deeper problems or recommendations.  When you find yourself using one of these terms when writing a message board post or sending feedback, ask yourself what you are really saying and replace it with detail.  Instead of asking for more casual-friendly content, ask for more single-group events that don't require raid gear.  Instead of complaining about timesinks, ask for more Ring of Scale faction options.  We love our meaningless terms but our communication becomes stronger and SOE's ability to respond becomes greater when we say exactly what we mean.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 September 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Focus and the Flip Flop</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000030.html" />
<modified>2004-09-04T00:53:29Z</modified>
<issued>2004-09-03T19:12:29Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.30</id>
<created>2004-09-03T19:12:29Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today we discuss the great foci change of &apos;04 with a bit of discussion on the politics of language thrown in for a bit more flavor.  An essay from 1946 probably doesn&apos;t count as a pop culture reference, but I&apos;m working on it.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>In case you live in Paw, the great Foci debate spread across every Everquest related forum on the entire web.  This <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=63311">official notice</a> declares that all foci will begin scaling at a rate of 10% per spell level after the level cap of the foci.  This means Spell Haste 4, a 15% reduction in casting time up to level 65, will drop to 13.5% at level 66, 11% at level 67, and so on until it reaches 7.5% at level 70.</p>

<p>This has most high-end raiders in a fury.  They spent months working through very difficult encounters in Gates of Discord where foci of 45% on some items will drop to 22.5% at level 70.  Some call this the worst nerf ever even though it's not a nerf but an enhancement.  SOE made a far better decision than letting the items cut off at 65 as they were advertised to do.</p>

<p>Originally, I agreed with the change.  First and foremost, it helps all spellcasting players below level 65 which is the most important subject of this change.  Most spend their time on this topic discussing 65+ gear, however.  I remember the dark days where Focus 3 items stopped working at all.  I expected my 65 gear would stop in much the same way.  This was a good change in my mind.  Others, however, felt sure that their high-end items would last forever (note: no item ever lasts forever.  One should always want to upgrade eventually.) and became quite horribly vexed when they learned they would eventually desire to upgrade.</p>

<p>The summit forums, where yours truly gets all manner of uberfruit tossed at him on a daily basis, was no exception to this.  In one of our dozens of heated messages I was called an uber / casual "flip flopper".  We will get back to this in a moment.  I spent much time considering this Foci situation.</p>

<p>What becomes clearer to me the more I test Omens and the more I think about Gates is that the two expansions seem to have come out in the wrong order.</p>

<p>Imagine if Omens came out four months ago with open zones, elemental level raid content, a lot of single-group content with equipment progression above LDON / Ornate, and most importantly level 70.  Those who finished Time and LDON raids head into the more difficult Omens content (more difficult because they have no Gates gear) while they level up to 70 and acquire that content.</p>

<p>Then Gates comes along.  The content is a lot harder.  Much more of the expansion is locked but even single-groupers have an easier time with the sewers and mountain trials.  Single group people are able to defeat the Ikkinz trials without raid gear.  The people who made it through Omens now hit that super-hard content (scaled for level 70 Omens gear) at Qvic and above and earn that super high quality loot.</p>

<p>Things seem a lot smoother in that obviously simplified theory.  There is a larger bridge between the single group hunters of LDON and the Planes to the single-group content in Gates.  The raiding guilds have smoother progression to the high-end raid content and the rewards for that gear fits their level better.</p>

<p>If you can't tell, I began to cave.  Perhaps being called a "flip flopper" finally did it.  I must have laughed for hours about the use of such a politically motivated word in a discussion about Massive Online Gaming.  I am a great fan of the use, reuse, and misuse of words as society changes.  George Orwell's 1946 essay <a href="http://mikeshea.net/orwell">Politics and the English Language</a> shows how the word "Fascist" got so misused that it became all but meaningless back in the 40s.  Geoff Nunberg's <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/1586482343/qid=1093987266/sr=8-1/ref=pd_ka_1/103-0239897-5576631?v=glance&s=books&n=507846">Going Nucular (sic)</a> talks about how the connotation of words like Plastic and Caucasian get horribly misused as our perceptions and politics change.  It wasn't until I was called a flip flopper that I really understood what they meant.  But I digress...</p>

<p>Very few people have high end Gates of Discord armor (don't scream yet, read on).  In a year or two, the flip flop of Gates and Omens (see, I used it again!) won't matter.  People will travel through the content in the most reasonable way, probably Omens to Gates.  For them, it makes little sense to have high-end Gates items, items that will be more difficult for them to acquire even at level 70 not work on spells up to level 70.</p>

<p>While I will not use my vast powers of the active voice ("Increase high-end Gates gear foci limits from 65 to 70"), I will say that it makes sense that high-end Gates gear scales to level 70.  More importantly, it will make more sense in a year when new players won't remember whether or not Gates came out before Omens.  In a year, with focus gear scaling to 70, Gates will be the clear line of equipment progression for raiders.  Without gear scaling to 70, the high-end Gates zones will see little use.</p>

<p>However, there is another side to this, a side that is not apparent yet to those who scream about their gear becoming "worthless".  If your foci gear scales to level 70, you will most likely not see equipment progression in Omens since your gear was really meant (in my own theory above) to be acquired after Omens.  You will spend your days tearing through raid content in Omens and in a month you will hit the high-end of Omens and realize there is nothing left.  Unlike everyone else, current high-end raiders will have already torn through Gates like a drag line in a strip mine and they will realize there is no more coal to mine.</p>

<p>Then they may quit and that is what SOE wishes to prevent.</p>

<p>Let me conclude this essay on semantics, politics, itemology, and marketing by saying that increasing the level limit to level 70 on high-end GoD items makes sense.  No other foci should get a free pass.  All other Foci from Time, the Elements, and any equipment in GoD with Time or Elemental effects should scale as the original plan intended.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 September 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Visions and Omens</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000029.html" />
<modified>2004-08-28T04:35:28Z</modified>
<issued>2004-08-25T19:08:48Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.29</id>
<created>2004-08-25T19:08:48Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Our first exploration of Omens of War begins this week.  We look at some of the new zones, new alternate advance abilities, and the task system.  Promising times lay ahead.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>The Omens beta began in full last week.  Larger guilds began testing out raid encounters while the rest of us ran Guktan wizards to the corners of the world marveling at the strange sights.</p>

<p>Most of Omens of War reminds me of Kunark.  The architecture and the plight of the Dragorn empire squeezed within the Muramite's iron gauntlet creates a lot of similarities to the Iksar and their post-Shissar empires.  Massive castles and spired walls stretch across the green landscape.  Orange and red clouds flow over hills and ravines.</p>

<p>A first glance shows us nine open over-land zones and three sets of instanced expeditions: the caves, the sewers, and the catacombs, each with about four or five variants.  More zones await discovery.  The first overland zone and the first set of instanced expeditions supports level 45+ with beasts lower in power than those in Natimbi.  The beasts grow in power quickly beyond that point.</p>

<p>There looks to be some excellent hunting zones between 60 and 70, although I imagine SOE developers continue to tune experience modifiers.  Between Planes of Power, Gates of Discord, Lost Dungeons, and Omens of War zones, there appears to be no lack of hunting areas for any level up to 70.</p>

<p>I have seen no equipment or loot so I cannot know yet if the power-gap between single-group hunters and raiders will close in at all.  Hopefully Omens offers enough single-group equipment to get players through the single-group trials of Gates.  Too long have the mountain trials, Kodtaz, and the Ikkinz trials been closed to non-raiders.</p>

<p>Lists of new Omens of War alternate advance abilities popped up everywhere on Friday.  While the lists contain no associated costs for these skills, many of them are surprisingly good.  A lot of changes that we never expected to see began to show up.  New spell-gem slots, new buff slots, a gate for everyone, two binding areas for wizards, and a surprisingly large increased mana regeneration cap for pure casters.  I can only really speak for clerical abilities but the list looks good, with a lot of basic improvements to our core function including improved healing gift, healing adapt, celestial rejuvenation, and our first critical heal over time ability.  I purchased few AAs for Gates, but now I am glad I saved up the points for Omens abilities.</p>

<p>One nice thing about new Alternate Advance skills is that any player can acquire them regardless of where they hunt.  They don't get stuck on your body when you wipe out in Fear and they don't require camping obscure mobs in obscure places for a 1 in 6 chance at that one last spell you needed.</p>

<p>Spells in Omens are distributed with runes, one rune per level, similar to Gates of Discord.  SOE developers compared it to Planes of Power.  Spells will not be duplicated.  What isn't known is the difficulty in acquiring spells.</p>

<p>Task system testing also began late last week.  While continued testing and balancing needs to occur before release, the skeleton of the system shows promise.  Single players are able to complete tasks in under an hour and earn a noticeable reward for doing so.  The reward is nice enough to make a difference but small enough to keep players from ignoring requests for groups.  Single groups should always be the core Everquest hunting team.</p>

<p>The task system is the one feature of Omens that supports players from level 20 to (hopefully) 70.  SOE brings up the task system whenever the requests for solo instanced encounters arise.  I don't believe any system can match up to the expectations people have for it.  It will take a few such systems to cover all of the needs and desires for short-duration content.</p>

<p>The official website of Omens of War includes a couple of new features I hadn't yet heard about.  One of them, a voice macro of some sort, shows a lot of promise.  Now an interesting show on Tivo won't kill half a group in eight seconds.  Now raid leaders can wake up that 20% of their raid who always seems to be asleep.  None of this is yet in the beta so I cannot say exactly how it works.</p>

<p>This week, the Omens of War developers and SOE community represenatives had an moderated chat with players.  EQ Stratics posted <a href="http://eq.stratics.com/content/hoclogs/oowhoc.php">a log of the transcript</a>.  Few details are given, but topics such as spells, new epic quests, content for players under 50, and solo instances all came up.</p>

<p>Omens of War brings us over a dozen new zones, half of them instanced.  It expands the physical worlds of Norrath even further.  I wonder if SOE might best spend their time working on new expansions that take Everquest into directions other than new zones to explore.  Everquest is certainly wide, it is the largest physical game I've ever played, but it isn't very deep.  The vast majority of content builds around combat against bosses.  The numbers increase but the gameplay is generally the same.  New lines of progression need to be developed.</p>

<p>I could sit here and come up with ideas stolen from other role playing games, but I am sure SOE's developers can do the same so I will leave it into their capable hands.  I heard some exciting ideas thrown around at the guild summit and I only hope they attempt to run with some of them.  Omens is a strong expansion and its release opens up the future into entirely new possibilities.  Now is the time to consider and develop those new possibilities.  The world is yours.</p>

<p><br />
Loral Ciriclight<br />
27 August 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Five Steps to One Million Subscribers</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000028.html" />
<modified>2004-08-17T17:59:14Z</modified>
<issued>2004-08-17T17:46:21Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.28</id>
<created>2004-08-17T17:46:21Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we look at what steps SOE might take to double Everquest subscribers.  Improved retail versions, new PC graphics, another LDON expansion, a simpler interface, and improved stability can all lead SOE to a million Everquest subscribers and a better game for all of us.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>I want to see one million people playing Evequest.  I want to see Sony Online Entertainment double the subscribers they currently have.  I do not have a master's degree in business or marketing but that never stopped me from having an opinion before and it won't stop me now.  This article outlines five steps to improve Everquest's success.</p>

<p>Loral's Marketeer Five Step Evil PowerPoint Slide for the success of Everquest:</p>

<p>- Continue to release fresh retail versions of Everqust.  Make it clear to the consumer which one they should buy and cheap enough to compete with newer MMOGs.</p>

<p>- Update the PC models and graphics to compete with newer MMOGs and make EQ look like a brand new game.</p>

<p>- Release another Lost Dungeons of Norrath style expansion with scaling content for levels 20 to 70.</p>

<p>- Simplify the interface; perform usability studies; simplify the skill and discipline system.</p>

<p>- Improve Everquest stability; make patches modem friendly; offer updated versions of EQ on DVD as DVD drives proliferate.</p>

<p>Step 1: Market Everquest as a new game every expansion and offer a free version.  The release of the Everquest Platinum edition greatly improved SOE's chances for increasing subscribers.  For $30, a new player gets the basic game, all seven current expansions, and a month to try it out.</p>

<p>Release the basic game with a one month trial for free to let people try the game out.  Pass this single-disc version around like AOL.  Have people making coasters out of it and throwing it at that guy hovering over by the fax machine.  While the current free download helps, the sheer size of the game makes it almost inaccessible to new players.  Offering free CDs in gaming stores, magazines, and bulk mail will bring in a lot of new players.</p>

<p>Continually update this $30 version with everything but the most recent expansion.    Pull older versions off the shelves.  Make it clear which versions players need to buy.</p>

<p>Step 2:  Update player character graphics.  There are no graphics more important than PC graphics.  When people shop for a new MMOG, player graphics are the first thing they see.  Everquest has excellent world and beastie graphics, but the current player graphics need work.</p>

<p>SOE plans to release new player graphics by the end of the year.  It is important that they stick to this deadline.  EQ2, Worlds of Warcraft, and Final Fantasy X offer brand new and fresh player graphics.  New PC graphics is SOE's first chance to impress new players, it is the first graphics a new player sees. New player graphics are the most important change this year.</p>

<p>Player graphics require three things to succeed.  They must scale well on existing systems and offer good performance during raids.  They must be customizable enough to create unique characters identifiable from far away.  They must be good enough to let us escape into the lives of our characters.  </p>

<p>Step 3:  Release another Lost Dungeon-like expansion.  Lost Dungeons of Norrath offers the most highly scalable content in any of the previous expansions.  LDON offers usable and rewarding content from level 20 to level 65.  Mobs are always blue.  Treasure and rewards scale well.  Groups are easy to find and the camps are well connected.  The dungeons allow for easy corpse recovery but still offer a good challenge.  Players can finish an event in between 45 and 90 minutes.</p>

<p>A new Lost Dungeons expansion should use the Gates of Discord expedition system so players can leave if they have to.  Like LDON, it should allow players to work towards powerful items in small steps.  The storylines should put the players in the role of the hero and not the errand boy.  The storyline should progress as the players hunt.  Threats should seem real.  Adventure types should reward the players equally for equal difficulty and there should be a wider variety of them than the current ones.</p>

<p>Step 4: Simplify the interface.  Everquest's interface is very difficult for new players.  The basic controls alone require a lot of work but stack on communications and character improvement interfaces and you have one of the most complex game interfaces ever seen.</p>

<p>Reduce the number of windows a player must go through to set up disciplines.  Start all skills at 1 so they will raise on their own instead of requiring a player to run back and check with a guild master every couple of levels to see if there is a skill they missed.  Tell the player when a new discipline is available and let them scribe it like a spell.  Streamline the hotbox macro creation process so it is easy to build complex macros mixing skills, disciplines, spells, and other commands.</p>

<p>Perform usability tests with new players to see where interface elements break down and where they can be improved.  Basic usability tests are cheap to perform and can easily improve profits on even simple systems.</p>

<p>Simplify the interface and more players will stick with the game.</p>

<p>Step 5: Improve stability and lower network requirements.  When I first played Everquest Online Adventures on the Playstation 2, I was impressed by two things.  One, they download patches into three megs of space and it never gets any bigger.  Two, they focus almost entirely on game enhancements instead of stability improvements.</p>

<p>Make Everquest as stable as a console game.  Improve hardware testing and application testing so that players can reasonably expect the game to work every time they log in.  Many players still face a variety of technical issues and these issues are far more damaging to the game than almost any content problem.  The chaos of PC architectures makes testing very difficult.  Stability should be a number one concern for SOE developers.</p>

<p>The large patches that Everquest players face require a high-speed connection.  While the game itself plays well over dial up, downloading two hundred megs of updates cut off a lot of players from playing.  As DVD drives become more common on newer machines, offer Everquest with all expansions on a single DVD but lock the content the user didn't pay for.  Update this DVD with the most recent large patches so even existing players can go get the updates from a game magazine or from their local game shop.  Keep patches small and consider dial up players when they are released.  No patch should take longer than 30 minutes to download.  Even thirty minutes will cut out a lot of players.</p>

<p>I don't claim that these five steps are the keys to the success and future of Everquest, but from the five years I've played this game, the above steps seem to be the ones most hindering to new players.  New players are the key to success for Everquest in the years to come.  While a lot of players would rather SOE focus on the top 1%, that 1% is going to go away eventually and only by bringing in new and fresh players can Everquest continue to grow into the future.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
15 August 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Calm Before the Storm</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000026.html" />
<modified>2004-08-09T19:06:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-08-09T18:46:06Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.26</id>
<created>2004-08-09T18:46:06Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today we deliver another gathering of news from across the lands and across the ethereal worlds of the net.  We look at some new changes to test, some discussions of new LDON raids, and the continuing class issue updates.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>We seem to sit within the valley between one expansion and the next.  We had some great new patches since the release of Gates of Discord, and we hear of some nice future updates.  Even with Omens of War on the horizon we sit here in the gap of a slow news week all the same.</p>

<p>One of the most interesting threads floating around within the Everquest community is <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=testing&amp;message.id=2568">Hobart's Test Server Update</a>.  If you ever want to see what new changes we should expect in the next patch, thats the place to go look.</p>

<p>The most recent updates to the test server include a lot of features for the raid tool.  Raid leaders will soon be able to lock and unlock a raid, remove group leader flags from raiders, remove players from any group within the raid, and buttons to put group members into other groups.  These changes are wonderful organizational changes and may be the best changes to the raid tool since its release back in Planes of Power.  Even for smaller two or three group raids, it is wonderful to be able to switch which player is in which group without going through the shuffle.</p>

<p>Now, of course, this will lead to whole fields of raiders going AFK while raids organize and may lead raid leaders to ask for the next logical update: "Give me a Warcraft 3 interface so I can just control the whole raid myself".  I kid, of course.  These changes help raiders quite a bit and feedback from summit raid leaders has been very good.</p>

<p>Along with new raid organization functions comes new consent functions.  Many raiders and even a few groupers want more powerful consenting features for corpse dragging.  More than a few players see death as a nice opportunity for a much needed AFK break frustrating draggers to no end when they must send "CONSENT PLZZ" about fifty times before getting a response.  Soon players can consent guilds, consent groups, and consent raids for dragging.  Again, these improvements help solve a lot of problems mainly for raiding guilds.</p>

<p>Expect new hunting hot spots with the next patch, says Brenlo of the Hairy Feet.  Hot spots, zones with increased zone experience modifiers, help push players to explore some areas to which they might not always travel by rewarding them with much improved experience gain.  The current hot spots existed for some time now and a change is due.  We don't know which zones will turn into hot spots yet, but many await the change.  Hot spots are a great feature for mid-level players.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Stormhammer&amp;message.id=783">thread on the Stormhammer server forums</a> sheds a harsh light on the 12 person LDON raid recently released on Stormhammer and moving soon to the live servers.  While I heard it was tuned for level 55s to 65s, a few players who actually tried it say it is tuned for Elemental, Time, and GoD equipped players.  These equipment restrictions put this raid in the same category as all of the LDON raids.  They are too hard, restricted to only Elemental+ equipped players, and offer too little a reward to make it attractive to those able to accomplish it.</p>

<p>The LDON raid system and the Gates of Discord Expedition system offer a lot of potential for mid-levelers and non-raiders to experience some of the fun and excitement of raiding.  These expeditions can offer raid-level content at any set level with restrictions on who can enter and how often without blocking it behind a rare flag-mob.  This new two-group raid looked like a great way to get 55s to non-raid-equipped 65s into some Lost Dungeon raids but it appears it is just another raid for the top-tier raiders.  With all of the unused raid content of LDON, I don't know why SOE tuned this event for the same players who already ignore LDON raids.</p>

<p>We have seen little new information on Omens of War.  Everyone has questions about how it will support their play-style.  No one knows what levels 66 to 70 will do to older expansions like Lost Dungeons and Gates.  SOE released no official word on existing level 65 focus effects but rumors speak of a nice flexible solution.  The task system interests a lot of people but I still feel too much weight falls onto it.  It may be doomed just by the sheer amount of attention it will get.  I hope it lives up to the expectations but only time will tell.</p>

<p>With the lack of other major news, people spread to their sixteen camps and began the class wars once again.  SOE plans to provide class definition documents that they have worked on for some time now.  These definitions help define what each classes role is in a group and in a raid.  I don't know if they will cover soloing but I do believe they cover a class from levels 1 to 65 (probably to 70).</p>

<p>Every class should bring a combination of abilities to a group at all levels that sets it apart from other classes.  No one class should be better in all ways than another.  Every class should have options and use for soloing, grouping, and raiding.  Every class should have a unique identity and background.</p>

<p>Feedback on the new Mobhunter design has been good and very useful.  Our plan is to switch over to the new version next Saturday.  Please give <a href="http://mobhunter.com/new/">the new Mobhunter design</a> a look and try out the comment system.</p>

<p>I have a small update on one of my secondary requests on Loral's Evil Agenda.  It appears with Nvidia-based video cards, one can span Everquest across two windows.  I had little luck with an Nvidia Geforce 5500; the EQ window never got bigger than about 2400 pixels wide; but the new Geforce 6800 GT runs EQ in a window 3200 x 1150 pixels wide for a total of 3.6 million pixels.  There are a couple of problems, however.  One cannot run in full screen mode or they crash to desktop and the window can't be a full 3200 x 1200 or it slows down to one frame a second.  If you don't mind seeing your start bar all the time, it can be a wild way to play.  </p>

<p>Why would someone want to play across two monitors?  If one runs a "/viewport 1601 0 1600 1150" they get a normal EQ view on the right monitor and a black background on the other.  Chats, maps, inventories, spell gems, buffs, and any other windows you don't have to see right away can be thrown over to the other monitor.</p>

<p>Its a bit of a gimmick but it is a neat way to play.  Here is a picture of <a href="http://mobhunter.com/new/images/eq_dual_monitor.jpg">Everquest running across two monitors</a>.</p>

<p>Look forward to an editorial on Everquest's current state of corpse recovery in the next two weeks and until then, play on.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
7 August 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>

</feed>