<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://mikeshea.net/rss.css" type="text/css"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

  <channel>
    <title>LoralCiriclight.com</title>
    <link>http://loralciriclight.com/</link>
    <description>Tales and adventures of Loral Ciriclight in the online role playing game, Everquest.</description>
    <dc:language>en-us</dc:language>
    <dc:creator>mike@mikeshea.net</dc:creator>
    <dc:rights>Copyright 2004</dc:rights>
    <dc:date>2004-12-15T17:42:41+00:00</dc:date>
    <admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.movabletype.org/?v=3.01D" />
    <admin:errorReportsTo rdf:resource="mailto:mike@mikeshea.net"/>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>

    <item>
      <title>Refunds, Mergers, and Flags</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001234.html</link>
      <description>This week we saw the largest update in some time. Wednesday&apos;s patch included pages and pages of changes covering everything...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1234@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>This week we saw the largest update in some time.  Wednesday's patch included pages and pages of changes covering everything from the long awaited backflag solutions to new hotzones and alternate advancement point refunds.</p>

<p>We discussed a these changes previously so I will only touch on a few things.  The AA refunds, for the most part, seem to be very reasonable.  SOE's goal was to make the point costs of Gates AAs fit better with the costs found in Omens of War.  In a few days we should know how well this meets the desires of those it effects.</p>

<p>The backflagging solution should help guilds.  While some guilds stayed at their current rate of power and delved deep into Anguish, other guilds began opening their doors wide open to new recruits since the release of EQ2 and WoW.  These backflag changes help guilds continue to progress at the point they left off by using the 85/15 rule to bring in unflagged recruits.  Because guilds won't have to backflag, they should be able to retain members rather than lose them.  These backflag changes came at a good time for many raiding forces.</p>

<p>A few older zones had their experience modifiers increased including Shadeweaver's Thicket, Kurn's Tower, Unrest, Crystal Caverns, Solusek's Eye, Katta Castellum, Lower Guk, Nagafen's Lair, and Umbral Plains.  These new hot zones should help get newer players into zones they might otherwise skip for newer content.  I like the idea behind hotzones.  Without too much effort, older zones become much more desirable than they once were.</p>

<p>Tacvi, the deepest and darkest corner of the Gates of Discord expansion, had a couple of nice changes for those powerful enough to reach it.  It received a new zone in that doesn't require the weekly slaying of an ubermob to enter.  This prevents guilds from simply waiting until another guild comes by and takes care of the large fellow.  Tacvi also received a larger cache of new loot.  I would expect this loot to be on par with the equipment we see coming from the depths of Anguish.</p>

<p>We saw our first wave of epic alterations this patch.  These updates mainly handled the content required to receive the epic, but more than once we've heard that the epic effects themselves will be looked at.  Expect to see some changes to epic 1.5s and 2.0s coming soon.</p>

<p>Both /autofire and /melody made it into this patch.  Many archers and song singers rejoiced.</p>

<p>The two revamped zones, Mistmoore and Splitpaw made it to the Legends servers.  I haven't yet heard what sort of content we can expect, but rumors speak to Elemental-level beasties worming their way through the infected paw of the Karanas.  We shall wait and see.  Expect these zones to make it to the live servers in about a month.</p>

<p>While we saw many good changes for the upper-end of the game, we didn't see that many that effected the larger group of players below level 65.  Backflagging, epic 1.5 changes, and Tacvi matters to high-end raiders, but there wasn't much in this patch for the larger group of non-raiders and single-group hunters.  At this critical stage, SOE must consider the low end and mid-level game a priority over these changes to high-end content.</p>

<p>Hopefully in January we should see the much-anticipated task changes we heard about at the Fan Faire.</p>

<p>A few different board postings offer some excellent advice that effects every player, not just raiders.  Three interesting threads, one on <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48581">soloing and task changes</a>, one on <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48894">user interface suggestions</a>, and another on <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48560">grouping and LFG changes</a>, all have excellent suggestions and advice that effects a large majority of Everquest players.</p>

<p>Two topics seem to dominate the conversations over on the Live forums.  Class balance continues to raise its ugly head, usually wrapped in "SOE doesn't listen!"  Most of the time, the complaint isn't really that SOE doesn't listen, but that SOE doesn't agree.  People don't seem to want to hear it when their ideas are shot down.  In the meantime, to squash the rumors of lack of communication, continue to watch the dozen or so postings a day from various SOE employees over at the <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/tracker?role=Dev">dev tracker</a>.</p>

<p>One other topic became so prolific recently that threads had to be consolidated into one huge thread.  I speak of server mergers.  I think merging servers should be an absolute last resort for SOE.  It is the sort of change that cannot be undone, once done.  It breaks up of our identity within the community and it gives the (perhaps inaccurate) impression that EQ is on a steady decline without a chance of going back up.  Yes, numbers have been low, although anyone who tells you they have real data to support specific trends is most likely lying.  Nothing tells us that we won't see the continued trend of new players joining in and old players returning when a shipment of new shiny expansion boxes hits the shelf sometime between March and May.</p>

<p>Ok, time for the scoop....</p>

<p>Recently, a large group of players from the Zek servers, Tallon, Vallon, Sullon, and Rallos, got together with representatives from SOE to discuss their merger.  These servers, being evil red PVP servers, have a much different demographic and player base than the other pansy huggy blue servers.  They also, apparently, have many fewer active players.  </p>

<p>My vast network of spies tells me that SOE is indeed considering consolidating all four of these servers.  While they have no definite plans yet, there are discussions within SOE to consolidate these four servers together.  It is easy to consider this a reactionary move, however SOE apparently considered this merger well before EQ2's release and the meeting with the Zek players.  </p>

<p>Those same spies did not reveal what the rule set would be for this combined server, so they were all immediately put to death.</p>

<p>Many will use this to feather their giant "EQ is Dead" mardi-gras hats.  Yet, these same people will continue to pay their $12 a month and visit sites like this one and the EQLive boards.  People love to hate.</p>

<p>The MMOG business tells us otherwise.  Many other MMORPGs continue to not only run but bring out new expansions even with nearly 1/10th of the population of EQ.  I expect that the server numbers need to drop dramatically over a long period of time before SOE decides to pull the plug.  In the meantime, I see those who never enjoyed the game go off to greener pastures and those of us who do enjoy the game will form a new, tighter, and stronger community than ever before.</p>

<p>The day I don't hear anyone shouting "EQ is dead" is the day I really begin to worry.</p>

<p>Refunds, Mergers, and Flags</p>

<p>by Loral on December 15, 2004</p>

<p>This week we saw the largest update in some time. Wednesday's patch included pages and pages of changes covering everything from the long awaited backflag solutions to new hotzones and alternate advancement point refunds.</p>

<p>We discussed a these changes previously so I will only touch on a few things. The AA refunds, for the most part, seem to be very reasonable. SOE's goal was to make the point costs of Gates AAs fit better with the costs found in Omens of War. In a few days we should know how well this meets the desires of those it effects.</p>

<p>The backflagging solution should help guilds. While some guilds stayed at their current rate of power and delved deep into Anguish, other guilds began opening their doors wide open to new recruits since the release of EQ2 and WoW. These backflag changes help guilds continue to progress at the point they left off by using the 85/15 rule to bring in unflagged recruits. Because guilds won't have to backflag, they should be able to retain members rather than lose them. These backflag changes came at a good time for many raiding forces.</p>

<p>A few older zones had their experience modifiers increased including Shadeweaver's Thicket, Kurn's Tower, Unrest, Crystal Caverns, Solusek's Eye, Katta Castellum, Lower Guk, Nagafen's Lair, and Umbral Plains. These new hot zones should help get newer players into zones they might otherwise skip for newer content. I like the idea behind hotzones. Without too much effort, older zones become much more desirable than they once were.</p>

<p>Tacvi, the deepest and darkest corner of the Gates of Discord expansion, had a couple of nice changes for those powerful enough to reach it. It received a new zone in that doesn't require the weekly slaying of an ubermob to enter. This prevents guilds from simply waiting until another guild comes by and takes care of the large fellow. Tacvi also received a larger cache of new loot. I would expect this loot to be on par with the equipment we see coming from the depths of Anguish.</p>

<p>We saw our first wave of epic alterations this patch. These updates mainly handled the content required to receive the epic, but more than once we've heard that the epic effects themselves will be looked at. Expect to see some changes to epic 1.5s and 2.0s coming soon.</p>

<p>Both /autofire and /melody made it into this patch. Many archers and song singers rejoiced.</p>

<p>The two revamped zones, Mistmoore and Splitpaw made it to the Legends servers. I haven't yet heard what sort of content we can expect, but rumors speak to Elemental-level beasties worming their way through the infected paw of the Karanas. We shall wait and see. Expect these zones to make it to the live servers in about a month.</p>

<p>While we saw many good changes for the upper-end of the game, we didn't see that many that effected the larger group of players below level 65. Backflagging, epic 1.5 changes, and Tacvi matters to high-end raiders, but there wasn't much in this patch for the larger group of non-raiders and single-group hunters. At this critical stage, SOE must consider the low end and mid-level game a priority over these changes to high-end content.</p>

<p>Hopefully in January we should see the much-anticipated task changes we heard about at the Fan Faire.</p>

<p>A few different board postings offer some excellent advice that effects every player, not just raiders. Three interesting threads, one on soloing and task changes, one on user interface suggestions, and another on grouping and LFG changes, all have excellent suggestions and advice that effects a large majority of Everquest players.</p>

<p>Two topics seem to dominate the conversations over on the Live forums. Class balance continues to raise its ugly head, usually wrapped in "SOE doesn't listen!" Most of the time, the complaint isn't really that SOE doesn't listen, but that SOE doesn't agree. People don't seem to want to hear it when their ideas are shot down. In the meantime, to squash the rumors of lack of communication, continue to watch the dozen or so postings a day from various SOE employees over at the dev tracker.</p>

<p>One other topic became so prolific recently that threads had to be consolidated into one huge thread. I speak of server mergers. I think merging servers should be an absolute last resort for SOE. It is the sort of change that cannot be undone, once done. It breaks up of our identity within the community and it gives the (perhaps inaccurate) impression that EQ is on a steady decline without a chance of going back up. Yes, numbers have been low, although anyone who tells you they have real data to support specific trends is most likely lying. Nothing tells us that we won't see the continued trend of new players joining in and old players returning when a shipment of new shiny expansion boxes hits the shelf sometime between March and May.</p>

<p>Ok, time for the scoop....</p>

<p>Recently, a large group of players from the Zek servers, Tallon, Vallon, Sullon, and Rallos, got together with representatives from SOE to discuss their merger. These servers, being evil red PVP servers, have a much different demographic and player base than the other pansy huggy blue servers. They also, apparently, have many fewer active players.</p>

<p>My vast network of spies tells me that SOE is indeed considering consolidating all four of these servers. While they have no definite plans yet, there are discussions within SOE to consolidate these four servers together. It is easy to consider this a reactionary move, however SOE apparently considered this merger well before EQ2's release and the meeting with the Zek players.</p>

<p>Those same spies did not reveal what the rule set would be for this combined server, so they were all immediately put to death.</p>

<p>Many will use this to feather their giant "EQ is Dead" mardi-gras hats. Yet, these same people will continue to pay their $12 a month and visit sites like this one and the EQLive boards. People love to hate.</p>

<p>The MMOG business tells us otherwise. Many other MMORPGs continue to not only run but bring out new expansions even with nearly 1/10th of the population of EQ. I expect that the server numbers need to drop dramatically over a long period of time before SOE decides to pull the plug. In the meantime, I see those who never enjoyed the game go off to greener pastures and those of us who do enjoy the game will form a new, tighter, and stronger community than ever before.</p>

<p>The day I don't hear anyone shouting "EQ is dead" is the day I really begin to worry.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
15 December 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-12-15T17:42:41+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: News of the Winter&apos;s Moon</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001226.html</link>
      <description>We&apos;ve had a slow couple of weeks on the EQ front. No doubt concern arises from the perceived drop in...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1226@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>We've had a slow couple of weeks on the EQ front.  No doubt concern arises from the perceived drop in numbers and while we certainly cannot say what the future holds, it would be premature to follow in the same well-walked tread of picket sign wearing doomsday sayers.</p>

<p>A few factors all crashed together this year, more than any year previous that I can remember.  Instead of a holiday season with one or two new games coming out, nearly six must-have hit games came out at once.  In a discussion about EQ2 and its effect on some high end guilds, I heard guild leaders say that as much as they like the cross-game chat between EQ1 and EQ2, what they really need is cross-game chat to Half Life 2.  Now that may not be the case for everyone, but that is my point.  There isn't an easy conclusion to make about any of this.</p>

<p>I am an officer in a small guild built around helping the adventurers of Norrath.  During our regular weekly events Healers United travels around Norrath to popular hunting spots to offer our healing, buffing, resurrection, advise and gameplay help to those who need it.  Usually we had four to six people on during off hours and somewhere between fifteen and twenty during the core hours of 7pm to 1am EST.  Since Thanksgiving, our numbers dropped  closer to four to eight during prime time and one or two regular people on the off-hours.</p>

<p>Am I worried about this?  Yes.  What is my reaction to this worry?  Recruit newer members.  The game shifted for a lot of people in this time.  Some guilds wait to see what happens after the holidays and that's a smart move.  If a lot of folks really are playing Half Life 2, Halo 2, or Grand Theft Auto San Andreas, those games won't last forever and back to the doors of Anguish they will return.  Some are no doubt playing EQ2 and Worlds of Warcraft but those games won't be for everyone either.  Both are different enough from Everquest to turn away some long-time players of EQ.</p>

<p>I watch the larger guilds crash together and merge into new giant forms like huge floating balls of mercury.  I see others simply fall under the weight of their own lofty goals, lack of interest, and stubbornness to open their doors to new members or alliances.  The smarter leaders consider alliances with other individuals and organizations until they get a better feel for what sorts of numbers they require.  Once they see a solid trend, for example always having about 32 people online instead of around 54, they should begin to recruit new members.</p>

<p>None of us know what the true statistics are.  We only see what we see and we best react to what we know for fact.  It won't surprise me if we see a return to EQ in January and it certainly won't surprise me to see a larger surge of returning players when SOE announces and releases the next expansion.  At that point the new single-player games will be over, the shine of newer MMOGs will wear off, and people will fall where they have the most fun.</p>

<p>Over the last two weeks I balanced my time between both EQ and EQ2 and I noticed an interesting thing.  I like EQ2 a lot and I have fun hunting with little Pavlen the foppy roguish swashbuckler as he spies for Qeynos and slays vile stinking gnolls but when I return as the Venerable Loral Ciriclight, 68th cleric of Tunare, I have no less fun than I did before.  I still enjoy a heart-racing hunt in the Muramite Proving Grounds.  I still enjoy talking and meeting with my friends.  I still marvel at the look of Omens with its shiny skinned Dragorns and hideous glowing eyed Discordlings.  I still have a lot of fun playing Everquest.</p>

<p>SOE needs to focus on a few things to keep Everquest strong.  We need to see the world continue to change and shift.  We need to see new features for both new and existing players.  We need to continue to see new content meant to challenge and excite us and we need features to help us get together with friends and defeat these challenges.  I don't see them slowing down at accomplishing this at all.</p>

<p>So what sorts of improvements are we likely to see soon?  On December 15th a new patch will include a lot of new features that will help EQ continue to grow and evolve.  Stormhammer, the server for the cultural elite, will receive two revamped zones, Mistmoore and Paw.  The Everquest website includes descriptive lore about both <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=64379">Mistmoore</a> and <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=64380">Splitpaw</a>.  What Splitpaw really needs is a nearby Wayfarer camp or Knowledge stone.  Expect these zones to move to the proletariat servers in one to two months.</p>

<p>Both /autofire and /melody will move to the live servers.  These two long awaited features, mainly for rangers and bards, help players play those two classes with a bit more ease matching the other classes.  Positive changes to the way a player plays the game matter a lot more than any statistical change you might receive.</p>

<p>We should expect the task changes I heard about at the fan faire to move to the live servers in January.  Expect thousands more tasks with new task-types including things like fishing and foraging.  The more I look at the task system, the more I see the potential for an EQ2-like quest journal.  If SOE added some class-specific tasks, group tasks, and some item rewards to the task interface they already have, they would have a really strong new system for both new and older players alike.</p>

<p>Perhaps the biggest change we will see comes with the new backflag solution.  Ever since Planes of Power, backflagging has slowed down a lot of big guilds.  Guilds would fight their way past Rallos Zek, through some of the elemental planes, and, for a variety of reasons, lose enough players that they needed to reflag new members in order to continue.  This process, when you include Planes of Power and Gates of Discord flagging, might take up more time than actually hunting new content.  SOE hopes to fix this with a new backflag solution.</p>

<p>Nearly every flagged zone allows 15% of a raid to be unflagged upon entering it.   A small handful (perhaps two to six per zone-wide raid) of back-flag quest items drop per zone-wide raid.  These items lead unflagged attendees of these raids through a single-group quest to receive a flag for that zone only.  Now that raider is fully flagged for that zone.  The 85/15 rule will be applied to Time and to Gates of Discord flagged zones.</p>

<p>This solution will help guilds and high-end raiding alliances with their backflag woes.  As long as they have enough flagged people to get into and raid higher-tiered zones, they can help flag new members without sending most of their flagged members back to raid older content over and over.  </p>

<p>This solution will not help single-group hunters who desire these flags, but my favorite statement at the fan faire sums up the solution to this very well: The best way to fix the flagging problem is not to have progressive flagged content ever again.  In other words, expansions from Omens and on will hopefully only have a single flagged zone at the end of the expansion similar to Veeshan's Peaks, Sleeper's Tomb, Vex Thal, and Anguish.</p>

<p>Two new storyline entries whispered across the winds recently.  These stories begin to build better connections from the old world to the wars in the strange lands of Kuua and Taelosia.   I often complain that we have little understanding or in-game motivation to travel to these distant lands when threats such as the Rujarkian orcs, Mistmoore vampires, the horrors of Miragul the Lich, and the poisoned rivers of Guk pose much greater risks to our lands.  These stories, along with a few in-game changes (perhaps Muramites in Greater Faydark, Toxx Woods, the Commonlands or Qeynos Hills) would do a lot towards tightening up the loose storyline that ties Norrath to Taelosia and Kuua.</p>

<p>Strange shapes loom on the horizon.  While the doomsday heralds that plague New Tanaan's streets continue their cries to the gods of chaos about the end of days, I see a time for a new golden age.  I see a time of great wars and great victories.  I see lost friends returning home and new friends joining the ranks of the adventurers of Norrath.  Most importantly, I still have fun every time I log in and I plan to do so for a long time to come.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
6 December 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-12-06T21:19:50+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 54: Vxed</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001225.html</link>
      <description>Six figures slipped through the halls of Ferubi like the shadows of birds and stepped into the courtyard of Barindu....</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1225@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Six figures slipped through the halls of Ferubi like the shadows of birds and stepped into the courtyard of Barindu.  Ancient pyramids towered over the six adventurers; monuments to the lost race of Taelosia.  The Taelosians spent thousands of years building these temples of worship.  Intricate runes and glyphs covered every surface of the massive stone structures.  Like the magical weapons and armor of Norrath, the temples pulsed and throbbed with power.  They speared through the Astral and Ethereal planes, acting as wells and waterfalls through multiple worlds simultaneously.  These nodes of power once fed the Taelosians with spiritual and magical energy.  Now they fed the Muramites.</p>

<p>The armies of Mata Muram infested these temples like flies on a decaying corpse.  Loral stared at the old temples and the misshapen beasts that walked or crawled on its once holy surface.  Huge wolf-headed beasts wielding massive sythe-bladed axes swung their large heads and sniffed at the air.  Spine-backed humanoids, blind and scarred, crawled over the rocks like spiders.  Heavily muscled orange-skinned primitives scanned the gardens surrounding the temples with sharp pink eyes.  Loral's breath caught in his chest when those pink eyes scanned across him.</p>

<p>Loral felt a hand grasp the front of his cloak and pull him against the rock walls of the valley of Barindu.  Mici, the barbarian berserkser, snorted at Loral's pale face.  The berserker pointed to a canyon that cut into the rock wall with his double-bladed axe.  Loral ran.</p>

<p>Their cloaks of invisiblity broke apart seeming to spill the six adventurers into the dark sunlight burning through the red clouds.  An unpleasant stench of spoiled meat filled Loral's nostrils but he couldn't place it until they turned a corner of the canyon and saw the piles of decaying corpses.</p>

<p>The bodies lay in pieces under the hot sun.  Vultures and a world of insects feasted on the decaying meat of the dead.  Not since the Ringwar of Thurgadin had Loral seen such violence.  The bodies of these adventurers, two dozen at least, had not been cut down; they had been ripped apart.  The cynical voice of the veteran dwarf at the Natimbi camp spoke in Loral's memory.  This land devoured adventurers.  Now Loral saw the resulting regurgitation.</p>

<p>"Only one way to go."  Stonehewer tightened his breastplate agianst his barrel-shaped chest and tightened the leather collar around his throat.  The dwarf had seen hundreds of battles and every preparation he made was the result of a lesson learned in battle.  Stonehewer spat into his leather gauntleted hands and drew his heavily enchanted two handed sword.  The blade shone white in the dark light of the sun.</p>

<p>Illudar dropped a gauntled hand onto Loral's shoulder.  Loral and the two paladins had met Juror the shaman, Kaylessa the enchanter, and Mici the massive barbarian berserker in the ruined halls of Qinimi before deciding to travel through the canyons of Vxed.  Only through these canyons would they reach the larger temples of Kodtaz and see first hand what menace Norrath faced.  The six adventurers stepped over the bodies of the dead and continued their trek into the mountain pass.</p>

<p>It took little time before the party found out what caused such carnage to the fallen adventurers.  Massive lizards, twisted from the tainted power of the Taelosian temples now under Muramite control, attacked with the fury beyond even the demons of the outer planes.  Claws like steel and teeth as sharp as glass cut and slashed at the party.  Kaylessa bent the mind of one weak-minded beast and turned its sharp claws in their favor.  The party fought and continued its journey through the mountain pass.</p>

<p>The deafening roar of a thousand foot waterfall filled their heads as they continued until they stepped out onto a platform suspended over a thousand foot drop.  A waterfall fell the thousand feet to the icy waters below.  Two thousand-foot-tall statues stood on the left and right of the chasm, palms out and serenity on their smooth runed faces.  A bridge spanned across the chasm to another platform across the way.  Loral felt his legs grow weak when he looked over the bridge's edge.  Age had torn pieces of the bridge away and very little kept it from falling completely into the chasm below.</p>

<p>Loral felt his hair stand on end but it wasn't until the party traveled halfway across the bridge that the trap sprung.  Loral saw Stonehewer go rigid as though gripped by an invisible giant.  Illudar's sword clattered from his hand to the stone bridge's surface.  A figure slid out from the rocks on the other side of the bridge.  Long black hair flowed over the woman's ivory skin.  Her beautiful torso flowed into a hideously scaled serpent tail.  Her long fingered hands twisted and pulled as though pulling marionette strings.  Loral watched in horror as Stonehewer turned on legs not under his own control and began walking to the bridge's edge.</p>

<p>Illudar screamed.  His eyes had rolled back to their whites and he stood arms out at his side and wailed at the violet sky above.  Loral rushed out to tackle and pin Stonehewer before he would take himself over the edge but another sight stopped his movement.  A gray-skinned horror crawled over the bridge's edge.  It stared through eyes stitched closed and sniffed once before hissing at the cleric through razor sharp fangs.</p>

<p>Blackness overtook Illudar.  It enveloped him and surrounded him.  He suffocated under its thick pressure.  Visions filled his mind.  He was a child again.  He saw his mother smiling at him.  Sunlight from an unseen source shined in her golden hair.  Then shadows closed in on her.  They reached for her with sharp talons and long teeth.  He saw her cry but heard the cries of his friends far away in another world instead.  He sat helpless and small, crying out as the shadows ripped his mother apart.</p>

<p>Whatever horrid power trapped and twisted Stonehewer and Illudar had no effect on Mici and Juror.  The berserker drew a heavy axe and hurled it end over end at the serpent enchantress at the same time that the shaman finished chanting the words of a dreadful curse.  The axe caught the sorceress in the chest and clattered to the stone.  Loral heard her collar bone crack and blood gushed from the gaping wound.</p>

<p>Stonehewer's eyes focused and he spun his arms for balance, his feet half over the edge of the bridge that crossed the thousand foot drop.  Illudar cried out again, his mind snapping back to reality like a broken rope.  Stonehewer, his balance recovered, rushed forward and swept off the enchantress's head and the hand she held against her chest with a single stroke of his blade.</p>

<p>Seven inch claws slashed past Loral's face.  Only a clumsy tumble backward saved his eyes from being ripped out of their sockets.  The horrible gray-skinned creature hissed and crawled towards the fallen cleric.  It raised another jagged claw and swept down.  A line of silver flashed in the moonlight and the ukun's fingers flew into the night on tracing lines of black blood.  The beast roared in pain and frustration before lunging at the blue armored paladin, Illudar.  Its teeth tore into Illudar's chain coif.  Bright red blood flowed from the seams of Illudar's armor.  The high elf stabbed his blade into the creature's chest.  Its tip burst out of the creature's back, adding a silver spine to the bone ones already there.  The ukun's bite weakened.  Illudar twisted the blade.  The bite loosened more.  Illudar kicked the beast away before another slash of Stonehewer's sword sent the ukun's head tumbling into the icy waters below.</p>

<p>Blue waves of energy flowed from Loral's hands and over the wound at Illudar's throat.  The gaping would closed but the ragged scar would always remain.  It served Illudar well for decades to come as a distinction of battle in the political city of Felwithe.</p>

<p>The party crossed the bridge and spent a restless night on the far side.  Though they remained watchful, they never spotted the shadow that swept over the bridge behind them or the blind eyes of the Kyv that watched through sound and smell from above.  In its hand, it held a barbed arrow filled with black fire, an arrow that would steal the life of one of their members less than a day later.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Discord and War</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-11-25T16:38:45+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Everquest 2 Review</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001223.html</link>
      <description>Note: I wrote this review for both Mobhunter and EQ2 Caster&apos;s Realm. For bonus points, find four pop culture references!...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1223@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Note: I wrote this review for both Mobhunter and EQ2 Caster's Realm. For bonus points, find four pop culture references!</p>

<p>Since the days I began playing Everquest I heard about the development of Everquest 2. It took form over the years becoming less of a dream and more of a reality. I've bought games for the last twenty years now and I learned not to pay attention to previews. Ever since the days the glossy game mags touted Sewer Shark as a revolutionary step towards interactive entertainment, I learned to ignore the hype and pay attention to the game itself when released.</p>

<p>I felt different about Everquest 2 than most new games. I looked forward to its release, but I felt trepidation instead of giddy excitement. I still love Everquest. I still want to play it. I don't want my friends to leave; I don't want my guild to fall apart. SOE doesn't want players switching games either, they prefer to drag in a whole new pack of angry wizards, but that doesn't mean it won't happen. While I knew I would buy EQ2 and I was pretty sure I'd play it for a long while, part of me didn't WANT to like it. So it was with this trepidation that I opened up the beautifully packaged EQ2 box and installed the two DVDs filled with Norrath's new world.</p>

<p>For the past two weeks, young Pavlen, my half-elf rogue, reached level 15. What I've seen impresses me a lot. So today I write a review of Everquest 2 from the eyes of a long-time Everquest player.</p>

<p>Character generation alone shows the depth of this game. What impressed me most was how different two characters of the same race can look. The variations between two half-elves were as extreme as the difference between high elf, half elf, and wood elf. The wide range of hair styles, hair color, skin color, and even physical size helps create a truly unique character. The details of cheek hight, chin size, eye slant, and mouth width probably went too far; few people will see your big goofy Bruce Campbell chin as you race around the city, but more detail is always better. (That's two pop-culture references so far, Moorgard.)</p>

<p>While graphics in a game like Everquest get people to ooh and ahh at magazines, demonstrations, and videos, they matter little when compared to gameplay. Massive online games have to pay close attention to steady yet limitless progression, class desirability, class interdependence, social connectivity, and encounter variance. Graphics are important but people pay less and less attention to them the longer they play. But yes, the graphics are stunningly beautiful.</p>

<p>EQ2 includes graphic settings so advanced that EQ2 will push machines to their limits five years from now. I had to set my machine, which screams through Doom 3's most advanced settings, to performance-level to achieve a reliable framerate. This thread on setting graphic performances has a lot of good advise. One thing that will drastically increase your framerate is to set "complex shader distance" to "-1", all the way to the left, in your "Performance" menu under display options. It removes the pretty bumps from things but will result in sometimes a 20 FPS increase. It appears, however, that Everquest 2 graphics will scale well into the future. As hardware gets better, so will EQ2's appearance.</p>

<p>The quest journal is the core of Everquest 2. As I grew from a young adventurer on the Isle of Refuge to the seasoned hunter of Antonican Gnolls, I constantly added new quests into my quest journal. I didn't push to progress in levels or equipment. I pushed to find quests and complete them.</p>

<p>The quests in Everquest follow a very wide range of tasks including delivery, collection, slaughter, exploration, completing tradeskills, and mini-zone clearing. Quests arrive from anywhere. Poke a wooden boat on the beach and find a strange rune inside that leads to a whole new quest. Get a brass key from a rat and discover a quest to unlock a room full of dark elf spies. Buy books in the library to learn of long lost treasures.</p>

<p>Quests follow every path of the game; whether you want to explore, hunt, tradeskill, or travel around a city. Quests drive you to find new zones and new places. Each quest is a small story for you to follow. The game doesn't force you down any one path; you choose which of these quests you wish to pursue; but there is little reason to hunt without having a quest to drive you.</p>

<p>The low-level quests from level 5 to 7, especially the collection and delivery quests, help you learn the layout of the huge cities of Qeynos and Freeport. These delivery quests frustrate people at first but once finished, it is far easier to find one's way around.</p>

<p>Quests lead you through all forms of progression. I spend little time worrying about my equipment or level. Instead, I watch my quest journal. What quests can I accomplish fast? Which ones are too old? Are there quests that other people have? One great feature lets you peek into your group member's quest books. If they have a quest you don't, you can learn where this quest starts and get it yourself.</p>

<p>It's far too early to tell if this will continue throughout Everquest 2. Much of what I describe is also true for Everquest 1 at this level. I do not know if quests become far fewer and less rewarding at the higher levels, forcing us to go back to camping in one spot and grinding experience.</p>

<p>So far it appears that Everquest 2 embraced its title. We may very well quest forever.</p>

<p>Now lets talk a little about the cities. After taking Pavlen up to level 15, I rolled up a dark elf enchanter and took him through level 7 in Freeport. The vast difference in atmosphere between Freeport and Qeynos astounded me. While Qeynos feels like Minis Tirith or Camelot, Freeport feels like H.P Lovecraft's version of planet Gidi Prime in Dune. Huge red tendrils of power hold a vast tower floating above the torn city. What horrors lie in that tower? What power could lift such a thing? Freeport is vast and scary. I love it.</p>

<p><br />
EQ2's combat system is another big change from Everquest. Efficient combat requires a lot of interaction. Combinations of moves, a wide range of skills, and situational requirements require that a player constantly pay attention to the battle and press the right attack at the right time.</p>

<p>As a 15 rogue, nearly all of my damage comes from my variety of bending and twisting stabs and slashes. If I were to set on auto-attack and go get a pop-tart, my efficiency in group would drop to less than 10%. I have to pay attention.</p>

<p>Heroic opportunities, a mix of fighting-game style combinations and the most graphically advanced version of Simon Says, offer a collaborative dimension to combat. Some groups seem to ignore them completely, but when they work they're very exciting.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 based class dependence around archetypes. Each player decides on an archetype in two steps before picking a particular class. Each class has the basic abilities of the archetype. All scouts can improve run speed, track creatures, and hide in shadows. All priests can heal and resurrect. This breakout of four archetypes should help keep each class useful in any group. We cannot yet tell how this will work out at the higher levels, but it seems to work fine at the low.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 focuses on trying to give people more content at each level. Leveling too quickly robs the player of a lot of opportunities. Some players will always drive as high as they can go as far as they can go, like Icarus trying to reach the sun, but the best way to play this game is to enjoy it at your own pace and let leveling and gear come as they come.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 built in a lot of tools to improve social interaction. Players can invite other players into a group anywhere in a zone. Players can directly invite others from the "Looking for Group" tool. Players can target other players in a group and see their name highlighted across the zone no matter how far away. There are world-wide channels for new players, classes, and cities.</p>

<p>SOE streamlined the actions of getting into a group, finding your group, following your group, hunting in your group, and leaving your group. Every class, upon achieving citizenship in the citizenship quest, receives a daily gate to your home city helping players leave the game quickly when real life rears its ugly head and demands a sacrifice.</p>

<p>It is too early to poke big holes in a game this big but a couple of things stick out as potential problems. While raiding doesn't require more than 24 people, a limit that may radically change the forming of the dreaded uberguild, a level system for guilds promising a new path for content could alienate guilds of lower power or lower membership. This may not be a problem as long as it doesn't become the only form of progression available. EQ1 seemed to drive players into uberguilds once they reached a certain level. At the high levels joining a raiding guild became the only way to increase one's power. Still, a guild-based level system seems to stretch outside of simple social interaction and into the realm of cliques and elitism; something I detest in massive online games.</p>

<p>Everquest 2's biggest problem is time. I don't plan on quitting Everquest 1. I already filled my day with work, writing, the dreaded Tivo, and my nightly hunts in Everquest. I have yet to successfully play two massive online games at the same time. Whichever game I happen to be in, I feel like I'm missing something going on in the other.</p>

<p>Everquest 1's numbers certainly dropped in the last two weeks. However, I hear other guild leaders say that Halo 2, Half Life 2, Grand Theft Auto: San Andraes, and the holidays in general take more players away from EQ than World of Warcraft or Everquest 2. While it looks like EQ numbers dropped in the last couple of weeks, we won't know its real impact until the worlds settle and we see where everyone ends up. I wouldn't count anything as fact until early next year.</p>

<p>It is easy to look at the release of Everqust 2 as an earth-shaking event. We play in a community where the decisions of a sword or a bow bring hundreds of angry rangers to the doors of SOE. From some of the passion we read on the EQ forums and even on the comments on previous Mobhunter articles, it would seem we traveled far outside the realm of a simple game.</p>

<p>But Everquest and Everquest 2 are games. We buy them, we install them, we play them, and we talk about them. Sure, these aren't like any other games before them. No couple ever met and got married over Ratchet and Clank. Everquest is one of the best games I have seen. If my dollar is my vote, I bought two copies of the game, one as a gift, and signed up for a year-long subscription including all of the web features. The total price was over $200 but I expect a high entertainment reward for my investment. Everquest 2 is an amazing game and I look forward to watching young Pavlen progress through this vast world.<br />
Note: I wrote this review for both Mobhunter and EQ2 Caster's Realm. For bonus points, find four pop culture references!</p>

<p>Since the days I began playing Everquest I heard about the development of Everquest 2. It took form over the years becoming less of a dream and more of a reality. I've bought games for the last twenty years now and I learned not to pay attention to previews. Ever since the days the glossy game mags touted Sewer Shark as a revolutionary step towards interactive entertainment, I learned to ignore the hype and pay attention to the game itself when released.</p>

<p>I felt different about Everquest 2 than most new games. I looked forward to its release, but I felt trepidation instead of giddy excitement. I still love Everquest. I still want to play it. I don't want my friends to leave; I don't want my guild to fall apart. SOE doesn't want players switching games either, they prefer to drag in a whole new pack of angry wizards, but that doesn't mean it won't happen. While I knew I would buy EQ2 and I was pretty sure I'd play it for a long while, part of me didn't WANT to like it. So it was with this trepidation that I opened up the beautifully packaged EQ2 box and installed the two DVDs filled with Norrath's new world.</p>

<p>For the past two weeks, young Pavlen, my half-elf rogue, reached level 15. What I've seen impresses me a lot. So today I write a review of Everquest 2 from the eyes of a long-time Everquest player.</p>

<p>Character generation alone shows the depth of this game. What impressed me most was how different two characters of the same race can look. The variations between two half-elves were as extreme as the difference between high elf, half elf, and wood elf. The wide range of hair styles, hair color, skin color, and even physical size helps create a truly unique character. The details of cheek hight, chin size, eye slant, and mouth width probably went too far; few people will see your big goofy Bruce Campbell chin as you race around the city, but more detail is always better. (That's two pop-culture references so far, Moorgard.)</p>

<p>While graphics in a game like Everquest get people to ooh and ahh at magazines, demonstrations, and videos, they matter little when compared to gameplay. Massive online games have to pay close attention to steady yet limitless progression, class desirability, class interdependence, social connectivity, and encounter variance. Graphics are important but people pay less and less attention to them the longer they play. But yes, the graphics are stunningly beautiful.</p>

<p>EQ2 includes graphic settings so advanced that EQ2 will push machines to their limits five years from now. I had to set my machine, which screams through Doom 3's most advanced settings, to performance-level to achieve a reliable framerate. This thread on setting graphic performances has a lot of good advise. One thing that will drastically increase your framerate is to set "complex shader distance" to "-1", all the way to the left, in your "Performance" menu under display options. It removes the pretty bumps from things but will result in sometimes a 20 FPS increase. It appears, however, that Everquest 2 graphics will scale well into the future. As hardware gets better, so will EQ2's appearance.</p>

<p>The quest journal is the core of Everquest 2. As I grew from a young adventurer on the Isle of Refuge to the seasoned hunter of Antonican Gnolls, I constantly added new quests into my quest journal. I didn't push to progress in levels or equipment. I pushed to find quests and complete them.</p>

<p>The quests in Everquest follow a very wide range of tasks including delivery, collection, slaughter, exploration, completing tradeskills, and mini-zone clearing. Quests arrive from anywhere. Poke a wooden boat on the beach and find a strange rune inside that leads to a whole new quest. Get a brass key from a rat and discover a quest to unlock a room full of dark elf spies. Buy books in the library to learn of long lost treasures.</p>

<p>Quests follow every path of the game; whether you want to explore, hunt, tradeskill, or travel around a city. Quests drive you to find new zones and new places. Each quest is a small story for you to follow. The game doesn't force you down any one path; you choose which of these quests you wish to pursue; but there is little reason to hunt without having a quest to drive you.</p>

<p>The low-level quests from level 5 to 7, especially the collection and delivery quests, help you learn the layout of the huge cities of Qeynos and Freeport. These delivery quests frustrate people at first but once finished, it is far easier to find one's way around.</p>

<p>Quests lead you through all forms of progression. I spend little time worrying about my equipment or level. Instead, I watch my quest journal. What quests can I accomplish fast? Which ones are too old? Are there quests that other people have? One great feature lets you peek into your group member's quest books. If they have a quest you don't, you can learn where this quest starts and get it yourself.</p>

<p>It's far too early to tell if this will continue throughout Everquest 2. Much of what I describe is also true for Everquest 1 at this level. I do not know if quests become far fewer and less rewarding at the higher levels, forcing us to go back to camping in one spot and grinding experience.</p>

<p>So far it appears that Everquest 2 embraced its title. We may very well quest forever.</p>

<p>Now lets talk a little about the cities. After taking Pavlen up to level 15, I rolled up a dark elf enchanter and took him through level 7 in Freeport. The vast difference in atmosphere between Freeport and Qeynos astounded me. While Qeynos feels like Minis Tirith or Camelot, Freeport feels like H.P Lovecraft's version of planet Gidi Prime in Dune. Huge red tendrils of power hold a vast tower floating above the torn city. What horrors lie in that tower? What power could lift such a thing? Freeport is vast and scary. I love it.</p>

<p><br />
EQ2's combat system is another big change from Everquest. Efficient combat requires a lot of interaction. Combinations of moves, a wide range of skills, and situational requirements require that a player constantly pay attention to the battle and press the right attack at the right time.</p>

<p>As a 15 rogue, nearly all of my damage comes from my variety of bending and twisting stabs and slashes. If I were to set on auto-attack and go get a pop-tart, my efficiency in group would drop to less than 10%. I have to pay attention.</p>

<p>Heroic opportunities, a mix of fighting-game style combinations and the most graphically advanced version of Simon Says, offer a collaborative dimension to combat. Some groups seem to ignore them completely, but when they work they're very exciting.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 based class dependence around archetypes. Each player decides on an archetype in two steps before picking a particular class. Each class has the basic abilities of the archetype. All scouts can improve run speed, track creatures, and hide in shadows. All priests can heal and resurrect. This breakout of four archetypes should help keep each class useful in any group. We cannot yet tell how this will work out at the higher levels, but it seems to work fine at the low.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 focuses on trying to give people more content at each level. Leveling too quickly robs the player of a lot of opportunities. Some players will always drive as high as they can go as far as they can go, like Icarus trying to reach the sun, but the best way to play this game is to enjoy it at your own pace and let leveling and gear come as they come.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 built in a lot of tools to improve social interaction. Players can invite other players into a group anywhere in a zone. Players can directly invite others from the "Looking for Group" tool. Players can target other players in a group and see their name highlighted across the zone no matter how far away. There are world-wide channels for new players, classes, and cities.</p>

<p>SOE streamlined the actions of getting into a group, finding your group, following your group, hunting in your group, and leaving your group. Every class, upon achieving citizenship in the citizenship quest, receives a daily gate to your home city helping players leave the game quickly when real life rears its ugly head and demands a sacrifice.</p>

<p>It is too early to poke big holes in a game this big but a couple of things stick out as potential problems. While raiding doesn't require more than 24 people, a limit that may radically change the forming of the dreaded uberguild, a level system for guilds promising a new path for content could alienate guilds of lower power or lower membership. This may not be a problem as long as it doesn't become the only form of progression available. EQ1 seemed to drive players into uberguilds once they reached a certain level. At the high levels joining a raiding guild became the only way to increase one's power. Still, a guild-based level system seems to stretch outside of simple social interaction and into the realm of cliques and elitism; something I detest in massive online games.</p>

<p>Everquest 2's biggest problem is time. I don't plan on quitting Everquest 1. I already filled my day with work, writing, the dreaded Tivo, and my nightly hunts in Everquest. I have yet to successfully play two massive online games at the same time. Whichever game I happen to be in, I feel like I'm missing something going on in the other.</p>

<p>Everquest 1's numbers certainly dropped in the last two weeks. However, I hear other guild leaders say that Halo 2, Half Life 2, Grand Theft Auto: San Andraes, and the holidays in general take more players away from EQ than World of Warcraft or Everquest 2. While it looks like EQ numbers dropped in the last couple of weeks, we won't know its real impact until the worlds settle and we see where everyone ends up. I wouldn't count anything as fact until early next year.</p>

<p>It is easy to look at the release of Everqust 2 as an earth-shaking event. We play in a community where the decisions of a sword or a bow bring hundreds of angry rangers to the doors of SOE. From some of the passion we read on the EQ forums and even on the comments on previous Mobhunter articles, it would seem we traveled far outside the realm of a simple game.</p>

<p>But Everquest and Everquest 2 are games. We buy them, we install them, we play them, and we talk about them. Sure, these aren't like any other games before them. No couple ever met and got married over Ratchet and Clank. Everquest is one of the best games I have seen. If my dollar is my vote, I bought two copies of the game, one as a gift, and signed up for a year-long subscription including all of the web features. The total price was over $200 but I expect a high entertainment reward for my investment. Everquest 2 is an amazing game and I look forward to watching young Pavlen progress through this vast world.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
22 November 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-11-23T21:22:02+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caster&apos;s Realm: How To Find A Group</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001231.html</link>
      <description>A reoccurring problem shows up on the EQ Live and community forums from time to time. Often it leads to...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1231@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>A reoccurring problem shows up on the EQ Live and community forums from time to time.  Often it leads to lengthy and tiring debates about class balance or the inevitable doomsday prediction that Everquest is finally (after five years of inaccurate doomsday predictions) dead.  This problem surrounds the single action of just about every player (except wizards): finding a group.</p>

<p>It seems these days like becomes more and more difficult to find a group.  Perhaps this is a fact and perhaps it is simply perception.  The release of LDON gave us the perfect period of time for finding a good hunting group.  LDON progression took place in ninety minute periods, the LFG tool had been out for awhile, and LDON dungeons offered good experience and loot rewards in one place.</p>

<p>Since then, some find Omens and Gates to be less group-friendly.  A larger level limit means players spread across a larger level spectrum.   Some days it can take hours to find a good group with which to hunt and for those below 60, it can sometimes be impossible.</p>

<p>We still desire to group, however, and this guide gives you the tips you need to help yourself find and hunt in a group.</p>

<p>Step 1: Use the LFG tool</p>

<p>Though released years ago, many people still do not use the LFG tool.  The LFG tool is perhaps the greatest tool to help players find and hunt in groups.  Use the LFG tool often, use the comments to sell yourself above the others in your level bracket, announce the number of AAs you have, and use the LFG tool to start up your own hunting groups.  Teach others to use the LFG tool and use it yourself when you need to fill in that one last spot.  Only through a lot of use by a lot of people will the LFG tool help everyone find groups.</p>

<p>Step 2: Build Your Own Group</p>

<p>Instead of using your time LFG writing nasty board postings about the end of Norrath, use that time to build your own group.  Ignore specific classes and instead pick from the four basic EQ architypes; healers, armor, crowd control, and damage dealers.  Ignore that perfect group for a group of mixed classes that may teach you a thing or two about group composition.  Use the LFG tool to find these new hunters.  Have a destination and a plan to help people arrive.  Pick a hunting area easy to get to.  Keep the group moving and delay as little as possible.  Above all, be nice to folks and remember that you're here to have fun with other players.</p>

<p>Step 3: Travel to the zone in which you wish to hunt</p>

<p>Sometimes people don't use the LFG channel when they seek a new member for their group.  They often look in-zone to see who's nearby.  Go to the zone in which you wish to hunt or go to the zone with the most characters around your level.  Being local gives you a leg up on those who would need five to ten minutes of travel time to get a group.</p>

<p>Step 4: Be Familiar With The Lands</p>

<p>Use your time LFG by exploring the lands you wish to hunt in.  Learn how to get from zone to zone.  Use invis potions (or your native ability if you're lucky enough to have it) to help you learn how to get from zone to zone.  Use the in-game map system and load it with new maps for the zones not included.  The faster you can get from zone to zone, the more desirable you will be in a group.  Waste not that time sitting on a rock waiting to get invited on a hunt, use it to learn of the lands around you.</p>

<p>Step 5: Advertise</p>

<p>Advertise yourself in a few different ways when you seek a group.  Use the LFG tool mentioned above.  Use "/ooc" to announce your desire for a group in a well-populated hunting zone of your level.  Join large open channels on your server that may have group leaders seeking players.  Join alliances that offer a pool of players around your level and a channel to find them in.  When you get to a zone with a lot of full groups, send a tell to each group leader and ask to get on their list.  Most groups will keep a list of players to join them, it is an old-school method of grouping we old fellas had to use before the LFG tool was out.  It still helps today.</p>

<p>Step 6: Join a Grouping Guild</p>

<p>Seek out and join a guild of characters around your level that enjoy grouping.  Many groups seek members of their own guild first; the larger the guild, the more likely members become available for a hunt.  Seek a guild with the same desires as you and you will have an easier time finding a group.</p>

<p>Step 7: Experiment with Different Group Configurations</p>

<p>I mention this earlier, but experimenting with different group configurations may lead to wonderful results.  I remember battling in Sebilis with five necromancers and a cleric.  I have seen the strangest groups defeat amazing encounters.  Ignore the stereotypes and grab any five people for a bit of fun.  You may not end up victorious in the Muramite Proving Ground's hardest trials, but the results may surprise you.</p>

<p>Above all, take an active role in seeking a group.  Finding a group can be hard work sometimes, especially at lower and mid levels.  Don't despair, don't assume it's because you're class X and everyone seeks Class Y.  Don't assume you need only one particular class and don't be afraid to experiment with strange group configurations.  If you follow all of these steps and use all possible options to find a hunting group, you will have much better chances than simply putting up your LFG tag and watching reruns of Dynasty on the Tivo.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
18 November 2004</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Caster&apos;s Realm Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-11-18T17:51:27+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: November News Roundup</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001218.html</link>
      <description>Everquest 2 hit the shelves on Tuesday and the world didn&apos;t end. Few people know exactly what will happen over...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1218@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Everquest 2 hit the shelves on Tuesday and the world didn't end. Few people know exactly what will happen over the next six months but numbers in EQ will no doubt be low throughout the next few weeks. For the raiding guilds that require 54 people all night every night, this might end up causing a bit of trouble but for the single-group pickup hunters, life shouldn't be so bad. There will be less groups overall but each group still needs six members. Spots that were once over camped may open up. The great hoards of treasure falling out of the lands of Kuua should distribute to fewer people, giving each one a greater chance for a nice item or rune of power.</p>

<p>Not all communication methods are up and running yet between EQ and EQ2 but cross-game tells and EQ2 channel joining from EQ1 works. From within EQ you can send a tell to your EQ2 friend by typing "[tell eq2.antonia_bayle.pavlen hail" where antonia_bayle is the servername he or she is on and pavlen is his or her character name. You can send a tell from EQ2 to Everquest by typing "/tell eq.quellious.loral hello". I hoped that this would be a little easier. With all of the various / ; [ ways to send tells it is easy to get confused. One would think, with the various server names, that we wouldn't have to put the game title in front to send a tell. "/tell antonia_bayle.pavlen" has enough information to tell the vast self-aware machine farm at SOE that I want to send a tell to EQ2. "[tell eq2.antonia_bayle.pavlen" makes me feel like I'm writing my own email headers.</p>

<p>Moorgard announced that you can also send tells to Star Wars Galaxies characters using the same method: "/tell swg.servername.charname message". I don't know anyone playing SWG so I couldn't test it out.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 players cannot yet subscribe to EQ1 channels but you can subscribe to EQ2 channels within EQ1 by typing "[join eq2.servername.channel" (there's that stupid bracket again). Hopefully we'll see EQ1 channel subscribing from within EQ2 soon.</p>

<p>I plan to write a full review and comparison of Everquest 2 during a slow news week but I love it so far. It won't drag me off of EQLive any time soon, but the quest system is very rewarding and I hope we see a system like it in EQLive sometime soon.</p>

<p>SOE released the details of the backflagging solution this week. Some mobs, like those in Plane of Time, drop items that let previously unflagged players become flagged. Some zones require a single-group quest once an unflagged player acquired a quest piece from a raid-level mob inside the zone they wish to enter. Most zones will soon have an 85-15 rule, allowing 15% of a raid to enter a zone without needing a flag. There will be a variety of other quests to backflag people for lower-tier Planes of Power zones. Read the full backflagging report from my summit friend, Emil.</p>

<p>This is a fine solution for backflagging. It will not help unflagged groups get flags, however. At this point in the game's life, I don't know that that matters. Unflagged raiding organizations now have a wide range of unflagged raids to conquer. Gates and Omens offer a lot of unflagged raid-level content with rewards higher than Plane of Time. I still see many guilds or raiding groups banging their heads on the walls of Time and losing members in the process. With the probable drop in members due to EQ2, Grand Theft Auto, Halo 2, WoW, and the holidays in general, an enterprising raid force would be wise to try new targets with greater rewards. It is also a good time to open your doors a little bit and let some typical non-raiders into your raids.</p>

<p>Grumbuk, SOE's resident coder at the Fan Faire, wrote a lengthy report on some current collision changes. We can expect a few performance tweaks in areas that previously gave us a bit of trouble and getting out of that chilly water should finally come a bit easier.</p>

<p>A series of strange new spells, all available to level 20 priests and casters, hit the dark pages of Lucy on the 9th. These spells, called "blessings" each correspond to one of the known gods. When cast, these spells summon a strange unknown item. If I had to guess, and it is probably wishful thinking on my part, I would say they could summon a single-charge, no-rent gate device usable by typical non-gaters. If it isn't, well, it should be.</p>

<p>Caster's Realm, one of the more popular EQ websites, underwent a change of command. Baelish, the previous administrator, moved on to help SOE develop the Station Players website for EQ2. My friend Gemdiver, the previous administrator of the wizard community forum, Graffe's, now maintains Caster's Realm and plans to take it to all new levels. He recruited a few community writers to write content for the site including your favorite cleric who started with a Raidleader's Guide to Raiding posted late last week. Now if I can just convince Gemdiver not to burn Plane of Knowledge to the ground, I could make real progress.</p>

<p>It's been a slow couple of weeks since the Fan Faire but in December we can expect a patch or two with some exciting changes. In the mean time, help save the Dragorns from the plight of their Muramite overlords and get some fine armor in the process.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 November 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-11-11T14:53:27+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 1: Leaving Home</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001216.html</link>
      <description>Pavlen stood in the doorway of his small room where he had spent eighteen years of his life. His eyes...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1216@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Pavlen stood in the doorway of his small room where he had spent eighteen years of his life.  His eyes picked up every little detail and each detail held a story.  It was a ten foot room holding a lifetime of memories.  He looked at the bird skull hanging over his bed and remembered his father's cry of excitement when Pavlen had shot the flying vulture with a slingshot.  He looked at the blanket and remembered the story of his mother knitting it while she hobbled around with young Pavlen still in her belly.  He looked at the rocks he had collected as a boy, hiking into the northern mountains with his father.  He wasn't sure if he would ever see this room again and though he hadn't left yet, he already missed it.</p>

<p>Pavlen stepped outside of his family's farmhouse and into the chilled autumn air.  Large gray clouds billowed across the sky.  The autumn breeze blew dead leaves against the log house.  Pavlen smelled the clean burning wood of the house's stove in that air.  Pavlen pulled his cloak tight around his shoulders.  His parents stood on a hill nearby, their bodies contrasted against the gray sky.  They stood hand in hand and the sight nearly broke Pavlen's heart.  It was a sight he would remember for the rest of his life.  His mother, tall and slender, stood straight and smooth, her raven hair blowing over her pointed ears and creamy skin.  His father slouched slighty from a lifetime behind a plow but a wide grin and shining eyes filled the stout man with life.  His father, nearly ten inches taller than his high-elven wife, wore a wide-brimmed leather hat older than Pavlen.</p>

<p>For nearly all of his eighteen years Pavlen dreamed of adventure.  He talked of traveling to the reaches of Antonica ever since his father read him tales of lore when Pavlen was just a child.  Now, with his leather pack full of provisions over one shoulder and a plan to travel east to the city of Qeynos, Pavlen didn't want to go.  It would take only one reason or request from his parents for him to stay.  They gave him none.</p>

<p>His mother's deep brown eyes spoke volumes.  She knew the danger of sending her son into the wilds of Norrath.  She knew the danger of keeping him home was worse.  Breaking his spirit of adventure would kill him as surly as a knife.  He might live sixty years if he stayed home but those years would be hollow.  She smiled at her son and brushed his brown hair over his own pointed ear, her people's legacy to him.  She smiled and hugged him tightly.  When she broke the embrace she handed him another leather satchel.  Three books, two large and one small, sat inside along with three quills and a bottle of black ink.  Pavlen recognized the two larger books.  His parents both read these books to him many times and he read them himself many more.  The tales of adventure within fueled his fire for adventure and lead him to this day.  He opened the small leatherbound book to discover a blank journal.  Pavlen marveled at the ivory paper threadbound within the small black book.  The paper alone must have cost a month's work at the farm.</p>

<p>"Now you can write your own tales."  Pavlen's mother smiled at him again and a tear fell down her ivory cheek.  Pavlen's father sniffed and Pavlen embraced him.  His father kissed him on the cheek and Pavlen smiled at the way his father's whiskers ticked his skin.</p>

<p>"I love you, Son."</p>

<p>"I love you too, Dad."</p>

<p>Pavlen held the embrace a long while and then stepped back.</p>

<p>"Go."  Pavlen's mother smiled and pointed west.  Pavlen tightened his leather pack on his back and took his first steps as an adventurer of Norrath.</p>

<p>Above him, the shattered moon of Luclin marked the broken lands that lay ahead.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>The Tales of Pavlen</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-11-10T12:53:31+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caster&apos;s Realm: A Raidleader&apos;s Guide to Raiding</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001230.html</link>
      <description>&quot;He who wishes to be obeyed must know how to command. &quot; - Niccolo Machiavelli Gray clouds blanket the sky,...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1230@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>"He who wishes to be obeyed must know how to command. " - Niccolo Machiavelli</p>

<p>Gray clouds blanket the sky, blocking the carnage of war from the eyes of the gods.  Snow falls on grim faces.  Gloved hands clutch the hardened wooden handles of spears and swords.  Cold eyes, alive now but perhaps soon dead, stare over the dunes of white snow.  A rumble grows in the distance.  It gets closer, followed by the rings of armored plates crashing together.  The first giant appears over the horizon.  Another appears beside it.  Then another and another.  They are huge.  They roar the name of Rallos Zek and raise their own swords, ten feet long and sharp as razors.  One adventurer holds his sword high into the air and returns the roar.  A battle explodes in sweat and steel and blood.</p>

<p>At one time or another in our paths as adventurers on Norrath we might find ourselves at the lead of one such battle.  Few of us are born into leadership as the warlords of Felwithe are.  Sometimes we find ourselves leading three dozen people without an ounce of experience under our belt.  Sometimes a guide like this is all we have.</p>

<p>This guide outlines a crash course in leading a raid.  Rather than specific tactics against various beasts, this guide outlines the strategies and basic tips for leading a successful raid.  For many powerful warlords, this guide will help little.  The following guidelines are written to last the ages, whether you target Emperor Crush or Fennin Ro.  Let us begin.</p>

<p>Plan Ahead</p>

<p>Before any successful raid can begin, one must seek all knowledge of this raid.  Read message boards, post questions, seek answers from the great oracles of Google.  Most have fought your battle before, learn from their triumphs and their mistakes.  There is little worse than a raid leader who does not understand his or her own raid.  Do not fear asking for help from those who have battled what you soon face.  Add an advisor to your command group.  Ask for help from them, and them alone, through tells or in a group chat.  Do not ask an entire raid for advise or you make your ignorance clear to all and that leads quickly to failure.</p>

<p>Decide Swiftly and Stay with that Decision.</p>

<p>Be decisive in all of your actions.  Choose a path and stick to it.  Know exactly what it is you seek and exactly how you plan to get there.  Do not lead by bureaucracy, only you command.  Do not allow any other to speak for you except for a single delegated second-in-comand.  If voices rise up in protest, crush them down or let them leave to their own path.  You lead raids against Norrath's mightiest beasts, do not let someone's loud voice quiet your own.</p>

<p>Start On Time</p>

<p>Choose a time for your raid and start within 30 minutes of the start time.  If you do not have the forces to start within 30 minutes of your start time, do not waste your time or the time of everyone who showed up on time by waiting for stragglers.  Choose another time and cancel the raid.  Remember that every person at your event spends their time on top of your own.  A single hour raid with 30 people takes up 30 hours of people's time.  Do not waste 15 people-hours waiting for people to log in.  Do not insult the promptness of those who showed up on time by bowing down  to those who do not.  Be prepared to cancel your raid if you cannot start on time.</p>

<p>End On Time</p>

<p>"The way of the warrior is resolute acceptance of death." - Miyamoto Musashi</p>

<p>Have an end goal and an estimated time.  Tell people how long a raid should take and end it on time.  Do not drag those who would fight with you through hours of unscheduled events.  Do not change the focus of a raid half way in and end up turning a two hour raid into a six hour one.  Generally, plan all raids for under two hours.  People won't want to battle much longer than that.</p>

<p>Delegate</p>

<p>There are many jobs on a raid and no one person should do them all.  Delegate out the portions not requiring your personal attention.  Use people you trust to assist you with individual tasks.  Assign a second-in-command to lead the raid should you die or go linkdead.  Make sure he or she understands what the raid needs to accomplish at all times and is prepared to step into leadership at a moment's notice.  Assign a scout, a puller, a main tank, a loot distributer, and group leaders.  Choose people you trust.  Make sure raiders use the chain of command starting with their group leader first, the second-in-command next, and finally you.</p>

<p>Move</p>

<p>"Fixed fortifications are monuments to the stupidity of man." - George S. Patton.</p>

<p>Always keep a raid in constant motion.  Always have beasts in the camp to fight.  Stay still for as little time as necessary.  Do not waste too much time buffing or planning.  You should already be prepared and ready to do what you need to.  Keep a raid constantly moving and attacking.  The more you wait, the less people will be ready when you do.  Avoid people going afk by keeping them constantly in battle or constantly running.  A raid should be a whirlwind of motion from the minute it starts until the minute it ends.</p>

<p>Define Goals and Rewards</p>

<p>Before a raid is called, know the goal of the raid.  Keep this goal in mind at all times and stick to it.  Do not change a raid's goal.  If treasure is involved, make sure it is clear to all raiders how treasure will be distributed.  Make sure your treasure distributer, the person you delegated treasure handling to, understands clearly how loot will be distributed.  Should loot be distributed randomly, roll on it as soon as you can, do not wait.</p>

<p>Compose Balanced Groups<br />
Know how classes should be distributed within each group and use the "raid lock" feature to rearrange groups to the way you want them.  Build a command group, a group with your delegates, scouts, advisers, and primary armored bladeswinger.  Most groups should have a healer to keep an eye on a group's health but the rest of the group may change depending on the situations.  Know beforehand how groups should be balanced.</p>

<p>"Know your enemy and know yourself and you will be successful in 100 battles" - Sun Tzu, the Art of War</p>

<p>Know Your Tools</p>

<p>There are many in-game tools to lead raids and we gain new ones often. Understand how these tools work.  Spend some time learning about them from other successful raid leaders.  Read up on new features.  Experiment with them before you lead a raid.  Use the raid window, the "raid lock" feature, and the new raid voice macros to assist you with your battles.</p>

<p>Think forward</p>

<p>When planning a raid, plan raids that others have not done before.  You will not get people to come on an event that may be many years old.  Our world constantly shifts and changes and it is important that we change with it.  Find new fun events that few have done before and always keep your eye forward to new events.  You will watch your ranks swell if you continually fight forward.</p>

<p>Don't Let Perfect Be the Enemy of Good</p>

<p>"The Marines don't want robots, they want killers." - Full Metal Jacket</p>

<p>Keep control of your raid but not too much control.  You don't want to waste time on pointless exercises  in discipline.  Keep your raid hungry and make sure they stay focused but remember that they are each individuals.  As long as the raid is fun and successful, little else matters.  If you continually move your raid, your raiders will have little choice but to follow through with you.  If you stay still, they are more likely to run off on their own or sit where they are when you need them to move.</p>

<p>These are just a few guidelines for leading a successful raid.  The best way to learn how to raid is to raid.  As you join other raids, watch how people lead them.  Whether good or bad, you will learn much watching the leadership of others.  Raids come in many varieties.  No one set of rules will work for all possible circumstances.  Use the rules above and your chances for success increase.  Ignore them and the folly is yours.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
4 November 2004</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Caster&apos;s Realm Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-11-04T17:49:48+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: October 2004 Fan Faire Report</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001213.html</link>
      <description>The following article was written for both Mobhunter and Caster&apos;s Realm. I return from the Bayou, black notebook laden with...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1213@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>The following article was written for both Mobhunter and Caster's Realm.</p>

<p>I return from the Bayou, black notebook laden with facts, details, rumors and the philosophies from the silver temple of the west. SOE put on a fine event, as entertaining as it was informative. SOE developers and staff made themselves available throughout the three-night event, happy to discuss anything the fans could bring up.</p>

<p>If you care not to hear of the festivities, skip down right into the juicy morsels of goodness below. If you have not been to a Fan Faire, however, it is quite a treat. There's always a bit of nervousness going to such an event. We all know each other in-game but to meet face to face can be a bit daunting. Non stop contests, presentations, late-night gatherings, and panels filled out three days perfectly. It wasn't uncommon to see three fellows walking down Burbon Street, hurricanes high, shouting "hail" at everyone they saw. "Train to Zone" they'd shout as a pack of bikers drives by with grim looks on their bearded faces.</p>

<p>Your head swims with after-images as you fly back home. Brenlo hurls sharp-edged boxes at the heads of players in the manifestation of his ultimate Community Relations dream. Vannoth teaches players how to train zones ("OMGZ RUN") and Cyb3r barbarian females in Everquest 2 ("OMGZ YUO USED ME!"). The costumes, the contests, the dialog, the tales of adventure, the personalities; they all add up to a weekend packed with enough memories to last six months. If you ever get a chance to go to a Fan Faire, take it.</p>

<p>Ok, now on to the juicy morsels of goodness.</p>

<p>A large amount of the Fan Faire focused on Everquest 2. By now most people have heard of the November 8 release date. SOE had planned on this date for some time; it was not a knee jerk reaction to the rumored simultaneous release date of World of Warcraft. Who really believes those EBGames dates anyway? Shame on you.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 showed up everywhere. A 24 hour Everquest 2 contest awarded an Alienware PC to the player with the highest level and experience. Over 30 machines were open for Fan Faire attendees to play. Every Fan Faire attendee earned an EQ2 beta account upon registration. I will leave it to other reviewers to discuss the details of Everquest 2 but I will discuss a few interesting tidbits.</p>

<p>I finally met my predecessor, Moorgard. During our discussion he mentioned that EQ2 went through a series of focus tests and usability tests for both new and veteran players. I hope Everquest goes through such tests if it has not done so already. Making the game easy to start and play is a key to bringing in new customers.</p>

<p>SOE demonstrated the new Station Players website for Everquest 2 players. The website offers a wide range of excellent features including guild website tools, Magelo-like player profiles, web-based guild chat, and server community forums. There's a lot to like and demonstrations are available on the EQ2 website. SOE intends to implement these features for all SOE games including EQLive in the next six to eight months.</p>

<p>Now let us dig into EQLive news.</p>

<p>In the next patch or two, the task system will gain over one thousand new tasks including tasks up to level 70. Tasks will include a variety of new actions such as foraging and fishing on top of the existing kill 10, collect 4, talk to an NPC, or visit a location. SOE plans to balance many old tasks as well. Kaikachi, the task developer, reinforced that he uses bug reports and feedback to balance tasks so make sure to /bug or /feedback them if you find a task that doesn't work.</p>

<p>Backflagging came up more than once this event and SOE appears to have a viable solution in the works. SOE will extend the 85-15 flagging rule, the rule that allows 15% of a raid to enter a flagged zone without the flag, to Time and many Gates zones. Raid mobs within flagged zones will drop one or two quest items that let unflagged members begin a quest to receive a permanent flag for that zone. Flags achieved this way will not backflag characters for previous zones. A Time flag quest, for example, will not award a Fire flag.</p>

<p>Rashere, the primary Alternate Ability developer, has a list of AAs to review. He already wrote a spreadsheet of point cost reductions for Gates AAs. A piece of code will soon let players receive AA refunds without losing AAs over 30 should they zone. It will not let players store more than 30 new AAs, however. Players who already purchased AAs at the higher cost will receive the difference; they will not get a full refund for abilities unless the ability itself changes.</p>

<p>During the "Maintain a Living World" panel a pompous jackass of a moderator brought up the Everquest's Economy. According to Lyndro, tributes helped take money out of the economy but targeted the wrong players. High-end players hold most of the money in Norrath but rarely use tributes. Items like horses only take money out of the economy once. SOE designed systems like trade skills to take money out of the economy but SOE always considers new solutions.</p>

<p>SOE does not plan to add new LDON loot. Like Kunark and Velious, SOE intends players who get through the content of LDON to travel onwards to expansions like Omens and Gates. LDON is not intended to offer progression through the entire range of the game. Now that Omens offers fine equipment to single-group hunters, I agree with their assessment.</p>

<p>SOE plans to continue changing hot-zones to get players traveling out to old world zones. From time to time they may add Fabled-like items to old-world content like they did with the fifth anniversary. These changes, on top of epic quests and tasks, help get new players to older world zones.</p>

<p>Rogue's Hour, the first in a series of four planned Everquest-based novels, hit the shelves a couple of weeks ago and Scott Ciencin signed books and discussed future publishing plans. Each of the next three books will come out every three months including one by Elane Cunningham, the author of many fine Forgotten Realms books. These books help add new depth to our world and I look forward to their continued release.</p>

<p>Class tuning came up many times and SOE has plans to address class issues. SOE will release class descriptions, not full class definitions, which contain a lot of SOE internal statistics. SOE community relations folk meet often with developers to help make sure the class issues get discussed and to make sure each class has a clear group role and is fun to play.</p>

<p>I spent a time far shorter than I would have liked speaking with Vahlar regarding lore and story progression. I mentioned my desire to see the Muramites invading Norrath and she assured me that some big changes would hit Norrath in coming weeks. SOE heard the player's cry for a more cohesive storyline, one built from original EQ lore and plans to improve this. The return of Firiona Vie and the Lifeguide to the storyline begins this return to older lore.</p>

<p>SOE already began the design of a new EQLive expansion but details are scarce. Lyndro stated clearly that expansions will follow the Kunark, Velious, and Omens trend for one single locked zone, not a series of progressive locked zones such as those we faced in Planes of Power and Gates of Discord. SOE rebuilt much of Omens, far more than I expected, after the guild summit in June. SOE hears what players ask for and they heard us very well with Omens. I have high hopes and look forward to January's announcement.</p>

<p>The future looks bright. We see many exciting changes on the way and every SOE employee I spoke to said many of the things I wanted to hear. EQ2 presents a huge unknown variable but it is clear that no SOE employee on either team wants EQ players quitting one for the other. I do not see EQ2 affecting EQLive's future in any way but for the better.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
2 November 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-11-02T12:33:06+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 53: Natimbi</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001209.html</link>
      <description>Violet clouds swam across the dark sky. Hills rolled green and thick over the lands. The temples of the Taelosians...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1209@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Violet clouds swam across the dark sky.  Hills rolled green and thick over the lands.  The temples of the Taelosians lay scattered across the hills.  Each ancient temple was a vault of priceless and unseen magic.  Statues to gods long forgotten guarded the once sealed doors of the temples.  Infesting these temples of nobility and light were the Muramites.</p>

<p>They stood in sharp contrast to the beauty around them.  Powerful beasts of orange skin and white hair roared in battle lust.  Huge werewolves the size of giants wielded massive axes.  Scarred gray-skinned assassins knocked barbed arrows in huge bows.  And behind them all the black-robed priests floated on atrophied legs with telepathic serpent enchanters slithering at their sides.  Few worlds could endure the perfect savagery of the Muramite hoards.  There was only one last hope for the survival of Taelosia, the adventurers of Norrath.</p>

<p>Loral stepped onto the stone dock of Natimbi.  He brushed back a rogue lock of his white-gray hair and looked out over the strange lands and the sky above them.  A breeze of hot air blew over Loral from the deep river valley.  Every sight, every sound, and every smell told Loral one thing.</p>

<p>He was no longer on Norrath.</p>

<p>Loral traveled to the outer planes many times.  Weeks in the Plane of Nightmare, Disease, and Torment trained Loral's senses to detect the changes between worlds.  The differences were far more subtle here than in the alien worlds of the outer planes but they were there.  Loral could not place when he shifted out of Norrath and into this strange world.  Somewhere in the black night and unrelenting storm of the Abysmal Sea they had sailed across the ethereal plane and to this alien land.  Perhaps the Grozmok Stone led them across the gray spaces between worlds.</p>

<p>Dozens of adventurers gathered at the familiar quarter-dome bent-wood Wayfarer tents.  Loral saw a small elf-like being half the size of Loral with a rounded face, almond-shaped eyes, tall pointed ears, and white hair pulled back into a topknot.  Loral recognized the creature as a Taelosian, the small native beings of this war-torn land.</p>

<p>"The Wayfarer's wave him like a flag."  Loral heard the gruff voice and  turned to the speaker, a human swordsman, who stepped up next to the elven cleric. "Come see the plight of Taelosia and bleed for their liberation."  Deep scars, only weeks old, lined the man's face.  The armored swordsman's left arm was gone at the elbow.  "The Kings of Freeport had a parade for us when we left.  They gave us jewels and flowers and told us what a great adventure lies beyond the seas.  Then this land devoured us."</p>

<p>The swordsman looked to Loral with dead gray eyes.  "I left for the lost temples with seventeen companions.  We made it as far as the Hanging Gardens.  Four of the demon-dogs, the Ukuns, hit us like a wall of knives.  Only I and two others survived. </p>

<p>"They sent us here to seek the power of Taelosia but we find only death."  The man walked up the stone gangway and stepped onto the Wayfarer's landing skiff.  He sank to the benches on each side of the craft, his shoulders sagging and his head down.</p>

<p>A cry from the camp shot a line of adrenaline down Loral's spine.  People in the camp shouted and pointed across the river.  Loral looked in the direction of their horrified gazes and saw the hills of Natimbi.</p>

<p>One of the hills moved.</p>

<p>Loral shook his hand and looked again.  It wasn't until the huge beast turned its head that Loral understood what he saw.  It stretched over two hundred meters from tale to head, and naerly forty meters wide across the chest.  It took four huge steps.  The vibration in the earth followed a few seconds later.  It tilted its head to the sky and opened its massive mouth.</p>

<p>"My lady Tunare."  In response to Loral's whispered prayer, the beast's cry broke across the camp like thunder.  Wooden struts in the tent quivered.  Rocks on the shore cracked against each other.  People dropped to their knees and covered their ears.</p>

<p>"Impressive, ain't she?"  Loral turned and relief flooded into him.  Stonehewer the stout dwarven paladin stood leaning on the cross guard of his double-bladed sword.  The high-elf, Illudar, stood behind the dwarf holding his own sword over his blue-armored shoulder by the scabbard in a style known to the swordsmen of the east.  Like Loral, Illudar's hair was pulled back in an efficient battle ready pony-tail.  Both of the Healers United paladins smiled at Loral's expression.</p>

<p>"They call her the Queen." Another of the creature's cries rolled over the camp.</p>

<p>Loral could almost see the black poison of the Muramites flowing over these once green lands, creating mutated beasts like this one from simple rock-lizards.  Somewhere deep in the mountains a rift to a world of darkness spilled poison and shadow over Taelosia like a festering sewer.</p>

<p>Loral looked to the Taelosian in the Wayfarer's camp.  This land could be Faydwer.  The Taelosians could just as easily be Koada'Dal.  Perhaps in fifteen or twenty years it would be Felwithe that filled with the diseased clouds of the Muramites.</p>

<p>Loral saw the look of defeat and sadness in the eyes of the Taelosian.  Perhaps Felwithe was right to send him here.</p>

<p>"There is a city entrance to the north-west."  Stonehewer seemed to have already concluded this debate for himself.  The fire in Illudar's eyes spoke of the same conclusion.  "The Taelosian's call it Qinimi."</p>

<p>Loral looked again at the massive beast standing on the horizon of the alien landscape, a beast that would crush Felwithe to the ground in a day.</p>

<p>"Let us go."</p>

<p>The three armored adventurers began their trek along the foreign shores of Natimbi.  They did not see the shadow flowing through the cracks between rocks that followed behind them.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject></dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-10-26T19:43:48+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>


  </channel>
</rss>

