<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>I&apos;ve done Karazhan about three times now. Mostly I find it hard to get into a good enough group</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I&apos;ve done Karazhan about three times now. Mostly I find it hard to get into a good enough group to clear it. I&apos;m in a pretty big guild that has about three or four regular groups but all of them are filled up. Pickup groups are usually nasty in attitude and quick to break up.

So instead, when I want to play for under two hours, I work on dailies. I just got my epic flying mount and am working on the absolutely awful Netherdrake quests.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I have to agree with the general sentiment that this review seems inconherent, while at the same tim</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I have to agree with the general sentiment that this review seems inconherent, while at the same time contradicting your statements in previous articles.  

1. Focus on Solo Play

Richard Bartle is essentially only correct in one aspect: World of Warcraft has established a paradigm that no one will defy, and as failed games like Vanguard show, consumers exclusively prefer.  However, the notion that &quot;rich relationships&quot; were somehow an i</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I think I have to agree with Kaelon&apos;s diagnosis that your guild just isn&apos;t working for you</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I think I have to agree with Kaelon&apos;s diagnosis that your guild just isn&apos;t working for you, but let me suggest an alternative treatment: leave your 70 hunter in the guild, but level up a new character from a more group-friendly class. If what you want to do is play with other people, you&apos;ll have a much easier time doing so as a tank or healer. Then be sure to fight the temptation to follow the path of least resistance and spend you</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Come join my guild on Icecrown, you would be more than welcome!</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Come join my guild on Icecrown, you would be more than welcome!</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Is it me or has this site finally keeled over?  I have been reading this site for 4 years after I ga</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Is it me or has this site finally keeled over?  I have been reading this site for 4 years after I gave up my eq accounts.  

But this is the truest indicator as far as I&apos;m concerned.

Thank you Moorgard and Loral for your hard work over the years.  You have been like a nicotine patch...weening my eq addiction.

R.I.P. Everquest and Mobhunter, safe travels to both of you.....</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Since comments are locked on the previous topic, I&apos;ll respond here.

&quot;In fact, since SoE d</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Since comments are locked on the previous topic, I&apos;ll respond here.

&quot;In fact, since SoE does not see that type server as being a long term success, and the changes so far mentioned are directly aimed at helping retain new players for the long term, I think it specifically argues against the likelyhood of a new classic/progression server as part of this process.&quot; - Redhenna

&quot;Given that they had to merge the two progression se</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Ok, as promised...my list of WoW weaknesses.


It&apos;s a Small World After All

This may sound ung</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Ok, as promised...my list of WoW weaknesses.


It&apos;s a Small World After All

This may sound ungrateful given that we just got a bunch of new content--free even--but the fact remains that there&apos;s too little variety, too much recycling of old content, and not enough of what Kaelon aptly calls &quot;depth.&quot;

WoW now has something on the order of 20 times the subscribers EQ had at its peak. In theory that means they&apos;ve got 20 time</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Weakness 1, A Focus on Solo Gameplay
I’d have to say that while at the surface your comments have me</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Weakness 1, A Focus on Solo Gameplay
I’d have to say that while at the surface your comments have merit, if you look deeper into the waters, they lack insight.
Let’s look at game mechanics that entice a user to do more than solo.  Guilds, Guild banks, Quests designed with groups in mind, Dungeons.
The missing element from older MMO’s is dependency.  No one in World of Warcraft is dependant on the good graces of anyone else by core design.
Past th</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>You guys are all idiots for playing WoW.

&quot;Abuse is a service I happily provide&quot;
</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>You guys are all idiots for playing WoW.

&quot;Abuse is a service I happily provide&quot;
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>More info on the WotLK expansion this week, including a couple things that are relevant to Loral&apo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>More info on the WotLK expansion this week, including a couple things that are relevant to Loral&apos;s list.

Five-man instances are being built to take an hour. Sources differ as to whether that means they&apos;re smaller than TBC instances (which can be done in an hour or less but frequently aren&apos;t) or not. So a possible win for Loral here.

Vehicles...originally they were for PvP, but they say the quest designers latched onto them to mak</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>
10 man raids?  That&apos;s not a raid, that&apos;s a group with a couple outside healers.  Shesh.  </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>
10 man raids?  That&apos;s not a raid, that&apos;s a group with a couple outside healers.  Shesh.  </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nolrog,

Your really not doing much to improve your reputation as someone that makes well thought ou</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Nolrog,

Your really not doing much to improve your reputation as someone that makes well thought out convincing arguments.  You are how ever reinforcing a general dislike of the elitist attitude that lives on the EQ forums.  Further your reminder of just how narrow minded you people are has done a wonder in squelching any warmth toward the changes being made in EQ and has completely removed and urge to re-up an EQ account.
Thank you for those po</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Don&apos;t feed the troll. (Especially since Loral will probably delete it all.)</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Don&apos;t feed the troll. (Especially since Loral will probably delete it all.)</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I suspect that the first of the two posts is not actually Nolrog, or if it was, he intended it as le</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I suspect that the first of the two posts is not actually Nolrog, or if it was, he intended it as less harsh than it sounds.  Nolrog just does not normally make blind insults like that.  The second one, I am not sure, but probably not him either.  Some one finds it amusing to post insulting crap here using other peoples names.  Loral, any chance you could update to a newer blog type system, with regestered users and such?

Shadow of Former Self--</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>A daily quest is simply a quest that can be completed once a day, as opposed to regular quests that </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>A daily quest is simply a quest that can be completed once a day, as opposed to regular quests that can be completed only once. They&apos;ve become far and away the best source of gold in the game. They also improve your reputation with the faction that gives them, and at the maximum (&quot;exalted&quot;) each faction that gives dailies makes a few items available which are comparable to early raid items. This provides a progression path of a sor</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>