<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://mikeshea.net/rss.css" type="text/css"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

  <channel>
    <title>LoralCiriclight.com</title>
    <link>http://loralciriclight.com/</link>
    <description>Tales and adventures of Loral Ciriclight in the online role playing game, Everquest.</description>
    <dc:language>en-us</dc:language>
    <dc:creator>mike@mikeshea.net</dc:creator>
    <dc:rights>Copyright 2004</dc:rights>
    <dc:date>2004-10-05T02:08:45+00:00</dc:date>
    <admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.movabletype.org/?v=3.01D" />
    <admin:errorReportsTo rdf:resource="mailto:mike@mikeshea.net"/>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>

    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Early October News</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001201.html</link>
      <description>This week we take a look at some of the news appearing throughout the Everquest community. On Halloween SOE hosts...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1201@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>This week we take a look at some of the news appearing throughout the Everquest community.</p>

<p>On Halloween SOE hosts the <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/fanfaire/index.jsp">New Orleans Fan Faire</a>.  SOE posted the  <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/fanfaire/event_schedule.jsp">schedule</a> for this year's Fan Faire last week.  Your favorite cleric (that's me in case you forgot) will be in attendance armed with an all new agenda to stuff into the pockets of anyone with an SOE badge.  Like the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000016.html">summit agenda</a>, I will post this agenda here a week or two before the Fan Faire.</p>

<p>This week SOE announced <a href="http://soeworlds.station.sony.com/">SOE Worlds</a> a print magazine devoted to Everquest, Everquest 2, Everquest Online Adventures, Star Wars Galaxies, and the rest of SOE's army of massive online games.  The magazine includes strategy articles, general reviews, fiction, and interviews.  I expected something like this to come out eventually; I'm surprised it took as long as it did.</p>

<p>The largest buzz and attention in the last couple of weeks appears to focus on Epic 1.5s.  Every class board, hundreds of discussions on the EQ Live forums, and most of the developer and community feedback follows the progression of these quests.  Epic raids pour into most chat channels and even the non-raiders seem to have epic fever.  Why people seem to be more interested in epics than levels, AAs, spells, or other gear seems beyond me.  It may be the most popular Omens feature for high-level players.</p>

<p>A bit of nastiness hit quite a few people last week.  People's Omens accounts shut off without warning and sent level 66+ players back to their level 65 self.  At first rumors spoke of credit transaction problems but reports came in from people who bought their copy in the store.  Sony jumped on it and posted <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=63626">this statement</a>.  I heard of nearly half a dozen people losing their level in this manner but all of them seemed to get it back without too much of a hassle.  This seems to be the only major bug in an otherwise smooth expansion release; certainly smoother than Gates of Discord which suffered from random linkdeaths for nearly a week.</p>

<p>A new <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=testing&message.id=4617">feature on test</a> has bards cheering.  Bards will soon have the ability to auto-twist songs using a new "/melody" command.  Typing "/melody 1 2 3" will play each of the three songs in sequence.  The change helps bards become more social creatures, giving them the time to chat with friends and watch Tivo until their friends shout "Heal Me, Dolt!".  Some bard purists complain that it removes one of the great tests of skills for bards but most bards agree that the loss of challenge is worth the reduction in repetitive motion stress.</p>

<p>66+ spell costs dropped from 140,000 plat on the first few days to 60,000 plat today on Quellious.  I expect to see them drop to 10k before they meet the balance of supply and demand.  This should probably happen in a month or two.  I still know little about the location of 69 and 70 spells.  The no-drop requirement worries me.  Instead of living the twilight of my levels where I choose, I will probably have to hunt in Muramite Provingrounds and Riftseeker's in order to receive 69 and 70 spells.</p>

<p>People continue to migrate in long lines to the Wall of Slaughter.  Though better experience and loot awaits discovery in Ruined City of Dranik and its two sets of instances, people prefer the easier hunting ground and higher drop-rate of the Wall.  I cannot blame them and it is better to have one zone like the Wall than none at all, but it will be nice to see people spread out a bit more into the other lands.  In the mean time, for great fun and high adventure, travel to the Ruined City of Dranik through the Bloodfields.  If you are truly a band of hearty adventurers, attempt the Sewers and Catacombs expeditions.</p>

<p>One thing that definitely appears to be missing are random rare drops on normal mobs.  Instead of spending hours camping the same two spawn areas in the Hollows, I'd prefer to have a low chance (1/100) of receiving a rune drop or a loot item off of a normal beast.  Perhaps they haven't been found and reported yet, but so far I have seen none.</p>

<p>Expect a new system for the loading screens between zones.  People in beta had problems with the original one looking too much like a system hanging forever so they put in the loading screen.  The loading screen, however, breaks the flow of the game too much.  Sony builds a new system as we speak.  Perhaps we will see it in the mid-October patch.</p>

<p>I look with narrowed eyes to find problems for the single-group hunter in Omens and I find few.  Spell drops seem reasonable.  I received a piece of loot in a single-group battle I could immediately use, something that hasn't happened to me in a long while.  High level players can reach high level loot without required raiding.  We have so many useful zones that some excellent hunting areas like the Ruined City of Draniks sit empty.  Most of the problems I find and report are little more than nitpicks.  Overall I still give Omens a big thumbs-up.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
4 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-10-05T02:08:45+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: After Omens</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001200.html</link>
      <description>Every new expansion changes the face of Everquest. Omens is no different. I had a conversation with a guild leader...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1200@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Every new expansion changes the face of Everquest. Omens is no different. I had a conversation with a guild leader today who said he had great trouble bringing his guild together to defeat raid targets in Planes of Power. Their guild focuses on reaching the Plane of Time but each day he finds it more and more difficult to gather his forces. When I asked what they were doing instead, he said they hunted in Omens. I see little surprise there.</p>

<p>There seem to be two attitudes towards Omens. One all but ignores it and continues progression down the same path they followed two years ago. People seek the same flags, people hunt in the same experience zones, people all but completely avoid the new worlds.</p>

<p>The other takes the opposite approach. They seek to tear through all of the content in Omens as fast as possible. They hunt in the most lucrative experience zones in the game until they reach level 70 twenty hours later. They earn AAs and buy the best abilities as soon as they can. The random drops of spells and equipment hold them back, so instead they switch to Epic 1.5s. I remember being asked to help with all new epic raids within three days of entering the lands of Kuua.</p>

<p>A healthy balance exists between these two extremes. The world of Norrath changed with the opening of the portals of Discord. Powerful equipment becomes easier to acquire. We find new levels, spells, AAs, quests, and zones. We should seek out and learn more of these new paths. We should enjoy our journeys and adventures without feeling like someone pokes a spear in our back. The journey is more rewarding than the goal.</p>

<p>Most of the epic 1.5 quests have already been completed. The puzzle solvers worked day and night to solve the quests and epic 1.5 spoilers now sit on almost every class forum. I didn't receive my happy clicky stick until almost a year and a half after Kunark came out. I am in no hurry now. Instead, I'll pick short term goals and begin working on my quest when my own power and the power of my friends grows.</p>

<p>Spells in Omens so far prove difficult to obtain. All spells except teleports come from dropped runes. While the runes ensure that no class gets duplicate spells and all spell casting classes can use these runes, they drop perhaps half the time on rare mobs.</p>

<p>There are two things I would have liked to have seen with spells in Omens. I would like to see one spell given out at each level off of a vendor or a short quest. A single spell at each level gives players a bit more motivation to level than just new aas. I would also like to see a more progressive, less random, quest to receive new spells.</p>

<p>Again, I fall back to the point system in LDON. It took 11 adventures to receive a new spell but I knew I made progress with each successful adventure. I did not compete with my group to receive it; we all earned equal rewards for our adventures. Instead of only dropping muramite runes off of random rare mobs, why not drop pieces of runes randomly off of every mob. Collect 10 pieces, build yourself a rune.</p>

<p>Speaking of LDON, prepare for a flip flop. Four months ago I asked SOE to add new LDON equipment to the LDON vendors. At the time it would help non-raiders access more Gates content and give high-level LDON adventurers a few more trinkets to seek. I was told at the Summit that these items would be added. Later I was told they would be added, but not until after Omens.</p>

<p>At this point in the game, most of the "after Omens" fixes are obsolete. Like instancing the Plane of Time, new content overshadows the desire for such a large fix. If we want higher end items than the LDON vendors, we can go to one of three instanced expeditions and earn better loot. We can hunt named in the Wall of Slaughter and Ruins of Dranik. Like the gear in Kunark, Velious, and Luclin, LDON gear becomes obsolete with age. LDON equipment works well up to 65 but when one outgrows it, one should head head to Omens.</p>

<p>I could be a pain in the arse and demand that SOE follow through with new LDON loot. I know many high-end raiders will still demand a Time instance even though instanced zones in Gates and Omens offer better loot without any guild-based competition. Instead, SOE should focus their resources on the problems that matter most and the features that help the game grow further.</p>

<p>I'd rather see them work on new LDON-style adventures with new themes, new adventure types, new beasts, and new loot than rehash the loot on the adventures in which many people have already fought. Even if they did put focus 5 items on LDON vendors, I'd probably stay over in Omens for awhile.</p>

<p>I would prefer SOE look at the expeditions in Omens and add more LDON-like features to them than rebuild LDON. I would like to see an incremental quest for spells in addition to random drops. I would like to see a in-game goal and a two-hour duration for each expedition. I would like to see the removal of spawns so groups crawl from the beginning to the end. I would like to see boss-mobs spawn after the party kills a number of normal beasts.</p>

<p>Expeditions have a lot more potential than instanced group hunting content. Expeditions are controlled environments for the developers to build fun and interesting scripts. They use some of these scripts for the Muramite Proving Grounds trials, but few will see those powerful events and far fewer will survive them.</p>

<p>I asked for new LDON items and better LDON adventures, but now I would rather focus on the future. I would prefer to see Omens filling in the gaps left open with LDON. Omens includes enough content to keep almost any player busy for a long time regardless of the amount of time they play or the style of play they enjoy. A few changes to the expeditions would help bring the best parts of Lost Dungeons to new and more flexible expeditions. After that, all we must fear are the sharp teeth of the Dragorns and the green gasses of the umbrella people.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
28 September 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-09-29T19:45:21+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Omens of War Review</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001198.html</link>
      <description>Last week SOE released Everquest&apos;s eighth expansion in five years, Omens of War. There is no way to fully review...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1198@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Last week SOE released Everquest's eighth expansion in five years, Omens of War. There is no way to fully review an expansion after only one week, so consider this the first of at least two reviews of the expansion. In later weeks we will discuss whether the expansion filled in all of the gaps it intended to fill. For now we focus on what we know so far. Omens of War is a very strong expansion and well worth $30.</p>

<p>Omens includes a lot of new, useful, and fun zones to hunt in. There are eight over-land zones starting at level 45 and quickly reaching into level 65 and 70. There are three sets of instanced expeditions, the sewers, catacombs, and hollows. One locked zone awaits the arrival of big fancy people, and a set of Justice-like instanced group and raid trials await the corpses of level 70s.</p>

<p>The zones in this expansion look great. The wide open wastelands of the Wall of Slaughter stretch to the crushed walls of the Dragorn keeps. Ancient bridges cross the canyons of the Ruins of Dranik. All of these zones resemble lands at war, with scorched earth and skies of smoke.</p>

<p>Unlike Planes of Power, the better hunting zones of Omens are unlocked. The instanced expeditions guarentee that any player above 45 can find a place to earn good experience with little competition.</p>

<p>Omens has only one locked zone and none are expected to see it right away. Already we see treasures coming from the furthest reaches of the Muramite Provingrounds (sic) and Riftseeker's Sanctum. Flags prevented this sort of gold rush in Planes of Power and Gates of Discord, but the advantages of unflagged zones outweigh the disadvantages.</p>

<p>It is no surprise that characters began reaching level 70 two days after release. Characters have been at level 65 for a long time and not being at the top level seems unnatural. Many seek to reach that top end not because they want it but because they feel they deserve to have it.</p>

<p>More troubling is where they go to get it. Instead of joining five friends and exploring these new lands, fast-track hunters head to the Plane of Fire. Message threads string across the net with discussions of the Plane of Fire and the experience within. Some report waiting in lines to kite at the tables, the single best place to earn experience in the game. If ever a place needed to be modified to increase the risk vs reward, that is it.</p>

<p>The alternate advanced abilities in Omens appear far more useful than the ones we saw in Gates. Most continue the progression of previous AAs such as critical damage increases, healing increases, and stat increases. Some offer a lot of utility such as a ninth spell-gem and five more buff slots. For 25 AA points, one can up their mana regeneration cap from 15 to 20. Each class has a few unique and interesting abilities as well.</p>

<p>The shiny loot of Omens appears to fill in the power gap between level 65 single-group hunters and high-end professional raiders. We now reached a point where a character can level from 1 to 70, gear up with bazaar, Ornate, and LDON loot, and then earn gear in the high-end of Omens without ever needing to raid to get better gear. Raiding always offers greater rewards, as it should, but single-group progression now has a bridge deep into Gates of Discord and the high-end of Omens of War without requiring raiding.</p>

<p>The task system improved a lot since the early days of beta. Tasks break up into a set of four sub-tasks involving exploration of places best left alone, shady meetings with Wayfarer agents, collecting four shiny things, and killing ten evildoers. Tasks range from level 5 to level 65 with more tasks on the way in coming weeks. Their difficulty varies but I completed two or three different ones by myself at level 65, not bad for a weak and pasty cleric.</p>

<p>The greatest improvement to the task system is the scaling reward. While some classes solo much better than others, players earn rewards based on class. Clerics, paladins, and warriors who generally have more trouble hunting alone receive a higher reward than necromancers, bards, and wizards who can complete tasks much faster. The rewards of the task system make it useful without ruining the rewards of grouping. Triggered beasts and events locked for the triggering player would add a lot of excitement to the tasks. Perhaps that is a feature we will see later on.</p>

<p>The graphics in Omens are astounding. Detailed carvings and erosion on walls look good enough to run a hand over. Torchlight shines on the scaly skin of a Dragorn as it rushes down a hallway. Red eyes shine bright from the six eyes of a Chimera. Moonlight shines off of the water over the Abysmal Seas. Breath frosts out of the mouths of the hunters of Halas. Everquest's look improved much in the last five years and its visuals never cease to amaze me.</p>

<p>The lack of description and options for graphic performance makes these new graphics inconsistent from user to user. A new "advanced" tab in display options offers shadows, reflective waters, pixel shader 1.0, pixel shader 2.0, vertex shaders, reflective waters, and a few other options. It doesn't include Hardware TnL (don't ask me what it stands for) and Vsync, the option that tells the game not to run faster than your monitor can display. Vsync may be the most important feature to make Everquest look solid on faster machines and the only way to enable it is to put a "Vsync=1" variable under "Defaults" in one's eqclient.ini file.</p>

<p>Everquest needs a better interface for display settings with better auto-detection, a simple slider bar or check box for the features to enable. Most important are descriptions of what each feature does and what types of systems should enable it. Few people know what a pixel shader 2.0 is and no one should need to.</p>

<p>In the mean time, players must work hard to understand all of the available settings and figure out which they should use.</p>

<p>SOE released a lot of smaller features in Omens as well. The voice macro system lets tanks shout "Heal me, dolt!" when my eyes stray over to my Tivo too much. Guild tributes let officers donate junky gear so other members can have an extra point of mana regen. Custom titles ensure you can pick the title you liked the best. I always preferred Venerable to Exarch.</p>

<p>Omens is a great expansion. Excellent unflagged and unrestricted zones, new levels and AAs, new shiny loot for both single-group hunters and raiders, top-notch graphics, and a lot of fun new features make Omens one of the best Everquest expansions. It takes time to find all of the nooks and crannies in such a game, no one can write a complete review after only one week of play, but so far Omens is a lot of fun.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
20 September 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-09-25T00:02:11+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 52: The Abysmal Seas</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001196.html</link>
      <description>Cold wind ripped across the waves bringing with it a wall of rain. The sheet of rain smashed across the...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1196@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Cold wind ripped across the waves bringing with it a wall of rain.  The sheet of rain smashed across the wooden deck of the ship and over the cloaked figure, but he did not move.  A flash of lightning broke open the horizon of black clouds and black seas revealing intense blue eyes under the gray cloak of the stranger.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight, priest of Tunare, stood on the ship's deck, ignoring the tearing wind and cold rain.  He was an elf transformed.  His hair hung in thick strands down the front of his shoulders from under his hood.  He held his cloak tight around his body as the wind ripped through him.  Lighting crashed again and the huge boat creaked sending a flood of rainwater across the deck.  Loral's eyes never moved.</p>

<p>Two huge barbarians covered in spiked steel armor and carrying great-swords almost as tall as Loral stood guard over the focus of Loral's intense gaze.  Between them was the Grozmok stone.  For centuries the huge stone served demons and gods long dead.  For centuries it lead to the twisting and destruction of countless beings across countless worlds.  And now it was here on this boat in this storm.</p>

<p>Strange magic kept the huge slab afloat over its pedestal.  Loral saw horrible glyphs and sigils carved on its surface from a dark language beyond the realms of Norrath.  No word of this language ever spread across the lands.  No mortal tongue could ever hope to articulate the impossible multi-voiced syllables of the ancient language.  The guttural and deep words would hew into the minds of those who heard it, spreading like black poison and tearing away all moral and rational thought.  Men pierced the throats of their families under the orders of such words, spilling the blood of their loved ones onto the insatiable stone.  Lightning crashed again and Loral closed his eyes.</p>

<p>The two guards turned to the cloaked figure that stood in the storm and watched it stride forward.  Time appeared to slow.  The figure's hard boots thudded on the deck above the steady roar of the falling rain. The figure drew a  hand from within its cloak and traced a sign of Tunare in the air with two fingers.  His powerful decisive stride never stopped.  A flash of light erupted from within the folds of the figure's gray cloak.  The two barbarians placed their hands on the hilts of their huge swords.</p>

<p>The larger of the two guards began to draw his sword but before six inches of the steel blade left it sheath, a twisting cord wrapped around his wrist, waste, feet, and throat.  It tore him into the railing of the ship's deck and he screamed against another crash of lightning.  The other drew his own huge blade in a fast practiced draw.  He took no chances.</p>

<p>The unhindered guard cut hard in a horizontal slash that should have severed the cloaked figure in half.  The figure turned, putting his back against the blade's cut and although the blade cut into the figure's gray cloak, it shattered like glass against the shield the figure wore on his back.  A deep and low roar swept across the ship's deck.  Red flames leaped up from the cut in the figure's cloak.  </p>

<p>The figure's cloak whipped back and revealed a shining hammer in his hand.  The cloaked attacker smashed the head of the hammer into the guard's chest and with a crash of magical energy.  The cloaked figure drew back and then threw his hand forward hard as if tossing a huge stone.  Another deep thud sounded across the ship as blast of magical energy slammed into the guard, shattered the thick wooden railing, and sent him soaring onto lower deck below.</p>

<p>The figure leaped up onto the remaining railing holding his shining hammer high in one hand and a burning shield in the other.  Below his feet the Grozmok stone whispered in a dark tongue.  The figure smashed his hammer into the center of the stone.  The Grozmok stone exploded in black and white fire, shattering into dust.</p>

<p>Lighting cut again across the gray storm clouds and the boat rocked again tearing Loral from the vision of his attack.  How dearly he wished to destroy the accursed stone.  How much pain should Norrath continue to suffer?  The dark stone twisted the trolls of Grobb into unholy spiritcallers and destroyed the city of Guk.  Rumors spoke to the stone's participation in the surfacing of the orcs of Rujarkian.  The stone was a compass of death.  It dragged its followers into the pits of hell and it would do so again attached to this massive ship.</p>

<p>Loral became aware of silence in his mind.  Xuzl, demon imprisoned in Loral's burning shield, never missed such opportunities to torment the elven cleric.</p>

<p>"Why do you not speak, Demon," thought Loral.  Xuzl's words returned like a thin hiss, far different from the mental roar of flame he normally spoke through.</p>

<p>There is nothing to say.  Ware the stone, priest.</p>

<p>"What do you know of this thing?"  The voice of the demon prince flowed through Loral's mind much smoother and lower than it ever had.  It was a powerful contrast from the demon's normally overpowering voice.</p>

<p>Only a handful of such items exist across the known worlds.  Their power is endless, eviscerating worlds and spilling their entrails upon the open vastness that lies in between.  None know where such things are created.  They outgrow even those who build them.  Some say they are built from within the ethereal voids where not even the demon-princes dare to look.  Leave this place, priest.</p>

<p>Xuzl's words surprised Loral.  Even in his defeat at the hands of the adventurers of Lotus Cult, Xuzl never showed fear until now.</p>

<p>Loral turned and looked back across the crashing seas.  The clouds themselves seemed alien to Loral, as though the great ship of the Wayfarers had itself traveled across the rifts of Norrath and into unknown worlds.  Whatever awaited him on the shores to the west, Loral could only hope he would be ready.</p>

<p>The howling winds of the storm brought a cry to Loral's ears.  The ship's watchman sighted land.  A cold shiver flowed through Loral's veins as a whispered prayer to Tunare left his lips.  The gates of discord had opened, and chaos reigned within.</p>

<p>2</p>

<p>Dauleroun Alines walked slowly down the streets of Felwithe in the darkness of the late night.  The elven councilman's hard-soled boots echoed off of the stone pavement, the only sound in the deep night.  His pale skin sagged at his cheeks and neck; many in the council noted that the conservative voice of the council looked far older these last few days.  It was due to stress, no doubt, after the recent news and omens of war.</p>

<p>Shadows bent and twisted across the blue stone walkway and across the alleys of the closed shops.  The shadows flanked and followed the councilman as he made his way to his posh apartment in North Felwithe.</p>

<p>The councilman waved a hand past a red glyph on the stone door of his apartments.  The rune shifted to green and magical forces pushed the rumbling stone into a hidden compartment.  When the councilman entered, the door closed behind him.  The shadows, however, followed him inside.</p>

<p>Alines waved his hand again, and spoke a single word in elder Elvish.  A fire burst into life in his hearth, illuminating the room.  A low voice from the shadows of the room whispered in a much older and darker voice.  The fire died low in the hearth.  Alines turned and faced the dark corner.</p>

<p>All of the shadows of the small room twisted and turned, shifting and drawing in.  Chilled wind flowed through the room blowing papers off of Aline's old desk and whipping the room's drapes and table cloths like the wings of bats.  The shadows came together in one spot and filled out a tall humanoid shape.  Red eyes blazed from the shadows and the vampire lord stepped into the light.</p>

<p>"Speak."  The vampire's voice was low and smooth.  The red eyes shifted through the full spectrum of light from red to violet and back, finally settling on a burning green.</p>

<p>"Lord Varlow."  Alines's confident voice broke apart as he spoke the name of the vampire lord who had taken him. "I did as you asked.  The emissaries, scouts, and adventurers head west across the Abysmal Seas following the agents of the Wayfarers.  We sent word to all of our field agents."</p>

<p>"And the priest?"  Varlow's hands slid from within his pitch black robes.  The long fingers ended in sharp thick nails.</p>

<p>"He travels west as well."</p>

<p>"Excellent."  The vampire lord's green eyes looked behind Councilman Alines.  "Glave, You know what to do."</p>

<p>"Yes, my master."  The hissing voice sent bolts of electricity through the elven councilman.  Alines whipped around to behold a shadowed figure less than two feet from his exposed back.  </p>

<p>Like Varlow, the figure had white skin but unlike the other vampire, tiny sigils, glyphs, and runes covered nearly every inch of this figure's skin .  His eyes were pure black orbs that shone in the dim flashes of the firelight.  He wore a flat black tunic and black trousers tucked into tall heavily creased boots.  A cloak draped over his sholders and a low hood covered the shade's bald tattooed head.  A pair of daggers, hilted in silver and adorned with black pearls, hung on the creature's wide black belt.  The pitch black eyes focused on the shaken councilman and the vampire shade smiled revealing horrible pointed teeth.</p>

<p>"Leave us."</p>

<p>The vampire shade, Glave, smiled again at the councilman and stepped toward the door.  Glave turned sideways and seemed to fold into a thin line before floating through the crack of the door.</p>

<p>The shocking site of something so unnatural faded and the councilman turned back to the elder vampire.</p>

<p>"What of me now?"</p>

<p>"One day you may serve me as well as Glave.  It took him five centuries to earn my trust and enter my inner circle."  The vampire smiled, his long teeth glistening.  "For now, you serve me here."</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-09-19T14:31:13+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: The Meaningless Words of Everquest</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001194.html</link>
      <description>Jargon plagues Everquest. We find meaningless words or phrases everywhere. Everyone has an idea, everyone has a complaint, and everyone...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1194@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Jargon plagues Everquest. We find meaningless words or phrases everywhere. Everyone has an idea, everyone has a complaint, and everyone has something about the game they want to talk about. Instead of finding ways to properly communicate what our problem is, we fall back to generalizations and buzzwords that may have meaning to us but lose that meaning the more they are used and misused. These words don't help us communicate with SOE. Instead of articulating a problem, they muddy the conversation and cloud the real problems.</p>

<p>Five terms in particular get used dozens of times each week on the various forums. These words add nothing to our conversations and don't help SOE find and fix the problems we gloss over. If we eliminate them from our vocabulary and speak in detail, we increase SOE's ability to respond. Lets take a look at these meaningless words:</p>

<p>Uber: The German word for “Over” describes high end characters, guilds, equipment, or abilities. We hear about uberguilds and ubermobs. We use the word as insult or praise when a friend acquires a new shiny item. Uber is anything more powerful than you. Some 65 paladins with 300 AA points don't consider themselves uber. Level 25 rangers tear through Crushbone like a tornado and everyone in the zone considers them uber. There is no specific use of the word that helps describe a particular state of the game, guilds, or players. In almost every Mobhunter article I wrote for my first three months, my editor, the uber wizard Azile Ciricbane, had to edit out my use of “uberguild” and told me to replace it with something more specific.</p>

<p>Casual: Casual is the most misunderstood and misused phrase in the Everquest community. There are casual guilds who raid the Elemental Planes. Some casual players have hundreds of AA points and play 40 hours a week. Everyone has a different definition of a casual gamer. Sometimes it means low level. Other times it means non-raiders. Instead of asking for changes for the casual gamer, we need to describe exactly what it is we desire. Do we need more short-duration events? Do we need less locked content? Do we need higher power equipment available to single LDON / Ornate equipped level 65 groups? Avoid the word casual, speak in detail.</p>

<p>Mudflation: This ancient term gets used any time someone sees the game progress and doesn't like it. Mudflation means little but has a built-in wrapper of negativity that lets us label progression like a package of spoiled meat. Few describe exactly what they mean when they use the term and fewer can describe how to fix it. The game gets larger. The high-end zones get higher. Level limits increase. Equipment grows in power. That isn't mudflation, that's progress.</p>

<p>Timesink: This is one of my favorites. Timesinks describe any action in Everquest that someone doesn't enjoy. Everquest is a timesink. Reading a book is a timesink. I know one perfect way to avoid timesinks. If you aren't enjoying what you do, do something else. Before you begin telling me that you HAVE to camp shards to get intoVex Thal or you HAVE to get your Ring of Scale faction up, remember that this entire game is voluntary and the world is big enough to find a million other and often more enjoyable things to do. If you find a particular event or hunt that bores you to tears, instead of labeling it a timesink, just tell SOE what you don't like about it. Speak in details, not overused and meaningless generalities.</p>

<p>Class Balance: Classes, by definition, cannot be balanced. Every class is good at some things and bad in others. There is no way to balance the wide variety of skills from one class to another. How does one compare the blasts of a wizard to the slows of a shaman to the healing of a cleric? With limited combat interaction it becomes difficult to make every one of the sixteen classes unique yet not required for a group. SOE can tweak class abilities and help support those unique roles. SOE can also tune encounters so they work well with particular class archetypes as they did with knights and the Ikkinz trials. There is never a clear solution for class balance and there is no conclusion. Classes cannot be balanced without ruining the unique skills that each class has to offer.</p>

<p>Every day players interact with SOE and every day players use these terms to gloss over deeper problems or recommendations. When you find yourself using one of these terms when writing a message board post or sending feedback, ask yourself what you are really saying and replace it with detail. Instead of asking for more casual-friendly content, ask for more single-group events that don't require raid gear. Instead of complaining about timesinks, ask for more Ring of Scale faction options. We love our meaningless terms but our communication becomes stronger and SOE's ability to respond becomes greater when we say exactly what we mean.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 September 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-09-13T13:03:19+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: The Focus and the Flip Flop</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001191.html</link>
      <description>In case you live in Paw, the great Foci debate spread across every Everquest related forum on the entire web....</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1191@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>In case you live in Paw, the great Foci debate spread across every Everquest related forum on the entire web.  This <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=63311">official notice</a> declares that all foci will begin scaling at a rate of 10% per spell level after the level cap of the foci.  This means Spell Haste 4, a 15% reduction in casting time up to level 65, will drop to 13.5% at level 66, 11% at level 67, and so on until it reaches 7.5% at level 70.</p>

<p>This has most high-end raiders in a fury.  They spent months working through very difficult encounters in Gates of Discord where foci of 45% on some items will drop to 22.5% at level 70.  Some call this the worst nerf ever even though it's not a nerf but an enhancement.  SOE made a far better decision than letting the items cut off at 65 as they were advertised to do.</p>

<p>Originally, I agreed with the change.  First and foremost, it helps all spellcasting players below level 65 which is the most important subject of this change.  Most spend their time on this topic discussing 65+ gear, however.  I remember the dark days where Focus 3 items stopped working at all.  I expected my 65 gear would stop in much the same way.  This was a good change in my mind.  Others, however, felt sure that their high-end items would last forever (note: no item ever lasts forever.  One should always want to upgrade eventually.) and became quite horribly vexed when they learned they would eventually desire to upgrade.</p>

<p>The summit forums, where yours truly gets all manner of uberfruit tossed at him on a daily basis, was no exception to this.  In one of our dozens of heated messages I was called an uber / casual "flip flopper".  We will get back to this in a moment.  I spent much time considering this Foci situation.</p>

<p>What becomes clearer to me the more I test Omens and the more I think about Gates is that the two expansions seem to have come out in the wrong order.</p>

<p>Imagine if Omens came out four months ago with open zones, elemental level raid content, a lot of single-group content with equipment progression above LDON / Ornate, and most importantly level 70.  Those who finished Time and LDON raids head into the more difficult Omens content (more difficult because they have no Gates gear) while they level up to 70 and acquire that content.</p>

<p>Then Gates comes along.  The content is a lot harder.  Much more of the expansion is locked but even single-groupers have an easier time with the sewers and mountain trials.  Single group people are able to defeat the Ikkinz trials without raid gear.  The people who made it through Omens now hit that super-hard content (scaled for level 70 Omens gear) at Qvic and above and earn that super high quality loot.</p>

<p>Things seem a lot smoother in that obviously simplified theory.  There is a larger bridge between the single group hunters of LDON and the Planes to the single-group content in Gates.  The raiding guilds have smoother progression to the high-end raid content and the rewards for that gear fits their level better.</p>

<p>If you can't tell, I began to cave.  Perhaps being called a "flip flopper" finally did it.  I must have laughed for hours about the use of such a politically motivated word in a discussion about Massive Online Gaming.  I am a great fan of the use, reuse, and misuse of words as society changes.  George Orwell's 1946 essay <a href="http://mikeshea.net/orwell">Politics and the English Language</a> shows how the word "Fascist" got so misused that it became all but meaningless back in the 40s.  Geoff Nunberg's <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/1586482343/qid=1093987266/sr=8-1/ref=pd_ka_1/103-0239897-5576631?v=glance&s=books&n=507846">Going Nucular (sic)</a> talks about how the connotation of words like Plastic and Caucasian get horribly misused as our perceptions and politics change.  It wasn't until I was called a flip flopper that I really understood what they meant.  But I digress...</p>

<p>Very few people have high end Gates of Discord armor (don't scream yet, read on).  In a year or two, the flip flop of Gates and Omens (see, I used it again!) won't matter.  People will travel through the content in the most reasonable way, probably Omens to Gates.  For them, it makes little sense to have high-end Gates items, items that will be more difficult for them to acquire even at level 70 not work on spells up to level 70.</p>

<p>While I will not use my vast powers of the active voice ("Increase high-end Gates gear foci limits from 65 to 70"), I will say that it makes sense that high-end Gates gear scales to level 70.  More importantly, it will make more sense in a year when new players won't remember whether or not Gates came out before Omens.  In a year, with focus gear scaling to 70, Gates will be the clear line of equipment progression for raiders.  Without gear scaling to 70, the high-end Gates zones will see little use.</p>

<p>However, there is another side to this, a side that is not apparent yet to those who scream about their gear becoming "worthless".  If your foci gear scales to level 70, you will most likely not see equipment progression in Omens since your gear was really meant (in my own theory above) to be acquired after Omens.  You will spend your days tearing through raid content in Omens and in a month you will hit the high-end of Omens and realize there is nothing left.  Unlike everyone else, current high-end raiders will have already torn through Gates like a drag line in a strip mine and they will realize there is no more coal to mine.</p>

<p>Then they may quit and that is what SOE wishes to prevent.</p>

<p>Let me conclude this essay on semantics, politics, itemology, and marketing by saying that increasing the level limit to level 70 on high-end GoD items makes sense.  No other foci should get a free pass.  All other Foci from Time, the Elements, and any equipment in GoD with Time or Elemental effects should scale as the original plan intended.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 September 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-09-03T23:25:40+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Visions and Omens</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001188.html</link>
      <description>The Omens beta began in full last week. Larger guilds began testing out raid encounters while the rest of us...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1188@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>The Omens beta began in full last week.  Larger guilds began testing out raid encounters while the rest of us ran Guktan wizards to the corners of the world marveling at the strange sights.</p>

<p>Most of Omens of War reminds me of Kunark.  The architecture and the plight of the Dragorn empire squeezed within the Muramite's iron gauntlet creates a lot of similarities to the Iksar and their post-Shissar empires.  Massive castles and spired walls stretch across the green landscape.  Orange and red clouds flow over hills and ravines.</p>

<p>A first glance shows us nine open over-land zones and three sets of instanced expeditions: the caves, the sewers, and the catacombs, each with about four or five variants.  More zones await discovery.  The first overland zone and the first set of instanced expeditions supports level 45+ with beasts lower in power than those in Natimbi.  The beasts grow in power quickly beyond that point.</p>

<p>There looks to be some excellent hunting zones between 60 and 70, although I imagine SOE developers continue to tune experience modifiers.  Between Planes of Power, Gates of Discord, Lost Dungeons, and Omens of War zones, there appears to be no lack of hunting areas for any level up to 70.</p>

<p>I have seen no equipment or loot so I cannot know yet if the power-gap between single-group hunters and raiders will close in at all.  Hopefully Omens offers enough single-group equipment to get players through the single-group trials of Gates.  Too long have the mountain trials, Kodtaz, and the Ikkinz trials been closed to non-raiders.</p>

<p>Lists of new Omens of War alternate advance abilities popped up everywhere on Friday.  While the lists contain no associated costs for these skills, many of them are surprisingly good.  A lot of changes that we never expected to see began to show up.  New spell-gem slots, new buff slots, a gate for everyone, two binding areas for wizards, and a surprisingly large increased mana regeneration cap for pure casters.  I can only really speak for clerical abilities but the list looks good, with a lot of basic improvements to our core function including improved healing gift, healing adapt, celestial rejuvenation, and our first critical heal over time ability.  I purchased few AAs for Gates, but now I am glad I saved up the points for Omens abilities.</p>

<p>One nice thing about new Alternate Advance skills is that any player can acquire them regardless of where they hunt.  They don't get stuck on your body when you wipe out in Fear and they don't require camping obscure mobs in obscure places for a 1 in 6 chance at that one last spell you needed.</p>

<p>Spells in Omens are distributed with runes, one rune per level, similar to Gates of Discord.  SOE developers compared it to Planes of Power.  Spells will not be duplicated.  What isn't known is the difficulty in acquiring spells.</p>

<p>Task system testing also began late last week.  While continued testing and balancing needs to occur before release, the skeleton of the system shows promise.  Single players are able to complete tasks in under an hour and earn a noticeable reward for doing so.  The reward is nice enough to make a difference but small enough to keep players from ignoring requests for groups.  Single groups should always be the core Everquest hunting team.</p>

<p>The task system is the one feature of Omens that supports players from level 20 to (hopefully) 70.  SOE brings up the task system whenever the requests for solo instanced encounters arise.  I don't believe any system can match up to the expectations people have for it.  It will take a few such systems to cover all of the needs and desires for short-duration content.</p>

<p>The official website of Omens of War includes a couple of new features I hadn't yet heard about.  One of them, a voice macro of some sort, shows a lot of promise.  Now an interesting show on Tivo won't kill half a group in eight seconds.  Now raid leaders can wake up that 20% of their raid who always seems to be asleep.  None of this is yet in the beta so I cannot say exactly how it works.</p>

<p>This week, the Omens of War developers and SOE community represenatives had an moderated chat with players.  EQ Stratics posted <a href="http://eq.stratics.com/content/hoclogs/oowhoc.php">a log of the transcript</a>.  Few details are given, but topics such as spells, new epic quests, content for players under 50, and solo instances all came up.</p>

<p>Omens of War brings us over a dozen new zones, half of them instanced.  It expands the physical worlds of Norrath even further.  I wonder if SOE might best spend their time working on new expansions that take Everquest into directions other than new zones to explore.  Everquest is certainly wide, it is the largest physical game I've ever played, but it isn't very deep.  The vast majority of content builds around combat against bosses.  The numbers increase but the gameplay is generally the same.  New lines of progression need to be developed.</p>

<p>I could sit here and come up with ideas stolen from other role playing games, but I am sure SOE's developers can do the same so I will leave it into their capable hands.  I heard some exciting ideas thrown around at the guild summit and I only hope they attempt to run with some of them.  Omens is a strong expansion and its release opens up the future into entirely new possibilities.  Now is the time to consider and develop those new possibilities.  The world is yours.</p>

<p><br />
Loral Ciriclight<br />
27 August 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-08-27T21:05:31+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Five Steps to One Million Subscribers</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001187.html</link>
      <description>I want to see one million people playing Evequest. I want to see Sony Online Entertainment double the subscribers they...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1187@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I want to see one million people playing Evequest.  I want to see Sony Online Entertainment double the subscribers they currently have.  I do not have a master's degree in business or marketing but that never stopped me from having an opinion before and it won't stop me now.  This article outlines five steps to improve Everquest's success.</p>

<p>Loral's Marketeer Five Step Evil PowerPoint Slide for the success of Everquest:</p>

<p>- Continue to release fresh retail versions of Everqust.  Make it clear to the consumer which one they should buy and cheap enough to compete with newer MMOGs.</p>

<p>- Update the PC models and graphics to compete with newer MMOGs and make EQ look like a brand new game.</p>

<p>- Release another Lost Dungeons of Norrath style expansion with scaling content for levels 20 to 70.</p>

<p>- Simplify the interface; perform usability studies; simplify the skill and discipline system.</p>

<p>- Improve Everquest stability; make patches modem friendly; offer updated versions of EQ on DVD as DVD drives proliferate.</p>

<p>Step 1: Market Everquest as a new game every expansion and offer a free version.  The release of the Everquest Platinum edition greatly improved SOE's chances for increasing subscribers.  For $30, a new player gets the basic game, all seven current expansions, and a month to try it out.</p>

<p>Release the basic game with a one month trial for free to let people try the game out.  Pass this single-disc version around like AOL.  Have people making coasters out of it and throwing it at that guy hovering over by the fax machine.  While the current free download helps, the sheer size of the game makes it almost inaccessible to new players.  Offering free CDs in gaming stores, magazines, and bulk mail will bring in a lot of new players.</p>

<p>Continually update this $30 version with everything but the most recent expansion.    Pull older versions off the shelves.  Make it clear which versions players need to buy.</p>

<p>Step 2:  Update player character graphics.  There are no graphics more important than PC graphics.  When people shop for a new MMOG, player graphics are the first thing they see.  Everquest has excellent world and beastie graphics, but the current player graphics need work.</p>

<p>SOE plans to release new player graphics by the end of the year.  It is important that they stick to this deadline.  EQ2, Worlds of Warcraft, and Final Fantasy X offer brand new and fresh player graphics.  New PC graphics is SOE's first chance to impress new players, it is the first graphics a new player sees. New player graphics are the most important change this year.</p>

<p>Player graphics require three things to succeed.  They must scale well on existing systems and offer good performance during raids.  They must be customizable enough to create unique characters identifiable from far away.  They must be good enough to let us escape into the lives of our characters.  </p>

<p>Step 3:  Release another Lost Dungeon-like expansion.  Lost Dungeons of Norrath offers the most highly scalable content in any of the previous expansions.  LDON offers usable and rewarding content from level 20 to level 65.  Mobs are always blue.  Treasure and rewards scale well.  Groups are easy to find and the camps are well connected.  The dungeons allow for easy corpse recovery but still offer a good challenge.  Players can finish an event in between 45 and 90 minutes.</p>

<p>A new Lost Dungeons expansion should use the Gates of Discord expedition system so players can leave if they have to.  Like LDON, it should allow players to work towards powerful items in small steps.  The storylines should put the players in the role of the hero and not the errand boy.  The storyline should progress as the players hunt.  Threats should seem real.  Adventure types should reward the players equally for equal difficulty and there should be a wider variety of them than the current ones.</p>

<p>Step 4: Simplify the interface.  Everquest's interface is very difficult for new players.  The basic controls alone require a lot of work but stack on communications and character improvement interfaces and you have one of the most complex game interfaces ever seen.</p>

<p>Reduce the number of windows a player must go through to set up disciplines.  Start all skills at 1 so they will raise on their own instead of requiring a player to run back and check with a guild master every couple of levels to see if there is a skill they missed.  Tell the player when a new discipline is available and let them scribe it like a spell.  Streamline the hotbox macro creation process so it is easy to build complex macros mixing skills, disciplines, spells, and other commands.</p>

<p>Perform usability tests with new players to see where interface elements break down and where they can be improved.  Basic usability tests are cheap to perform and can easily improve profits on even simple systems.</p>

<p>Simplify the interface and more players will stick with the game.</p>

<p>Step 5: Improve stability and lower network requirements.  When I first played Everquest Online Adventures on the Playstation 2, I was impressed by two things.  One, they download patches into three megs of space and it never gets any bigger.  Two, they focus almost entirely on game enhancements instead of stability improvements.</p>

<p>Make Everquest as stable as a console game.  Improve hardware testing and application testing so that players can reasonably expect the game to work every time they log in.  Many players still face a variety of technical issues and these issues are far more damaging to the game than almost any content problem.  The chaos of PC architectures makes testing very difficult.  Stability should be a number one concern for SOE developers.</p>

<p>The large patches that Everquest players face require a high-speed connection.  While the game itself plays well over dial up, downloading two hundred megs of updates cut off a lot of players from playing.  As DVD drives become more common on newer machines, offer Everquest with all expansions on a single DVD but lock the content the user didn't pay for.  Update this DVD with the most recent large patches so even existing players can go get the updates from a game magazine or from their local game shop.  Keep patches small and consider dial up players when they are released.  No patch should take longer than 30 minutes to download.  Even thirty minutes will cut out a lot of players.</p>

<p>I don't claim that these five steps are the keys to the success and future of Everquest, but from the five years I've played this game, the above steps seem to be the ones most hindering to new players.  New players are the key to success for Everquest in the years to come.  While a lot of players would rather SOE focus on the top 1%, that 1% is going to go away eventually and only by bringing in new and fresh players can Everquest continue to grow into the future.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
15 August 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-08-27T21:04:43+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 51: Tarlin and Taelosia</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001183.html</link>
      <description>Loral knew pain. He had seen suffering and felt both physical and emotional pain many times in his travels. None...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1183@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Loral knew pain.  He had seen suffering and felt both physical and emotional pain many times in his travels.  None matched the pain he felt when he saw his father.</p>

<p>Ciric had told Loral that his father was in a coma.  Loral expected to see his father prone, eyes closed, in deep sleep.  What he saw was a man in pure agony.  Tarlin, his skin hanging loose over atrophied muscles and bones, writhed on the bed.  His mouth opened and closed in silent screams.  His eyes rolled back in his head as his head shook from side to side.  Loral always remembered his father as a tall proud elf, well muscled and a head of thick blond hair.  How his hair hung stringy and loose and his body lay broken.</p>

<p>Tears rolled down Loral's face.  He sat down next to Tarlin and put his hand over his father's hand.  He felt heat radiating off of him.  Tarlin's skin was yellow and glistening with sweat.  Loral felt his father's hand twist into a pained claw tearing at the bed.  Loral closed his eyes and whispered a prayer to Tunare.  Warmth flowed through him and he channeled it into Tarlin.  It rolled off of the broken figure like water over stone.  His father's state did not change.</p>

<p>Loral heard a light rapping at the door and Ciric entered.  Loral looked to his mentor, his eyes begging for help from the old Eruidite.</p>

<p>"Heal him."  Loral's voice cracked and fresh tears rolled down his cheeks.</p>

<p>"My friend.  Your skills far surpass my own but there is nothing you or I can do for him."  Ciric's spoke in a voice low and even.  "He is not sick." Loral looked dumbfounded.  Ciric continued.  "No poison flows through his veins.  No disease eats at his organs.  There is nothing physically wrong with him that four months of hot meals and exercise would not solve.  Something eats at his mind.  His body and mind grew used to Torment; as used to it as any mortal mind can.  He faced horror you and I cannot ever dream of."</p>

<p>"How can we heal him?"  All of Loral's power and experience did nothing to take away the helplessness he felt.</p>

<p>"We can feed him.  We can keep him as comfortable as possible.  We can pray."</p>

<p>Loral looked at his longtime friend.  A feeling of helpless rage burned through him.  He looked at the Erudite and spoke two words sharp and powerful.</p>

<p>"Leave us."</p>

<p>Ciric turned to leave.  He closed the door and Loral heard his sandals on the hardwood floor of the small church.  While Ciric understood Loral's need for privacy, he did not understand that "us" meant "us three".</p>

<p>You can speak to him can't you?</p>

<p>Loral opened his mind and closed his eyes.  His mind expanded outward to the edges of the room.</p>

<p>YES.</p>

<p>The word filled Loral's head with red fire.  It was the voice of a thousand mouths, a voice of a thousand years.</p>

<p>What do you see?</p>

<p>Laughter fell upon Loral sharp as glass and heavy as stone.  Veins broke out on Loral's forehead.</p>

<p>PAIN.</p>

<p>Channel me to him.  Open his mind to me.</p>

<p>Silence greeted Loral's request.  Loral felt the burning shield on his back.  He felt the thick burning presence of the demon-lord, Xuzl within it.  He could feel the burning green eyes tearing holes into his back.  The laughter came again.</p>

<p>The world exploded.  Loral felt cold wind rip across his skin.  A claw dug into his neck.  His vision turned outside of himself and he saw a cloaked face, skin of blue and teeth like a shark.  Red eyes flashed and Loral felt a black jagged dagger rip through his chest.  Blackness filled his mind and he fell through the black stone floor under his feet into a sea of blood.  A world of blood awaited him.  Huge muscular arms covered in thick coarse hair picked him off of the ground, one of Loral's arms in each huge three-fingered hand.  He saw the face of a huge tusked boar, black saliva dripping and death screaming in the demon's eyes.  The demon pulled his arms apart.  Loral felt his muscles rip in his chest and shoulders.  He heard bones pop.  He felt skin tear.  Loral screamed.</p>

<p>The morning sun and a chilled breeze awoke Loral.  He sat up on a small bed and saw his robes and boots on a chair in the corner of a small room.  Outside the sounds of Qeynos set a contrast from the horrors of his visions.  He dressed in the green robe and stepped out into the halls of the church.  Ciric waited for him at a wooden table, a meal already prepared and waiting for the elven cleric.</p>

<p>"I don't know what happened to you but it knocked you unconscious for two days."  Ciric poured a cup of tea into a plain glass.  "Whatever you did, don't do it again."</p>

<p>"I had to try something."  Loral's weak voice brought concern to Ciric's eyes.  "He had been there before."  Loral sipped his tea and grimaced as it burned down his throat.  "To Hate, I mean.  I saw it.  Sometime during the first battles of Kelethin, my father fought Innoruuk's hoards."  Loral fixed his firey blue eyes on his old teacher.  "My father was a demonslayer."</p>

<p>"I tried to help him but I could not.  Saryn's torture-masters broke him under their cloven hooves.  I don't know if he will ever feel peace again."  Loral's head dipped.  "Until he dies."</p>

<p>The words hung in the air.  The implication made Ciric's shoulders sag.  He lifted a parchment sealed in black wax and handed it to Loral.</p>

<p>"This arrived for you yesterday.  It came through the sewers."  Loral looked up at the tone in Ciric's voice.  Both Loral and Ciric knew what it meant.  For years, rumors spoke of a cult of Bertoxxulous infesting the sewers of Qeynos.  Dark rites and the disappearances of children fed these rumors to the people of Qeynos.  "You have shady friends, Loral.  Be wary."</p>

<p>As a young acolite of Quellious, Ciric traveled by foot from Erudin to Kaladim in a journey that took three weeks.  He traveled over two oceans, a half dozen forests, two mountain ranges, and dozens of open planes.  Two hundred years later, Loral made a similar journey in less than an hour.</p>

<p>Loral's mind stretched across the webwork of power that fell over Norrath like a net.  Thin lines of ethereal magic stretched from the cities to the hub of New Tanaan, a pocket universe in the center of the Plane of Knowledge.  Many of these thin lines crossed the hundreds of miles between distant cities.  One of these lines stretched far across the skies to the moon of Luclin.  Some lines, tainted with darkness and filled with black poison, pierced through the thin fabric of Norrath's world and into into the pits of the lower worlds.</p>

<p>The stones of Knowledge anchored the beams to the hub of Tanaan while the books of Knowledge, material icons or metaphors of the vast distance one traveled along the cords of etheria, anchored the thin beams to the material worlds they connected. It was the line from Qeynos to Tanaan and from Tanaan to Shadowhaven that Loral sought this day.  </p>

<p>Loral looked at the strange book and stone pillar that sat like a splinter of another world through the green earth of Qeynos.  He imagined the thin lines stretching through a black universe of emptiness, a void of chaos.  Creatures beyond mortal comprehension whispered within those voids, threatening to slice the cords and send travelers into the waiting arms of a cold black hell.  Loral remembered a time not so long past when rumors spoke of the lines snapping.  The protective currents of the streams of knowledge snapped like threads.  Some awoke hours from their destinations.  Some awoke buried half within the earth, their organs burst and legs shattered from the earth and stone around them.  Some poor souls never returned at all.  To travel in the outer worlds risked the worst forms of death or banishment imaginable.</p>

<p>These grim thoughts followed Loral as he approached Qeynos's book of Knowledge.  The book shimmered in front of him.  He never liked using these strange artifacts, but like all of Norrath's adventurers, they quickly became too useful to pass up.  He read a strange book describing this planar travel, a book that described it in one word:  Todash.</p>

<p>The otherworld word sat on his lips as he placed his hands on the book and felt the world shift and shatter around him.  The cord pulled and a thousand miles passed by in seconds.</p>

<p>Minutes later, Loral arrived at the city of Shadowhaven deep within the moon of Luclin.</p>

<p>It was quiet in Shadowhaven's most popular inn and tavern.  The opening of the paths to the outer worlds sent most stout adventurers away from the  mysterious lands of Luclin.  Chairs sat upside down on the large thick tables.  Five or six patrons drank thick strange drinks after hard battles in the nearby hostile caverns of Paludal.  Their young age never ceased to surprise Loral.</p>

<p>"I was never so young," Loral whispered to himself.</p>

<p>A single figure sat in the corner of the bar where the shadows grew thickest.  The figure pulled back a black hood revealing the smooth bald head of a dark elf.  The dark elf gave Loral a smile that made the priest's skin crawl.</p>

<p>As he approached the dark elf, Loral became aware of how quiet it became.  It felt like a deep buzzing that quivered subconsciously in his mind ceased to buzz.  A clarity filled his mind.</p>

<p>The dark elf lifted one of his high soft leather boots and pushed a char out with its pointed toe.  Loral saw the short blade that hung low from the rogue's wide leather belt and a pair of dagger hilts sat comfortably in the tops of both boots.</p>

<p>"You look tired."  The dark elf's low guttural voice sounded like the hiss of a lizard preparing to strike a wounded animal.</p>

<p>"I've little time for chatter, Xarrak.  What do you have for me?"  Xarrak stretched his arms behind his back and Loral saw two more daggers strapped hilt downward on Xarrak's wrists.  Loral imagined that the rogue could send those two daggers twirling through the air before an eye could blink.</p>

<p>"Much has happened in your soft elven kingdom.  Mordin Rasp's agents stretch far, even into the circle of the council."  The thin rogue tipped lightly back in his chair, balancing only on two of the thin legs.  "The Wayfarer's attention strayed from the five lost dungeons.  Mordin Rasp commissioned a marvelous ship, huge and expensive."</p>

<p>"How did he fund it?"</p>

<p>"A year ago Rasp stumbled upon Nagafen's lost hoard.  It took him months to extract it all but once he did he had enough for his network of spies, his coven of magi, his five Wayfarer camps and the treasure they reward to the hapless adventurers who follow this barbarian like cattle to the slaughter.  Now he uses it to fund this ship."</p>

<p>"What does he want?"</p>

<p>"The Wayfarers sail west.  They found a new land, a land that sits between worlds.  There, a race of small elvish folk known as the Taelosians fight a hoard of powerful out-worlders called the Muramites."</p>

<p>Loral rolled his finger in the air beckoning the rogue to skip ahead.  Xarrak stopped speaking, letting the silence sit between them.</p>

<p>"He has the Grozmok stone."</p>

<p>Loral's eyes widened.  A chill flowed throug his veins like ice water.  Visions of the stone's dark power filling the Trolls of Grobb with their dark powers, twisting the Frogloks of Guk into horrible malformations of their once noble selves, and breaking open the pits of vampires that now infested Faydwer like an infected wound.  The stone was responsible for death and destruction and horror for a thousand years.  And now it was in Mordin Rasp's hands.</p>

<p>"Where."  The word slipped out of Loral's mouth in a low whisper.  Xarrak smiled.  The rogue sat silent until Loral's patience was at an end.  Just before the cleric exploded in rage, Xarrak spoke.</p>

<p>"On the ship.  Rasp uses it to find these new lands."</p>

<p>"The fool!"  Loral's shout sent the few eyes of the tavern his way and he quieted.</p>

<p>"The stone should be broken apart and scattered across the pits of the lower worlds.  It is an artifact of evil for evil.  The barbarian will bring ruin on us all."  Loral's shoulders sank.  "Who knows what horrors lurk in those dark lands, horrors awakening to the stone's dark wail."</p>

<p>"Indeed."  The dark elf slipped a long fingered hand towards Loral, a folded parchment magically appearing from the shadows of his palm.  "Your orders from the church.  I took the liberty of bringing them myself.  Those messengers of Felwithe are born into incompetence.</p>

<p>"And what do the orders say?"</p>

<p>"You will travel west with Rasp's crew.  You will travel to Taelosia."</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-08-11T04:25:16+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: The Calm Before the Storm</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001182.html</link>
      <description>We seem to sit within the valley between one expansion and the next. We had some great new patches since...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1182@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>We seem to sit within the valley between one expansion and the next.  We had some great new patches since the release of Gates of Discord, and we hear of some nice future updates.  Even with Omens of War on the horizon we sit here in the gap of a slow news week all the same.</p>

<p>One of the most interesting threads floating around within the Everquest community is <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=testing&amp;message.id=2568">Hobart's Test Server Update</a>.  If you ever want to see what new changes we should expect in the next patch, thats the place to go look.</p>

<p>The most recent updates to the test server include a lot of features for the raid tool.  Raid leaders will soon be able to lock and unlock a raid, remove group leader flags from raiders, remove players from any group within the raid, and buttons to put group members into other groups.  These changes are wonderful organizational changes and may be the best changes to the raid tool since its release back in Planes of Power.  Even for smaller two or three group raids, it is wonderful to be able to switch which player is in which group without going through the shuffle.</p>

<p>Now, of course, this will lead to whole fields of raiders going AFK while raids organize and may lead raid leaders to ask for the next logical update: "Give me a Warcraft 3 interface so I can just control the whole raid myself".  I kid, of course.  These changes help raiders quite a bit and feedback from summit raid leaders has been very good.</p>

<p>Along with new raid organization functions comes new consent functions.  Many raiders and even a few groupers want more powerful consenting features for corpse dragging.  More than a few players see death as a nice opportunity for a much needed AFK break frustrating draggers to no end when they must send "CONSENT PLZZ" about fifty times before getting a response.  Soon players can consent guilds, consent groups, and consent raids for dragging.  Again, these improvements help solve a lot of problems mainly for raiding guilds.</p>

<p>Expect new hunting hot spots with the next patch, says Brenlo of the Hairy Feet.  Hot spots, zones with increased zone experience modifiers, help push players to explore some areas to which they might not always travel by rewarding them with much improved experience gain.  The current hot spots existed for some time now and a change is due.  We don't know which zones will turn into hot spots yet, but many await the change.  Hot spots are a great feature for mid-level players.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Stormhammer&amp;message.id=783">thread on the Stormhammer server forums</a> sheds a harsh light on the 12 person LDON raid recently released on Stormhammer and moving soon to the live servers.  While I heard it was tuned for level 55s to 65s, a few players who actually tried it say it is tuned for Elemental, Time, and GoD equipped players.  These equipment restrictions put this raid in the same category as all of the LDON raids.  They are too hard, restricted to only Elemental+ equipped players, and offer too little a reward to make it attractive to those able to accomplish it.</p>

<p>The LDON raid system and the Gates of Discord Expedition system offer a lot of potential for mid-levelers and non-raiders to experience some of the fun and excitement of raiding.  These expeditions can offer raid-level content at any set level with restrictions on who can enter and how often without blocking it behind a rare flag-mob.  This new two-group raid looked like a great way to get 55s to non-raid-equipped 65s into some Lost Dungeon raids but it appears it is just another raid for the top-tier raiders.  With all of the unused raid content of LDON, I don't know why SOE tuned this event for the same players who already ignore LDON raids.</p>

<p>We have seen little new information on Omens of War.  Everyone has questions about how it will support their play-style.  No one knows what levels 66 to 70 will do to older expansions like Lost Dungeons and Gates.  SOE released no official word on existing level 65 focus effects but rumors speak of a nice flexible solution.  The task system interests a lot of people but I still feel too much weight falls onto it.  It may be doomed just by the sheer amount of attention it will get.  I hope it lives up to the expectations but only time will tell.</p>

<p>With the lack of other major news, people spread to their sixteen camps and began the class wars once again.  SOE plans to provide class definition documents that they have worked on for some time now.  These definitions help define what each classes role is in a group and in a raid.  I don't know if they will cover soloing but I do believe they cover a class from levels 1 to 65 (probably to 70).</p>

<p>Every class should bring a combination of abilities to a group at all levels that sets it apart from other classes.  No one class should be better in all ways than another.  Every class should have options and use for soloing, grouping, and raiding.  Every class should have a unique identity and background.</p>

<p>Feedback on the new Mobhunter design has been good and very useful.  Our plan is to switch over to the new version next Saturday.  Please give <a href="http://mobhunter.com/new/">the new Mobhunter design</a> a look and try out the comment system.</p>

<p>I have a small update on one of my secondary requests on Loral's Evil Agenda.  It appears with Nvidia-based video cards, one can span Everquest across two windows.  I had little luck with an Nvidia Geforce 5500; the EQ window never got bigger than about 2400 pixels wide; but the new Geforce 6800 GT runs EQ in a window 3200 x 1150 pixels wide for a total of 3.6 million pixels.  There are a couple of problems, however.  One cannot run in full screen mode or they crash to desktop and the window can't be a full 3200 x 1200 or it slows down to one frame a second.  If you don't mind seeing your start bar all the time, it can be a wild way to play.  </p>

<p>Why would someone want to play across two monitors?  If one runs a "/viewport 1601 0 1600 1150" they get a normal EQ view on the right monitor and a black background on the other.  Chats, maps, inventories, spell gems, buffs, and any other windows you don't have to see right away can be thrown over to the other monitor.</p>

<p>Its a bit of a gimmick but it is a neat way to play.  Here is a picture of <a href="http://mobhunter.com/new/images/eq_dual_monitor.jpg">Everquest running across two monitors</a>.</p>

<p>Look forward to an editorial on Everquest's current state of corpse recovery in the next two weeks and until then, play on.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
7 August 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-08-11T04:24:48+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>


  </channel>
</rss>

