<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>A couple more potential reasons why it&apos;s coming up now:

Because doing level 71 or 72 content w</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>A couple more potential reasons why it&apos;s coming up now:

Because doing level 71 or 72 content when some or all of your vital spells are still level 68 is harder than doing level 70 content with level 68 spells.

Because what might be an okay challenge for &quot;the ultimate spells&quot; is merely discouraging for spells which are stepping stones to higher content--especially when the higher content makes getting spells so much easier. And th</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Keisa

I appreciate your comments and am sure they are well intentioned.  Thank you.

so you suggest</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Keisa

I appreciate your comments and am sure they are well intentioned.  Thank you.

so you suggest that I take on a few easy quests to restore my positive attitude? I&apos;m a level 71 - un pl and un twink so you know I did it the old fashioned way no fancy gear etc

then follow Loral&apos;s plan to somehow level to 74 to get the replacement spells I need (and skip the OOW spells altogether) even though I am useless to groups without my spells </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>oh yeh I forgot to mention that only certain classes can research all those missing spells and Im no</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>oh yeh I forgot to mention that only certain classes can research all those missing spells and Im not a class that can so can you imagine how much i would have to pay for the service?  if anyone was willing to do it for me?  makes the earlier comments about not wanting the farmers to profit look like a joke when the bazaar is flooded with upgrades to the purchased 71+ spells..</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>If you&apos;re in a guild in which you don&apos;t have any friends, people who will not group with y</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>If you&apos;re in a guild in which you don&apos;t have any friends, people who will not group with you off-raid times, I have wonder why you are in the guild. 

For the most part, people who got their spells (69-70), worked together.  Unfortunately, expansions have moved on and it is harder to find help in older content. This is where true friends/groupmates come in.

Right now, I&apos;m back in DoD doing the progression missions. I haven&apos;t </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Keisa,

I gotta tell you, you have the most wild eyes happy view of the current state of the game of</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Keisa,

I gotta tell you, you have the most wild eyes happy view of the current state of the game of anyone I&apos;ve seen and read the comments on, and that includes people like Nolrog, so that&apos;s saying something.

First you seem to beleive that a re-tool of the AA exp system that effectively leaves people who have worked hard to finally be able to solo as a caual player and make headway on those 1500+ aa&apos;s stranded with no place to go</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Lane,

The first thing I would tell you is get rid of the concept that you are useless in a group.  </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Lane,

The first thing I would tell you is get rid of the concept that you are useless in a group.  Look at what you can bring to a group and work off that.  No class brings nothing to a group without high level spells.

If you are an enchanter or a shaman, you bring at the very least slow.  I am a beastlord.  Your slow will be at least as good as mine and that is the strength that gets me at least 50% of the groups I am in.  In either case, your</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Keisa,

Tell you what.  Ignore everything I just posted.

I just quit.  Logged into SOE Station, clo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Keisa,

Tell you what.  Ignore everything I just posted.

I just quit.  Logged into SOE Station, closed the account.

There is a time when you have to realize that what a game was, it isn&apos;t any more.  The rules change, there is no clear vision on what the game is supposed to entail.  It looses it&apos;s fun factor.

So what ever you where about to say.  Enough.  You win.

I quit.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Can I have your stuff?</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Can I have your stuff?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Richard,

We all pay our money to enjoy playing a game and be entertained by it.  There comes a time</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Richard,

We all pay our money to enjoy playing a game and be entertained by it.  There comes a time when we no longer enjoy doing the things we did, or because of changes to us or to the product, we are no longer entertained by it.  That is the time to move on and find other things to do with our time and our money.  For the record, that&apos;s partially paraphrasing what you said and making it more general.

I wish you the best in whatever you </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Not to rub anyone&apos;s face in it but it looks like that in WoW&apos;s new expansion, spells that </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Not to rub anyone&apos;s face in it but it looks like that in WoW&apos;s new expansion, spells that were previously dropped only (but tradable) will now be trainable at your class trainer; albeit at a higher level.

i.e. so at level 62, you can now train your &quot;hard to get&quot; level 60 spell.

one would think, that EQ&apos;s content was designed with the idea in mind that not everyone had all their spells?  For example, it has been said tha</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Of course the hard core players dont understand how poeple cant go without spells or why they dont h</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Of course the hard core players dont understand how poeple cant go without spells or why they dont have them yet. LOL because them have them and can probably solo to thier runes content. PLEASE spare me your &quot;Im better than you double talk&quot;</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>This may come as a shock to you, but a reasonably bazaar geared player today can have a hell of a lo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>This may come as a shock to you, but a reasonably bazaar geared player today can have a hell of a lot better gear than we did when we were camping these runes.  We didn&apos;t have GM armor or DON crystal armor and augments when we first went to MPG or RSS.  We had uberty 50-75 hp gear.  Now, you can collect not only that, but nice cloaks and gear.

So, you should be quite capable of doing these things.  No one is bragging about being uber here.
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>So Keisa, if it&apos;s as easy as you say, why do you think it is that so many people don&apos;t hav</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>So Keisa, if it&apos;s as easy as you say, why do you think it is that so many people don&apos;t have those spells?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Balancing equipment between raid and group need not be so special.  The drops achievable in either k</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Balancing equipment between raid and group need not be so special.  The drops achievable in either kind of event should be a bump up from the gear needed to be able to win it.  If handled with great skill, determination and the knowledge from many a wipe it should be a largish bump up.  If the group or raid is equipped well enough a moderate effort wins it should be a smallish upgrade.  Given gear good enough to turn the event into a mindless gri</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Keisa 

your suggestion to do what we can .. ie be a buffer only for instance take the fun out of th</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Keisa 

your suggestion to do what we can .. ie be a buffer only for instance take the fun out of the game  what happened to the tactics required to be successful?  when all we can contribute is to HO HUM haste cause mez dont work or slow when others have better and go afk between buffing sessions.  and all for?  to level?  what good is level if its no fun getting there?

it&apos;s a nice concept but not a very fun way to spend a session.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>