<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>Concerned1, you simply being obtuse now.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Concerned1, you simply being obtuse now.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>so the truth hurts and theres no where else to go so you attack me personally? how typical is that? </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>so the truth hurts and theres no where else to go so you attack me personally? how typical is that? i&apos;m on the outside.....i&apos;m looking in.....i see your true colors....</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>*sigh*

Know what? I never ever got to max level on any MMO. Ever, and I been playing MMOs since one</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>*sigh*

Know what? I never ever got to max level on any MMO. Ever, and I been playing MMOs since one week before Kunark came out. From MY perspective, you are no casual gamer at all, so stop trying to cry a river of blood here just because the big guys got some content they can actually take part off in the new expansion.

There are some TRUE casuals that wont ever get to max level, yet do you see me whining about how little kids like you can get</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>When I started playing the game, there were those people that prophisied the end of EQ.  They compla</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>When I started playing the game, there were those people that prophisied the end of EQ.  They complained about the uber players that rushed onward to the top end of the game and the fact that only raiding guilds could get the best stuff.

I joined a good guild and enjoyed playing the content, and worked my way through the levels.  I was not willing to give up the many zones of enjoyment SOE provided for me in order to speed past and get to the tw</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Sorry for my lack of communication, I&apos;ve been busy. The good news is that my WOW hunter is near</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Sorry for my lack of communication, I&apos;ve been busy. The good news is that my WOW hunter is nearly level 60. The bad news is that I completely missed a dev chat yesterday.

Skuz said: 

&quot;I do not agree with Loral that all groupable zones should be groupable by casuals however, but unlocked zones that destroy all but the currently very high end, may in future offer part of what he wants from group progression when future aa &amp; level &q</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Am I the only one (former raider / semi-casual these days) that appreciates the latest instanced con</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Am I the only one (former raider / semi-casual these days) that appreciates the latest instanced content? People who miss the non-instanced stuff don&apos;t seem to remember the underside of it all. The blown spawns (Coirnav &amp; PoE ring, thats &quot;fun&quot; for you), the rival trains to each other&apos;s raids, the contested kills, the huge lagfests when two 100 person zerg raids collide, flamewars, petitions and counter petitions to GMs.

I</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral &quot;I do not like paying for zones today that I can&apos;t use until I get new levels in ano</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Loral &quot;I do not like paying for zones today that I can&apos;t use until I get new levels in another expansion I buy two years from now. That&apos;s like some sort of evil reverse lay-away program.&quot;

You don&apos;t? Then every single expansion with top end raid-content in it must have burned you up.

If an expansion has 20 uninstanced zones and as a level 75 you have access to 18 of them, ok so probably 10 are aimed at a playerbase so fa</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The only valid point on all that garbage post of his is:

&quot;ubers alone cant keep eq afloat.&quo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The only valid point on all that garbage post of his is:

&quot;ubers alone cant keep eq afloat.&quot;

As the other  points covered by Loral on his last post were not noted on Concerned1&apos;s last post.

I agree there has to be equipment progression for everyone. I agree the two non instanced zones will be underused, but I bet the intent of the devs is for raiders to single group, and if they somehow managed to encourage this, then the two zon</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;Comment Posted by: Skuz Bukit on August 12, 2006 02:56 AM

Loral &quot;I do not like paying fo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;Comment Posted by: Skuz Bukit on August 12, 2006 02:56 AM

Loral &quot;I do not like paying for zones today that I can&apos;t use until I get new levels in another expansion I buy two years from now. That&apos;s like some sort of evil reverse lay-away program.&quot;

You don&apos;t? Then every single expansion with top end raid-content in it must have burned you up.&quot;

Every expansion that has focused on a lot of raid content has burned</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I think I&apos;m going to have to disagree on this one. This isn&apos;t like PoP, where the only thi</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I think I&apos;m going to have to disagree on this one. This isn&apos;t like PoP, where the only thing that kept non-raiders from getting all the benefits of grouping in the elemental planes was not being flagged. Here the prerequisite is gear.

I think it&apos;s safe to assume that many (most?) raiders don&apos;t want to spend all their time raiding. Some may even want to spend time playing in a single group. And when they do, they want the same</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I remember posting a suggestion years ago when the raider/non-raider gear gap first raised its head.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I remember posting a suggestion years ago when the raider/non-raider gear gap first raised its head. Essentially you cant design content for both so stop trying. ie release 2 expansions one for raiders and one for groupers and them in the end segregate the servers to raid only content and non raid content perhaps delivered by 2 different teams. It will save SOE money not having to run so much underused content on hardware and allow itemisation/ab</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>@ Sabrex

Thats not a good model, like has been pointed out the game needs players at all levels, no</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>@ Sabrex

Thats not a good model, like has been pointed out the game needs players at all levels, not just in gear terms but also at a social level, to ignore the social side of eq is a mistake.

But the way you put it made me think of a new way to look at this &quot; i pay $xx.xx for xx% of content i don&apos;t get to use&quot; 

Well I think thats true both ends of the scale, a large portion of the group content is either pointless, or too easy</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>From my perspective I havent grouped with a raider since mid Ldon other than begging a friendly tank</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>From my perspective I havent grouped with a raider since mid Ldon other than begging a friendly tank to solo a named in GoD for us. The reality is I cant group anywhere they find worth doing and I wasnt flagged for their traditional xp zones. My argument is not I dont get my moneys worth, but rather its an economic rationalist view point. If we have to persist with two distinct populations incapable of grouping together for mutual benefit why con</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>You raise some good points and Ideas in your final Paragraph Sabrex.

What I would agree with is the</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>You raise some good points and Ideas in your final Paragraph Sabrex.

What I would agree with is the 80% of raider power, for one thing I think it would benefit the raid guilds as new applicants are not going to be vastly underpowered &amp; can perform their role on a raid without dying in a heartbeat, a 20% lower geared player is a gap that is viable for a raid to cover imho.

As far as how groupers can reach that 80%, I think repetition shouldn</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Im assuming getting to 80% for a non raider will be hard and involve the completion of many quests a</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Im assuming getting to 80% for a non raider will be hard and involve the completion of many quests and in general there will be an overlap of raider and non-raiding powers. ie high end raiders will depending on their effort be 60-100% while non raiders 40-80%. What I want to see is for the commited players of either stream a good overlap 55-75% during the prime time of an expansion in which either can group together for mutual benefit. </description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>