<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always be better than s</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always be better than single-group gear in the same expansions, or even up to three expansions back, but level 65 Tacvi gear shouldn&apos;t be better than the best single-group level 75 gear this far into the game.

Narrowing the gap would help the game out a lot.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral said --&gt;I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Loral said --&gt;I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always be better than single-group gear in the same expansions, or even up to three expansions back, but level 65 Tacvi gear shouldn&apos;t be better than the best single-group level 75 gear this far into the game.

Narrowing the gap would help the game out a lot


I agree with this completely. When i said &quot;close&quot; the gear gap I should have sai</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>[quote = Loral]I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always b</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>[quote = Loral]I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always be better than single-group gear in the same expansions, or even up to three expansions back, but level 65 Tacvi gear shouldn&apos;t be better than the best single-group level 75 gear this far into the game.

Narrowing the gap would help the game out a lot.[/quote]

I think I would put the gear from the hardest, best designed, complex group missions</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I have come to point i believe where I can no longer play and enjoy this game. I dont have the time </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I have come to point i believe where I can no longer play and enjoy this game. I dont have the time to raid so I&apos;m screwed. I&apos;m in a small family guild, Screwed. I play a Melee and if group not on i sit LFG for 3+hours, Screwed. 

I thought the push to 75 was good for the game but after getting there I now believe otherwise. I cant solo or Duo anything that would produce a decent drop for me. And now im too high to get decent XP in the </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I agree the gap is huge now, but I think you overstate what is required to get the TSS armor, and I </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I agree the gap is huge now, but I think you overstate what is required to get the TSS armor, and I don&apos;t think it should be easier to get, as many of the camps are trivial (ie light blue trash) at 75.  The power sources drop almost every time you kill a named in Vald for example, and both together require a similar overall effort as past armor quests.

What surprised me most when I returned was that my gear was still pretty good, even after</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>(quick reply: Raiders shouldn&apos;t fuel the gear for a server.  Players should be able to go out O</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>(quick reply: Raiders shouldn&apos;t fuel the gear for a server.  Players should be able to go out ON THEIR OWN (either 1 or 2 groups) to get their major upgrades.  Sure make a few soloable to make it a little easier.)

I think &quot;The Gap&quot; can&apos;t be discussed in terms of HP/MANA anymore.  (I don&apos;t know if it&apos;s just the terminology we use for this topic??)

There are really lots of subgroups for the itemization: weapons (rati</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>While you are right in that HP/Mana are perhaps a bit over rated in their item power comparion, they</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>While you are right in that HP/Mana are perhaps a bit over rated in their item power comparion, they are however a common requirement for all classes and so can be used to involve all in the discussion. Also with it being easy to hit the cap on all the primary stats worrying about the stats on items is useless. As a necro I am 82 points over my INT cap and some of the items I use don&apos;t have INT at all. For me I look at item power in terms of</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Or to summarize.

Current EQ game design is hopelessly FUBAR&apos;ed.

Been that way ... well foreve</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Or to summarize.

Current EQ game design is hopelessly FUBAR&apos;ed.

Been that way ... well forever. 

You are in thier world now ... suck it up.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Tuppet wrote:-TSS 70+ Single Group Weapons.
-Weapons in TSS So far

*I think Merloc is looking at tu</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Tuppet wrote:-TSS 70+ Single Group Weapons.
-Weapons in TSS So far

*I think Merloc is looking at tuning these for next patch not sure though

Tuppet wrote:-Teir 4 Helms: Warrior 90ac, Paladin 70ac, Chain 70ac Why?

*already fixed for next patch as far as I know. cant point to the thread but Merloc said it was probably a error and he fixed it

Tuppet wrote -Lack of focuses on end game class only items (Focus affects after level 70)

*no clue if t</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Ever since EQ began, its been clear: the more you put in, the more you get out. More what? Time? Yes</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Ever since EQ began, its been clear: the more you put in, the more you get out. More what? Time? Yes but that’s not all. Will you commit to bend your brain around certain problems? Will you take on encounters that may be unpleasant so that you can win a prize? Will you undergo flags? Will you help others get theirs? Will you wait in line until the raid is ready, til the OTM is called.

If you think there should not be a reward for those that go t</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I think you guys look at it wrong, esp you Loral.

I think you need to look at the best gear you can</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I think you guys look at it wrong, esp you Loral.

I think you need to look at the best gear you can achieve in group format, then when you have 6 folks in top end group&apos;d gear, go back and look at what &apos;&apos;raid&apos;&apos; mobs that group could now kill. Primals/qvic goats spring to mind. Then once those have been farmed by this group. What else can they now kill? And so on. Untill they hit the hardline where you need more than 6 to</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I have a lot of respect for you Loral, but you have made some real mistakes here.  Your comparison i</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I have a lot of respect for you Loral, but you have made some real mistakes here.  Your comparison is the first one.  The single group helm is trivial to get, and anyone wanting to get it can,without much difficulty. The raid helm on the other hand is extremely difficult to get,requiring tons of raiding, plus more difficult(and more annoying)quests.  One is available and doable by anyone, the other is available, at the current time,only to the mo</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>How gear is acquired isn&apos;t really my point. Again, this isn&apos;t about who deserves what for </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>How gear is acquired isn&apos;t really my point. Again, this isn&apos;t about who deserves what for their time or energy.

The gear gap makes it nearly impossible for SOE to balance group content at the highest level because they don&apos;t know whether that level 75 is wearing DON armor or Ashengate armor. We have clerics in one guild alone where the available mana pool goes from about 7500 to 13,000 and that&apos;s only up to Anguish armor.

Ge</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Then again Loral, that&apos;s just the Tier 1 raid gear, which is far easier to obtain now that it w</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Then again Loral, that&apos;s just the Tier 1 raid gear, which is far easier to obtain now that it was a year and a half ago. The Tier 3 highest level raid gear will still be able to last into level 70. And so will the Tier 2 and 2.5 gear. Though, the way they&apos;ve found to allow that type of progression is to finish their stuff after they release it unfinsihed. I mean we&apos;re still waiting for half of SoL.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>How about we reward the people who have huge amounts of time to spend playing, instead of catering t</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>How about we reward the people who have huge amounts of time to spend playing, instead of catering to regular people who love instant gratification. 

Everquest for the most part, wasn&apos;t designed for the casual player, and that is its most endearing trait.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>