<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://mikeshea.net/rss.css" type="text/css"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

  <channel>
    <title>LoralCiriclight.com</title>
    <link>http://loralciriclight.com/</link>
    <description>Tales and adventures of Loral Ciriclight in the online role playing game, Everquest.</description>
    <dc:language>en-us</dc:language>
    <dc:creator>mike@mikeshea.net</dc:creator>
    <dc:rights>Copyright 2005</dc:rights>
    <dc:date>2005-02-05T03:22:57+00:00</dc:date>
    <admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.movabletype.org/?v=3.01D" />
    <admin:errorReportsTo rdf:resource="mailto:mike@mikeshea.net"/>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>

    <item>
      <title>Everything You Need to Know About Writing Successfully - in Ten Minutes, by Stephen King</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001256.html</link>
      <description>&quot;Everything You Need to Know About Writing Successfully - in Ten Minutes&quot; by Stephen King (reprinted in Sylvia K. Burack,...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1256@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>"Everything You Need to Know About Writing Successfully - in Ten Minutes"</p>

<p>by Stephen King<br />
(reprinted in Sylvia K. Burack, ed. The Writer's Handbook. Boston, MA: Writer, Inc., 1988: 3-9)</p>

<p>I. The First Introduction</p>

<p>THAT'S RIGHT. I know it sounds like an ad for some sleazy writers' school, but I really am going to tell you everything you need to pursue a successful and financially rewarding career writing fiction, and I really am going to do it in ten minutes, which is exactly how long it took me to learn. It will actually take you twenty minutes or so to read this essay, however, because I have to tell you a story, and then I have to write a second introduction. But these, I argue, should not count in the ten minutes.</p>

<p>II. The Story, or, How Stephen King Learned to Write</p>

<p>When I was a sophomore in high school, I did a sophomoric thing which got me in a pot of fairly hot water, as sophomoric didoes often do. I wrote and published a small satiric newspaper called The Village Vomit. In this little paper I lampooned a number of teachers at Lisbon (Maine) High School, where I was under instruction. These were not very gentle lampoons; they ranged from the scatological to the downright cruel.</p>

<p>Eventually, a copy of this little newspaper found its way into the hands of a faculty member, and since I had been unwise enough to put my name on it (a fault, some critics argue, of which I have still not been entirely cured), I was brought into the office. The sophisticated satirist had by that time reverted to what he really was: a fourteen-year-old kid who was shaking in his boots and wondering if he was going to get a suspension ... what we called "a three-day vacation" in those dim days of 1964.</p>

<p>I wasn't suspended. I was forced to make a number of apologies - they were warranted, but they still tasted like dog-dirt in my mouth - and spent a week in detention hall. And the guidance counselor arranged what he no doubt thought of as a more constructive channel for my talents. This was a job - contingent upon the editor's approval - writing sports for the Lisbon Enterprise, a twelve-page weekly of the sort with which any small-town resident will be familiar. This editor was the man who taught me everything I know about writing in ten minutes. His name was John Gould - not the famed New England humorist or the novelist who wrote The Greenleaf Fires, but a relative of both, I believe.</p>

<p>He told me he needed a sports writer and we could "try each other out" if I wanted.</p>

<p>I told him I knew more about advanced algebra than I did sports.</p>

<p>Gould nodded and said, "You'll learn."</p>

<p>I said I would at least try to learn. Gould gave me a huge roll of yellow paper and promised me a wage of 1/2¢ per word. The first two pieces I wrote had to do with a high school basketball game in which a member of my school team broke the Lisbon High scoring record. One of these pieces was straight reportage. The second was a feature article.</p>

<p>I brought them to Gould the day after the game, so he'd have them for the paper, which came out Fridays. He read the straight piece, made two minor corrections, and spiked it. Then he started in on the feature piece with a large black pen and taught me all I ever needed to know about my craft. I wish I still had the piece - it deserves to be framed, editorial corrections and all - but I can remember pretty well how it looked when he had finished with it. Here's an example:</p>

<p>(note: this is before the edit marks indicated on King's original copy)</p>

<p>        <blockquote>Last night, in the well-loved gymnasium of Lisbon High School, partisans and Jay Hills fans alike were stunned by an athletic performance unequaled in school history: Bob Ransom, known as "Bullet" Bob for both his size and accuracy, scored thirty-seven points. He did it with grace and speed ... and he did it with an odd courtesy as well, committing only two personal fouls in his knight-like quest for a record which has eluded Lisbon thinclads since 1953....</blockquote></p>

<p>(after edit marks)</p>

<p>        <blockquote>Last night, in the Lisbon High School gymnasium, partisans and Jay Hills fans alike were stunned by an athletic performance unequaled in school history: Bob Ransom scored thirty-seven points. He did it with grace and speed ... and he did it with an odd courtesy as well, committing only two personal fouls in his quest for a record which has eluded Lisbon's basketball team since 1953....</blockquote></p>

<p>When Gould finished marking up my copy in the manner I have indicated above, he looked up and must have seen something on my face. I think he must have thought it was horror, but it was not: it was revelation.</p>

<p>"I only took out the bad parts, you know," he said. "Most of it's pretty good."</p>

<p>"I know," I said, meaning both things: yes, most of it was good, and yes, he had only taken out the bad parts. "I won't do it again."</p>

<p>"If that's true," he said, "you'll never have to work again. You can do this for a living." Then he threw back his head and laughed.</p>

<p>And he was right; I am doing this for a living, and as long as I can keep on, I don't expect ever to have to work again.</p>

<p>III. The Second Introduction</p>

<p>All of what follows has been said before. If you are interested enough in writing to be a purchaser of this magazine, you will have either heard or read all (or almost all) of it before. Thousands of writing courses are taught across the United States each year; seminars are convened; guest lecturers talk, then answer questions, then drink as many gin and tonics as their expense-fees will allow, and it all boils down to what follows.</p>

<p>I am going to tell you these things again because often people will only listen - really listen - to someone who makes a lot of money doing the thing he's talking about. This is sad but true. And I told you the story above not to make myself sound like a character out of a Horatio Alger novel but to make a point: I saw, I listened, and I learned. Until that day in John Gould's little office, I had been writing first drafts of stories which might run 2,500 words. The second drafts were apt to run 3,300 words. Following that day, my 2,500-word first drafts became 2,200-word second drafts. And two years after that, I sold the first one.</p>

<p>So here it is, with all the bark stripped off. It'll take ten minutes to read, and you can apply it right away ... if you listen.</p>

<p>IV. Everything You Need to Know About Writing Successfully</p>

<p>1. Be talented</p>

<p>    This, of course, is the killer. What is talent? I can hear someone shouting, and here we are, ready to get into a discussion right up there with "what is the meaning of life?" for weighty pronouncements and total uselessness. For the purposes of the beginning writer, talent may as well be defined as eventual success - publication and money. If you wrote something for which someone sent you a check, if you cashed the check and it didn't bounce, and if you then paid the light bill with the money, I consider you talented.</p>

<p>    Now some of you are really hollering. Some of you are calling me one crass money-fixated creep. And some of you are calling me bad names. Are you calling Harold Robbins talented? someone in one of the Great English Departments of America is screeching. V.C. Andrews? Theodore Dreiser? Or what about you, you dyslexic moron?</p>

<p>    Nonsense. Worse than nonsense, off the subject. We're not talking about good or bad here. I'm interested in telling you how to get your stuff published, not in critical judgments of who's good or bad. As a rule the critical judgments come after the check's been spent, anyway. I have my own opinions, but most times I keep them to myself. People who are published steadily and are paid for what they are writing may be either saints or trollops, but they are clearly reaching a great many someones who want what they have. Ergo, they are communicating. Ergo, they are talented. The biggest part of writing successfully is being talented, and in the context of marketing, the only bad writer is one who doesn't get paid. If you're not talented, you won't succeed. And if you're not succeeding, you should know when to quit.</p>

<p>    When is that? I don't know. It's different for each writer. Not after six rejection slips, certainly, nor after sixty. But after six hundred? Maybe. After six thousand? My friend, after six thousand pinks, it's time you tried painting or computer programming.</p>

<p>    Further, almost every aspiring writer knows when he is getting warmer - you start getting little jotted notes on your rejection slips, or personal letters . . . maybe a commiserating phone call. It's lonely out there in the cold, but there are encouraging voices ... unless there is nothing in your words which warrants encouragement. I think you owe it to yourself to skip as much of the self-illusion as possible. If your eyes are open, you'll know which way to go ... or when to turn back.</p>

<p>2. Be neat</p>

<p>    Type. Double-space. Use a nice heavy white paper, never that erasable onion-skin stuff. If you've marked up your manuscript a lot, do another draft.</p>

<p>3. Be self-critical</p>

<p>    If you haven't marked up your manuscript a lot, you did a lazy job. Only God gets things right the first time. Don't be a slob.</p>

<p>4. Remove every extraneous word</p>

<p>    You want to get up on a soapbox and preach? Fine. Get one and try your local park. You want to write for money? Get to the point. And if you remove all the excess garbage and discover you can't find the point, tear up what you wrote and start all over again . . . or try something new.</p>

<p>5. Never look at a reference book while doing a first draft</p>

<p>    You want to write a story? Fine. Put away your dictionary, your encyclopedias, your World Almanac, and your thesaurus. Better yet, throw your thesaurus into the wastebasket. The only things creepier than a thesaurus are those little paperbacks college students too lazy to read the assigned novels buy around exam time. Any word you have to hunt for in a thesaurus is the wrong word. There are no exceptions to this rule. You think you might have misspelled a word? O.K., so here is your choice: either look it up in the dictionary, thereby making sure you have it right - and breaking your train of thought and the writer's trance in the bargain - or just spell it phonetically and correct it later. Why not? Did you think it was going to go somewhere? And if you need to know the largest city in Brazil and you find you don't have it in your head, why not write in Miami, or Cleveland? You can check it ... but later. When you sit down to write, write. Don't do anything else except go to the bathroom, and only do that if it absolutely cannot be put off.</p>

<p>6. Know the markets</p>

<p>    Only a dimwit would send a story about giant vampire bats surrounding a high school to McCall's. Only a dimwit would send a tender story about a mother and daughter making up their differences on Christmas Eve to Playboy ... but people do it all the time. I'm not exaggerating; I have seen such stories in the slush piles of the actual magazines. If you write a good story, why send it out in an ignorant fashion? Would you send your kid out in a snowstorm dressed in Bermuda shorts and a tank top? If you like science fiction, read the magazines. If you want to write confession stories, read the magazines. And so on. It isn't just a matter of knowing what's right for the present story; you can begin to catch on, after awhile, to overall rhythms, editorial likes and dislikes, a magazine's entire slant. Sometimes your reading can influence the next story, and create a sale.</p>

<p>7. Write to entertain</p>

<p>    Does this mean you can't write "serious fiction"? It does not. Somewhere along the line pernicious critics have invested the American reading and writing public with the idea that entertaining fiction and serious ideas do not overlap. This would have surprised Charles Dickens, not to mention Jane Austen, John Steinbeck, William Faulkner, Bernard Malamud, and hundreds of others. But your serious ideas must always serve your story, not the other way around. I repeat: if you want to preach, get a soapbox.</p>

<p>8. Ask yourself frequently, "Am I having fun?"</p>

<p>    The answer needn't always be yes. But if it's always no, it's time for a new project or a new career.</p>

<p>9. How to evaluate criticism</p>

<p>    Show your piece to a number of people - ten, let us say. Listen carefully to what they tell you. Smile and nod a lot. Then review what was said very carefully. If your critics are all telling you the same thing about some facet of your story - a plot twist that doesn't work, a character who rings false, stilted narrative, or half a dozen other possibles - change that facet. It doesn't matter if you really liked that twist of that character; if a lot of people are telling you something is wrong with you piece, it is. If seven or eight of them are hitting on that same thing, I'd still suggest changing it. But if everyone - or even most everyone - is criticizing something different, you can safely disregard what all of them say.</p>

<p>10. Observe all rules for proper submission</p>

<p>    Return postage, self-addressed envelope, all of that.</p>

<p>11. An agent? Forget it. For now</p>

<p>    Agents get 10% of monies earned by their clients. 10% of nothing is nothing. Agents also have to pay the rent. Beginning writers do not contribute to that or any other necessity of life. Flog your stories around yourself. If you've done a novel, send around query letters to publishers, one by one, and follow up with sample chapters and/or the manuscript complete. And remember Stephen King's First Rule of Writers and Agents, learned by bitter personal experience: You don't need one until you're making enough for someone to steal ... and if you're making that much, you'll be able to take your pick of good agents.</p>

<p>12. If it's bad, kill it</p>

<p>    When it comes to people, mercy killing is against the law. When it comes to fiction, it is the law.</p>

<p>That's everything you need to know. And if you listened, you can write everything and anything you want. Now I believe I will wish you a pleasant day and sign off.</p>

<p>My ten minutes are up.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject></dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-02-05T03:22:57+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Of Wing and Fang</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001253.html</link>
      <description>SOE released quite a large patch this week. You can read the entire patch message here but I will highlight...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1253@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>SOE released quite a <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?article=7543">large patch</a> this week.  You can read the entire patch message here but I will highlight a few of the more interesting features.</p>

<p>Lost Dungeons received a much requested selection menu for one of the four mission types.  While this decision will certainly be popular for those who still adventure, it basically removes the assassination and rescue missions from the list.  The collection and murder spree missions are much easier than the assassination and rescue missions.  Few would ever select a mission that offers a harder difficulty for no gain in reward.</p>

<p>One of my problems with LDON is the lack of a story arc.  I actually prefer going on assassination missions because they are one of the only adventure types that has a building plot and a final confrontation.  Boss mobs and anti-heroes are important not only in video games but also in traditional fantasy.  Walking into a dungeon and killing 58 skeletons or collecting 28 bone chips doesn't have the same energy as going into a dungeon, killing 57 skeletons and then killing Ograth the Skeleton King.  </p>

<p>A better solution to the selection choice would be to make rescue and assassination missions offer up a higher reward for their difficulty.  Giving boss mobs nice loot or rescued NPCs offering up a reward for their return might have made the difference enough that people would once again select them. This change puts a band-aid on the problem of convenience.</p>

<p>SOE revamped two older zones this week including Mistmoore and Paw.  Both zones now harbor beasts above level 60.  Walking into Mistmoore at level 69, I was reminded of how I felt entering the dark castle at the young age of 30.  Mistmoore was always a very difficult dungeon and well known to eat even the heartiest of adventures.  It is nice to see it return to its former danger.</p>

<p>Part of that danger, however, came from some of the quirks of the dungeon.  Mob pathing was never very good and it wasn't uncommon to see enormous trains pour out of the castle and tear across the courtyard killing anything that moved.  That tradition remains today.  It isn't uncommon to see a mob run in the opposite direction and return with a couple of friends when you pull it.  From the item links floating through our network of channels, the loot supports the reward, but it would have been nice to have a zone whose danger didn't come from its unexpected bug-based behavior.</p>

<p>I have yet to step foot into the new paw but from the equipment I see, I imagine it is as difficult as Mistmoore was.  Paw always had one of the most difficult dungeon layouts that only the oldest old-world dungeons had.  Remember upper and lower guk?  How about Kedge Keep?  I am sure old timers wax nostalgia about the difficulty of old-world dungeons but few ever went deep into paw.   Most groups found a cozy corner near the zone and pulled what they could see.  Only adventures many levels above the zone population would dare to delve deep in and even then they had a gate potion at the ready.</p>

<p>One very small fix in this patch that had me cheering out loud was a fix to the font system.  I always preferred Verdana over Arial as a font but using such a wide font ended up breaking the item counts on stackable items.  This last patch fixed this problem.  It was a small but useful fix.</p>

<p>This patch did not implement the task changes I had hoped to see. We will not see these new tasks and task improvements until the release of Dragons of Norrath.  It would have been nice to see these new tasks before the release of the next expansion but improvements to the task system at any time will hopefully help those who prefer to hunt solo.</p>

<p>This week EQ Stratics hosted a <a href="http://eq.stratics.com/content/hoclogs/donhoc.php">developer chat</a> with Travis Mcgearthy and Ryan Barker of the EQLive design team to talk more about Dragons of Norrath.  This was the first time SOE discussed the details of the new Mission system with those outside of the Dragons of Norrath beta.  While a future preview of Dragons of Norrath will go into more detail on this system and the other features of DoN, I can make a few general statements on what we see so far.</p>

<p>Of all of the features of Dragons, none excite me as much as the Mission system.  The Mission system ties together the Omens of War task system, the Gates of Discord expedition system, and the Lost Dungeons adventure point system.  Players pick a particular mission, one with much greater variety than the four LDON types, and complete that mission in an instanced part of a larger dungeon zone.  Completing this mission awards a sort of currency that can be used to purchase new items.</p>

<p>There are a number of advantages to this system.  They have well-defined timeframes for completion, in this case, about an hour.  They reward every member of a group equally rather than favoring one lucky party member with random loot.  They offer gameplay variants other than sitting and hunting at a particular camping spot.</p>

<p>For those of us who thought LDON was one of the great improvements in Everquest, the Mission system answers our roar of requests.  Unlike LDON, however, Dragons features a lot of raid content (dragons!) and general overland and dungeon non-instanced zone exploration.</p>

<p>We had a busy week and I expect a few more in the future.  In the next couple of weeks I will write a preview of Dragons of Norrath that will go into further detail into these systems and the other features of this expansion.  In the mean time, lets hunt some vampires.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
2 February 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-02-02T14:58:31+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 56: Glave</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001252.html</link>
      <description>Cold wind swept through the mountain pass. No creature stirred. The two figures sat motionless as the wind whipped through...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1252@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Cold wind swept through the mountain pass.  No creature stirred.  The two figures sat motionless as the wind whipped through their cloaks and robes.  One, fair-skinned and robed in green, sat and watched the other with eyes of pale blue.  The other, cloaked and hooded in black, stared back with two solid black eyes as cold and empty as the abyss.</p>

<p>Loral listened for the sounds of the Muramites as they crawled over the Taelosian temples of power.  He heard nothing.  Truth seeped into his mind as the cold seeped into his skin.  He and this dark figure were not in Taelosia.  They were somewhere else.</p>

<p>Since those first four words, the glyph-skinned being said nothing to Loral.  Beyond those four words, the two would never speak again.  Loral watched the black script on the vampire's skin shift and weave.  Loral saw quick glimpses of elder elvish script shifting into an older and far more terrifying abyssal script.  The runes, if read, would drive a man mad.  Loral felt the age and deep dark power within the vampire that sat silently across from him.  This was no mere minion of Mistmoore.  This was a vampire lord; an assassin of dark kings.  This was a creature beyond Loral's power and it meant to kill him.</p>

<p>The attack, one of Glave's weaker strikes meant to test his opponents, struck Loral like a dark lance.  The telepathic black spike ripped into Loral, though the vampire never moved .  Loral cried out in pain as a bolt of steel tore into his mind.  Another black spike appeared in the air above Glave's head and speared  in.  Loral's eyes blazed and a crystal shield appeared before him.  The black spike smashed into it and shattered into shards of onyx that evaporated before they touched the ground.</p>

<p>Loral now realized where they were.  They were in some sort of pocket in space and time, some micro-world between their two minds.  They sat in a battlefield where their minds would clash like gladiators in the arena.  The winner would awaken as though nothing had happened.  The other would not wake up at all.</p>

<p>Three more black lances raced in and all three burst against Loral's mental shields.  A droplet of sweat dripped down the side of Loral's face.  A vein stood out on the side of his head.  Glave, hardly breathing at all, smiled.</p>

<p>A memory, nearly a century old and two continents away, returned to Loral.  "Thankfully, few beasts possess any sort of telepathic ability.  Most of those that do possess nothing more than slight empathy or projection."  A wizard of the Towers visited the church of Tunare when Loral was fourteen.  The long haired wizard lectured the acolytes on the strange magics of Norrath.  Loral found it fascinating.  "Most telepathic power beyond this is limited to the demons, devils, daemons, demodands, and celestials of the outer planes.  Very few mortals ever possessed such abilities.  Old dark texts speak to some undead possessing such powers after eons of work in the dark crypts below the earth.</p>

<p>"We have read of telepathic battles from some time long past.  These battles take place mostly in symbolism and metaphor.  The complexity of telepathic battle is too difficult to handle directly.  Instead, each combatant imagines physical representations of psychic energy.  A sword, a shield, a wall, a fox, a bird; any of these can serve to focus and visualize the offensive and defensive powers of telepathy."</p>

<p>Loral now understood exactly what that wizard meant.  Only three times had he experienced what the old wizard had spoke of.  The first time, the undead dragon, Trakanon, paralyzed him with an onslaught of the dragon's lifetime of experience.  It burned through Loral like a poisoned nightmare.  The second time the Shissar telepaths drilled into Loral's brain feeding him a world so real he still had trouble separating it from the world he now resided in.  The third time...</p>

<p>Three more lances arched in, shattering Loral's thoughts of the past.  Loral repelled all three but with much effort.  Glave smiled again, revealing small sharp teeth.  A black squid burst open above Glave's hooded head.  Dozens of tentacles writhed in the cold air.  Two tentacles pierced in but a shining sword burst into existence over Loral's head and parried the two tentacles away.  The sword, covered in blue fire, came from deep in Loral's memory but he could not place it, nor did he have time to consider it.  The sword wove and weaved, cutting and parrying as the black psychic tentacles stabbed and twisted in.  Twenty slick tentacles grew where ten had been.  Like an unholy sunflower, the tentacles weaved and writhed above the grinning hooded vampire.</p>

<p>Loral's sword continued to slice through and parry but as the speed of the tentacle attack increased, he could not keep up.  Loral knew he was going to lose.  One of the tentacles twisted around the blade and pierced into Loral's shoulder.  It burned like black fire.  Loral felt his life draining away, sucked out by the oily spear.  The blade severed the attacking tentacle and it fell into the ground continuing to writhe as it faded from existence.</p>

<p>Two tentacles twisted around the pommel of the sword and wrenched it out of the way.  Two more tentacles punctured into the sides of Loral's temples.  Loral felt visions and memories rush through his breaking mind.  He saw his father and his teacher.  He saw the son he never had, a false memory implanted by the Shissar.  He felt the tentacles sucking his memories out of his head and feeding into Glave's tainted power.</p>

<p>A voice spoke in the deep reaches of Loral's mind.</p>

<p>"Release me."  Xuzl spoke in the ancient tongue of the demon princes of Fire.  His voice was full of dread and power.  "He is beyond you, but not beyond me.  Release me and we bargain later."  </p>

<p>Loral screamed in frustration and pain.  He saw the demon trapped in a vault of steel and magic.  He imagined the key.  The key turned and Loral released the demon.</p>

<p>The effect was immediate.</p>

<p>The two tentacles that pierced Loral's temples burst into hot flame.  They grayed and turned to ash almost at once.  Glave grunted in pain and his smile disappeared.  Few creatures could match Glave's telepathic ability.  Xuzl didn't match it, he far surpassed it.  The demon lord had eons to practice his telepathic abilities, crushing the minds of millions before Glave ever walked the earth.</p>

<p>Glave tried to break the telepathic bond but Xuzl grabbed his mind in a burning claw and did not let go.  Glave brought up his own shield, a twisting sphere of black and gray but the sphere exploded into white fire.  Loral heard a dark whisper of ancient and horrible words.  He thanked Tunare that he did not understand them or he surely would have gone insane, but he knew the goddess he prayed too was far from this place.  The words were thankfully unknown to Loral but not to Glave.  </p>

<p>The vampire screamed.</p>

<p>Loral saw Glave's eyes burst into balls of rolling flame.  Tears of molten metal rolled down his cheeks.  His gray skin burst open, spattering the ground with black blood.  His cloak and hood smoldered in smoke.  Still the vampire screamed.  He should have been dead, but Xuzl would not let him.  Xuzl poured every ounce of hatred and fury he held since falling into the steel trap of Loral's shield.  The demon wanted Glave to feel every ounce of hell he had to give.</p>

<p>It took a long time.</p>

<p>Loral woke at dawn.  Stonehewer's face was close it  made Loral jump.</p>

<p>"We worried for you,"  said Stonehewer.  "You cried out in your sleep."</p>

<p>Loral looked around the canyons of Kodtaz.  The Muramite hoards still swarmed on the temples.  The dwarf followed his gaze.</p>

<p>"What is our plan now?"</p>

<p>Loral thought back to the battle.  Before Xuzl had ripped Glave apart with claws of fire, Loral saw something, something Glave had tried to keep back.  The vision was blurry but it gave Loral direction.</p>

<p>"We cannot win here."  Loral held his cloak close to his cold body.  He and his companions looked over the hoards of beasts tearing into the ancient temples of Taelosia.  "We go home."</p>

<p>On his back, the shield of Xuzl burned with delight.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Discord and War</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-01-31T23:58:13+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: The World Has Changed</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001247.html</link>
      <description>We remember the battles of Bloody Kithicor. The older adventurers speak to the newer ones of the days when it...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1247@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>We remember the battles of Bloody Kithicor.  The older adventurers speak to the newer ones of the days when it was safe to cross the forest at night, the days before the wars came and tore the dead from the ground.  Now only the boldest adventurers dare to cross the unholy grounds of Kithicor at night.</p>

<p>We remember the fall of Grobb.  The ancient Guktans, children of Marr, crawled from the depths of Guk and marched upon Grobb.  The trolls were sent north to Neriak with an eternal fire in their eye for their homeland.</p>

<p>We remember the god-battles of Lesser Faydark.  The avatar of Tunare and the avatar of Cazic Thule battled upon the cursed lands of Lesser Faydark calling heroes of both light and darkness to their sides.  The outcome of this battle, different in each of our splinter worlds, changed the face of the Faydark for some time.</p>

<p>Dynamic events set Everquest apart from other traditional games.  We never watch the landscape of Final Fantasy or Baldur's Gate shift, grow, or collapse unless it is part of the linear story.  Everquest isn't a story, however.  Everquest is a world, and events like these prove it.</p>

<p>Two weeks ago, a knight of Tunare stood on the bridge of Felwithe and asked for aid in locating Firiona Vie.  Pieces of her cloak and evidence of her travel lay about the old lands.  Further investigation revealed a dark plot surrounding the Tower of Frozen Shadows in the Iceclad ocean.  Powerful beasts roamed the icy lands and a guardian barred all entrance into the dark tower.  Even the sky spoke of great evil.</p>

<p>Now dark elves spy over the Dreadlands.  Who knows where this will lead, but one thing is for sure; like Bloody Kithicor, the Fall of Grobb, and the god wars of Lesser Faydark; the world of Norrath will not remain the same when these times are over.</p>

<p>So now the future lies in our hands.  Will we at least witness these changes?  Of the three events mentioned above, I witnessed none of them personally.  I did hunt down and return pieces of evidence of Firiona's travel.  I helped the parties seeking to rescue Firiona from the tower by turning in pieces of evidence among the ruins of the Tower's beasts.  I have seen the scouts of Dreadlands.  Yet few others seem to see this.</p>

<p>So now we uncover another strange behavior I have witnessed for a long time.  A lot of players tend not to try anything new, instead preferring to hunt in commonly known and safe lands.  We lose sight of the forest through the trees.  Our chance for the safe acquisition of levels, AAs, and gear takes us away from some very entertaining one-time events.  Many will miss these events because they either do not hear of them, or do not care to witness them and leave their safe Wall of Slaughter group.</p>

<p>I noticed this same behavior at the beginning of each expansion.  People didn't seek out MPG and Riftseekers when Omens came out, they went to Fire and earned their levels and AAs there.  People continued working on LDONs and everyone wanted to finish their epic 1.5 as fast as possible rather than see some of the deeper lands of Kuua.  Perhaps my narrow view only sees these types of players, but sometimes it feels like we forget what we really seek.  We hunt down new higher numbers instead of seeking new adventures.</p>

<p>Over the next three weeks, we will see a great shift in Norrath.  If you seek it out, you can witness this change and fight alongside your allies in the battles ahead.  When these events are complete, you will never have the chance to see them again.</p>

<p>Speak to your friends, to your guild, and to your groups, and let them know of these changes.  Put together a small team of explorers and seek out these strange signs.  Take your raiding force that threatens the same beast you destroyed a dozen times before and attack the creatures you will never have a chance to see again.</p>

<p>Remember that this game isn't only about levels or AAs or gear.  It's about fun.  In this case, the fun has a lifespan and it will never come back again.  Don't miss it.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
24 January 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-01-24T20:54:45+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caster&apos;s Realm: Loral&apos;s Guide to Roleplaying</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001254.html</link>
      <description>Everquest is a vast stage. It is a game unlike any traditional single-player games we play. We might have moments...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1254@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Everquest is a vast stage.  It is a game unlike any traditional single-player games we play.  We might have moments in games like Baldur's Gate, Final Fantasy, or Knights of the Old Republic when we actually feel like our character.  Perhaps, if our imagination is good enough, we can actually go deeper than the character we play. There is little reward for roleplaying in single-player games, however.  No one else is there to appreciate it.  It may get us deeper into a game just as digging into a character gets us deeper into a book or movie, but the lack of any interaction on the other side removes a lot of the fun.</p>

<p>Everquest is different.  Now, when you find willing participants, roleplaying becomes its own dynamic storyline.  To some, roleplaying is the breath of life in a game built from polygons, texture maps, and particle effects.  Each of us is a character with our background, motivations, dialect.  We are each one thread in a huge rope of epic adventure.  We don't know where the story will end up.  We don't know what the others are going to do.  The stories build themselves around us often greater than the sum of their parts.</p>

<p>What does one need to do to roleplay?  How can we break that social barrier that tells us that playing make-believe is for kiddies?  Lets look at a few steps:</p>

<p>1.  Get over yourself.  You're playing Everquest at midnight on Friday night.  You're already not cool.  Get over the idea that you're playing with a bunch of dorks and accept that you enjoy what you enjoy and might enjoy it more if you dig into it.  If you really don't want to roleplay because it's not fun, thats a fine decision to make, but some people who might enjoy it give it up because they got beat up in junior high school for doing something similar.  Professional actors do this all the time and they get to marry (and divorce) Jennifer Andison.  Forget about how dorky your high school friends might think it is and just enjoy it.  You might be surprised.  Typing out lines of in-character dialog won't turn you into the D&D guys from Reno 911.</p>

<p>2.  Build your character.  There are three basic steps to character creation I like to use for quick and simple characters.</p>

<p>First, pick a character in a book or movie and use it as your character's archetype.  It doesn't matter if its Clint Eastwood in The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly or Woody Alan in Annie Hall.  If the character fits, steal it.  Using this archetype helps you fill in your character's gaps.  It helps you to react as your archetype would react when faced with a situation you haven't prepared for.  Over time, this archetype will fade and what remains may be much different from the original.</p>

<p>Second, write a brief history.  Where does your character come from?  What did they do previously?  How did they get where they currently are?  With new characters, it's best not to overdo this step.  No more 'orphaned by orcs' or 'left by mysterious forces in a glade near the elven city'.  We're not all the main character; we're one of thousands of other characters, each just as important as we are.  Pick a simple background but one that helps define your context for future encounters.</p>

<p>Three, write out your character's motivation.  What does he or she want?  Are you an adventurer or a greedy thief?  Are you a spy for Neriak or the Sword of Mithanial Marr?  What motivates you?  Again, don't get too hardened to this, it will probably change as you play, but keep it flexible enough that it fits the type of game you want to play.</p>

<p>Those three steps help you build a quick character.  They give you enough fuel to begin to roleplay but the more you roleplay, the more these will fade into the background and your true unique character will shine.</p>

<p>3.  Roleplay with hotkeys.  Hotkeys and macros are an extremely easy way to roleplay without having to type reams of dialog.  Pick ten traits about your character, ten typical reactions to common circumstances, and add them to a bank of macros.  Hit these macros as often as the situation presents itself.  Here are some examples:</p>

<p>/me opens a great tome of lore and begins to read.<br />
/me wipes streams of bright red blood off of his notched sword.<br />
/me looks over the landscape ahead with wanderlust in her eyes.<br />
/me cowers behind %T to escape the horrors ahead.<br />
/me feels a great darkness closing in.<br />
/me roars to Crom before attacking with furious might.<br />
/me wiggles her fingers in preparation for a devastating spell.<br />
/me feels her hands grow hot from the internal elemental flames.<br />
/me keeps an arrow knocked and a keen eye seeking new prey.</p>

<p>These emotes are easy to set up and easy to use.  They help build little bits of your character in the minds of others and often begin as an interaction between players.  Some jokers may decide to play off of them with wacky puns, but just keep rolling with them and enjoy what they create.</p>

<p>4.  Roleplay, and others will roleplay around you.  While not so much a rule, it is one good reason to roleplay.  Many people, once you fall into character, will see ways they too can fall into theirs.  They may not even realize they are roleplaying, instead simply working along the story.  For many, simply showing them that roleplaying is acceptable  is enough to get them to at least give it a try.</p>

<p>5.  Don't become a roleplay critic.  The whole name of the game is fun.  If someone breaks character, let them.  Don't be too hard about when you're roleplaying and when you're not.  Don't yell at people or criticize them for breaking character.  Enjoy it while it happens and don't fret if it falls away.  Each of us roleplays as much or as little as we choose.  There are no strict rules we have to follow or punishments for breaking character.</p>

<p>6.  Try roleplaying through obvious out-of-game situations.  For a fun exercise, try roleplaying through events that obviously broke character.  Did the server just crash? Perhaps a great ethereal wind just swept through the lands sending everyone into unconsciousness.  Did a mob just despawn while you were fighting it?  Perhaps rifts in the timelines created a paradox or the Gods, unhappy with your actions, removed the beast themselves.  Back in the 80s, Marvel comics ran a contest called the 'no-prize'.  If you found an obvious error in one of their comics, you sent in a description of the error but then a reason that the error wasn't actually an error at all.  If yours was good enough, you received a book of hundreds of Marvel's previous errors.</p>

<p>Roleplaying isn't for everyone.  Some people just want a chat room wrapped around a fantasy game.  They don't care if the world lives or breathes as long as they are challenged and enjoy the gameplay.  For others, however, roleplaying adds a whole new layer to the game-world we play in.  Finding another roleplayer and having a truly entertaining roleplay session is often more fun than earning a bit of loot or raising a level.  It is a whole internal dimension to play and massive online games are the perfect place to play it without getting an atomic wedgie.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
14 January 2005</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Caster&apos;s Realm Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-01-14T15:01:40+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Breaking News: Dragons of Norrath</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001244.html</link>
      <description>Early today rumors started spreading like wildfire of a new Everquest expansion. This evening we finally have more details. Most...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1244@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Early today rumors started spreading like wildfire of a new Everquest expansion.  This evening we finally have more details.  Most of your questions can be answered at the <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/dragonsofnorrath/index.jsp">Official Dragons of Norrath Website</a>.  Lets dig right into the main features:<br />
<blockquote><strong><br />
Everquest: The Dragons of Norrath, release on February 15th.</p>

<p>- New Zones, Creatures and Content - From Lavastorm to the Thundercrest Isles adventure in graphically enhanced zones with all new themes.  Brave challenging new quests, discover new treasures, and battle new NPCs including drakes, goblins, and fierce dragons.</p>

<p>- New Interactive World Map - A full-color interactive map of the world allows players to point-and-click from a world view, to a continent view, to a zone view of the traditional line maps.</p>

<p>- Player Barter System - Allows players to set up their own method of giving platinum or items for other items.  Players can now buy items!</p>

<p>- Potion Belt - Allows for quick use of consumable items, such as potions or food.</p>

<p>- Bandolier Equip - Lets your character have pre-arranged, multiple sets of weapons accessible by a single mouse click.<br />
	<br />
- New spells and Tradeskill Recipes</p>

<p>- All-New Guild Halls - Individual instanced Guild Halls for guild members to meet and prepare for playing. Includes the following features and benefits:<br />
	<br />
- Guild Bank - Bank slot for storage of items accessible by all (designated) members of a guild.</p>

<p>- Mana/health Regen Pool - Allows players to easily regenerate their mana and health in preparation for battle (available only at the Guild Hall).</p>

<p>- Mass Corpse Summoning Altar - Allows guilds to summon guild corpses en masse to the altar room after a wipe out.</p>

<p>- Guild Portal - Allows guild members to purchase the ability to have a persistent port to pre-determined areas around the world.<br />
	<br />
- Guild Tradeskill Objects - Various tradeskill tools are located in the guild hall for easy access by guild members.</p>

<p>- Guild 'Looking for Members' Tool - Allows guilds to recruit by placing persistent “ads” on bulletin boards, search for player characters who match guild criteria and send in-game emails to those members.</p>

<p>- Players 'Looking for Guild' Tool - Allows players to find guilds recruiting members.</p>

<p>- Buff Timers - In the Guild Halls buff times can be paused for Guild Members.</p>

<p></strong></blockquote></p>

<p>The front page also mentions a "In-game email system" when you highlight one of the crazy spires.</p>

<p>Loral's Comments:</p>

<p>The front page of the website mentions a release date of February 15th (Looks like I may owe Nanyea a drink).  I didn't expect it this soon but the schedule fits inside of the traditional six month delivery of new expansions since PoP.  While the boards already crawl with "but they haven't fixed all the doors in Freeport" comments already, and while many others feel that SOE is bringing this out too soon, history since PoP shows a six month delivery cycle.  Personally, I enjoy seeing the world shift and change as often and as radically as it does.  Change is growth and growth is good.</p>

<p>I love the mentioned guild features, however, I fear the associated in-game costs.  Hopefully the guild costs scale well for non-high end raiding guilds.  The mass summon corpse feature interests me the most.  While I feel SOE should give this feature to every player of the game in the form of a Shadowrest NPC, even in a guild hall this feature will help many players.  However, if the cost is scaled around guilds with 54 raiders of level 70, it won't scale well for a guild of 12 level 20 to 50 players.  The costs of guildhall features should scale well for guilds of all sizes in order to be a truly great feature.</p>

<p>In-game email, a guild recruitment service, and a player search of recruiting guilds will help people get together and find groups of friends with similar goals and play-styles.  I like that a lot.  Now if only we would see a "recruit" guild status to streamline the guild recruitment process.</p>

<p>The UI elements look to be nice additions.  One of these, the bandolier, was a feature asked for at the guild summit.  The world map should help new players but many of us who have the zone maps permanently laid over the neural paths of our brains will find little use in them.</p>

<p>The beta signup appears and disappears on the front page of EQLive.  If you don't blink at the wrong moment and you desire to betatest the expansion, keep watch the Everquest homepage.</p>

<p>In other news, John Smedley, president of SOE, posted an interesting note about Everquest 2 including this comment about a new form of $5 bit of content called "Adventure Packs":</p>

<p>"Adventure Packs are a new style of content that we are introducing to EverQuest II. You can think of them as being similar to "Modules" from traditional tabletop RPGs. They will be heavily story driven and themed adventuring areas. We will provide a part of each of these Adventure Packs, at no extra charge, to all of our players. This should give everyone the opportunity to see if a particular Adventure Pack is the kind of thing they are interested in. You'll be able to buy these at any time, since they will be delivered digitally. We plan on keeping the price point for these low... In fact, our first one will be just US$4.99."</p>

<p>Read the <a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive.vm?section=Headline&id=311">John Smedley's full EQ2 letter</a>.</p>

<p>Adventure packs interest me.  This is an opportunity for SOE to release mini-games or campaigns for EQ2 in a more traditional RPG sense.  I imagine modules like Temple of Elemental Evil and Queen of the Demonweb Pits.  I imagine single story lines that progress from beginning to end.  Where typical EQ2 expansions will focus on large scale world-based content, these adventures will offer a specific and focused story, gameplay element, zone, and quests.  So why not have this for EQ1?  The idea of paying another $5 every three months will turn some people off, but considering the time we get for our dollar, $5 for twenty hours of content is a pretty good deal.</p>

<p>Earlier today, Everquest Executive Producer, Robert Pfister, posted <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=TNZ&message.id=146526#M146526">The State of Everquest in 2005</a>.  In it he discusses many of the past and future points of interest for Everquest including possible server merges for the Zeks and a review of other servers after Dragons of Norrath, the class role review, and the release of Dragons of Norrath.  It is unclear when we may first see class changes occurring and I would bet it won't be until after the release of Dragons of Norrath.  That will surely vex some people.  Minor class tweaks don't excite me like a new expansion does, however, and I bet I am not alone.</p>

<p>Yes, I get all googly eyed when I see the glossy propaganda for a new expansion.  I know we still have class discussions ahead of us and new patches that update old-world content like the task system.  I know there are still plenty of bugs.  But I see a screenshot like <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/dragonsofnorrath/images/screenshots/EQ000099.jpg">this Frost Giant</a> and I can't help but get giddy.  I love Norrath and I love watching it grow.  I look forward to the days ahead.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 January 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-01-11T20:15:37+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Topics of the New Year</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001239.html</link>
      <description>With SOE&apos;s developers on vacation this week, life in Norrath has been quiet. So let us sit back, relax, and...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1239@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>With SOE's developers on vacation this week, life in Norrath has been quiet.  So let us sit back, relax, and enjoy our new year with a look at some of Norrath's most recent topics of discussion.  Four big topics continually seem to dominate the live forums:  EQ's lifespan, server consolidation, class balance (egads), and the summit.</p>

<p>Let us get the most painful one out of the way first.  For nearly the entire time I've written for Mobhunter, people complain about class balance.  I covered it a couple of times before, but let me step back from my own views on the matter and talk about what we see.  </p>

<p>Early on when the new EQLive forums stood up, Kytherea and Ashlanne began keeping track of the top ten class issues for each class.  Regardless of the continuing disclaimers on these threads, people assumed this meant these class issues would all be addressed.  Now even though many classes have had some of their issues addressed, people lean towards statements like "SOE isn't listening" and "none of our class issues are being met".  How easily we forget.  I had a conversation a couple of days ago with someone who stated that even though some of their class issues were met, they were things that should have been fixed anyway and didn't count.  </p>

<p>My head swam with the spiral I see people swimming down.  Then, my friend Boanerges from EQClerics linked a document called <a href="http://www.legendmud.org/raph/gaming/laws.html">The Laws of Online Game Design</a> gathered by Raph Koster.  Raph worked on a variety of online games including Ultima Online, and Star Wars Galaxies and now acts as the Chief Creative Officer over at SOE.  One of these rules shined like Frodo's Light of Earendil:</p>

<p>"<em>Hans Henrik Staerfeldt's Law of Player/Admin Relations: The amount of whining players do is positively proportional to how much you pamper them.</em> Many players whine if they see any kind of bonus in it for them. It will simply be another way for them to achieve their goals. As an admin you hold the key to many of the goals that they have concerning the virtual environment you control. If you do not pamper the players and let them know that whining will not help them, the whining will subside."</p>

<p>Another one might articulate this better:</p>

<p>"<em>Hal Black's Elaboration:</em> The more responsive an admin is to user feedback of a given type, the more of that type the admin will get. Specifically, as an admin implements features from user suggestions, the more ideas for features will be submitted. Likewise, the more an admin coddles whiners, the more whining will ensue."</p>

<p>We might argue that not listening or responding to player concerns ends their whining simply because they go away.  If you don't listen to your customers and address the issues that must be addressed, they will go away.  Sometimes, however, I wonder if badgering the developers into making changes has become its own progressive massive online game.  Why should I hunt for a new hammer when I can get the developers to make the one I have better?  Why fight so hard against the Luggalids in Nadox when I can convince SOE to make them easier?  It seems the EQLive forums became their own sort of meta-game.  I might receive more improved items and upgraded spells there than I will hunting in game.</p>

<p>This brings up a multitude of questions.  Should SOE have ever validated class issues by keeping track of them on an open forum?  Do those class issues really represent the whole set of players who play those classes?  Now that they have validated these concerns, what should they do to address them?  Will simply addressing them as-is result in breaking the game even further?  Do the players really know whats best for the whole of the game?  There are few easy answers and a whole lot of theory.</p>

<p>Let us shift paths and discuss server consolidation.  Recent threads reveal no official words on any move by SOE to consolidate servers although I stand by my rumor that they at least consider and discuss Zek consolidation.  It makes more sense for those servers with their wide variety of rule-sets on top of population issues.  While more and more threads pop up each day, I wouldn't expect SOE to make any other move to consolidate servers until after the release of the next expansion.</p>

<p>Shifting paths again we reach the Guild Summit.  SOE had originally planned a summit in January but announced that they pushed the date back to July.  The original January announcement started a series of interesting feedback threads on <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48581">soloing and tasks</a>, <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48894">user interface</a>, and <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=50919#M50919">grouping improvements</a>.  While it would have been nice to get a deeper look at the next expansion, a June summit may hit at a more opportune time to offer feedback.  As far as the summit effecting the longevity of the game, I don't think opinionated egotists like myself have as much impact as we would like to think.  For all we know, Firiona Vie's hem-line has more to do with EQ subscriptions than any feedback found on a website.</p>

<p>Which leads into the last path we will walk today, the life of Everquest.  I wrote an article for Caster's Realm titled <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=7411">Is Everquest Dying?</a>.  Anyone who read any of my other articles already knows my answer but in case you have not, the answer is "no, it isn't".  When we look at the longevity of previous MMOGs and how few users can still finance new expansions, I think it is safe to say that Everquest has a long life.</p>

<p>This brought up an interesting question for me, however.  Can Everquest last the rest of our lives?  While it is obviously difficult to predict forty or fifty years of technology, we can assume that bandwidth and server costs will continue to go down. The value of continuing to maintain Everquest may be worth the bragging rights of maintaining a MMOG for ten, twenty, perhaps fifty years.  Will people still want to play?  People still want to play Pong, so probably.</p>

<p>For my last act, I would like to make a formal statement.  I was wrong.  Yes, I know it is hard to believe and I risk influencing the vast markets in the bazaar with my mere spoken word, but...I was wrong.  The prices of Muramite Runes still seem to fluctuate between 20 and 30k in the bazaars well after my Thanksgiving 10k prediction.  While I am confident that the prices will continue to go down, it would appear that more people are willing to pay for runes at that price to keep the market high. Shame on you.</p>

<p>Keep an eye out next week for a new article entitled "Loral's 2005 Predictions" for more lies, propaganda, and inaccurate financial outlooks.  In the mean time, enjoy the new year and all of the possibilities it brings.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
2 January 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-01-03T04:03:28+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caster&apos;s Realm: Is Everquest Dying?</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001248.html</link>
      <description>Is Everquest Dying? This question seems to flood every EQ-based message forum since the release of EQ2 and Worlds of...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1248@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Is Everquest Dying?</p>

<p>This question seems to flood every EQ-based message forum since the release of EQ2 and Worlds of Warcraft.  Is our beloved Norrath crashing to the ground?  Are the city streets empty?  Do lone adventurers stare over the empty wastelands of a once rich and populated land?  Today we will discuss the future of Everquest and address the most difficult question we have had to answer since EQ came into being.</p>

<p>Let me start with the answer.  No, Everquest is not dying.  But let us go back a step further and define what dying and death are for a game such as this.  Here is Loral's Definition for the Death of Everquest:</p>

<p>If SOE no longer produces new expansions or new extensive content patches, then Everquest is dying.</p>

<p>If SOE no longer continues to maintain the servers and we are no longer able to go online, then EQ is officially dead.</p>

<p>Some might argue with these definitions.  Death, being a very general and melodramatic term when used for a description of a computer game, means different things to us all.  To some it is the destruction of a guild.  To others it is an inability to find a group.  To others it is the point when previously powerful guilds are no longer able to defeat encounters they once were or no longer able to progress beyond current encounters.  Others use the number of people in the bazaar to determine death or population.</p>

<p>But let us ignore these definitions for a moment and stick to the two I mention above.  As long as SOE continues to bring out new expansions, our world will grow and continue to bring new challenges to our doorsteps.  We will walk with worn leather boots across lands we never dreamed about.  We will continue to grow in power, riches, and knowledge of faraway places.  More importantly, new expansions keep Everquest on the shelves where new players find it and jump in.</p>

<p>With the release of each previous expansion, the numbers of active players increase.  After a few months these numbers dip back down again until the next expansion release occurs and players come back again.  As long as new expansion releases continue, players will return and new players will join.  The quality of that expansion might determine how long those players stay.</p>

<p>Will SOE continue to release new expansions?  So far, yes.  SOE already began work on a new expansion.  I estimate an announcement sometime in mid-January or early February for a new expansion release sometime between April and June.  Only then will we know the nature and features of this expansion but given what we've seen with Omens, I am quite optimistic.</p>

<p>How long will SOE continue to release new expansions?  SOE will continue to release new expansions as long as it remains cost effective to do so.  While only the great gold-hoarding dragons at SOE could say for sure what amount of subscriptions it takes to pay for new expansion development, we can look at other MMOGs with fewer players to get a rough estimate.  Let us pick three other MMOGs with lower player numbers.  All statistics came from Bruce Sterling Woodcock who maintains a set of subscription numbers based on company press releases and other sources of data.  Unfortunately his latest page is down, but the Internet Archive had his statistics  from one year ago which is enough to work through my theory.</p>

<p>According to Bruce Woodcock (chuckle), Eve Online had 40,000 subscribers, Anarchy Online had about 40,000 subscribers, and Shadowbane had about 50,000 subscribers.  Now you may wonder why I ignored bigger MMOGs like Ragnarok or Final Fantasy XI.  I ignored them because I specifically wanted MMOGs with lower subscription numbers.  The three games above had subscription numbers at roughly 10% of Everquest's subscriptions.  More importantly, all three of them continued to release expansions.</p>

<p>Now I am jumping far out into the realm of speculation, but I speculate that SOE could continue to fund new Everquest expansions with 10% of the subscribers they had when Gates of Discord came out, roughly 430,000 active subscribers (source: GoD Press Release ).</p>

<p>So based on that obviously loose data, we can say that we know SOE is going to release a new expansion and will probably continue to do so for a long while.  It will be a long time before EQ's population drops to less than 40,000 active subscribers.</p>

<p>Now obviously the number of active players has gone down in the last couple of months.  This is due to a few different factors including the holidays, a slew of new and excellent single-player games such as Halo 2, Half Life 2, Grand Theft Auto San Andraes, and nearly a dozen more hot games, and yes, the release of Everquest 2 and Worlds of Warcraft.  </p>

<p>The holidays are just about over.  Those single-player games won't hold people forever.  While some may leave EQ for EQ2 and WoW, some will not.  Some will try out those new games for a while but return back to the game they already enjoy.  This will be especially true when a new expansion comes out.  Nothing brings people back like a box of new content and features to dig into.</p>

<p>Server consolidation is another major topic of discussion.  As the player subscription numbers do go down, SOE may eventually consider consolidating servers.  Such a move is very severe and may end up driving even more players out of the game.  We all grow very attached to our own world and the people within it.  Most of us don't want to suddenly get packed into a new world with a new name and a bunch of strangers we didn't know.  I would expect, when the time comes to consolidate servers, that SOE will do a lot of them all at once.  Like ripping off a bandage, SOE will want to make the pain as quick as possible and never do it again if they don't have to. </p>

<p>I wouldn't expect any such decisions on server consolidation to happen until after the next expansion.  SOE will want to see how many players come back to EQ once the new expansion is released.  If they don't see a big jump and the numbers of active and online players remains low, then they may decide its time to consider server consolidation.</p>

<p>Before considering anything as drastic as server consolidation, SOE will want to find ways to help people find groups and help lower-number raids find fun and meaningful content.</p>

<p>Change frightens us.  The release of Everquest 2 brought many of questions to  every Everquest community to which I belong.  Would EQ2 kill Everquest?  Would Worlds of Warcraft kill both?  Would our groups of friends break off and never speak again?  These are all scary questions.  No one wants to lose their friends.  The answers to these questions are much fuzzier than any single statement can articulate.  Some will leave, some will stay, some will come back, some new people will join.</p>

<p>Is Everquest dying?  No, it's not.  SOE stated their continued support for this game many times.  Our look at other MMOGs, their subscription numbers, and the continued release of expansions shows us that even with much lower subscription numbers, Everquest will remain alive and healthy.  No one can say for certain what will happen.  SOE has very smart people spending a lot of time analyzing these trends and even they cannot predict what will happen in the long run.  We can be confident, however, that the world of Norrath will remain strong for a long while.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
31 December 2004</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Caster&apos;s Realm Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-12-31T03:26:53+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 55: The Kyv Heartstriker</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001236.html</link>
      <description>The six adventurers continued their slow journey within the treacherous crags of Tipt. They fought in scores of battles and...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1236@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>The six adventurers continued their slow journey within the treacherous crags of Tipt.  They fought in scores of battles and not one of them was free from one wound or another, many of them quite deep.  Loral's healing energy kept the six adventurers alive, but every one of them nursed a wound that Loral's powers could not fully close.  Infection ran free in this cursed land, it appeared, and Loral fought hard to hold back the rotting disease that attempted to swim through their blood.</p>

<p>While many of the beasts lacked any intelligence beyond the savage hostility of hunger and rage, the Ukuns and Nocs were quite cunning.  The gray-skinned Ukuns crawled on lithe limbs among the rock before racing down hissing long into the night.  The Nocs, a mutated monstrosity between a goblin and a tusked lower vampire, sought blood.  Their eyes shone yellow in the low light and the stench of decay wafted off of their black skin.  Between waves of cragbeasts and stonemites, small spined flatworms that bit and sprayed the open wound with acid, the Nocs attacked with spiked tusks and long claws.</p>

<p>Throughout the battles, Loral's demon-possessed shield was silent.  Loral felt the shield's trepidation at falling into the hands of such creatures.  Since the gods turned their back on Norrath, Xuzl spoke little.  On the evening of their fourth day, the demon said a single sentence that sent a deep chill over Loral's skin.</p>

<p>"A shadow follows us."</p>

<p>The telepathic voice was not the booming cry of the damned Loral heard previously.  It was still powerful, but low and quiet.  Something cold and wicked followed behind them; something old.</p>

<p>Loral had only seconds to contemplate this before the first arrow screamed across the night and into their camp.</p>

<p>Juror stumbled on a rock in the dark and that troublesome rock saved the barbarian's life.  The arrow streaked past cutting a lock of Juror's silver hair from his head with its razor-sharp tip.  Juror would recount this tale many times, showing how the lock of his hair burst into fleets of silver as the arrow streaked past his head missing his eye only by inches.</p>

<p>The arrow buried itself in the stone wall of the canyon behind him.  Juror wheeled around in time to catch another of the wicked arrows in his left arm.  The large barbarian tugged experimentally at the shaft in his arm but the barbs stuck deep in the cords of his muscles.  Juror clenched his teeth and pushed the arrow through, cursing the gods above and below and bellowing into the night.  The barbed head shined red in the moonlight from the back of his arm.  Juror snapped the shaft and pulled the arrow through.  White magic flowed into the deep spurting wound from Loral's hands closing it and healing the damage inside Juror's massive shoulder.</p>

<p>The party, now fully alert, saw a figure skate down the steep side of the canyon.  Gray skin covered his tall agile frame.  A tunic of hard leather covered a robe of green.  The figure slid easily down the rock on high leather boots folded down at the knee and tied tight with leather straps that wound like serpents around his legs.  The figures long white hair flowed back as he slid easily down the steep rock walls.  Kyv Heartstriker Jhiru, chaos ranger of the Muramites, fired another arrow from his long recurve bow.</p>

<p>Mici the dwarven berserker roared and rushed in, but his charge stopped dead when an arrow cut through his breastplate and exploded in the dwarf's stout heart.  The dwarf fell to his knees and then down to the ground.  No magic would repair or revive the noble companion.  The Muramites added another body to the mountains of corpses that lined the shores of Taelosia.</p>

<p>Loral looked from the dead dwarf to the murdering archer.  Black eyeless sockets returned the look from a self-scarred face.  Loral had heard of these fiends, the scouts, rangers, and assassins of the Muramite legions; the Kyv.</p>

<p>Loral raised his shield and another arrow exploded into flame when it hit the cursed steel.  A rush of insects engulfed the Kyv and loral heard it hiss in an alien tongue.  Kaylessa chanted in a long and melodious spell.  Her hands and eyes began to glow, illuminating the dark night.  The Heartstriker heard her words, turned, and fired.  The arrow would have torn through her chest but Stonehewer lept and slashed the arrow out of its flight with his double-bladed sword.  The arrow exploded in white arcs of energy.  </p>

<p>The Kyv hissed again, drew back his massive bow, and Stonehewer knew he had no chance in stopping the deadly arrow aiming at his own chest.  The dwarf responded with a prayer to Brell, practically seeing the mountain path that would lead him to Brell's Castle when the deadly Heartstriker roared in pain and the arrow fired wildly into the sky like a comet.  Illudar had slashed the back of the agile Kyv's knee, cutting through thick woven breeches, gray flesh, and thick cords of tendon.  </p>

<p>The Kyv Heartstriker whirled, falling to one knee, and fired a barbed shaft right through Illudar's stomach.  The air filled with the crash of the arrow as it exploded against the mountain wall.  A wave of healing light flowed through Illudar as Loral sealed the wound and healed Illudar's pierced organs before the mortal would stole Illudar as it stole poor Mici.</p>

<p>Stonehewer cleaved into the back of the Heartstriker's neck so fast that the Kyv's hair, tied back with a string of leather, fell open and into a wide cloud around his severed head.  The ranger of Chaos fell dead, his head rolling across the stone ground.</p>

<p>Illudar pressed his fingers against the spot in his chest where the arrow had pierced him.  Juror tested his wounded arm.  Kaylessa complemented Stonehewer for his amazing cut and kissed the blushing dwarf on his thick forehead.</p>

<p>They buried Mici in the crags with his axe in his hands.  Each whispered a prayer to the gods for his safe passage into Brell's halls.</p>

<p>They traveled the next day without incident, as though the beasts of the treacherous crags knew the party had slain their greatest champion.  On the afternoon of the second day, with the sun breaking low atop the mountains, they entered the valley of Kodtaz and beheld the lost temples within.</p>

<p>The sight filled them with simultaneous feelings of awe, wonder, and fear.  Never had they seen temples so old or so massive.  The ziggurats towered over the canyon walls and statues of Taelosians stretched into the violet sky in worship to ancient gods.</p>

<p>Hoards of Muramites covered each one of these temples like insects feasting on a fallen bit of sugar.  They feasted from the power of these temples and they grew stronger with each pulse of the temple's energy.</p>

<p>"Lord Brell, what are we supposed to do against that?"  Stonehewer ran a hand down a braid of his long woven beard.</p>

<p>"Lets rest here tonight and consider our options in the morning,"  spoke Juror.  The barbarian sat with his back against a rock and exhaled as though he held his breath since they entered the canyon.</p>

<p>Loral woke late into the night.  The moon of Luclin shimmered overhead.  An ethereal mist twisted and flowed over the stone ground.  The others were gone; Loral was alone.  He was dressed in his green clerical robes, not the golden battle-scarred armor he wore when he fell asleep.  A lone figure, cloaked and hooded in black sat across from him.  Loral saw the figure's pitch black eyes like orbs of night staring unblinking at him from within the hood.  Runes and glyphs shifted and twinkled on the figure's gray skin.  Loral felt the terror and dread he had felt only once before.  He felt exactly the same when he faced the Vampire Lord Aviatis in the crypts of Mistmoore.</p>

<p>Glave spoke clearly and smooth, like a thin needle sinking into soft flesh.</p>

<p>"We have much to discuss, elf."</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-12-18T16:54:25+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Refunds, Mergers, and Flags</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001234.html</link>
      <description>This week we saw the largest update in some time. Wednesday&apos;s patch included pages and pages of changes covering everything...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1234@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>This week we saw the largest update in some time.  Wednesday's patch included pages and pages of changes covering everything from the long awaited backflag solutions to new hotzones and alternate advancement point refunds.</p>

<p>We discussed a these changes previously so I will only touch on a few things.  The AA refunds, for the most part, seem to be very reasonable.  SOE's goal was to make the point costs of Gates AAs fit better with the costs found in Omens of War.  In a few days we should know how well this meets the desires of those it effects.</p>

<p>The backflagging solution should help guilds.  While some guilds stayed at their current rate of power and delved deep into Anguish, other guilds began opening their doors wide open to new recruits since the release of EQ2 and WoW.  These backflag changes help guilds continue to progress at the point they left off by using the 85/15 rule to bring in unflagged recruits.  Because guilds won't have to backflag, they should be able to retain members rather than lose them.  These backflag changes came at a good time for many raiding forces.</p>

<p>A few older zones had their experience modifiers increased including Shadeweaver's Thicket, Kurn's Tower, Unrest, Crystal Caverns, Solusek's Eye, Katta Castellum, Lower Guk, Nagafen's Lair, and Umbral Plains.  These new hot zones should help get newer players into zones they might otherwise skip for newer content.  I like the idea behind hotzones.  Without too much effort, older zones become much more desirable than they once were.</p>

<p>Tacvi, the deepest and darkest corner of the Gates of Discord expansion, had a couple of nice changes for those powerful enough to reach it.  It received a new zone in that doesn't require the weekly slaying of an ubermob to enter.  This prevents guilds from simply waiting until another guild comes by and takes care of the large fellow.  Tacvi also received a larger cache of new loot.  I would expect this loot to be on par with the equipment we see coming from the depths of Anguish.</p>

<p>We saw our first wave of epic alterations this patch.  These updates mainly handled the content required to receive the epic, but more than once we've heard that the epic effects themselves will be looked at.  Expect to see some changes to epic 1.5s and 2.0s coming soon.</p>

<p>Both /autofire and /melody made it into this patch.  Many archers and song singers rejoiced.</p>

<p>The two revamped zones, Mistmoore and Splitpaw made it to the Legends servers.  I haven't yet heard what sort of content we can expect, but rumors speak to Elemental-level beasties worming their way through the infected paw of the Karanas.  We shall wait and see.  Expect these zones to make it to the live servers in about a month.</p>

<p>While we saw many good changes for the upper-end of the game, we didn't see that many that effected the larger group of players below level 65.  Backflagging, epic 1.5 changes, and Tacvi matters to high-end raiders, but there wasn't much in this patch for the larger group of non-raiders and single-group hunters.  At this critical stage, SOE must consider the low end and mid-level game a priority over these changes to high-end content.</p>

<p>Hopefully in January we should see the much-anticipated task changes we heard about at the Fan Faire.</p>

<p>A few different board postings offer some excellent advice that effects every player, not just raiders.  Three interesting threads, one on <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48581">soloing and task changes</a>, one on <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48894">user interface suggestions</a>, and another on <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48560">grouping and LFG changes</a>, all have excellent suggestions and advice that effects a large majority of Everquest players.</p>

<p>Two topics seem to dominate the conversations over on the Live forums.  Class balance continues to raise its ugly head, usually wrapped in "SOE doesn't listen!"  Most of the time, the complaint isn't really that SOE doesn't listen, but that SOE doesn't agree.  People don't seem to want to hear it when their ideas are shot down.  In the meantime, to squash the rumors of lack of communication, continue to watch the dozen or so postings a day from various SOE employees over at the <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/tracker?role=Dev">dev tracker</a>.</p>

<p>One other topic became so prolific recently that threads had to be consolidated into one huge thread.  I speak of server mergers.  I think merging servers should be an absolute last resort for SOE.  It is the sort of change that cannot be undone, once done.  It breaks up of our identity within the community and it gives the (perhaps inaccurate) impression that EQ is on a steady decline without a chance of going back up.  Yes, numbers have been low, although anyone who tells you they have real data to support specific trends is most likely lying.  Nothing tells us that we won't see the continued trend of new players joining in and old players returning when a shipment of new shiny expansion boxes hits the shelf sometime between March and May.</p>

<p>Ok, time for the scoop....</p>

<p>Recently, a large group of players from the Zek servers, Tallon, Vallon, Sullon, and Rallos, got together with representatives from SOE to discuss their merger.  These servers, being evil red PVP servers, have a much different demographic and player base than the other pansy huggy blue servers.  They also, apparently, have many fewer active players.  </p>

<p>My vast network of spies tells me that SOE is indeed considering consolidating all four of these servers.  While they have no definite plans yet, there are discussions within SOE to consolidate these four servers together.  It is easy to consider this a reactionary move, however SOE apparently considered this merger well before EQ2's release and the meeting with the Zek players.  </p>

<p>Those same spies did not reveal what the rule set would be for this combined server, so they were all immediately put to death.</p>

<p>Many will use this to feather their giant "EQ is Dead" mardi-gras hats.  Yet, these same people will continue to pay their $12 a month and visit sites like this one and the EQLive boards.  People love to hate.</p>

<p>The MMOG business tells us otherwise.  Many other MMORPGs continue to not only run but bring out new expansions even with nearly 1/10th of the population of EQ.  I expect that the server numbers need to drop dramatically over a long period of time before SOE decides to pull the plug.  In the meantime, I see those who never enjoyed the game go off to greener pastures and those of us who do enjoy the game will form a new, tighter, and stronger community than ever before.</p>

<p>The day I don't hear anyone shouting "EQ is dead" is the day I really begin to worry.</p>

<p>Refunds, Mergers, and Flags</p>

<p>by Loral on December 15, 2004</p>

<p>This week we saw the largest update in some time. Wednesday's patch included pages and pages of changes covering everything from the long awaited backflag solutions to new hotzones and alternate advancement point refunds.</p>

<p>We discussed a these changes previously so I will only touch on a few things. The AA refunds, for the most part, seem to be very reasonable. SOE's goal was to make the point costs of Gates AAs fit better with the costs found in Omens of War. In a few days we should know how well this meets the desires of those it effects.</p>

<p>The backflagging solution should help guilds. While some guilds stayed at their current rate of power and delved deep into Anguish, other guilds began opening their doors wide open to new recruits since the release of EQ2 and WoW. These backflag changes help guilds continue to progress at the point they left off by using the 85/15 rule to bring in unflagged recruits. Because guilds won't have to backflag, they should be able to retain members rather than lose them. These backflag changes came at a good time for many raiding forces.</p>

<p>A few older zones had their experience modifiers increased including Shadeweaver's Thicket, Kurn's Tower, Unrest, Crystal Caverns, Solusek's Eye, Katta Castellum, Lower Guk, Nagafen's Lair, and Umbral Plains. These new hot zones should help get newer players into zones they might otherwise skip for newer content. I like the idea behind hotzones. Without too much effort, older zones become much more desirable than they once were.</p>

<p>Tacvi, the deepest and darkest corner of the Gates of Discord expansion, had a couple of nice changes for those powerful enough to reach it. It received a new zone in that doesn't require the weekly slaying of an ubermob to enter. This prevents guilds from simply waiting until another guild comes by and takes care of the large fellow. Tacvi also received a larger cache of new loot. I would expect this loot to be on par with the equipment we see coming from the depths of Anguish.</p>

<p>We saw our first wave of epic alterations this patch. These updates mainly handled the content required to receive the epic, but more than once we've heard that the epic effects themselves will be looked at. Expect to see some changes to epic 1.5s and 2.0s coming soon.</p>

<p>Both /autofire and /melody made it into this patch. Many archers and song singers rejoiced.</p>

<p>The two revamped zones, Mistmoore and Splitpaw made it to the Legends servers. I haven't yet heard what sort of content we can expect, but rumors speak to Elemental-level beasties worming their way through the infected paw of the Karanas. We shall wait and see. Expect these zones to make it to the live servers in about a month.</p>

<p>While we saw many good changes for the upper-end of the game, we didn't see that many that effected the larger group of players below level 65. Backflagging, epic 1.5 changes, and Tacvi matters to high-end raiders, but there wasn't much in this patch for the larger group of non-raiders and single-group hunters. At this critical stage, SOE must consider the low end and mid-level game a priority over these changes to high-end content.</p>

<p>Hopefully in January we should see the much-anticipated task changes we heard about at the Fan Faire.</p>

<p>A few different board postings offer some excellent advice that effects every player, not just raiders. Three interesting threads, one on soloing and task changes, one on user interface suggestions, and another on grouping and LFG changes, all have excellent suggestions and advice that effects a large majority of Everquest players.</p>

<p>Two topics seem to dominate the conversations over on the Live forums. Class balance continues to raise its ugly head, usually wrapped in "SOE doesn't listen!" Most of the time, the complaint isn't really that SOE doesn't listen, but that SOE doesn't agree. People don't seem to want to hear it when their ideas are shot down. In the meantime, to squash the rumors of lack of communication, continue to watch the dozen or so postings a day from various SOE employees over at the dev tracker.</p>

<p>One other topic became so prolific recently that threads had to be consolidated into one huge thread. I speak of server mergers. I think merging servers should be an absolute last resort for SOE. It is the sort of change that cannot be undone, once done. It breaks up of our identity within the community and it gives the (perhaps inaccurate) impression that EQ is on a steady decline without a chance of going back up. Yes, numbers have been low, although anyone who tells you they have real data to support specific trends is most likely lying. Nothing tells us that we won't see the continued trend of new players joining in and old players returning when a shipment of new shiny expansion boxes hits the shelf sometime between March and May.</p>

<p>Ok, time for the scoop....</p>

<p>Recently, a large group of players from the Zek servers, Tallon, Vallon, Sullon, and Rallos, got together with representatives from SOE to discuss their merger. These servers, being evil red PVP servers, have a much different demographic and player base than the other pansy huggy blue servers. They also, apparently, have many fewer active players.</p>

<p>My vast network of spies tells me that SOE is indeed considering consolidating all four of these servers. While they have no definite plans yet, there are discussions within SOE to consolidate these four servers together. It is easy to consider this a reactionary move, however SOE apparently considered this merger well before EQ2's release and the meeting with the Zek players.</p>

<p>Those same spies did not reveal what the rule set would be for this combined server, so they were all immediately put to death.</p>

<p>Many will use this to feather their giant "EQ is Dead" mardi-gras hats. Yet, these same people will continue to pay their $12 a month and visit sites like this one and the EQLive boards. People love to hate.</p>

<p>The MMOG business tells us otherwise. Many other MMORPGs continue to not only run but bring out new expansions even with nearly 1/10th of the population of EQ. I expect that the server numbers need to drop dramatically over a long period of time before SOE decides to pull the plug. In the meantime, I see those who never enjoyed the game go off to greener pastures and those of us who do enjoy the game will form a new, tighter, and stronger community than ever before.</p>

<p>The day I don't hear anyone shouting "EQ is dead" is the day I really begin to worry.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
15 December 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-12-15T17:42:41+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>


  </channel>
</rss>

