<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>Richard Henson wrote:Armarant, you might want to do a little fact checking. Currently most WoW serve</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Richard Henson wrote:Armarant, you might want to do a little fact checking. Currently most WoW servers are at max capacity. There&apos;s actually a posted list of servers that are allowing new character creation on them. Blizzard just released three new servers.

Yet its ok for people like you to bash down EQ saying that its dieing and the servers are lower in population. anyone can create a list saying whatever they want. the fact that blizzard </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>a good website to check out is..  

http://www.warcraftrealms.com/activity.php

it has a census of s</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>a good website to check out is..  

http://www.warcraftrealms.com/activity.php

it has a census of sorts.. with 

46080 on alliance side.. and
49357 on horde side..

they take a census of how many people log in daily.

they have been averaging
923 on alliance side.
612 on horde side.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>So 1 in 50 active accounts plays at any given time at WoW.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>So 1 in 50 active accounts plays at any given time at WoW.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Armarant,

You might want to re-read what I posted.  I did not &quot;bash&quot; EQ.  Rather I sugges</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Armarant,

You might want to re-read what I posted.  I did not &quot;bash&quot; EQ.  Rather I suggested to you that you might want to avoid bashing other games as a way of making EQ look good.

That said, you may want to go back and read the posts from the SOE developer staff and thier press releases prior to the time that the server mergers where made.  SOE stated that the active player population had dropped to the point that they felt it was n</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Richard Hinson Wrote:That said, you may want to go back and read the posts from the SOE developer st</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Richard Hinson Wrote:That said, you may want to go back and read the posts from the SOE developer staff and thier press releases prior to the time that the server mergers where made. SOE stated that the active player population had dropped to the point that they felt it was needed for the health of the game to make those mergers. Please note, it was SOE that said the populations had dropped.

Yes, and toward the same alot of people were also post</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>If you had looked a little harder at that web site Armarant, you&apos;d have found data that are muc</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>If you had looked a little harder at that web site Armarant, you&apos;d have found data that are much more relevant to what you&apos;re trying to prove. The following graph shows average number of players logged in in prime time per server for the last six months:

http://www.warcraftrealms.com/weeklyfactionactivity.php?serverid=-1

You&apos;ll see no sign of a drop in population; in fact average Horde population has been trending up. Of course i</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;So 1 in 50 active accounts plays at any given time at WoW.&quot;

Which means at least 100K co</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;So 1 in 50 active accounts plays at any given time at WoW.&quot;

Which means at least 100K concurrent players. Nothing to sneeze at.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Rumor has it that the NEW UI is gonna be mandatory with the next expansion.

PLEASE SAY IT ISN&apos;</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Rumor has it that the NEW UI is gonna be mandatory with the next expansion.

PLEASE SAY IT ISN&apos;T SO 

It&apos;s SO awful !!!</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>No, the new UI will not be mandatory for PoR RosesAreRed.  They are not updating the defualt_old UI,</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>No, the new UI will not be mandatory for PoR RosesAreRed.  They are not updating the defualt_old UI, but most likely, some one will update it and post the updates at eqinterface.com.  Also, custum Ui&apos;s that are updated for PoR will still be uaeable.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Teremar wrote:If you had looked a little harder at that web site Armarant, you&apos;d have found dat</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Teremar wrote:If you had looked a little harder at that web site Armarant, you&apos;d have found data that are much more relevant to what you&apos;re trying to prove.

I think it also changes daily sometimes based on how many &quot;Hits&quot; they get. since they cant just do a straight out census they have to rely on people sending in /who data for each server.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thanks, Red  ....

Forcing an ugly, inflexible UI on us would be the last straw.  </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Thanks, Red  ....

Forcing an ugly, inflexible UI on us would be the last straw.  </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>RosesAreRed wrote:  &quot;Thanks, Red ....

Forcing an ugly, inflexible UI on us would be the last s</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>RosesAreRed wrote:  &quot;Thanks, Red ....

Forcing an ugly, inflexible UI on us would be the last straw.&quot;

As long as SOE supports custom UIs, the above would never be an issue.  Now, the fact that the &apos;default_old&apos; almost instantly became just another unsupported custom UI probably annoys people -- especially those who liked the old UI and don&apos;t want to have to screw with manually supporting it after every patch -- but we do</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I can tell you that the WoW servers are not half as populated as they were a year ago. I know becaus</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I can tell you that the WoW servers are not half as populated as they were a year ago. I know because I was playing a year ago and am playing now. The 2 servers that I play on have insane queues to log in that far surpass any I have ever seen in the past. On one server recently the queue was over 700 long, the other around 380, at the same time. When I get into the game I see people everywhere, no zones are ever empty. Now some servers are lower </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;As long as SOE supports custom UIs, the above would never be an issue. Now, the fact that the </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;As long as SOE supports custom UIs, the above would never be an issue. Now, the fact that the &apos;default_old&apos; almost instantly became just another unsupported custom UI probably annoys people -- especially those who liked the old UI and don&apos;t want to have to screw with manually supporting it after every patch -- but we do always have the choice to spend hours every patch keeping things up-to-date instead of conforming to what S</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The defualt_old UI is something some still like to use in my guild, and in a discussion on that, one</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The defualt_old UI is something some still like to use in my guild, and in a discussion on that, one member found this:  http://maddave.dnateam.com/everquest/everquest.html

This might help those who like the old UI.  Personally, I have used cusum UI&apos;s forever(Sars most of that time, as it is to my mind the cleanest, best looking UI around).  Keeping the UI&apos;s up to date is usually pretty trivial, with fixes usually posted the same day w</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>