<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>Wow! i actually like DoDh and PoR. No clue what the problem is from above posters..hah! it seems lik</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Wow! i actually like DoDh and PoR. No clue what the problem is from above posters..hah! it seems like one of them is annoyed that the raiding content is too hard? that is fine, but i would ask, too hard for who? only reason im not at high end por is playtime, thats all. The actual events ain&apos;t too hard, they are challenging, and we get each event we come ot eventually and have a blast doing it.

No clue on PoR/DoDh being worth the money etc.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I think they should get rid of Raiding alltogether and let the raiders go on to other games that are</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I think they should get rid of Raiding alltogether and let the raiders go on to other games that are comming out. Casuals are the majority anyway!</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Naw leave raiding in the game. We hear all the time how it is so fun, then just remove any xp / loot</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Naw leave raiding in the game. We hear all the time how it is so fun, then just remove any xp / loot rewards from it. If it is so damn fun then the raiders will continue to do it even though it provides no reward to them.

Lets see their feelings if that was to happen, they would scream louder about that then they whine about solo / casual players.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I like your Idea better lets go with that&gt; LOL</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I like your Idea better lets go with that&gt; LOL</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;seems like one of them is annoyed that the raiding content is too hard? that is fine, but i wo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;seems like one of them is annoyed that the raiding content is too hard? that is fine, but i would ask, too hard for who?&quot;

Well, looking at the numbers, I&apos;d say too hard for 80% of the EQ paying customer base. The 20% that do use it must thank the 80% who help fund it for them.

Most expansions contain a very larger percentage of raid content and lately, fewer and fewer people are bothering with it. Either because it&apos;s too ha</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I disagree. Since mergers took place the nice friendly atosmpheir on my server has hit the seweres. </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I disagree. Since mergers took place the nice friendly atosmpheir on my server has hit the seweres. It is almost unheard of to get a group and traveling to arcstone as a single is a non start. Often you can sit in arcstone and see 15 people in zone, shout lfg and nothing. I have often traveled to watch and there are 3 groups of 5. Peeps refuse to let most in. If you want to help alot of us make some stuff for solo, like the LDON was suppose to ha</description>
</item>
<item>
<title> I dont know how every one else feels but I for one am very tired of zones that require navigating p</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description> I dont know how every one else feels but I for one am very tired of zones that require navigating paths that are way high up in the air.  The slightest bit of lag and a nasty corpse run or back to the guild lobby for a stone.  Man but I hate all that only being able to navigate a zone by flying.

  I am not really too pleased with much of the DoDH expansion.  The graphics are nice but the game play for me has proved to be very undesirable.  The </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I see lots of posts on how bad POR/DoD were but nothing to say how it should be put right. Such nega</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I see lots of posts on how bad POR/DoD were but nothing to say how it should be put right. Such negativity means that you are not here to help put things right and/or are considering leaving the game.

DoD group drops offered non raiders extremely good armour upgrades from instanced drops (IMO).

The slipgear aug offered an alternative to folks not wanting to back track through LDON stuff.

The overarching mask quest offered a very good Mask that</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>glormane wrote:My main niggles on DoD are that the upgrades somewhat trivialised some raiding conten</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>glormane wrote:My main niggles on DoD are that the upgrades somewhat trivialised some raiding content I am still active with and that instanced drops were better than open content zones.

--

Even kunark/velious raiding items were eventually trivialized by expansions. cant expect content to be the best forever.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Glormane Wrote:1. Provide other camps for Belfast Faction and Gnomish Clockwork bolts/Mechanotablest</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Glormane Wrote:1. Provide other camps for Belfast Faction and Gnomish Clockwork bolts/Mechanotablests. These are needed to make the POR uber type 12 augs but once a pharmer or dedicated guild get there, its locked for weeks.
--
I beleive all the clockworks in the zone can drop Bolts/Tablets just need to not care about takeing the small faction hit. and I think there is even a instance with clockworks you can kill in for these peices.


Glormane W</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>ezez,

Mark me down as another who was disappointed SOE discontinued their special $99 annual fee.  </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>ezez,

Mark me down as another who was disappointed SOE discontinued their special $99 annual fee.  What really bothered me about that whole thing was the fact that they had promised to automatically renew accounts at the same price when the deal was offered last year.  In other words, I signed up a number of accounts not only for the reduced rate but also for a price guarantee that SOE now refuses to honor.

The extra $50 per account isn&apos;t </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>have you seen that soe is trying to buy out vanguard from microsoft now? guess they started getting </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>have you seen that soe is trying to buy out vanguard from microsoft now? guess they started getting afraid of the competition....</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Actually If You read The Vanguard forums,its the other way arounsd Sigil approached them.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Actually If You read The Vanguard forums,its the other way arounsd Sigil approached them.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Regarding Vanguard.  I had posted in another thread here that I was unsure of Vanguard&apos;s abilit</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Regarding Vanguard.  I had posted in another thread here that I was unsure of Vanguard&apos;s ability to be popular.  Having went to the site again, and then learning Microsoft was going to publish, since that thread has closed and it was brought up here, I wanted to say that as a game it does look like it has legs.  Microsoft publishing it would have made it transition from not well known to having Microsoft muscle behind it, the same as Blizzar</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I get the feeling that MS probably was pressuring them to make it xbox 360 compatible. I can&apos;t </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I get the feeling that MS probably was pressuring them to make it xbox 360 compatible. I can&apos;t see any way else they could interfere since it&apos;s already a Windows platform game.  Possibly another pressure point could of been release time. MS would want it out regardless if its ready and Sigil probably is willing to wait another year to fix it up.

Sigil bought themselves out then was left with not much choice but to find another publishe</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>