<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Mobhunter</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/" />
  <modified>2006-11-20T02:58:21Z</modified>
  <tagline></tagline>
  <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7</id>
  <generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="3.01D">Movable Type</generator>
  <copyright>Copyright (c) 2006, Loral</copyright>
  <entry>
    <title>The State of the Equipment Gap</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001509.html" />
    <modified>2006-11-20T02:58:21Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-11-18T19:57:37-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1509</id>
    <created>2006-11-19T00:57:37Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral takes a look at the current state of the equipment power gap between raiders and single-group hunters at the highest levels after the release of The Serpent&apos;s Spine.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>During the initial dark days of the release of Planes of Power, life was hard for non-raiders. Experience rewards had dried up for levels above 60 and the available unflagged hunting areas in the Planes were few.</p>

<p>For weeks I ran a Sunday morning Plane of Justice Executioner Trial event that would help non-raiders get into Valor and Storm so they could find areas worth hunting in. These trials, tuned for "high level players" proved nearly impossible for lower-equipped players. The way I got around this was easy: I brought in a ringer. High-end raiders from Luclin had no problem getting through these trials yet non-raiders could barely get through a trial without wiping out in the first encounter. This was my first experience with the danger of the equipment gap.</p>

<p>Few topics get as much attention or as much excitement as the discussion of the equipment gap. Often these discussions begin focused around a specific circumstance, for example the power of a new piece of armor dropping in Ashengate, but degenerate into large and long winded arguments about the core reward system found across Everquest over the past seven years.</p>

<p>While many equipment gap discussions can be easily discounted and ignored with no harm to either the players or the game, there are some important things for players and designers to both consider.</p>

<p>First, let us scope our discussion. </p>

<p>We will define the term "equipment gap" as the gap in statistical power between level 75 gear available to non-raiding high-end level 75 players, and the statistical power of level 75 high-end raid-level gear. Other power levels in older raid content will also be discussed and compared to current level 75 non-raid gear.</p>

<p>There are many zones in which the equipment rewards given are less<br />
powerful than that which is required simply to enter the zone, let<br />
alone defeating any of the bosses.  One such zone is the Theater of<br />
Blood.</p>

<p>We will define "raid equipment" as any equipment that requires more than six people to acquire. We will also define "raid equipment" as any equipment that can only be accessed by those with a raid flag or those with equipment acquired in raids.</p>

<p>We will define "raids" as any event that requires more than six people.</p>

<p>We will scope the whole topic of the equipment gap at levels 71 to 75. Any characters lower than 71 can probably find equipment of sufficient power to hunt in zones for the experience required to take them to level 75. However, it is important to note that level 65 raid gear still outstrips level 75 single group gear in some areas like Tacvi.</p>

<p>We will not define "casual" or "hard core" or "uber" in this article - they are meaningless and worthless terms.</p>

<p>So, with thos caveats laid out, lets look at the current state of the equipment gap and why it is an important point to consider.</p>

<p>The following helmet is the highest powered helmet available to a single-group level 75 cleric. It requires drops from a rare mob in Sunderock Springs, three more common drops from Direwind, and a Softly Glowing Powersource that drops very rarely in Vergalid Mines or Valdeholm, two level 70+ dungeons in TSS:</p>

<p>Mana-Fused Plate Helm<br />
AC: 55<br />
STR: +14 CHA: +15 WIS: +16 AGI: +13 HP: +215 MANA: +225<br />
SV FIRE: +10 SV DISEASE: +13 SV COLD: +12 SV POISON: +15<br />
Shielding: +2% Regeneration: +3 Mana Regeneration: +2<br />
Effect: Truesight (Worn) at Level 75</p>

<p>This next helmet is a raid-level cleric helmet available in the high-end raiding zones in TSS:</p>

<p>Mysaphar's Spiritmind Helm<br />
AC: 70<br />
STR: +30 STA: +30 CHA: +25 WIS: +35 AGI: +20 HP: +445 MANA: +455<br />
SV FIRE: +30 SV COLD: +35 SV MAGIC: +25 SV POISON: +35<br />
Shielding: +2% DoT Shielding: +4% Mana Regeneration: +3 Damage Shield: +3<br />
Effect: Faerune (Worn) at Level 75</p>

<p>When you consider the power of augments available at both of these areas of the game, the statistics get even more wide-spread, with a high-end of about 315 mana for a single-group equipped character and up to 650 for a raid-level equipped character - both at level 75.</p>

<p>With the release of The Serpent's Spine, the equipment gap between raiders and non-raiders is larger than it has ever been before. While single-group equipment power has gone up significantly since the previous expansions, it has not yet outstripped raid-level equipment released six expansion's ago even though that equipment was designed around characters ten levels lower than the current level cap.</p>

<p>One has to go back to early Gates of Discord and even Planes of Power in some cases to find equipment dropping in raids that is less powerful than the gear available to single group level 75 players in the most recent expansion.</p>

<p>Why does equipment matter?</p>

<p>Some specifics aside, and as a general rule of thumb, equipment power equals about 1/2 of the power of the character barring big discrepencies in alternate abilities. From the standpoint of raw numerical statistics, about half of the hitpoints and mana of a character can come from equipment. With level 75 Ashengate-level raid gear just about doubling the power of level 75 Ashengate single-group gear, a raider can be just about 150% more powerful than a non-raider at level 75 due to equipment alone.</p>

<p>Of course, this discounts a few important factors such as alternate abilities and player skill which can dramatically change the overall power of a character but these variables stacked with the variables in equipment power make it even more difficult to balance content.</p>

<p>The arbitrary numbers associated with gear don't matter outside of the game. There is no real extra joy that comes from a pair of 450 mana boots over a pair of 250 mana boots. The real problem comes from SOE's inability to properly balance content at the highest level. SOE isn't alone in this - Blizzard shows that they have the same trouble even more so in battlegrounds where two level 60 players will have dramatically different abilities to defeat opponents based on gear alone.</p>

<p>The gap in power between raiders and non-raiders makes it very difficult to properly balance content and SOE has proven unsuccessful almost all the way back to Planes of Power.</p>

<p>In Depths of Darkhollow, SOE attempted to account for the equipment gap by offering "Normal" and "Hard" selections on single-group missions. However, some "Normal" missions still proved far too hard for those without some type of raid-level equipment and "Hard" missions were still trivial to raiders wearing the highest-end armor from one or two expansions back.</p>

<p>The wide range of equipment power makes it impossible to pinpoint any setting of "normal" or "hard. Most content is tuned somewhere in between but ends up being only useful for a very select audience.</p>

<p>We saw this with Ashengate where SOE admitted that the range in equipment power meant that the zone would have been unusable to a large section of the player-base. However, in the tuning, they made it trivial for high-end raiders even before those raiders geared up on the new TSS raid armor.</p>

<p>The player gap is an important problem simply because properly tuning single-group content at the high end has proven unsuccessful for nearly eight of the twelve expansions.</p>

<p>What can be done to solve this?</p>

<p>There are a variety of methods to look into this problem, but the one that comes easily to mind is to simply reduce the gap. Offer higher-end armor for non-raiders and make it easier to acquire.</p>

<p>SOE should decide now how far back raid content should go before becoming obsolete. Particularly on level-cap increasing expansions, gear power should jump more significantly than it has in the past. For example, with the release of The Serpent's Spine, SOE could have decided that any gear found in high-end raids before the Citadel of Anguish in Omens of War should be easier to acquire for level 75 single-group hunters in TSS.</p>

<p>Raid content is important to keep alive, so improving it any more than that would make too much raid content obsolete and remove a lot of the entertainment found in places like Anguish, the DON dragons, DODH, and POR raids.</p>

<p>How would these changes improve the game?</p>

<p>Reducing the equipment gap helps the game in three ways:</p>

<p>First, it helps SOE properly tune content for certain level ranges instead of tuning around one point in a huge spectrum of player powers.</p>

<p>Second, it helps guilds gear up without having to repeatedly fight through very old raid content just to power up new members.</p>

<p>Third, it helps smooth the path for non-raiders to enter the raiding game. The raid game is a clear advantage of Everquest over competing massive online games. SOE should do what it can to make it easier for newer players to enter this area of the game's focus.</p>

<p>The power level that SOE decides to release for single-group and raid-level equipment in each expansion can have repercussions that last for years. It is important that SOE structure the power levels of equipment and thus improve their ability to properly tune high-end content.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
20 November 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Review of the Serpent&apos;s Spine</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001506.html" />
    <modified>2006-11-05T01:50:34Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-11-04T08:49:15-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1506</id>
    <created>2006-11-04T13:49:15Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Two months after release, Loral takes a full look at the Serpent&apos;s Spine and discusses each of the new features found in this cyclopean expansion.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Nearly two months have passed since the release of the Serpent's Spine and with one major patch and a few minor ones released, now is the perfect time to review Everquest's twelfth expansion, the Serpent's Spine.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine is the largest expansion since Planes of Power in the number of zones and the variety of content. It offers content at all levels of play from brand-new level 1 players all the way to high-end level 75 raid zones. The Serpent's Spine is a huge contrast to the smaller and heavily instanced content in Dragons of Norrath and Depths of Darkhollow.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine includes thirteen large non-instanced zones and two instanced raid zones. The zones are huge, rivaling those found in Omens of War, Scars of Velious, and Shadows of Luclin. Unlike many large static zones in older expansions, most of the zones in the Serpent's Spine are well-used. It isn't uncommon to find a dozen players in each of the zones and many more in the higher-level zones at any given time. This is a great change from Prophecy of Ro where many new zones sat deserted and empty shortly after release.</p>

<p>As a new starting city, Crescent Reach is the first zone to let younger players see powerful dragons up close, but it lacks the same power and awe as the rebuilt city of Freeport. For example, all of the guild masters for every class all reside in one large hall. The cleric guild master and the necromancer guild master stand right across from one another. It feels like a college career day instead of a guild hall. The graphical lag in Crescent Reach is also the worst found in the expansion.</p>

<p>The new Drakkin model gets mixed reviews but it is clearly nice to see a model that sits correctly, has armor that reflects light properly, and doesn't fall apart when it sits on a horse with a shield. Hopefully this new model will lead to the rebuilding of player models for all races in the future.</p>

<p>What Crescent Reach lacks in awe it gains back in quests. There are tons of quests throughout the city for every level. These quests don't end with Crescent Reach either, one will find dozens of quests throughout all of the zones in the Serpent's Spine. There are quest arcs for exploration, hunting, and an arc that can follow a new player from level 1 all the way to level 75.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine offers piles of huntable content at all character levels and equipment power. The designers intended to bring many of the techniques they use for higher-end content in recent expansions down to all levels in the game and they succeeded in this. Lower level players have many "single-group raids" they can experience as well as common quest arcs found typically at higher-end hunts in older expansions.</p>

<p>For high-end players there are between four and six huntable zones depending on levels, Alternate Advancement points, and gear power. Direwind, Icefall, Vergalid, Valdeholm, and for some, Frost Crypt and Ashengate all offer good challenges, good experience rewards, and good loot for those hunting there. Most importantly, the zones are very popular making it much easier to find a group and get to hunting. </p>

<p>There are no instances for group content in the Serpent's Spine. Some players complain that this lack of instancing has returned the game to the dark ages of spawn camping, kill stealing, training, and other vileness that accompanies large amounts of players piled into one space. However, instanced content would likely have made the new static zones much less popular. With so much instanced content in the game already, there is little reason to include it in every new expansion. Instanced content, however, is the only clear feature missing from this expansion.</p>

<p>Equipment rewards are one of the big drivers for players to experience new content and the Serpent's Spine includes a lot of it. There are many new armor sets at all levels except a level 60 set. The level 75 single-group armor comes in multiple pieces, is clearly more powerful than Qvic class armor, and rivals the class armor found in Theater of Blood. Ashengate and Frost Crypt include many high-end items close in power to the high-end raid items of Gates of Discord and the non-Anguish raid armor in Omens of War. Tier 2 spells also act as a solid catalyst to get players hunting in various zones.</p>

<p>The high-end spell system is the best ever developed. Instead of making high-end spells simply dropped and increasingly more rare at the highest levels, spells in the Serpent's Spine are broken down into tiers. The lowest tier includes nearly every level 71+ spell for every class and can be purchased from merchants spread around the new zones. Tier 2 spells add a bit more power and drop across the higher-level hunting zones. Tier 3 spells drop off of raid targets and use a system similar to the Omens of War rune system.</p>

<p>Overall, the spell system lets players power up quickly upon leveling, I added five new spells to my spell book seconds after leveling to 75, without removing the desire to hunt for more powerful versions in the new hunting zones.</p>

<p>Any expansion that includes new levels will quickly become popular. Leveling is the fastest and easiest way to increase in player power. The level increase opens up older high-power content to new players. For example, the MPG single group trials and the Depths of Darkhollow spell arcs are much more easily done at level 75 than it was at level 70. More players will be able to defeat older raid targets and older content that was extremely challenging at lower levels. New piles of Alternate Advancement abilities also increase this power and give players new reasons to hunt for experience.</p>

<p>Along with the large amount of lower level content and high-level single-group hunting areas, The Serpent's Spine has the largest amount of high-end raiding content since Gates of Discord. The Serpent's Spine includes two full high-end raid zones that rival Anguish in the number of raids. This doesn't even include the static raids and the instanced Vergalid raid. The large amount of high-end raid content gives high-end raiders a wide range of content above the Demiplane of Blood and Deathknell level. These high-end raid zones include a new tier of class armor as well, something not included since Anguish.</p>

<p>One big complaint I have with the Serpent's Spine is that it does nothing to address the power gap between raiders and non-raiders. Yes, the level 75 non-raid armor is a good step up from what was available before, but it could have been more powerful without hurting older raid content. I will cover this problem in more depth in a future article.</p>

<p>When beginning to ponder this article, I tried to think back to older expansions to determine how this one compares. From the factor of raw features and usable content, no other expansion compares to the scope of the Serpent's Spine. No expansion since Luclin included level 1 to max level content. No expansion since Omens offered a level increase as substantial as TSS. No expansion since Gates offered as much high-end raid content. The Serpent's Spine sits high on the list of expansions and towers above the expansions released over the past two years.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine is an extremely strong expansion that offers new levels, spells, AAs, equipment, and huntable content at all levels of play. It is a great breath of life in a game that continues to grow well beyond its seven year life. At $30, it's a steal.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
4 November 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Are Massive Online Games Getting Worse?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001504.html" />
    <modified>2006-11-05T14:52:48Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-10-17T22:39:05-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1504</id>
    <created>2006-10-18T03:39:05Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral takes a step back and considers the past and future of massive online games. We all love instances, easy corpse recovery, shorter travel, and fancy new LFG windows, but what price do we pay for their inclusion?</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>One day in the city of Erudin, a young cleric of Quellious had a dream. He wanted to travel from his homeland of Odus to the faraway dwarven lands of Kaladim. It would be a long journey, one filled with unimaginable dangers. He had no way to teleport, no magic stones that shifted him from city to city with a touch, not even a reliable method to bind in the cities along his journey. With nothing but a few spells and a cracked staff, the cleric Ciric spent a week traveling across two oceans, the plains of Karana, the forest of Kithicor, and through the cities of Qeynos, High Keep, Rivervale, and Freeport. It seemed as though he had a lioness on his arse the whole way yet he survived his journey and to this day I still share his tale.</p>

<p>I will warn you ahead of time. This article will likely spawn more questions than answers. You won't learn where to get all of the shiniest treasures held within the Serpent's Spine. You won't learn what powerful dangers lurk in Ashengate. Today we're going to step back for a moment and consider the history and future of Massive Online Games.</p>

<p>Long ago I read an article entitled "<a href="http://www.gamegirladvance.com/archives/2003/07/28/not_yet_you_fools.html">Voice Chat in MMOGs? Not Yet, You Fools!</a>" by Richard Bartle, the designer of the first multi-user dungeon back in 1978. The article was my first glimpse at some theories that new technologies and new advances in MMOs, in this case voice chat, might actually be more harmful to a game than helpful.</p>

<p>More recently, Bartle wrote another article entitled "<a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/features/20041103/bartle_pfv.htm">Why Virtual Worlds are Designed By Newbies</a>". Again I raised an eyebrow at some of the statements made. The article implies that many of the more recent improvements to MMOs might actually do more harm to the long-term benefit of the game than it will to help. Examples include instancing, death recovery, and instant travel.</p>

<p>I don't agree with everything in the article and I'm not sure the theory that short-term improvements to massive online games have done harm, but it did bring up some interesting questions.</p>

<p>When we look at recent games like World of Warcraft, Everquest 2, and the recent revisions of Everquest, we see a game with many improvements over first generation massive online games. We have teleportation stones, griffin rides, LFG windows, instanced dungeons, corpse summoning, PVP restrictions, no-drop loot, and many other features that have streamlined these games to widen the audience. Many of the rough edges are gone but perhaps it was those rough edges that made the game exciting in the first place.</p>

<p>No, I'm not waving the "SOE is dumbing down the game!" flag. Many of these improvements have made the game a lot more enjoyable to a lot more people. I can't imagine playing EQ without the corpse summoner, knowledge stones, or instanced dungeons. I like those features. Yes, a lot of players jumped over to the Progression servers to see EQ back the way it was back in the old days, and many of them came running back to the game we have today.</p>

<p>No improvement comes without cost, however. There is something lost for the ease of griffin travel in World of Warcraft. Unlike EQ's Knowledge Stones, a player must at least travel to a griffin master by foot before gaining the ability to fly on griffinback, but how much different would the world be if travel took far longer in Azeroth than it does today? How would we view the scope of the world? Would the game's slower pace result in stronger social ties between players in a group? Would travel itself be the primary source of adventure instead of the destination?</p>

<p>What of instancing? The convenience of a spawned world built for one specific group is strong enough that all three of the top fantasy MMOs in the U.S. include it. Yet what price do we pay for these conveniences? It is hard to find a feature that does more to break the metaphysical nature of the game than instancing. How clumsy do we feel when we try to explain instances using examples from real life? And what of the lost social opportunities? How many friends did you miss meeting simply because you never occupied the same dungeon?</p>

<p>The Everquest design team has moved away from instances with the past three expansions. In Prophecy of Ro, the result was all but completely disastrous. Static and instance zones alike see little use. Overland zones in Prophecy, Depths of Darkhollow, and Dragons of Norrath, were little more than travel conduits to the instances of these expansions.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine broke away from instances almost completely and with much more success. Well designed overland zones now host as many as three dozen players in each of the expansion's thirteen zones. The popularity of the zones sometimes results in complaints that Everquest is returning to its former overcrowded state, but how do such complains sound to SOE? Perhaps they sound like success.</p>

<p>Richard Bartle talks about the memories formed from massive online games and the catalysts for these memories. Players don't remember playing through scripted events nearly as well as they remember interactions with other players, especially the unpredictable ones. It is the sharp-edged rubbing of a MMO's population that creates the most dynamic and unique situations. When you remove those sharp edges and stick those players in smooth, clean instances where no one bumps elbows and no one gets hurt, that's when the life is removed from a MMO.</p>

<p>I say these words only as one theory. I'm not sure I believe them. The numbers for World of Warcraft subscribers prove them wrong. I don't know how many people played Richard Bartle's MUD but I'm guessing it wasn't ten million. I've spoken out against soloing as a basis for progression in a MMO, it would seem contradictory to the purpose of a MMO in the first place, but again the numbers prove me wrong. I enjoy WOW as much as the next guy and a lot of it has to do with the convenience afforded by soloing.</p>

<p>A few days ago Blizzard announced a new LFG tool for World of Warcraft to help players find groups and groups to find players. On the surface it appears to be a clone of the LFG window SOE added to Everquest a few years back.</p>

<p>I can't help but wonder if this tool is the right answer. Do we really need another widget? Will another UI box help us? Couldn't Blizzard have come up with something new or found a better way to direct players into groups and into content? SOE found a new way to get groups together in Everquest, they did it with good solid huntable and rewarding content. I'm guessing the Burning Crusade will have lots of that as well, I only wish they could have been a bit more creative about getting groups together than another UI box full of drop-down menus and tabs.</p>

<p>Every feature added to a MMO also takes something away. The smoother the world gets, the more common our experiences will be. Maybe this is what happened to EQ over the past few years. The game got smoothed out and streamlined and now everyone does monster missions until they join the high-end raiding game. What will a new window or a new portal stone do to the long-term future of a MMO? It isn't known, but we do know that nothing is free.</p>

<p>One day as a young paladin on a forgotten server, I stumbled into the dungeon of Befallen. I cut down a few skeletons, explored some broken rooms in a shattered temple, and soon I spotted a well. I peeked down the well. My footing slipped. Seconds later I found myself broken and ripped apart by ghouls twice as powerful than I was. A powerful cleric of Tunare, one of the unimaginable thirty second level, came to my rescue. He looted my broken corpse, cut down a troll shadowknight, and returned to the entrance of the dungeon with my banded mail and bronze mace. That encounter changed my whole view of Norrath for the rest of time.</p>

<p>What stories will the new adventurers of Norrath share?</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
17 October 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Battle of Ashengate</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001502.html" />
    <modified>2006-10-18T03:50:10Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-10-05T16:10:24-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1502</id>
    <created>2006-10-05T21:10:24Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week Loral takes a look at the recent change and controversy surrounding the two high-end hunting zones in The Serpent&apos;s Spine.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>In my preview of the Serpent's Spine I had one major criticism: the ultra-high-end difficulty of Ashengate and Frostcrypt, the two high-end hunting zones in the expansion. As I understood it, Ashengate and Frostcrypt were designed for "ultra-high-end" players. While the definition itself was not clearly explained, I assumed that meant it was designed for those hunters equipped in high-end raid gear.</p>

<p>Upon release, the difficulty matched the power of these ultra-high-end raiders. The only hunters capable of effectively hunting in these two zones were those in very high-end raid armor. The orcs, drakes, golems, and oozes of Ashengate unleashed catastrophic levels of damage. High-end raiders spoke well of their hunts there except for one complaint:</p>

<p>For high-end raiders, the rewards were too low powered.</p>

<p>Now we get into the twisting argument of raid-level single group hunting. There are four rules which overlap and half contradict one another, four truths we have seen since the days of Velious.</p>

<p>Truth 1: Raiders want challenging content.</p>

<p>Truth 2: Single-group hunters want to progress to the most challenging single group events.</p>

<p>Truth 3: All players want meaningful tangible rewards.</p>

<p>Truth 4: Single-group content cannot drop raid-level rewards or raiding becomes obsolete.</p>

<p>When the development team builds high-end encounters, events, or zones, and sends them through the filter of these four truths, they end up with weird results:</p>

<p>Result 1: Events are too underpowered for high-end raiders because they have to be tuned so single-group hunters could eventually reach them.</p>

<p>Result 2: Single group hunters can't progress to raid-level power because they don't raid.</p>

<p>Result 3: Raiders rarely receive meaningful equipment rewards from single group hunts.</p>

<p>Last Friday night, on 29 September, Ashengate changed. The mobs hit for a lot less and had fewer hitpoints. Suddenly the high end raiders started carving down the beasts that troubled them before and high-end single group hunters or raiders of lower powered raid targets could hunt effectively and profitably within Ashengate.</p>

<p>The boards lit up with anger at the change from the high-end raiders who enjoyed the challenge of this beautiful and entertaining zone. After pages of discussion, Rashere, the lead designer of the Serpent's Spine, had this to say:</p>

<p>"It's a no-win situation.  If we tune the content to be a serious challenge for high-end raiders in a single group, you'll complain that the loot is worthless since the only upgrades you could use are raid-level upgrades and those aren't going to come off single group content.  If we threw that aside and tune up both the content and the loot so that its an upgrade to your raid gear, you'll complain that there's no reason to raid anymore cause the gear is available from single groups.  And, obviously, if we tune the content to the point where its challenging to players who can use the loot coming out of it, you'll complain that the zone is too easy."</p>

<p>For years the equipment power gap between high-end raiders has been discussed. In one of my favorite historical articles, Moorgard describes the gear canyon between the single group and raid gear in Scars of Velious over five years ago. I've written half a dozen articles on that topic alone and referenced it hundreds of times elsewhere.</p>

<p>Now it comes to a peak in Ashengate. Now we have a zone that both raiders and non-raiders want but only one of them can have. Now the twisting logic of high-end raiding versus high-end single grouping is articulated in that one statement by Rashere.</p>

<p>What can solve this no-win situation? Is there a solution? Many people propose many theories, including myself, but almost all of these theories are swayed by the play style of the theorist. They all boil down to the following:</p>

<p>Solution 1: Put in content difficult enough that it challenges high-end raiders. Put in rewards that matter to them but won't make raiding obsolete. Of course, what would that be?</p>

<p>Solution 2: Tune all single group content around single-group players. Raiders raid and non-raiders don't. The problem is, raiders don't raid all the time and they don't want to. They like single group challenges too and being a high-end raider shouldn't cut them off from that. As a counter argument, however, non-raiders are cut off from all kinds of content in every expansion so why is it a problem that raiders are likewise cut off?</p>

<p>Solution 3: Put in two versions of a zone with a "normal" and "hard". They tried this in Depths of Darkhollow but the differences between the two versions were slight. People can't so easily be broken down into those two groups and improper tuning could make both versions worthless.</p>

<p>Solution 4: Close the gap. Make equipment progress from level 1 to high-end level 75. Offer clear equipment paths for single group hunters all the way up to the highest single group content and make the power of that gear closer to the power of raid gear. The problem with this could be quite severe. If its too powerful a lot of high-end raids of previous expansions get cut out.</p>

<p>This also brings up some questions better asked and answered by SOE. For a long time SOE has remained fuzzy when it comes to the tuning of content. They speak of difficulty compared to old zones, not compared to the levels, AAs, and gear power of players. Level, gear, and AAs are specific good metrics against which to tune content but it is largely avoided. So lets ask SOE these questions:</p>

<p>Question 1: How can SOE apply metrics to gear just as they have to level and AAs?</p>

<p>Question 2: How can SOE tune content around levels, gear, and AAs instead of basing it on the difficulty of underused or outdated content from the past?</p>

<p>Question 3: What can SOE offer high-end raiders that will reward them for single group hunts but not make raiding obsolete?</p>

<p>It all comes down to the same general philosophies held by the designers and held by the players. Who deserves what? Do high-end raiders deserve as much challenging single group content as one who only does single groups? Who deserves high end equipment and what should be required for them to receive it?</p>

<p>There are some other questions worthy of consideration. Recently, Blizzard announced that World of Warcraft would be moving to a 20 person maximum raid count. Everquest 2 caps their raids at 24. This leaves Everquest alone as the game with the largest raids of any MMO. I would aruge that Everquest has the largest and most well developed raid game of any massive online game.</p>

<p>Should SOE capitalize on this? Should they further develop this raid game? Should they seek ways to get more players into that area of the game as players progress? Or is the raiding game a black hole that will never have enough players willing to spend the kind of time required to progress through Everquest's vast raid content?</p>

<p>Most importantly, what would Loral recommend? I'm glad you asked.</p>

<p>Loral's recommendations to SOE:</p>

<p>1. Begin tuning content around existing player power including level, AAs, and gear power. Come up with a simple metric for gear power that consolidates damage output, statistical bonuses, combat bonuses, and focus effects. Each piece of gear should have a well defined "power level".</p>

<p>2. Tune content around the current and proposed breakdown in player power. If most players are level 70 raiders, tune content towards them. Tune expansion content at the percentage breakdown equal to the power of existing playing players as well as where you expect them to be and where you would like them to be.</p>

<p>3. Clearly decide when raid content can be acceptably trivialized by single-group drops. Is it one year after release? Two? Three? Right now single group equipment just barely reaches the power of raid equipment from Gates of Discord, an expansion released five expansions back and two and a half years ago.</p>

<p>4. In instanced expansions, offer well-tuned "normal" content for high-end non-raiders and "hard" content for high-end raiders.</p>

<p>5. Shorten the equipment gap. Make single group gear 75% of raid gear in the same expansion. If raiders can now receive 400 hitpoint and mana gear average from the expansion's end-zone, offer 300 hitpoint and mana gear for high-end non-raiders.</p>

<p>6. Build in content that helps non-raiders get into the raiding game. The raiding game is a clear strength of Everquest. Establish strategies that will reveal this strength to more players. Make it easier for non-raiders to become raiders. Locate the gaps faced by those who want to raid and those who do and address them. Build in better pickup-raid tools and content.</p>

<p>As the spine of the world continues to settle, our eyes watch the burning fires of Ashengate. Therein two armies battle against each other in a war that has lasted six years. Therein lies the foundation for the future of Norrath.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
5 October 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Three Big Changes to Everquest</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001499.html" />
    <modified>2006-10-18T03:50:23Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-09-19T22:24:02-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1499</id>
    <created>2006-09-20T03:24:02Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">In today&apos;s article, Loral discusses three big changes to Everquest: out of combat regeneration, expendable alternate advancement points, and the new tiered spell system available in the Serpent&apos;s Spine expansion.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Today's release of the Serpent's Spine brings us three new new features, one of them to all players and two of them to those who purchased the Serpent's Spine expansion. Today we will discuss the impact of the out of combat regeneration system, the expendable alternate advancement system, and the tiered spell system.</p>

<p>So long have we suffered under the long regeneration time of the Everquest of old. So long have we sat and waited, surfing Allakhazam's for new mana regeneration items, that we can't even comprehend how important a change like this is.</p>

<p>World of Warcraft and Everquest 2 both showed how important it is to limit downtime. Both games offer fast gameplay with short periods of regeneration in between combat. Before today, Everquest had no way to add such a system without unbalancing the game. Everquest could not know when you were in battle and when you were resting. Now, however, SOE has figured out a way to track a player's in-combat and out-of-combat state to allow very high regeneration when not in battle.</p>

<p>For long-time EQ vets, this system must be experienced to be understood. The impact is huge. No longer must players wait after buffing classes fully buff a group. No longer will raids have to wait very long periods of time for their melee classes to regenerate endurance. No longer is clarity a requirement for any group to hunt with any efficiency.</p>

<p>This feature changes how we play. It is no longer imperative for a cleric to hold on to 95% of his or her mana when he or she can regenerate to full in three minutes. Mana can drain and flow quickly, allowing for a lot more action in every encounter.</p>

<p>There are a few complaints of this system, as there are with any big change. Necromancers and Shaman had cornered the market on quick regeneration and now some feel that all of the other classes gained this ability as well. The difference is that necromancers and shaman can still use their abilities while in combat while other classes must wait 30 seconds after a battle to begin regenerating.</p>

<p>Those who spent fortunes of time and money on high mana regeneration items might feel that their efforts are pointless now, but again these regeneration items and spells work while in combat. They will still speed up combat, just not as much as they did before.</p>

<p>Others shout that this change should have happened years ago and they're right. EQ2 and World of Warcraft both had these systems over a year ago and it took a long time for SOE to add it into Everquest. Now we have it, however, and little can be done about the past.</p>

<p>The most baffling complaints come from those who feel that the downtime somehow resulted in greater skill when all it really did is give us more time for Tivo. Many of these complaints come down to the idea that with the downtime change, Everquest is now a more reasonable and possibly more popular game resulting in more players that make those of us willing to suffer with lousy mechanics less special.</p>

<p>Of all the major changes we receive with the Serpent's Spine release, the out-of-combat regeneration feature is, by far, the biggest and best change in a long time.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine also includes a new set of expendable alternate abilities. Unlike normal AAs, high-end characters can spend three AAs to receive a one-time ability. These abilities might include damage increases, hitpoint increases, damage mitigation abilities, and other unique abilities.</p>

<p>While this feature does not seem monumental on the surface, consider that this is the first time in any of the big three fantasy MMOs that experience will always be useful.</p>

<p>Everquest had a very high amount of rewards for experience earned. 70 levels and over a thousand points worth of alternate abilities meant that only a select few would ever get to the point where experience meant nothing. Now even those few will always have a use for AAs. Unlike Warcraft, where players hit level 60 and then receive very little in return for the hunting style that got them there, Everquest players can continue to earn and use experience throughout very long careers.</p>

<p>The returns for experience earned always diminishes. Levels matter more than AAs, some initial AAs are far more powerful than later AAs, and some AA sets seem almost completely pointless. Now expendable AAs add a bit more return for the AAs spent, but at the cost of being temporary.</p>

<p>Again, this system isn't without complaints. Some feel that they will be expected to earn and use these abilities for extremely challenging encounters. Some worry that encounters will have to be tuned around those with these AAs, making it more difficult to defeat the encounters without them. These are all valid concerns, but the advantage of a limitless upper end to experience gain makes up for it.</p>

<p>The last big change we will discuss today is the new tiered spell system of the Serpent's Spine. Many complained about the difficulty in achieving spells in Omens of War. While players could reach level 70 simply by hunting, spells above level 68 only came from very select encounters. These spells were not tradable and the system in place with Omens meant that one would have to collect up to six runes for each level to get all of the spells of their class. In some cases, the spell most sought after was the last spell on the list.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine includes a new tiered spell system where each spell at each level can possibly have three to four tiers of power. Each tier is more powerful than the previous, so a tier 3 blast will do more damage or have a better damage to mana ratio than earlier tiers. Most of the tier 1 spells are purchasable off of vendors in the new zones. Even though a player will not have the most powerful version of a spell at each level, they will have the base spell right away.</p>

<p>The tiered spell system isn't an entirely ground breaking feature, but it is a strong improvement over the spell systems of the past. It gives players the chance to upgrade to new abilities quickly but still give them improvements as rewards later in their hunts.</p>

<p>Though seven years old, Everquest continues to evolve every year. These three changes take systems we have lived with for years and greatly improves upon them, making the game as fresh and exciting today as it was years ago. Keep an eye out for a future full review of the Serpent's Spine in the weeks to come.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
19 September 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Success Criteria for the Serpent&apos;s Spine</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001496.html" />
    <modified>2006-10-18T03:50:34Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-08-27T20:48:33-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1496</id>
    <created>2006-08-28T01:48:33Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral takes a look at the elements required for the success of the Serpent&apos;s Spine.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>What does the Serpent's Spine, Everquest's twelfth expansion, need to be successful? What will define that success? Prophecy of Ro looked quite strong when we reviewed it during beta and shortly after its release. Only a couple of months in did we determine how deep the problems lay. Today we will look at the criteria for a successful expansion and match these criteria against what we know of the Serpent's Spine right now.</p>

<p>Defining Success.</p>

<p>There are many ways to define success for an expansion but I will stick to the actual features of an expansion that I find useful or fun. I will not define success based on commercial monetary gain for SOE, but by my own standards.</p>

<p>In short summary, a successful expansion should include the following criteria: progressive rewards, huntable zones, challenging raids, and pickup-group-friendly content. While not all of these are important to everyone and many other criteria are omitted, these criteria can directly affect the perceved success of an expansion.</p>

<p>Progressive Rewards.</p>

<p>We already know that the Serpent's Spine will include five new level ranges and a host of new alternate advancement abilities. This alone will make it a more useful expansion than the last. New levels and new AAs give everyone a reason to hunt for experience. Experience hunting encourages to grouping and grouping leads to the true strength of Everquest in the first place: getting players together to have fun.</p>

<p>Some players complain about the perceived forced requirement to level and earn AAs.  Without a level increase and more AAs, the game becomes stagnant. Players at the max level with large amounts of AAs don't bother to hunt in groups, and hence many players have more difficulty grouping.</p>

<p>The power gain from new levels and AAs also helps previous expansions. Players who aren't geared in top-end gear have the opportunity to earn enough power to defeat previously undefeated content. I get nervous, however, when content is released in current expansions with the intent that players will earn enough power later to come back.  I pay $30 for content I might be able to use in two years? What sort of evil reverse lay-away program is that?</p>

<p>Progressive gear paths are also very important. Ensuring that all players at all power levels have reasonable paths available to improve gear should be a top priority for the itemization of Serpent's Spine.</p>

<p>Good Huntable Zones.</p>

<p>Previous expansions have had limited success with static hunting zones. Dragons of Norrath, Depths of Darkhollow, and Prophecy of Ro all saw very limited numbers of players willing to hunt in the static content of those expansions. Instead players either focused on instances or on previously released but more rewarding zones like Riftseekers.</p>

<p>In order to break out of this downward trend, SOE will need to ensure that new static zones offer enough useful, huntable, exciting, and rewarding content to bring people out of the holes of instances from previous expansions and into the open. High experience rewards, fun but not frustrating encounters, beautiful but well performing zones, and the chance for good equipment upgrades will all be required.</p>

<p>Challenging Raids.</p>

<p>Raid targets are particularly tricky. To non-raiders it appeared Prophecy of Ro included a lot of raid content. To high-end raiders, much of this content was considered either too rewarding, not rewarding enough, tedious, or impossible. Finding the perfect balance of raid content so that it is challenging, rewarding, and offers a good path of progress is quite difficult. Only time will tell if the raid progress in Serpent's Spine meets the need.</p>

<p>Pickup-group-friendly content.</p>

<p>This is quite a debatable statement but, to me, the success of an expansion is directly proportional to the amount of pickup groups one finds within its zones. Players need to be able to get into the game, find a group, and make some progress all within a reasonable period of time. While some players are able to sacrifice a great deal of time to face the most extreme challenges of a game, others only desire a chance to find a quick bit of fun.</p>

<p>Pickup-group-friendly content is extremely difficult to get right. Lost Dungeons of Norrath had it. Omens of War had it. Dragons of Norrath had it but only for a very limited set of content: Creator and Gimblax missions. Depths of Darkhollow had it as long as raid-geared players were willing to bring a few non-raid-geared players along. Some players rely completely on ones ability to get groups from within their own guild but this still hampers players with only limited time.</p>

<p>Again, only time will tell if Serpent's Spine will offer suitable content to help pickup-groups form and succeed. The level and AA increase should help but beyond that is any one's guess.</p>

<p>Will Serpent's Spine succeed? It is impossible to answer the question with only the data we have available. Much of the frustration over the previous expansion was due to a limited set of usable content. The scope of the Serpent's Spine looks quite a bit larger but only with excellent tuning can it meet all of the needs players expect.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
27 August 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Prophecy of Ro Single Group Progression Video</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001495.html" />
    <modified>2006-09-18T16:38:06Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-08-24T23:10:03-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1495</id>
    <created>2006-08-25T04:10:03Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Based on the recent videos of Prophecy&apos;s raider end-game, Loral Ciriclight cuts up a little video showing the path of a single group hunter in Prophecy of Ro.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p><object width="425" height="350"><param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/nP6kSeU2gwk"></param><embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/nP6kSeU2gwk" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="600" height="350"></embed></object></p>

<p>Want a higher-res version? <a href="prophecy_single_group.wmv">Download it</a>!</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Preview of the Serpent&apos;s Spine</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001493.html" />
    <modified>2006-08-28T01:54:35Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-08-07T13:06:07-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1493</id>
    <created>2006-08-07T18:06:07Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral discusses his preview tour of the Serpent&apos;s Spine.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>On Friday, 4 August 2006, Travis McGeathy, lead designer for Everquest, took me on a tour of the Serpent's Spine, the twelfth Everquest expansion. We traveled across the new lands stretching from the back doors of High Keep to the dark reaches of Ashengate. Today I discuss what I saw and heard during these travels.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine takes a large departure from the expansions we've seen recently. While Dragons of Norrath, Depths of Darkhollow, and Prophecy of Ro all focused on or included a great amount of instanced content for both single-groups and raiders, Serpent's Spine returns to the older days of Everquest with a large expansion focused on static zones.</p>

<p>And large it is. This expansion includes thirteen huge zones; six outdoor zones, six dungeon zones, and a new city zone. The zone levels range from level 1 all the way to very-high-end level 75 zones. Each level range has two possible hunting zones with a few more at level 65 and above.</p>

<p>The biggest feature of this new expansion is the new race, the Drakkin. These dragon-blooded humanoids have more depth and possibility than the normal races. When one picks a Drakkin character, they don't just pick sex and class but also which type of dragon they are descended from. Redblooded Drakkin have resistances to fire, black have resistances to poison, and so on.</p>

<p>The Drakkin models, being mainly humanoid, are a possible leap forward for new player models, a feature requested for a long while. Adding a new player model to a new expansion gave the SOE developers some of the resources required to build a base model for many of the older races. While this new model won't directly lead to new models for older PCs anytime soon, it is a good step forward.  At the time of this writing, the Drakkin models were not yet released in the Beta of Serpent's Spine.</p>

<p>The Drakkin and the starting city of Crescent Reach gives players an opportunity to start Everquest from a new beginning. Rather than hunt and level through content designed years ago, lower-level players can see the sorts of things that higher-level players have experienced with recent expansions. For example, quests at low levels include a lot of scripting and features only found on high-end events.</p>

<p>The zones in Serpent's Spine are vast. They include a wide range of environments from deserts to glaciers to scorched volcanic rock. Large Sebilis-style dungeons are included at every level range. Many mini-dungeons, not instanced and not separated from the main zones exist as well.</p>

<p>I spent a few minutes with Rashere in the Stone Hive, a beautiful outdoor dungeon zone (sort of an oxymoron) that offers hunting for level 30 to 50. He and I discussed how players currently leveling up gravitate towards the content that offers the highest reward for the least effort. Such zones, I argued, might continue to be the popular choice even when alternatives exist. The Stone Hive, and the other zones in Serpent's Spine, will have higher experience rewards and better equipment drops than other zones of an equal level. This, mixed with the more interesting content and the beautiful artwork, should help to drive new players to these new zones. The intent of this mainly static content expansion is to get people together in common hunting areas instead of splitting them up into smaller six-person mini-zones.</p>

<p>Along with a focus on static hunting zones, the design team of the Serpent's Spine also focused on quests. There are hundreds of quests for all level ranges included in the Serpent's Spine, almost all of which use the quest window introduced with Omens of War and refined in Dragons of Norrath. These quests help to focus adventurers as they hunt across the vast landscapes included in the Serpent's Spine.</p>

<p>I will let the <a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/mshea01/SerpentSSpinePreview/">screenshots</a> speak to the graphic quality of the expansion. While some lands appear at first to be simple rolling hills and grasslands, one quickly discovers pockets of beauty and terror mixed within.  In particular, the framerate of the Serpent's Spine is better than Prophecy of ro. Only one area had any significant video lag, the inner city of Crescent Reach itself, but without the new models in it's hard to say how this will respond in the final game.</p>

<p>The story of the Serpent's Spine follows the Rallosian war, the invasion of the Plane of Earth by the giants and ogres of Rallos Zek. This eventually led to the curse of the Rathe. Throughout the expansion, one sees the results of this war. </p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine includes over a dozen new high-end raids and many multi-group events. Instanced versions of Frostcrypt and Ashengate house many of these raids on top of the static raids found throughout the expansion.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine also adds a few two-group events. These mini-raids may be a good vehicle for larger pickup events than those found with simple pickup groups. It is a good attempt to find ways for pickup raiding to be a viable option instead of focusing exclusively on high-end guild raids.</p>

<p>In another nice addition, low-level players will have exposure to some of the more powerful beasts of Norrath earlier on. Six dragons, not yet introduced into beta, will reside in Cresent Reach, letting new players see the power and might mostly holed off for only the highest end raiders. This is a good departure from previous expansions that hid the best models designed for Everquest behind raids that less than one percent of the player population could see.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine is a Y shaped expansion with a single geographical path up to the level 40ish zones and then a split. One side of the split leads through the new giant city and eventually to the ultra-high-end dungeon of Frostcrypt. The other split leads into the volcanic wastelands and eventually to the new Sebilis style ultra-high-end dungeon of Ashengate.</p>

<p>Like it or not, and Tunare knows it drives the development team crazy, loot is the primary driving force behind new content. At level 75 the Serpent's Spine will include new armor sets available both to single-group non-raiders and to high-end hunters and raiders who can brave the two ultra-high-end dungeons. With no loot yet populated in the beta, it is unknown if the development team found that difficult balance of risk versus reward.</p>

<p>Ashengate and Frostcrypt are worthy of their own discussion. These two static dungeons will pose a threat to even the mightest of adventurers. Huge and powerful beasts will cut, slash, and blast through those armored in the mightest equipment found in Norrath.</p>

<p>This is where we face one of my large concerns with Serpent's Spine. As it stands now, these two zones will offer single-group hunting for high-end raiders only. While anyone can enter these zones if they are able to reach them, the door guards hit hard enough to send anyone equipped in anything lower than Anguish scurrying back to Crescent Reach.</p>

<p>I love the idea of single-group ultra-high-end challenge zones. I love the idea of zones that will crush all but the mightiest. What bothers me is that the only path to these zones leads non-raiders into raiding. If you don't belong to the right guild, you can't hunt in a single group in these zones. An equipment progression path should exist that allows a level 75 single group player with enough AAs to hunt in Ashengate and Frostcyrpt.</p>

<p>High-level, high-AA, high-end single-group equipped players will hit a gap that forces them to either join a raiding guild or accept the fact that only those within raiding guilds will see the depths of Ashengate or Frostcrypt. The counter argument is that some day even single-group equipped players will be able to hunt here. History hasn't shown this to be true. </p>

<p>By the time a single-group equipped player can hunt in a raid-level zone, that zone and everything in it is obsolete.</p>

<p>SOE should rebuild one of these two zones into a high-end single-group-level zone that offers enough rewards to gear non-raiders up for the other ultra-high-end zone. A level 75 player with 300 or more AAs equipped in armor with around 200 hitpoints and mana should be able to hunt and hold their own in one of these two zones. As it stands now, both are designed to be equally inaccessible for most high-level players regardless of the time or effort they put in.</p>

<p>All of that said, there are four to six good level 70 to level 75 hunting zones that are accessible to non-raiders, so this power gap isn't likely to lead to a lack of huntable and profitable content.</p>

<p>The Serpent's Spine goes back to the days of vast expansions filled with wide-open spaces and hoards of beasts roaming the surface of Norrath. With a focus on static content, a large array of quests, and an entirely re-mapped out level 1 to level 75 progression path, this expansion should work well as a complement to recent expansions that included mostly instanced content. I can see how new Everquest players can hunt within the vast landscapes of the Serpent's Spine and then dive into the Depths of Darkhollow for single-group instances. Again, as it has many times in the past, the world of Norrath moves on.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
7 August 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Should You Become a Raider?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001491.html" />
    <modified>2006-08-25T04:44:46Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-07-30T10:27:02-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1491</id>
    <created>2006-07-30T15:27:02Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Loral takes a look at the advantages and disadvantages of the path of the high-end raider. Should you become a raider? Read on and learn what such a choice requires.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Since the dawn of Everquest, the adventurers of Norrath became split between those who raid and those who do not. After countless debates and discussions the split between these groups pulses between them, sometimes growing, sometimes shrinking. Yet at some time in the career of every high-level Everquest player, the question is raised:</p>

<p>Should one become a raider?</p>

<p>This article discusses the factors leading to this question and takes a look at how the game changes when one makes the leap to a raiding guild.</p>

<p>To begin, lets look at the advantages of raiding in Everquest:</p>

<p>1. It is a lot easier to get a group.</p>

<p>Since Gates of Discord, it has become time consuming and difficult to find a pickup group. Outside of Monster Missions, pickup groups outside of monster missions have shrunk. When one joins a raiding guild, these problems mostly disappear. Guild groups form quickly and easily. They focus on content that benefits individual members and the group as a whole. They move quickly and easily, their power is very high, and their success ratio is much higher than a pickup group. While most players join a raiding guild to raid, many find that grouping becomes much easier as well.</p>

<p>2. You will initially gain a great deal of power in a short period of time.</p>

<p>Unless you are joining a guild just beginning to raid, you will likely earn a great deal of powerful equipment in a short period of time. This process of gearing up new recruits is a common practice for guilds. It helps both the guild and the individual and with the power gap between raiders and non-raiders at a high point - it is likely that gear far above the power of a non-raid-equipped player will be worthless to most high-end raiders.</p>

<p>Over time, this progress will slow down but initially one can expect a few very powerful items to fall into their hands quickly.</p>

<p>3. You have access to more content, both raid and single-group.</p>

<p>As individual power grows, so does available content. Single group and multi-group events that were too difficult for non-raiders suddenly open up to raiders. Groups of raiders can hunt in Theater of Blood twinking alts with Qvic-level equipment. Groups of raiders can hunt for augments in Anguish. The MPG Trials, the DODH spell missions, the Skylance missions - these all become much easier as equipment power grows.</p>

<p>4. You can solo better.</p>

<p>As power grows, so does ones ability to solo. It seems odd that players who wish to solo would wish to join a raiding guild but at this stage in Everquest, the only players who can effectively solo at high levels are those with the high-powered equipment available to raiders.</p>

<p>If you want to solo well, you should join a raiding guild.</p>

<p>5. You can earn better gear in single groups than you could before.</p>

<p>Raids open up more single-group content including areas such as the Qvic Mshas and the Anguish augments. Groups of six can hunt in these zones and earn gear much higher than any available to non-raid-equipped single group hunters. As power grows, so does future profitability. This has a limit, of course. Eventually, when one earns enough powerful gear on a raid - the likelihood that they find something useful on a single-group hunt is low.</p>

<p>6. The encounters you face will be more interesting than those you faced before joining a raiding guild.</p>

<p>The high-end raid encounters past Gates of Discord are the most interesting events in the game. They are more dynamic, include better stories, and give players the most variety. Of course, they entice players with the most powerful loot in the game and include some of the best looking zones and models - models most of the population of Everquest will never see.</p>

<p>7. You will have more fun.</p>

<p>With better gear, a big jump in power, new and interesting encounters, new and interesting beasts, you are very likely to have more fun playing Everquest in a raiding guild than you are outside of one.</p>

<p>Clearly there are many advantages to becoming a raider. What disadvantages does one face when choosing the path of the raider?</p>

<p>1. You will get less sleep.</p>

<p>Raiding requires a lot of time. It is not uncommon to push back your bed time one or two hours. It is the nature of raids that the most interesting and rewarding content comes at the very end of a raid - the point that will be the latest in the evening. If you join a raiding guild, expect less sleep.</p>

<p>2. You will lose some friends.</p>

<p>As you make the transition from a non-raider to a raider, expect to lose some friends. While you may meet many new friends within your new guild, many of those with whom you hunted in your younger days will drift away from you or you will drift away from them. As the gap between your power and their power grows, so does your ability to hunt with them.</p>

<p>3. You won't have the freedom you had before raiding.</p>

<p>Raiding requires dedication and commitment. Your time is no longer your own. It is not uncommon for raiding guilds to require anywhere from three to five nights a week of raid time. The more powerful the raiding guild, the less free time you will find yourself with. Any hobbies you used to have in or out of game will suffer.</p>

<p>4. You will become less tolerant of less-skilled players.</p>

<p>When you have seen the skills of those in a well coordinated high-end raid guild, you become a lot less tolerant of those outside of your guild. Player skills will seem low and your trust of those you do not know will shrink. Expect to become an isolationist.</p>

<p>5. You can never go back.</p>

<p>Once you have geared up on high-end raid gear and once you have seen the powerful encounters that lay in the far depths of the game, you will never be able to let them go. Anything else will seem mundane and pointless. You are far more likely to quit completely than you are to leave the raiding game and go back to to the LFG channel.</p>

<p>Now that we have outlined the scope of the question it is time to look at it once again. Should you become a raider? Do you have the time? Do you have the desire? Are you tired enough of life as a non-raider? Do you want to see the best encounters, the best zones, and the best equipment in the game? There is only one choice to make.</p>

<p>So why would one not choose it? Let me speak for myself.</p>

<p>/em begins his editorial.</p>

<p>This game was not always so one dimensional as it is today. I was originally drawn to Everquest because of the sheer scope of possible things to do. Every time I logged in I faced a wide array of choices. I could group, I could solo, I could tradeskill, I could do an LDON instance, I could heal and buff new players, I could do some roleplaying, I could seek out lost treasures in ancient forgotten dungeons.</p>

<p>These days, at the highest levels of the game, there is really only one choice. Soloing is not profitable. The most beneficial content at level 70 is not achievable without raid gear. There comes a point where one can no longer progress until one chooses to raid.</p>

<p>I am just about at that point now. I log in and I sit in Arcstone watching people farm for low-powered gear on the demon's hill. I chat with my friends. I debate with other members of the Everquest summit - often with disastrous results. I pontificate and I brood and I dream - but I don't play. There is no gear better than what I have that is worth my time to acquire. I watch the titanic uberguilds roar past on their way to slay beasts in lands I will never see. I listen to the rumors of powerful equipment beyond anything I will see in the next four years.</p>

<p>I sit and I remember the times of LDON, the times where every night I could find a group for two hours and earn a fraction of a new piece of powerful equipment. I miss those days.</p>

<p>I want only three things:</p>

<p>1. I want to have a smooth path of individual power progression. Give me a set of 200 hp and mana primary armor available from sets of missions or quests.</p>

<p>2. I want to be able to quickly find a group and hunt for 90 minutes. Give me instanced or triggered quest encounters that have fixed durations so it won't make me late for work the next day.</p>

<p>3. I want to face fun and interesting encounters. Give me about thirty more of the Arcstone Spirit mob quests, give me thirty more missions like the 70 spell missions in DODH.</p>

<p>With Serpent's Spine on the way, I have hopes that I will have answers to these requests. Serpent's Spine can return us to the days where groups were plentiful and gear progression was possible at every level of play. Many are quick to point out that I had such hopes for Prophecy of Ro and they are right to question me. At this point we can only wait and see. If it does not return us to those days where the world was wide open and we chose our own path - perhaps it is time for Loral Ciriclight to consider the path of the raider.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight <br />
29 July 2006 <br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Snapping the Serpent&apos;s Spine</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001487.html" />
    <modified>2006-08-25T04:44:46Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-07-16T10:13:12-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1487</id>
    <created>2006-07-16T15:13:12Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">In today&apos;s article, Loral discusses the recent announcement that the Serpent&apos;s Spine expansion will be download only. Say it isn&apos;t so, Joe.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last week, Sony Online Entertainment announced the upcoming release of The Serpent's Spine, Everquest's twelfth expansion. This expansion breaks away from expansions primarily tuned for higher-level players and returns to expansions such as Ruins of Kunark and Shadows of Luclin by including a new race and content beginning at level 1.</p>

<p>Back in April, at the Spring 2006 Fan Faire, SOE had discussed a few of the details of this expansion, though the name was not yet released. The developers described it as a new beginning for Everquest. New players would have a chance to enter Everquest and progress from level 1 to level 75 without ever leaving the expansion. New players would be able to buy this expansion, take it home, and get right into the game as though it were completely new.</p>

<p>More surprising than the announcement of the new Drakkin race - the impact of which I will discuss in a future article - was the announcement that the game would only be available for download only. This method of distribution has not taken place since Legacy of Ykesha. Every other expansion has been a box on a shelf.</p>

<p>The choice to release the Serpent's Spine only as a download contradicts the intent of bringing new players to the game. New players aren't likely to surf around to SOE's website and wait for half a day to download a gigabyte of code and artwork. They are much more likely to buy a new glossy package on the shelf. A retail box is the best way to get new players into EQ.</p>

<p>I cannot begin to understand why anyone would think this is a good idea. Perhaps a boxed version of this expansion, or a new compilation pack including The Serpent's Spine, is due for release during the Christmas season. Perhaps SOE's marketing department knows secrets we can't possibly understand. Perhaps, and pardon me if I slip into paranoia, SOE is purposefully reining back Everquest to improve the sales of Everquest 2. As it appears now, the attempt to draw in new players with the Serpent's Spine seems cut off at the knees.</p>

<p>This is unfortunate since every other attribute of this expansion seems strong. A new player race, new level 1 to 75 content, the new level increase, and a focus on large open zones and numerous quests could all build an excellent new expansion.</p>

<p>SOE should reconsider their plan to release The Serpent's Spine as a download-only expansion and release a full retail package. With a retail package, the Serpent's Spine would be the strongest new way to get Everquest in the hands of new players.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
16 July 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Breaking News: Serpent&apos;s Spine Announced</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001485.html" />
    <modified>2006-08-25T04:44:46Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-07-10T22:48:12-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1485</id>
    <created>2006-07-11T03:48:12Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Tonight Sony Online Entertainment released new information on Everquest&apos;s twelfth expansion, the Serpent&apos;s Spine. Read on for our initial preview.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The Everquest website recently posted some initial information on the Serpent's Spine, the twelfth Everquest expantion. </p>

<p>View the <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/">official Everquest homepage</a> for this intial information or the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/72157594195122138/">Mobhunter capture</a> of the information.</p>

<p>The new race, a draconic race known as the Drakkin, was one big surprise. Most of the other information we heard at the last Everquest Fan Faire including a level increase to level 75 and content that will take a new player from level 1 to 75.</p>

<p>Recapping some of the information we gleaned from exhausted and inebriated designers at the last Fan Faire we know that the expansion will be mostly static content with a larger set of base zones and fewer instances. We will also see a new starting city called Crescent Reach.</p>

<p>No date has yet been given for the release.</p>

<p>While initial details are sketchy, I expect we will hear more over the next few days.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
10 July 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The New Hotzones of Everquest</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001483.html" />
    <modified>2006-08-25T04:44:46Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-07-01T11:46:04-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1483</id>
    <created>2006-07-01T16:46:04Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">In today&apos;s article, Loral discusses the recent chances to the hotzone mechanic including global rare drops, &quot;call for help&quot; NPCs, and new named creatures in all of the latest batch of hotzones.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>For the past few years, SOE used hotzones as a way to bring players together and help newer players experience older zones and encounters. This technique increased the experience reward of each hotzone to help entice players into traveling to these underused zones. However, SOE had sometimes gone as long as a year before hotzones had been updated. </p>

<p>In the last Everquest patch, SOE refreshed the concept of hotzones by adding new creatures and new loot to these hotzones as well. Last week I had the opportunity to talk to the designer of these new hotzone techniques, Nodyin, and the following article is based on these discussions.</p>

<p>Traditional hotzones were limited in a few different ways. First, since experience is a global reward, the only way to make a hotzone more enticing than an existing zone is to make the experience higher than the other. For example, in order to make a hotzone more popular than Paludal Caverns, a zone known to have a high experience reward per hour, the designers must increase the experience in an equal difficulty zone higher than Paludal. Sometimes, given that these zones offer a higher reward than the designers prefer, the designers are apprehensive about increasing the reward too much.</p>

<p>Other factors also affect the use of hotzones. If the zone is significantly more difficult to reach - Tower of Frozen Shadows at level 30 for example - players will still avoid it.</p>

<p>The new techniques included in the latest batch of hotzones entice players not only with experience, but loot. Loot, being unique items unavailable in other zones, can help bring players to new hotzones even if the experience reward per hour isn't as high.</p>

<p>Nodyin included two techniques for rewarding new items: global drops and named drops.</p>

<p>Named drops are the same drops we typcially expect. Every so often a unique NPC shows up. When killed, this NPC drops a new fancy item.</p>

<p>Global drops are items that can drop off of any mob in a zone or region. They are far more rare and higher in power than typical named drops. This type of drop will keep players interested in slaying the normal "trash" mobs of a zone on the chance that one of these mobs drops a global rare.</p>

<p>A new technique called "Call for Help" adds another twist. Regular mobs have a chance to "call for help" when their health gets low. A new named NPC will assist the original NPC against the party, forcing the party to handle two critters instead of just one. This named assisting NPC drops loot as often as typical named NPCs.</p>

<p>This mechanic, like the strange NPC behavior in Arcstone, adds a new flavor to typical fights players are used to seeing. Any mechanic that forces players to adapt to a changing battlefield helps keep players interested - as long as the mechanic is not simply frustrating.</p>

<p>Since experience is a global commodity, loot is the main driving force that takes players from one zone to another - especially at the high levels. The new itemization of older zones can help push players to these new zones instead of simply finding the most profitable experience reward available.</p>

<p>However, since level matters more than any other factor up until about level 65, players are still likely to "grind levels" more than worry about equipment until they reach the higher levels where gear is required for progression.</p>

<p>Right now, these techniques only affect zones from level 60 and below. Since recent expansions have all offered a lot of content at level 60 and above, there seems little need to revitalize zones for this level range. Hopefully, SOE should continue to use these interesting techniques in future.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
1 July 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Moss Snake Kicks You for 4 ^H^H^H^H^H</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001480.html" />
    <modified>2006-08-25T04:44:46Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-06-13T22:37:30-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1480</id>
    <created>2006-06-14T03:37:30Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we look at the most recent patch of Everquest, pontificate more on the Combine server, and mourn the loss of Everquest&apos;s greatest bug.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Much of the Everquest community's attention still lies on the Progression Server, now named "The Combine". SOE currently plans to release this server at the end of June. A lot of players are returning to the long forgotten lands of Norrath to remember the first days adventurers walked the lands. Whether or not they stay is a question yet answered.</p>

<p>Today brings the release of the largest patch since the release of Prophecy of Ro. While it contained few of the much needed content changes to Prophecy of Ro, it did contain a plethora of feature fixes.</p>

<p>Two improvements in particular may seem mundane to experienced players but do much to make Everquest a more accessible game for new players.  Players can now see group members on the in-game map, helping them locate their fellows when they get lost. I can't even fathom the amount of time I would earn back if this feature had been implemented six years ago. The next feature is the inclusion of the Guild Lobby into the core game. The ability for players to summon their body regardless of whether they purchased Dragons of Norrath is a huge improvement for lower and mid-level players who have neither the tools nor the experience to find corpses lost in the less forgiving pits of the older worlds. </p>

<p>These two improvements help bring Everquest closer to the industry standards for massive online role playing games. While many may shout, stamp their feet, and wave their fists saying that it is just the further "dumbing down" of Everquest - we will see how long they play on the Combine server suffering through eight hour corpse runs in Fear or sixteen-zone runs to get back their bronze armor. Long behind me are the days of horrifying corpse recovery - recovery that directly adversely affected my real life - and good riddance.</p>

<p>This patch also included the implementation of a new chat service back-end. While advertised as "transparent to the user", the service did have a few bugs.  Using a semicolon to send a cross-server tell no longer works and chatting in channels from EQIM also no longer works. No doubt this change helped SOE consolidate resources, but it would have been nice to ensure a truly transparent shift before implementation.</p>

<p>SOE modified experience gain for evolving items, intelligent items, and shrouds. In all three cases, experience gain has improved and now follows the same modifiers that regular experience follows when grouping. As players join others in groups, each player earns a higher percentage of experience than they would alone. Now experience earned by items and when transformed through shrouds includes the same bonuses.</p>

<p>Along with this change, SOE increased the amount of required experience for the single most popular evolving item, the cloak of the spirit tracker. This increase in total experience gain means that players who may have been 40% into the item's progression are now down to 10%. This change may be off-set by the overall increase in item experience, but again, only time will tell if the balance was met.</p>

<p>Today, SOE released one of the long awaited changes to the Everquest death system. Along with the full release of the guild lobby to all players, players will now begin losing experience and leaving equipped corpses starting at level 6. A corpse summoner in the tutorial will teach players how to recover their body using the summoners. While this doesn't meet the ideal circumstance of returning to a bind point fully equipped on death, it does help show players how to handle the death system in Everquest when they might be used to the systems in newer games.</p>

<p>This patch also released a new and much improved Nektulos forest. The previous version of Nektulos, released with the release of Depths of Darkhollow, often received complaints that it broke the realism of a forest. Instead of individual trees, that version had large single-sided objects painted with the texture of trees. This gave it the feel of a movie-set instead of a forest. The new Nektulos matches much of the layout of the original Nektulos but with a much improved look.</p>

<p>In the greatest retroactive nerf to the original Everquest legacy, no longer will moss-snakes kick. All animals not able to actually kick can no longer do so. While this change makes sense, it seems to be an extreme change to a piece of long lasting Everquest mythology. The elusive kicking moss snake will be forever missed.</p>

<p>Times are quiet in the lands of Norrath. The high-end raiders seek the beasts at the end of Deathknell and the treasures they hold. Others look to the history captured in the Combine. For those of us in between, we stare across the voids left in Ro's Prophecy and think to the days of adventure long past and far into the future.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
13 June 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Dangers of Progression, The Serpent&apos;s Spine, SOE&apos;s Vanguard</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001478.html" />
    <modified>2006-08-25T04:44:46Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-05-16T21:46:34-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1478</id>
    <created>2006-05-17T02:46:34Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week Loral takes a look at the news surrounding the Progression server, the rumored name of the next expansion, and SOE&apos;s co-publication of Vanguard.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The Antonican bards lean against their trees, leather bags empty. Little news from the lands of Norrath crosses the desks of the fifty gnomish editors of Mobhunter, so we focus this article on what little news we hear.</p>

<h2>The Progression Server</h2>

<p>Many players paid much attention to the Progression server, coming in June. SOE sent out a press release containing previously reported details and announcing a release in June 2006. The server will be named "The Combine".</p>

<p>I worry that both players and Everquest developers place too much anticipation on the progression server. We still do not know how popular the server will be when players realize the tedium involved in things such as travel and corpse recovery. While many players complained about the Knowledge stones and feel the corpse altar removed the thrill of danger in EQ, we do not know if these same players will actually play instead of talk about it on the forums.</p>

<p>I for one still remember the tedium involved with long-term travel. I remember how awful corpse recovery was from failed Vox raids. I remember camping to chat and buffing each member of a raid at a time. I remember dying in some unknown area at a low level and having no idea how I would recover my equipment. I don't want to return to those days.</p>

<p>I wrote an article for Caster's Realm late last year called "<a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001450.html">Why a Classic Server is a Bad Idea</a>" and I feel that many of the points are still valid.</p>

<p>SOE has spent six years coming out with improvements to Everquest. While not every improvement has been positive, many of those that were will be locked on the progressive server. All of those positive features, all of those improvements, will not be available for some time.</p>

<p>Time will tell whether the progression server is popular or not. I will keep a keen eye on it and, for the effort spent developing it, I hope it succeeds in its goal to draw more players back to EQ.</p>

<h2>The Serpent's Spine</h2>

<p>Rumors on the EQ Live forums and some investigative work by those with far too much time on their hands, has revealed the likely title for the next expansion: The Serpent's Spine. No other new information has been revealed except that SOE designers stated that while level 80 is not entirely out of the question, it is much more likely to increase the level range to 75. Given the difficulty in creating new items, disciplines, spells, and AAs at each level, and the great amount of new content discussed in the new expansion, we are very likely to see the cap at level 75, not higher.</p>

<h2>Vanguard co-published by Sony Online Entertainment</h2>

<p>In surprising news and resulting in a great gnashing of many sets of cynical teeth, SOE and Sigil Games Online announced that the two companies would co-produce Brad McQuaid's Vanguard: Saga of Heroes massive online role playing game.</p>

<p>While this stirred up great controversy, the outcome is likely not nearly as exciting.</p>

<p>Since Everquest, Sony Online Entertainment has acted as a sort of service provider for other massive online games. By consolidating resources such as technical support centers, data centers, backup and recovery, network connectivity, and in-game support, SOE can support a wider range of games much cheaper than any single company could on its own. We saw this recently with Matrix Online, added to SOE's extensive collection of MMOs including Everquest Online Adventures, Everquest 2, and Planetside.</p>

<p>Moving Vanguard to SOE makes sense if any game hopes to have any longevity. By running many games off of the same resources, SOE can afford to keep games alive much longer than a company producing only a single game. Expect to see more massive online games falling to one or two MMO service provider companies.</p>

<p>None of this speaks to any change in the direction of Vanguard or Everquest. The development teams are still separate and exclusive in their focus and direction.</p>

<p>Such ends the news for this period of slow news. Our spies will keep their ears open for any vibrations in Mobhunter's great web of information and pass along any such vibrations to you, our dear readers.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
16 May 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Five Recommended Improvements to Prophecy of Ro</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001477.html" />
    <modified>2006-08-25T04:44:46Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-04-30T18:10:26-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1477</id>
    <created>2006-04-30T23:10:26Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral Ciriclight looks at five ways to improve the latest Everquest expansion, Prophecy of Ro.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The release of Prophecy of Ro is now three months past. Many players focus their attention on the soon-to-come Progression Server. However, while many look to these two interesting glimpses into the future, the Prophecy of Ro lays unfulfilled. </p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro requires improvement. While some areas of this expansion have proved very popular such as Arcstone, the Spirit quests, the relic quests, and the Thurgadin monster missions; these features alone do not justify the cost of the expansion. This article outlines five areas for improvement in Prophecy of Ro.</p>

<p>1. Increase Spirit Mark drops.</p>

<p>The spirit marks, currently dropping only off of named mobs in Arcstone, help non-raiders increase their equipment to reach higher-end content such as the Depths of Darkhollow spell progression missions and the Omens of War Muramite Proving ground trials. Unfortunately, these marks only drop in Arcstone and drop rarely off of rare spawning named beasts. While it would be easy to increase the drop rate, instead SOE should add these drops to named creatures in Elddar, Relic, and Devastation to help bring players to these underused zones.</p>

<p>2. Improve Relic, Devastation, Elddar, and Stronghold of Rage.</p>

<p>Increasing loot rewards is only one factor in improving the usefulness of the Prophecy of Ro static zones. Currently only Arcstone sees a significant number of hunters. Devastation may see occasional groups for the saga skin mission, but with less frequency than Arcstone's spirit hunter missions. All four of these zones need to be improved to make them more huntable and more desirable. Increasing experience rewards, decreasing mob density, increasing random loot rewards, and decreasing mob damage output may help make these zones more desirable to those who purchased Prophecy of Ro.</p>

<p>3. Bridge the required-equipment gap between Dragons of Norrath and the Depths of Darkhollow and Muramite Proving Ground Trials.</p>

<p>There remains a constant wringing of hands and gnashing of teeth when it comes to discussions about the Creator mission in Dragons of Norrath. What these discussions often omit is that players spend a lot of time in content of this style. Creator offers nice rewards for a low investment of time. Rather than complain that creator is too easy, consider that many players want clear, consistent rewards for their time.</p>

<p>4. Scale more content to the level of difficulty and time investment of Creator. </p>

<p>Offer rewards that help single-group-equipped characters improve to the point where they can reasonably face the challenges of high-end spell-progression missions in Depths of Darkhollow, the Skylance missions in Prophecy of Ro, and the Muramite Proving Ground trials in Omens of War. Help bridge the required equipment gap between lower-powered Arcstone and Dragons of Norrath content and the higher-end single group content in Depths of Darkhollow and Prophecy of Ro.</p>

<p>5. Add more Spirit Hunter style missions.</p>

<p>Arcstone added five more "single-group raid" encounters to Everquest along with the Seeker event in Depths of Darkhollow. These events show single-group hunters the style of encounters that high-end raiders have seen for years. These events are fun, challenging, and rewarding. A great many players are able to face them, defeat them, and earn nice rewards for doing so.</p>

<p>Add more events of this nature to Prophecy of Ro. Add a series of legacy creatures to the new Desert of Ro including a Lich to the spectre tower, an ancient ancestor of Lockjaw, an ancient mummy lord, a sand giant lord, and the swashbuckler king of the waterboys. Add in a new quest to reward those willing to face these five new foes.</p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro has the potential to pull players out of instanced single-group content and back into large static zones. As it stands, however, Prophecy of Ro needs improvement in order to match the excellent content found in older expansions such as Depths of Darkhollow and Omens of War. With these five improvements discussed above, Prophecy of Ro could become one of the greatest of Everquest expansions.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
30 April 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>

</feed>