<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>* No personal attacks - Loral *</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>* No personal attacks - Loral *</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>And just to toss out a crazy thing like putting something into perspective.  Sims has been out 7+ ye</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>And just to toss out a crazy thing like putting something into perspective.  Sims has been out 7+ years now, 16 million copies, WOW has been out 2+ years now, 8 million copies.

Half the copies of Sims in 1/4 of the time. I still stand my my statement, WOW is the most successful game ever.  In 7+ years anyone betting against WOW having sold over 16 million copies is betting on a fool.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>* Removed since the original post was removed - Loral *</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>* Removed since the original post was removed - Loral *</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>* No personal attacks - Loral *</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>* No personal attacks - Loral *</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>* Removed since the original attack was removed - Loral *</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>* Removed since the original attack was removed - Loral *</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I didn&apos;t know I logged onto the WoW class discussion forums...</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I didn&apos;t know I logged onto the WoW class discussion forums...</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>* Removed the personal attack - Loral *


</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>* Removed the personal attack - Loral *


</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Someone has to market Everquest, SOE certainly does not, Nolrog is just about the only one.  I bet S</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Someone has to market Everquest, SOE certainly does not, Nolrog is just about the only one.  I bet SOE could save a bundle if they would just fire the PR staff, hire Nolrog.  They would get better results for alot less money.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I will admit, (its part of the recovery process to admit your mistakes, lol) I was a HUGE VAK (bring</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I will admit, (its part of the recovery process to admit your mistakes, lol) I was a HUGE VAK (bringing back an old Moorgard-ism, Verant AssKisser).  But you know what, you can only &quot;beat the dog with a newspaper for so long until it rips your arm off and runs away for good&quot;.

These guys have totally lost touch with the people who made them who they are.  They forget that if it wasnt for us taking that &quot;newspaper beating&quot; for </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>More content for the high end.  No content for the small group.

Every night I log on, and if I don&</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>More content for the high end.  No content for the small group.

Every night I log on, and if I don&apos;t want to raid, there is NOTHING for me to do.  I&apos;m ready, I&apos;m eager, I&apos;m disappointed.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The question is, does this expansion have what it takes to bring old 55+ players back? What does it </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The question is, does this expansion have what it takes to bring old 55+ players back? What does it take to visit Katta Castrum? Can you just PoK there or is it easily reached IE: LoY or GoD cities or do you reach there after a certain progression in the expansion? Hell, is there even a significant amount of pickup players to &quot;casually&quot; level and gear this expansion? Can you wander in and get a group like you could for Karnor&apos;s or </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Most of the content is unlocked to begin with. One final single-group zone is unlocked after accompl</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Most of the content is unlocked to begin with. One final single-group zone is unlocked after accomplishing a set of missions and the raid zone is likewise unlocked with another set of missions.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>more catering to the ubers. the so-called abguish level group gear will infact require you to alread</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>more catering to the ubers. the so-called abguish level group gear will infact require you to already have anguish level gear to obtain so that will cut casual players out to start with.soon it will be ghost town and a flop just like tss was. same old eq dev horse crap just released on a new day.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>/yawn

Nothing in this expansion has zip, zeal or pizzazz enough to bring people back or new people </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>/yawn

Nothing in this expansion has zip, zeal or pizzazz enough to bring people back or new people in.  Couple this with the fact that it comes out next week, (WTF !?!) and I havent seen one single advertisement for it on the web, in print magazines or even an email in my box telling anyone about it.

You know the old rules of thumb, when you start to see a trailer for a movie come out only 2-3 weeks before the movies release, your looking at a </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I&apos;m curious about how the point rewards shift depending on popularity. Is that actually dynamic</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I&apos;m curious about how the point rewards shift depending on popularity. Is that actually dynamic? (As in an automatic response rather than a dev making the decision?) If so I&apos;m impressed. Call it a &quot;wisdom of crowds&quot; thing but I&apos;ve always thought the usage numbers of the various zones are a more accurate reading of their practical risk vs. reward levels than any ideas a dev might have about them.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>