<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/" />
<modified>2005-08-17T03:51:09Z</modified>
<tagline>Everquest news, editorials, and commentary.</tagline>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2</id>
<generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="3.01D">Movable Type</generator>
<copyright>Copyright (c) 2005, Loral</copyright>
<entry>
<title>News After the Fall of Gukta</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000070.html" />
<modified>2005-08-17T03:51:09Z</modified>
<issued>2005-08-15T13:02:12Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.70</id>
<created>2005-08-15T13:02:12Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today we have a short update on the latest happenings in our constantly changing world of Norrath including the fall of Gukta, more on the Boar, and some interesting articles and rumors on the internets.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>The war of Antonica seems to have ended and our green Froglok friends find themselves in a new tent-city in south Rathe Mountains.  This was a bit of a surprise conclusion to the war.  No one expected that SOE would change the troll city from back whence it came.  I personally expected part of Freeport to be blocked off for Ykesha and his new men.  No doubt these changes upset the Froggie allies as much as the Troll allies were angered to lose their city in the first place.</p>

<p>The Frog city has it's charm.  It reminds me of Kelethin only lower to the ground (thank Tunare).  One other interesting change, it appears that Frogloks can now start as necromancers, shadowknights, and rogues.  That adds a bit more flavor to the race and will hopefully help fill out the low level game with some newer twinks.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/dod/">Depths of Darkhollow homepage</a> has been built up with a pretty flash introduction, the Depths movie, a bunch of screenshots, and pre-order information.  Depths pre-orders have brought up some interesting debates.  For the first time in a while, the free gift for buying the retail makes it worth running through traffic to buy the box instead of clicking the "download now" button.  The Clockwork Boar, a unique mount with the same power as a 10,000 plat horse or Drogmar mount, comes included with the boxed retail version of Depths.  Those who either buy depths in the store or download it will receive a gargoyle monster shroud.</p>

<p>Many have asked why SOE would offer such a great incentive for a store-bought purchase when they are no doubt making a bigger profit on the download.  The answer is: boxes on shelves sell EQ.  We are horrified at how well advertisement works, but it works.  If SOE can keep EQ on the shelves with new expansions, SOE gains more customers.  Expansions keep Everquest alive and boxed sales help bring in new players.</p>

<p>For those of us who are happy either way, it won't be fun battling Tuesday night traffic to get to Best Buy and find out it hasn't hit the shelves yet.  All of my friends will be running around me as wolves nipping at my boots and hooting while I stand there as my old boring self.</p>

<p>Of course, it will be worth it for that one time when I am stuck with a broken down smoking clockwork boar, telling my friend "I think it slipped a rod".</p>

<p>My friend Gemdiver over at Caster's Realm released some <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/dod/">exclusive Depths of Darkhollow screenshots</a> including a couple I took (that first double-wolf shot is one of mine).  More and more people find the opportunity to join the Depths of Darkhollow beta.  Keep a keen eye on the forums for chances to join in if testing is your cup of tea (*ignores the jeers of "but we're all betatesters in EQ you pompous egotistical loudmouth cleric!"*).</p>

<p>Our friend Zorillius recently announced that the Test server community would evolve.  There are a few advantages to the test server such as double experience and full veteran rewards.  SOE is going to add shorter reset times on all AAs, easier flagging requirements, and different boss timers.  The most controversial change, however, comes from an ability for those on Test to invite players on the live servers to copy their main character over to test.</p>

<p>Test has always been an interesting community.  They suffer through a lot so that we can have a more stable game (*once again ignores the cynical jeers*) and they don't mind telling you about it.  They live through client bugs that keep them off game for days, encounters that are far from tuned, and all sorts of strange oddities.  They do, however, get to see some of the latest changes sometimes months before we do.</p>

<p>Test is a community, however, and they act much like any of the other servers.  To see hoards of copied players rushing in threatens the community they built.  It will be interesting to see how this plays out, but I expect that SOE needs more players of all levels to help test EQ and this will solve that need.</p>

<p>Thanks to longtime Mobhunter supporter, Redcloud, we have a couple of interesting MMO articles to read.  <a href="http://www.pointlesswasteoftime.com/games/wowworld.html">A World of Warcraft World</a> takes an interesting and amusing look at how MMOGs will shape our world.  I have a theory that 50 million players in the US will be playing some sort of massive online game, whether it be fantasy or football (or both), by 2012.  Massive Online Games have changed our world and changed our lives.  We like to say "it's just a game" but I have never played a game for five years straight that got me to write 3000 words a week in articles for three different sites.  It's just A game but it's also not just a game at the same time.</p>

<p>Next Generation posted a reprint of <a href="http://www.next-gen.biz/index.php?option=com_content&task=view&id=723&Itemid=2">The Laws of Online World Design</a> by yukalale playing SOE big-head thinker, Raph Koster.  These are some of my favorite couch-potato game designer rules that we should all keep in our head when we critique and ponder this favorite game world of ours.</p>

<p>It appears the <a href="http://www.macworld.co.uk/news/index.cfm?NewsID=12317&Page=1&pagePos=14">Macintosh version of Everquest</a> has risen from the dark depths.  SOE is now offering a free download for the Macintosh version of Everquest including the base game, Kunark, Velious, Luclin, and Planes of Power.  SOE has had trouble maintaining and supporting the Mac version of EQ in the past.  A while ago we discovered that SOE only had one developer for the mac version and that developer had left.  It will be interesting to see if this catches on, but they have a lot of work to do to catch up to the PC version.</p>

<p>Last week I wrote an update of an old article of mine, now titled <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9347">Why I Play Everquest 2005</a>.  Every six months to a year I like to step back and really ask myself why I play this game.  I think it is a valuable method to ensure that I continue to have fun and don't ever feel like I'm wasting my time.  It's a bit pompous and perhaps even too high-brow for me to follow all the time, but hopefully its an entertaining read.</p>

<p>Thus ends this week's news roundup.  Keep watching the forums for the latest happenings.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
15 August 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Riddles in the Depths</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000069.html" />
<modified>2005-08-01T02:07:10Z</modified>
<issued>2005-08-01T05:23:28Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.69</id>
<created>2005-08-01T05:23:28Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">In this week&apos;s news roundup we look at the progression of the War of Antonica and dig into some of the clues given at the most recent EQ Stratics Developer Chat.  Learn the secrets of the Clockwork Boar!</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>The war of Antonica rages on. While the elves stay close to home after the orcish attacks three weeks ago, Barbarian mercenaries and the Frogloks of Gukta battle against Ykesha's armies in the southern rathe mountains. Armies of barbarians marched from Halas to rathe Mountains where they battled Ykesha's forces from the south. Many adventurers were chewed to pieces in the upper and lower jaws of this huge battle. Some, however, found a trinket or two within the piles of corpses.</p>

<p>The quality of these items and the dubious methods by which they were acquired made people angry. Some worried that items of such a high quality reduced the value of the items rewarded in higher-end raid content. The random rewards and the short duration of this event, however, won't build any threat against consistent raiding with known loot.</p>

<p>Warlord Ykesha himself faced adventurers on the battlefield. When it became clear that he was not meant to be destroyed by mortal hands, these adventurers found other ways. They brought armies of Frogloks against him for hours until the sustained damage became even too great for the warlord. These adventurers sadly discovered that Ykesha's shield was little more useful than a cloth cap; less useful, in fact. Still, the look of such a shield is no doubt a prize in itself.</p>

<p>Now we see the trolls looking south to Gukta and <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/images/forum_images/community/Absor.JPG">prophets of doom</a> already call the city lost. Let us all pray for our little green friends.</p>

<p>I wrote two more Reports of the Wilds for a total of six including:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50016">Report 1: Descent of the Trolls, Ithiasor the Black</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50017">Report 2: Warlord Bortar</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50020">Report 3: Xon Quexill's Plot, The Creature of Innothule</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50021">Report 4: The War of Greater Faydark</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50022">Report 5: Warlord Ykesha</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50023">Report 6: The War of Antonica</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Last Thursday EQ Stratics hosted another excellent <a href="http://eq.stratics.com/DoD/dodhoc.php">Developer's Chat</a>. More often that we'd like, dev chats don't give us a lot of news that us nosy website writers can't dig up on our own. The dev team likes to stay tight lipped on future efforts until they are sure they will occur. When announced, these new efforts usually show up on the EQLive forums rather than in a developer chat.</p>

<p>However, in this week's chat we received a lot of juicy detail on Depths of Darkhollow. Lets take a look.</p>

<p>Many Anguish-level raiders complained that Dragons of Norrath offered few raids at their power. It appears that Depths will include a significant number of raids aimed at players who have already finished Anguish. </p>

<p>I feel it is important to understand that not all raiders are of nearly the same power. Often raiders refer to themselves, other raiders, and raid targets as though they were all right around their same power. I have heard Qvic+ raiders state that true raiding doesn't begin until Qvic. I've heard Time raiders say that raiding means Time and above. Much like there are players of all levels, there are also raiders of all levels. Four Anguish level guilds may seem like a lot for a server, but there are hundreds of guilds on every server and dozens below Anguish who also want newer content.</p>

<p>However, when a guild defeats Anguish, there is nothing else out there to challenge them. Everyone below this power still has something ahead of them to defeat. That is probably the best reason why it is important that Depths include targets post Anguish to keep Anguish raiders happy.</p>

<p>This chat gave us a few more details about the "Play as a Monster" feature or as I like to call it - the Monster Mash. As we have heard, this feature is actually split into two parts: Spirit Shrouds, and Monster Missions. The Monster Missions will allow a group to switch into the bodies of monsters in order to complete a mission. Some of these missions will be flashbacks into the history of Everquest. </p>

<p>We learned from this chat that the monster missions will not have restrictions on the levels of the players who want to join them. This means that a group with a level 20, 34, 36, 54, 60, and 70 characters can all group together and go on a mission. Loot will be distributed based on your level. This is a huge improvement in the social features of this game. Now players can group with their friends regardless of class or level for these missions.</p>

<p>During Sprit Shrouding, a player can switch to a monster with a pre-defined class template of their level or below. During their time in a spirit shroud, players will earn items and experience as normal which will switch back to their main character. Spirit shrouding adds a whole new variable to the existing game. I can't wait to do the new Crushbone missions with a level 18 werewolf.</p>

<p>There will be normal missions in Depths of Darkhollow as well. The rewards for these missions will not be a point-based loot system. With Dragons, players focused on the missions that offered the best point rewards for the least effort, such as Creator or Gimblax. Depths missions will offer rewards to those seeking a variety of progressive missions instead of the those completing the same mission over and over. It isn't yet clear exactly how this will work or whether it will compete well against a point-based loot system for pickup groups.</p>

<p>New "Intelligent Items" will have many different abilities and will earn experience as characters do. Intelligent items can be acquired through regular hunting, raiding, or tradeskilling. They will have many personalities including cowardly, heroic, persuasive, or mocking.</p>

<p>If you purchase the retail version of Depths of Darkhollow you will receive a free Clockwork Boar mount. This may be the best retail purchase in-game reward yet. Over the years I have continually missed out on the retail rewards because retailers cannot keep up with my desire to play the expansion the minute it goes live. It looks like this year I may have to wait a day if I want that crazy clockwork boar!</p>

<p>It was a great dev chat and I look forward to the next one. In the meantime, let us look to our froggy friends to the south and wish them well.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
1 August 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Rising of the Trolls</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000068.html" />
<modified>2005-08-15T19:30:15Z</modified>
<issued>2005-07-16T15:52:45Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.68</id>
<created>2005-07-16T15:52:45Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we offer up a news roundup of the latest happenings in Norrath including the most recent patch, a couple of news articles of note, and the most recent War of Norrath.  Enjoy!</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>War rages across Norrath once again.  With the memories of the battles of Firiona Vie not so far behind us, we once again find a game-wide event unfolding over the month of July.</p>

<p>Adventurers found themselves sent to battle dragons in Kunark or cutting down a new troll warlord named Warlord Bortar.  A new two-group events has players defending strange high elves performing a ritual in Innothule.  Dark elves march on the Eastern Commonlands.  Neriak spies lurk in the shadows.</p>

<p>Then war found Greater Faydark.  For three nights the elven armies and orcish hordes gathered in the woods.  War Suppliers asked for armor and weapons.  No one knows for sure how the turn-ins effected the war but some believe they increased the forces on one side or the other.  Four or five sets of thirty or so elves faced an equal amount of orcish forces.</p>

<p>The serverwide.war channel fluttered like CNN.  Reports came in of orcish attacks.  Victors revealed powerful weapons dropped by slain Elvish commanders.  On Quellious, a force of over one hundred adventures faced off against an untargetable orcish general named Warlord Mish.  Unfortunately the battle did not find us yet and wouldn't until a day later when the orcs finally marched on the elves.</p>

<p>The war wasn't without problems.  Elven generals initially dropped far better loot than the orcish generals. Many opportunistic players switched sides and killed the generals who carried the shiniest items.  Elven enchanters often charmed or tashed orcs, causing players to quickly become the targets of vengeful elves when they accidently attacked the wrong orc.  Many of these problems were fixed but not until well into the war.  On Quellious, however, the elves were eventually successful in their defense against the orcs.</p>

<p>This battle was just the beginning, however.  The plots continue throughout the month and a new troll warlord far more powerful than Warlord Bortar begins to build his army in Lavastorm, Nektulos, and the Foreign Quarter.  Keep an eye out.</p>

<p>Over the past two weeks and probably continuing throughout July, I have written some in-character reports of these battles including the following:</p>

<p><a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001382.html">Report 1: Descent of the Trolls, Ithiasor the Black</a></p>

<p><a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001383.html">Report 2: Warlord Bortar</a></p>

<p><a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001384.html">Report 3: Xon Quexill's Plot, The Creature of Innothule</a></p>

<p><a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001385.html">Report 4: The War of Greater Faydark</a></p>

<p>Any such reports are almost always written after the event, however.  The best way to participate in the war is to watch the EQLive forums for new topics on the war and to join the serverwide.war channel by typing "/join serverwide.war".  That channel helps people share information about the war as it happens.</p>

<p>This past week SOE also released a <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=165#M165">minor patch</a>.  This patch mainly fixed a few outstanding bugs with the previous patch and added a few smaller features.</p>

<p>One feature of the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000067.html">patch that changed Everquest</a> that I did not talk about is the new option to autoconsent your group, guild, and raid to drag your corpse.  Like the game-wide invites, this is a smaller feature that has a huge impact.  Many many times entire raids have been destroyed because players can't drag corpses of their friends until that friend zones and consents.  This new feature makes groups and raids far more mobile even when faced with the death of a comrade.  Just grab the bleeding corpse by the belt, heave it over one shoulder, and head for the hills!</p>

<p>Of course, like the NewPlayers channel, General channel, and game-wide<br />
invites, these tools are only useful if people choose to use them.  Many players apparently don't read the patch messages very carefully.  One has to go to the Options menu (alt O) and select the autoconcent group, guild, and raid buttons.</p>

<p>There were a couple of interesting articles that had popped up last week including an IEEE Spectrum article called "Engineering Everquest" and another on "Virtual Sweatshops" in the Guardian.</p>

<p>The IEEE Spectrum article, <a href="http://www.spectrum.ieee.org/WEBONLY/publicfeature/jul05/0705eq.html">Engineering Everquest</a>, spent far more time talking about the game of Everquest than it did talking about the technology.  Considering the heavy competition in the Massive Online Gaming field, companies like SOE probably want to hold their system architectures close rather than give away all of their best secrets in a technical journal.  The article talks about the "Death Star" (I bet every gaming company has a server vault called the Death Star), a server farm containing over 500 servers in a 1500 server army spread across three buildings.  The article also talks a little bit about a recent software architecture change called "Just-in-time computing" that dynamically shifts system resources to the areas that need it the most.  It isn't clear from the article but I believe this is how instances work.</p>

<p>The Guardian article <a href="http://observer.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,6903,1436411,00.html">Virtual Sweatshops</a> talks about the third-world shops that hire people to play EQ, EQ2, and World of Warcraft to earn in-game resources sold out-of-game.  They take a detailed look at a fellow in Romania who works for ten hours a day in a backroom of a run down apartment where eleven employees keep accounts running for 24 hours straight.</p>

<p>The article does a good job of shattering its own title.  Compared to the child labor sweatshops where ten year olds work in heavy labor unsafe jobs for barely enough money to eat, these "virtual sweatshops" don't even compare.  Even the author admits that some people working at these outfits come in and play on their time off.  I doubt any ten year old kid went in on his time off to make more Nike shoes.</p>

<p>The article doesn't spend much time to show that this business is illegitimate and I suppose that is a small point when you talk about the larger topic of out-of-game sales of virtual property.  However, from within Everquest, such businesses harm the economy of the game.  It devalues virtual property when it is tied to an out-of-game economy.  If taken to the extreme, it would one day be so cheap to buy platinum that<br />
most anyone would choose to save time and just pay for it.</p>

<p>Whenever I read an article like this one I am reminded of an excellent short story by <a href="http://craphound.com/bio.php">Cory Doctorow</a> called <a href="http://www.mikeshea.net/articles/001292.html">Anda's Game</a> about a young girl who becomes a hitman in-game against competing virtual sweatshops.  It's a great read.</p>

<p>Thus ends this week's news roundup.  Keep an eye on the shadows and watch out for the rising of ancient powers.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
17 July 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Patch that Changed Everquest</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000067.html" />
<modified>2005-07-30T18:29:48Z</modified>
<issued>2005-07-04T15:35:44Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.67</id>
<created>2005-07-04T15:35:44Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week SOE released a patch that forever changed the face of Everquest.  While some of the features may seem subtle to some and even annoying to others, when one digs into what these changes mean, one sees a much more usable game and a tighter community.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>People tend to spend a great deal of time paying attention to very small things.  Last week's article on the Equipment Gap received 130 comments in six days.  We spend much time concerning ourselves with class balance, Time instancing, equipment statistic issues, and uber versus casual debates.</p>

<p>None of that is important.</p>

<p>What is most important in Everquest is meeting people and having fun.  The damage per second on wizard blasts makes little difference.  Adding another 50 hitpoints to a level 70 breastplate makes little difference.</p>

<p><a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=96330&view=by_date_ascending&page=1">This week's patch</a> added three major changes that helps bring in new players and ties the social community of Everquest closer together.  These include the new tutorial, the new level 10 to 20 quests, cross-zone group invites, and the autojoined chat channels.</p>

<p>Players now have a wide variety of tools to help find other players for groups.  Now you can use the LFG tool to find players looking for groups and ask in the General chat if anyone is interested.  If they are, you can immediately invite them into your group regardless of what they are. Group members can coordinate much easier when everyone is in a group instead of a barrage of tells.  The cross-zone invite is a great convenience as well as a tool for helping build social bonds between group members faster.</p>

<p>The new chat channels also create entire new social circles.  No doubt, due to the age of the game and the typical resistance to change, many people will immediately leave the public channels and stay with the channels they know best.  Many will stay, however, and hopefully some of the cynics will return to them.  These channels act as an excellent communication pathway.  The General chat cuts across all players, whether level 25 or level 70, whether a once-a-week player or a hard core raider.</p>

<p>Smart players will use this channel to find groups or build pickup raids.  Supportive players will use it to help people learn more about the game and teach them about their classes.</p>

<p>If you are a player who wants to help teach new players how to play Everquest, add "NewPlayers" to your autojoin list ("/autojoin NewPlayers").  This lets you join that channel regardless of your level.  New players are automatically added to this channel so you can easily find new players to help.  Using other players as a resource is the only way most players can cut through much of the complexity in this game.  Use of the General and NewPlayers channels help solve this very well.</p>

<p>If you're one of the cynics who found the channels invasive and distracting, consider at least joining the General channel and saying hello.</p>

<p>Over the past couple of days I have taken my new warrior through the newly released Everquest Tutorial, Mines of Gloomingdeep.  This tutorial will soon become the core of the "Escape to Norrath" free demo, but it is available to all new players now.</p>

<p>The new tutorial is a lot of fun.  While the popup windows on the initial lessons can be a bit distracting, especially for older players who learned six years ago how to "hail" someone, the rest of the tutorial is a blast.  The lessons are now done as quests in the quest journal, helping EQ compete with the quest journals of EQ2 and World of Warcraft.  </p>

<p>There are about fifteen quests including three group quests.  Along the way you can collect a new set of armor specific to the tutorial with statistics similar to the original newbie quest armor.  There are three boss encounters; the spider queen, the Kobold Overlord, and the demon in the pits.  I particularly enjoyed the pit demon mission.  The Kobolds in their digging dug too deep and released a great horror.  Only you and your heroic friends can stop it.</p>

<p>The new tutorial helps give direction to new players.  Both times I hunted there I saw over forty other players hunting as well.  Groups formed quickly and met challenges.  There was some twinking but powerleveling isn't really possible.  </p>

<p>The tutorial looks great.  The Mines of Gloomingdeep uses a unique zone, newer graphic models from Dragons of Norrath and even a new unique kobold model.  The graphics are very good with light reflections and excellent detail.  In my battle with the pit demon I marveled at how good EQ can look after six years.</p>

<p>If you haven't tried out the new tutorial, spend a few minutes rolling up a level 1 and go through it.  It is a lot of fun.</p>

<p>This patch also included a bunch of new level 10 to 20 quests from the Plane of Knowledge.  When a new player leaves Gloomingdeep they are now sent to the Plane of Knowledge, the central hub of Everquest, and given a set of new exploratory quests to help them get around.  While it detracts from the cultural bonding that we once knew starting out in our home cities, the low population of those cities made it harder for players to meet one another.  It is a difficult change but one for the better.</p>

<p>There were many other changes in this patch but my hand grows weary.  I will leave you with today's Mobhunter Exclusive:</p>

<p>Mobhunter Exclusive: Blood Boils Among the Trolls</p>

<p>As a reporter in the world of Norrath it is important for me to keep my fingers on all of the strands of information that cross our waters and travel over our mountains.  It is sometimes important for me to deal with unsavory and questionable people in order to learn everything I must know.  One of these unsavory characters, a young troll spy, sent me a scribbled note through the Antonican Bards and it is the contents of this troll spy's note I will report to you here.</p>

<p>It appears the trolls within Neriak begin to plot.  They speak of violence.  They speak of war.  They speak of a warlord named Bortar who will deliver them from Neriak and send them back against the Frogloks of Gukta.  These notes come at great cost; it took eight scholars and five engineers to teach the troll how to write with a quill.  Here are some of their whispers:</p>

<p># Luruk Dridor says 'Me hear talk  Trolls angry about being stuck here long time  Me wonder what happen next'<br />
# Grigdor says 'Me hear dat Daboo do most talking, dat Daboo almost kill Elf cause Elf try to tell him what to do'<br />
# Luruk Dridor says 'Me hear dat too  Me tink dat Daboo be lucky he stay calm  He kill Elf den we all end up in fight'<br />
# Grigdor says 'Me hear Draboo [sic] say stupid tings at bar too  Tings dat Elfs can hear and not like'<br />
# Luruk Dridor says 'What tings?'<br />
# Grigdor says 'Daboo say dat Elfs not let Bortar lead Trolls to kill Frogs  He blame Elfs for not giving Trolls enough room in stupid city'<br />
# Luruk Dridor says 'Me tink dat someting Daboo say  Sound like Daboo  Daboo not too smart'<br />
# Daboo Dogak says 'SHUT UP!  Me right here you know!'<br />
 <br />
# Gardunk says 'You hear Ranjor?  He loosing mind'<br />
# Kaglari says 'He just tired of Elf city and still mad about losing home'<br />
# Gardunk says 'He not only one  If Bortar not come back soon, Clan Grobb fight Dark Elves  Me not sure Clan Grobb win'<br />
# Kaglari says 'Grobb win if work together  Lots of Trolls here not want fight here, want fight for Grobb, kill dem frogs'<br />
# Gardunk says 'True dat  Kaglari have much control over Clan Grobb hearts  Kalgari talk to clan, calm down Ranjor'<br />
# Kaglari says 'Ranjor not listen anymore, me try  Me tink Hukulk more likely fight  He talk quiet, but his heart angry  Angriest in clan'<br />
# Gardunk says 'Me angry too  Me want fight  But me want home back, not take Elf home  Ugly place, Elf home'<br />
# Kaglari says 'Might not be able to stop fight, might only choose where clan fight  Me try to keep all quiet until Bortar come back'<br />
# Gardunk says 'Me hope you can'<br />
 <br />
# Zignal Luk says 'Me had enuf  Dis not Troll home!  Troll not belong in stupid Elf home!'<br />
# Wista says 'Me no mind  Make good money here'<br />
# Ootok says 'You not want home back?  You not want kill frogs!  You stupid as Ogre!'<br />
# Wista says 'Me want kill stupid frogs, but me like glowy things in elf city'<br />
# Zignal Luk says 'No matter what Wista like  We no wait more  Bortar lazy slob, no act  We take action soon, no matter what Bortar say anymore'<br />
# Ootok says 'Zignal right  Trolls wait too long for revenge'<br />
# Wista says 'Zignal maybe right, but Zignal talk too much  Elf no like talk of revenge, make too many trolls angry'<br />
# Zignal Luk says 'Me duty to remember Troll past, make Troll culture  If me shut up, nobody remember'<br />
# Wista says 'Zignal shut up before inkies hear'<br />
# Zignal Luk says 'Me be quiet, but me not be quiet long'<br />
 <br />
# Ranjor says 'Me tink it not a good idea'<br />
# Hukulk says 'Me tink you not real Troll  Me tink you coward'<br />
# Ranjor says 'I tink me gonna kill you now!'<br />
# Glubtak says 'Dey at it again  Stupid Trolls, fight each other not enemy'<br />
# Ranjor says 'You shut stupid mouth!  You not know nothing!'<br />
# Hukulk says 'She right  Me kill you not help Grobb Clan, so me not fight'<br />
# Ranjor says 'You coward!'<br />
# Hukulk says 'No, me smart  You not control self, you fool'<br />
# Glubtak says 'You both shut up  You know Bortar tell Trolls not fight Trolls  Me Bortar's friend, me not want to tell him you fight'<br />
# Ranjor says 'Me tired of talk!  All time talk!  Me want do something!'<br />
# Hukulk says 'You get chance soon enuf, Ranjor'<br />
 <br />
# Slunga says 'Hey, Capee, you kill anyone today?'<br />
# Capee says 'No  Me no find anyone to kill  But me hurt some Elf real good'<br />
# Slunga says 'Ha!  Dat good!  Me tired of dem Elfs  Wish me had time to smash some'<br />
# Capee says 'You no have customers, ever  You got time'<br />
# Slunga says 'Stupid Capee  Even if no customers, not allowed to leave  Boss make me stay'<br />
# Capee says 'Well, me hear dat some Trolls tinking of taking Elf city for selves  Me like dat plan'<br />
# Slunga says 'Dat sound good to Slunga'<br />
# Svunsa says 'You two shut up  Me not pay you to make trouble or talk stupid'</p>

<p>Changes are on the horizon.  Keep watch.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
4 July 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Equipment Gap</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000066.html" />
<modified>2005-07-13T15:11:41Z</modified>
<issued>2005-06-25T17:24:18Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.66</id>
<created>2005-06-25T17:24:18Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Things have gotten a bit too cozy on Mobhunter recently.  Today we take a look at that most popular of topics, high-end equipment balance.  Let the fun begin.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>"Remember how Kunark came out and suddenly players and items were just so much more powerful than in the original game? Remember when Velious came out and it seemed at first that items were only increasing in effectiveness by a small margin? Well, throw the curve out the window, students, because there is not just a gap between good items and awesome items, there's a freaking canyon."</p>

<p>- Moorgard, 29 June 2001, Mobhunter</p>

<p>Over the past few weeks we have talked about the fan faire, the new expansion, and some of the new directions SOE has taken Everquest.  This week I thought we would take a step back and talk about a topic in Everquest that has been around since the days of Kunark: Equipment balance.</p>

<p>No doubt this article will ruffle a few feathers.  My intent, however, is not to focus on one particular style of play but instead to look at the details of this topic that often get lost.  If all you see is "Loral wants better gear for the casual gamer again" then you're probably not reading hard enough.</p>

<p>There comes a point at the highest levels of the game when equipment can double the power between two equally leveled players.  This generally only happens at the highest levels, right now between levels 65 and 70.</p>

<p>Consider these two pieces of equipment:</p>

<p>Faithbringer's Breastplate of Conviction:  AC: +125 Str: +30 Dex: +25 Sta: +30 Cha: +25 Agi: +25 Fire Resist: +30 Cold Resist: +30 Magic Resist: +30 Poison Resist: +35 HP: +315 Mana: +355, Mana Regeneration: +5,  Regeneration: +10, Avoidance: +10, Shielding: +5%, Spell Shield: +6%, Effect: Blessed Healing Aura: Increase Healing by 50%, Focus Effect: Keldovan's Light: Decrease Spell Mana Cost by 25%, Required Level: 70</p>

<p>Plate Vest of the First Order: AC: +72 Dex: +12 Sta: +12 Wis: +12 Int: +12 Agi: +12 Fire Resist: +13 Disease Resist: +13 Cold Resist: +13 Poison Resist: +13 HP: +125 Mana: +120 End: +120, Required Level: 70</p>

<p>I want you to pay particular attention to the last part of these two lines: "Required Level: 70".  These items are designed for the same level character.  Yet the power of the first item is well over twice the power of the second especially when one considers the focus effects, regen, mana regen, avoidance, and shielding.</p>

<p>No doubt the difficulty in acquiring these items is vastly different.  One can be purchased from the Dragons of Norrath vendor after completing somewhere between 7 and 12 missions.  The other requires drops from the Arch Magus or Overlord Mata Muram in Anguish.</p>

<p>Obviously, these items don't compare in either power or in the difficulty to receive it.  However, there are some areas where these items must be compared.</p>

<p>Encounters are based on levels, not equipment.  At level 70, the same creatures are dark blue to you regardless of your equipment.  The same mobs give the same experience regardless of your gear.  Yet, based on the power of your equipment, an encounter could be either impossible or trivial depending on what type of equipment you use.</p>

<p>At level 70, level no longer accurately describes how powerful you are.  Yet systems in the game continue to use level as a way to determine encounter difficulty.  Lost Dungeon adventures and Dragons of Norrath missions scale their content based on level, not equipment.  The Omens of War Task system and the quests given to you in Dragons of Norrath are based on level, not gear.  Some of these are trivial to well-equipped players and impossible for the rest.</p>

<p>Even those with the best equipment expect growth yet they cannot get it from single-group hunts.  Not everyone raids all the time.  There comes a time when even high-end raiders want to get together in a group of six and fight an appropriate challenge.  At the highest end, even the most powerful single-group areas offer little reward for high-end raiders.  High-end raiders cannot increase their equipment power in single-group events.  This leads them towards a "raid or nothing" attitude.  Why bother hunting anywhere if there is no reward for doing so?</p>

<p>One single-group hunting zone or mission cannot challenge both single-group equipped players and high-end raid equipped players.  No challenge will be acceptable to both groups.  I hear it often.  Riftseekers is too easy for raid-equipped players and too hard for single-group equipped players.  The only players who seem to find the perfect challenge in this high-end zone are those who happen to be equipped with Time or Elemental gear of roughly 150 hps and mana each.</p>

<p>The power gap will come back as a hot topic when Depths of Darkhollow brings us monster templates based on level.  If these templates are built around single-group equipment, raiders will find them extremely low powered for the level.  If they are built around raid-level equipment, they will be more powerful than many players' main characters.  The only answer is to base them on single-group equipment and accept that raiders will find them extremely low powered.</p>

<p>How can SOE begin to close the equipment gap?  There are few, if any, easy answers.  It isn't just a matter of offering better equipment for single-group encounters.  Doing so devalues the reward of higher-end raid encounters.  </p>

<p>It is not unreasonable to expect that the absolute best single-group equipment available should meet 75% of the absolute best raid-level equipment.  If a cleric breastplate from Overlord Mata Muram includes a 50% healing focus and 355 mana, a breastplate from the hardest single-group encounter might offer 250 mana and a 35% healing focus.</p>

<p>Even with gear 75% of high-end raid gear there isn't anything to say that difficult single-group zones will still be impossible for non-raiders.  In places like Riftseekers that extra 25% power makes the difference between success and failure.</p>

<p>A more difficult solution would be to add some sort of "legendary" status to items.  Items with this status could have different statistics when used during a raid than they do when used during single-group events.  This lets equipment balance out during single-group events but meet the proper requirements during raid events.</p>

<p>Another solution, also radical, would be to add in a Dungeons and Dragons style "power level".  Equipment and levels could combine into a single power rating that determines the difficulty of an encounter.  However, after playing 3rd edition D&D for a year now, the power level in D&D isn't very accurate and doesn't help much when matched to challenges.  There is nothing to say that a power level in EQ would be any more accurate, but perhaps it would help.</p>

<p>Every new expansion increases the power for both raiders and non-raiders.  With the recent addition of slot 9 augments to Dragons of Norrath gear, single-group players now have customizable armor comparable to Elemental and Time level armor.  More of Norrath becomes accessible to more players with every increase in power.</p>

<p>However, it is clear that Everquest becomes very gear dependent at the highest levels of the game.  It has been this way for the last four or five years and I see few ways to fix this problem without radically changing the game.  As it has been since the days of the Ring War, the topic of equipment power will always continue to be a hot one.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
26 June 2005<br />
Loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Depths of Darkhollow  Preview</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000065.html" />
<modified>2005-07-13T15:11:41Z</modified>
<issued>2005-06-11T08:32:32Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.65</id>
<created>2005-06-11T08:32:32Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">We have a sneak preview of the Depths of Darkhollow expansion.  See how this expansion may tackle mentoring, class archetype issues, and unused content in a feature that may be the coolest feature ever added to EQ since Project M.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>I just returned from the preview of Depths of Darkhollow, the tenth Everquest expansion.  It is with cramped hand and full bladder that I bring you latest details on this exciting expansion.  The expansion has three major aspects; play as a monster, intelligent items, and the traditional expansion zones and missions.  SOE will release Depths of Darkhollow on 13 September 2005.  Let's dig right in.</p>

<h2>Play as a Monster</h2>

<p>The most exciting feature of Depths of Darkhollow lets players select monsters as play characters.  Anyone who remembers Project M remembers how much fun it was to jump into the body of a moss snake and pwn newbs.  The Play as a Monster features improves on this idea in many directions.</p>

<p>There are two ways to play as a monster: within missions and using a system called the Spirit Shroud.</p>

<p>Using the Spirit Shroud, players can select lower level beasts to hunt with lower level friends in old-world zones.  This meets a long-standing problem where friends of mixed levels could not hunt together.  Though high level players may pick lower level monsters, the experience gained will improve both their primary play character and their selected beast.  The creatures a player can polymorph into are limited by the infamous global memory file; a large file containing all of the player models, armor, weapons, pets, and other common world-wide models.</p>

<p>The second method of playing as a monster lets players jump into missions as any monster within the dark minds of the SOE designers and artists.  Players can jump into a variety of missions with a variety of different monster PC models.  We heard whispers of a lower guk mission with the PC playing the Froglok assassin or Froglok Shin Lord fighting the hoards of beasts from Cazic Thule’s armies.</p>

<p>These missions offer unlimited potential for historical EQ battles fought from the other side.  Players might play as Nagafen and eat raids full of NPCs who wish to slay the great red beast. Using spirit shrouds, players of high-end guilds can switch to a pack of level 50 beasts and hunt Lord Nagafen once again.</p>

<p>This feature alone fixes many outstanding difficulties in massive online games.  It lets players play with lower-level friends.  It helps players hunt even if they are missing a required class archetype.  It helps revitalize old-world content by making any zone lower than a player huntable once again.</p>

<p>Since missions, this is the most exciting feature I have ever seen added to EQ.</p>

<h2>Zones and Graphics</h2>

<p>The expansion itself will include seven large static zones and fifteen instanced missions.  This number doesn't include a large raid-level instance of the final zones, Darkspire, intended to offer a large amount of content for current high-end raiders who quickly run out of existing raid content.  This high-end zone will offer uninstanced single-group hunting as well as single-group and raid missions.</p>

<p>From the screenshots we see large dark forests inhabited by ghost-white werewolves (perhaps that's your friend Bob!  Hey Bob!).  We see huge bottomless caverns full of criss-crossing walkways between giant stalactites.  We see the giant cathedral of the Darkspire.  We see the twisted cities of the Illithid-Liches (Nanyea says they're called "Alhoon").  The first shot of the large forest is called "Nektulos".  Could a zone revamp of our favorite dark forest be in our future?  Further rumors say "yes" and you heard it here first - we will see a revamp of Nektulos Forest!</p>

<p>The zones look beautiful and it sounds like they'll have a lot of content for a lot of players.</p>

<p>The monsters themselves, both PCs and NPCs look excellent including werewolves, the liches mentioned above, eels, big mushrooms, minotaurs, gnomish lockwork rogues, orcs, and drachnids.</p>

<h2>Intelligent Items</h2>

<p>The final feature discussed during our preview of Depths of Darkhollow were Intelligent items, also referred to as "Evolving Items" and "Smart Items".  Did you ever read the R.A Salvatore Legacy of the Drow books?  Remember Dantag Banere’s intelligent demonic sword, Khazid'hea?  Imagine that in EQ.  Swords will insult their slain masters and desire the expert hand of another.  These weapons earn experience as though they were characters, growing in power as their master (or servant?) wields them.  The possibilities are endless.</p>

<p>During the last three days, Craig Knapp, Everquest producer describes his visions of Everquest growing in depth instead of breadth.  His philosophy seems to be both metaphor and literal at the same time.  Depths of Darkhollow looks to take Everquest into whole new directions.  Most importantly, the features of Depths of Darkhollow clearly define Everquest as a continued force in a fiercely competitive world.</p>

<p>Now go check out the <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/442275/">Depths of Darkhollow screenshots</a>.<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Notes from the West</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000064.html" />
<modified>2005-07-13T15:11:41Z</modified>
<issued>2005-06-10T18:47:35Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.64</id>
<created>2005-06-10T18:47:35Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Loral finds a few moments to post some notes from the Community Summit and the Las Vegas Fan Faire.  Read on for some exciting up-to-the-minute news and comments including information on the new expansion: Depths of Darkhollow!</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>I find myself with a moment to set quill to parchment and give you, dear reader, a glimpse at the treasures of the West.  This is not the sort of treasure you may be used to, glittering gems, jewels, or plates of gold (I lost 20 bucks at the slots in about twelve seconds).  I offer a far more valuable treasure: the golden vaults of knowledge.</p>

<p>Ok, enough metaphor.  This article will act as a working set of notes as this year's Fan Faire in Las Vegas, June 2005, continues on.  Keep an eye on this page for the latest notes and links to the articles and pictures of others.</p>

<p>Let us begin:</p>

<p>11:00 am, Friday 10 June:</p>

<p>The next expansion is called Depths of Darkhollow.  It appears to be an underdark-ish expansion but details will be thicker during the official announcement on Saturday.  The devs seem very excited about it and give the impression that they plan to take it in a new direction.  One unattributed quote: "No other MMORPG has done this yet".  We'll know more tomorrow.  Oh yeah, John Smedley, CEO for SOE, does a mean Axel Rose impression.</p>

<p>The new tutorial was also a big topic.  SOE plans to release the tutorial, a level 1 to 10 instanced zone with a variety of quests and missions, will be released in a single stand-alone format, both on CD and download.  New players can sign up for a station account and play the tutorial on a special server known as "escape".  New players can play up to level 10 without having to put in a credit card.  The tutorial has all new artwork, mostly from DON but some unique models such as the Kobolds.  This lets player get a good taste of EQ without having to commit anything more than download time.  </p>

<p>This whole package will be known as "Escape to Norrath".</p>

<p>Gemdiver, the manager for Caster's Realm, has an excellent <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=8993">article on the EQ Community Summit</a> including some great labeled pictures of the devs.</p>

<p>Kytheria from EQLive posted some <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=140">excellent pictures</a> from the Summit.  If you look really closely you can see the top of my head.</p>

<p>At the present I can hear lord Brenlo mocking the players of the PvP tournament.  The winner of the level 50 tournament walks away with a 42" plasma TV so I imagine the competition is fierce.  Periodic release of lions into the arena helps keep people honest.</p>

<p>I have had many conversations with the EQLive developers including a couple of conversations with Craig Knapp, the Everquest producer.  Craig has an excellent wide view of the game.  He knows, as do the EQLive developers, what is important and what is not.  Fun and community are paramount.  Craig's enthusiasm for the "Escape to Norrath" trial and Rytan's work on the tutorial and the level 10 to 20 quests show their commitment to bring new players to EQ.  </p>

<p>All of the developers seem quite excited about the announcement of the new expansion.  No doubt, releasing the first information about an expansion like this to a live audience can be nervewracking.</p>

<p>1pm Thursday, 10 June</p>

<p>I posted some <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/438212/">Las Vegas Fan Faire pictures</a>.  I will be posting more of these throughout the day as well.</p>

<p>2pm Thursday, 10 June</p>

<p>Rumors and whispers about the new expansion run wild.</p>

<p>There was a lot of discussion about cheating and hacking and general customer support issues - a topic that gives me an ice-cream headache.  The programmers are building tools and techniques to trap a lot of the typical cheats.  A lot of the summit reps felt that better reporting on the numbers of cheaters caught and banned would help scare away cheaters and help the rest of us see that things are getting done.</p>

<p>SOE mentioned that they were seeing a fair amount of people returning to EQ after some adventures out in EQ2 and WoW.</p>

<p>I have a couple more details on the "Escape to Norrath" package.  Craig Knapp mentioned that the CD for the next expansion will include the 400 meg Escape to Norrath demo so that players can give the discs away.  Any deals for distributing Escape to Norrath on CDs in magazines or hand-outs at retail chains are still under discussion.  It wouldn't surprise me at all to see EtN passed out frequently on CDs.  </p>

<p>SOE wants to make it as easy as possible for new players to get a hold of the demo, install it, and get playing without difficulty or invasive requests for credit cards.  The trial also has an unlimited duration.  This isn't a 10 day or 15 day trial.  Players don't have to worry about installing it only when they have the most free time, players are free to play at their leisure before any commitment.</p>

<p>This is something that frustrated me with my purchase of WoW.  When I first bought Warcraft I found it interesting (frustrating) that I had to enter a credit card number before I was even able to patch or play a single day.  Aside from nice box-art I had no guarentee that I would like WoW at all (I ended up liking it a lot, but thats not the point).  A limited trial of some sort helps me see what I am paying for, especially when I have already paid $50 for the retail box.</p>

<p>I have had excellent responses to both <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000063.html">Loral's Evil Agenda, Las Vegas Edition</a> and <a href="http://eq2.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=8957">Loral's Evil EQ2 Agenda</a>.  It sounds like a few of these ideas have already been kicked around the SOE offices with positive responses.  Some of them, like the Plane of Knowledge issues, are very contested even within the dev team.  That is something we don't often realize.  Many of the arguments we have about uber vs casual or class issues or models or the focus on knowledge all happen in the halls of SOE before we ever learn enough to debate them ourselves.  The end result are decisions often built from the debates of many people, not just one person's single decision (even Smed).</p>

<p>Oops, another thing on Escape to Norrath.  If you log into Test, you will see the new server-based newbie chat channels.  The Escape server will be no different but nice folks, such as yours truly, are able to join that chat channel and help folks out from our live servers with a typical /join escape.newbie or whatever the channel happens to be named.</p>

<p>I suggested some sort of big-brother big-sister program and other folks chimed in by recommending that some system where helping newbies awards leadership experience.</p>

<p>Oops, <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/18564638/in/set-438212/">sai Maddoc</a> just sat down to me.  I must be in trouble...</p>

<p>2:36pm, Thursday, 10 June</p>

<p>Yes, Character Models...</p>

<p>The short answer: We won't be seeing character models any time soon.  SOE, all of those individual folks I mentioned above, are all interested in adding new character models.  They articulated the complexity a little bit (I get frustrated with players who micro-manage SOE so I try to avoid such statistics).  Each Luclin model, including new animations such as multiple weapon strikes, take up over one hundred individual animations per model with 32 models.  Each piece of different armor requires its own animations.  The total number continues to grow and grow.  The final number, 8.5 man years just for models alone, still doesn't include everything it would take to add new models.  I know nothing about character animation but the devs seem to shake their head when they talk about how the Luclin models were done.  Here's another interesting statistic: it takes the same amount of work to rebuild one new player race and sex that it takes to add in all of the new models in Dragons of Norrath - including the dragons.</p>

<p>When I brought up the new EQ2 models - a set of asian-friendly models soon to be released - I heard that there was no silver bullet for those models, it took a lot of time and it was part of the deal between SOE and the company hosting the asian servers to make it more friendly to that environment.  Here's a funny bit.  Moorgard stated that the asian audience demands mouse-movement and one-handed gameplay so they never have to put down their cigarettes.  That cracked me up.</p>

<p>SOE doesn't seem to hold the same worry that I hold.  They aren't concerned that a new set of models would not be well received.  After the mixed reviews I hear about Luclin models, WoW models, EQ2 models, and the new asian EQ2 models, everyone has a different opinion and paying 8.5 man years for models that may receive similar criticisms doesn't seem like a real good investment to me.</p>

<p>So we will have to see.  New character models are a topic SOE hears a lot.  By their words it is something they really want to fix.  New character models are not off of SOE's master to-do list but it isn't something we will see any time soon.</p>

<p>4:17pm Thursday, 10 June</p>

<p>I just got back from the "EQ: Progression of Power" discussions.  A lot of individual class issues were discussed with a general theme that life is really hard in Anguish and people seem do die a lot - go figure.</p>

<p>Here's a micro-list of topics and answers:</p>

<p>Blind, it's the human crash bug that even R.A Salvatore mentioned in the intro to Rogue's Hour.  The EQ team wants to fix it but its not a priority.</p>

<p>Endurance regen:  The devs built the current endurance regen based on no regen components.  They don't intend to have any endurace regen items or spells.  However, they recognize that downtime in general is a problem and hope to come up with a solution.</p>

<p>Ranger discs:  A ranger wondered why he hasn't received a disc since Kunark.  Since rangers have hybrid spells, the discs for melees are meant to make up for that.  There's no intention to add more ranger discs.</p>

<p>Cleric CH isn't enough anymore:  A cleric was concerned that existing heals aren't powerful enough for existing mobs.  The devs disagree.  It's hard for a reason.</p>

<p>Cleric Melee:  I didn't get the answer to this one but Saroc, the cleric represenative, asked what the intention is for clerics soloing.</p>

<p>PoP backflagging:  There are a lot of bugs with backflagging including holes in the quests and no way to track it.  Why don't they just open up everything up to Time?</p>

<p>Cleric Plate Class issues:  Clerics are a plate class but get eaten a lot.  The dev team recognizes the extreme gap between tanks and non-tanks.  Tanks can survive but non-tanks are completely destroyed.  There is no intent to let any other class really tank but they do see the gap growing.</p>

<p>Warrior's epic 1.5 and 2.0 clicky has too long a casting time when getting hit and no channeling skill means it will always be interrupted.  SOE will look at the problem but instant cast items "are bad".</p>

<p>Cleric invis:  SOE is looking for a way to stack invis potions and make improved invis potions easier to acquire.</p>

<p>Ranger bows:  Why is the epic not a bow?  Bow DPS is meant to trail behind melee dps because ranged attacks are safer than melee attacks with repostes, rampages, and AEs.  SOE didn't want to gimp the epic 1.5 or 2.0.</p>

<p>Will Pally DPS vs undead get increased?  There's a lot of weird issues with situational DPS.  In general, Paladins aren't designed to out DPS other DPS classes even against undead.  Rytan will look at the numbers vs undead, however.</p>

<p>Regeneration on raid wipes take too long.  Downtime is a big issue in general and SOE wants to address it.  However, you did die...</p>

<p>Loot all:  SOE wants to do this and it's just a matter of finding a time.</p>

<p>Stuns as they are on Lucy are not accurate.  SOE feels that the existing stuns, 5.2 seconds on NPCs, 10 seconds on PCs, is appropriate.</p>

<p>Delay death isn't enough.  A player feels that delay death isn't enough of a boost.  Frankly, an extra 250 hps feels like a lot for me.</p>

<p>Warriors with lightning reflex.  I don't remember what this was.</p>

<p>Shaman Craigs, the Shaman CH:  No complete heal will be further touched.  Rytan feels they go outside the intent of the game.  While heal improvements will occur, they will not occur with any of the three CHs.</p>

<p>I was just informed that Curt Shilling, EQ fan and major league baseball player, arrived.</p>

<p>6:47pm Thursday, 10 June</p>

<p>I added over twenty new pictures to <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/438212/">Loral's Las Vegas Fan Faire photos</a>.</p>

<p>12:42am Friday 11 June 2005</p>

<p>We saw a preview for Depths of Darkhollow last night.  I have an article all written up and ready to go tomorrow afternoon.</p>

<p>However, I can say that SOE may have found a way to solve the problem of level 20 friends and level 70 friends grouping together, the character archetype problem for groups and raids, and the unused content problem in one swoop.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow lets you pick a monster and fight alongside your friends.  More details tomorrow but it looks very very cool.</p>

<p>Time for bed.</p>

<p>7:42pm 11 June 2005</p>

<p>It's been a crazy few days and I am bound to pay for it on Monday morning.  I just posted a full <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000065.html">Depths of Darkhollow</a> preview on both Caster's Realm and Mobhunter (there are very slight differences but mostly the same).  Everyone is really excited about it and the rumors run rampant.</p>

<p>I have a few other juicy tidbits as well.  It appears we will see a full geometric and graphical revamp of both Nektulos forest and the Plane of Knowledge!  Many times throughout the weekend, Craig Knapp has asked players what features would bring players together in one spot to find groups.  He suggested Minigames.  I suggested short-duration stackable buffs with regen and mana regen from a single unique NPC - just some bonus hp and mana for starting groups in this place.  Any other suggestions are welcome so post them here if you have a good idea.</p>

<p>There are only a couple of events left this evening.  I don't know how long I am going to last at the beach party tonight or how much more juicy information I might get as the night wears on and the alcohol runs free.</p>

<h1>Mobhunter Exclusive: Slap in the face!</h1>

<p>Though received positivly, not everyone understands the great wisdom of the Evil Agenda.  See Kytherea's iron gauntlet treatment of the concern of the casual!</p>

<p><img src="http://images.crgaming.com/9003.jpg" /></p>

<p>I'll have at least one more update before I travel home tomorrow.  In the mean time, check out the <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/442275/">Depths of Darkhollow screenshots</a>.</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda - Las Vegas, Summer 2005</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000063.html" />
<modified>2005-06-22T17:57:54Z</modified>
<issued>2005-06-01T16:28:04Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.63</id>
<created>2005-06-01T16:28:04Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Next week Loral travels west to the shining lands of pyramds and pirate ships armed with the following Evil Agenda.  Read on to see what areas SOE should focus on to continue to improve Everquest.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Next week I travel west to the Las Vegas Fan Faire and to the second Everquest Summit.  Once again I will bring my recommendations to help improve Everquest.  Many of the items discussed in previous Evil Agendas have been addressed by SOE and it is my hope that these issues will be addressed as well.</p>

<h2>Help Players Find Groups</h2>

<p>This is by far the number one issue in Everquest today.  SOE developers should do anything they can to help players find groups, build groups, and get groups off and hunting as fast as possible.  Players below 60 have much greater trouble finding groups than those above 60.  SOE should always look for ways to increase the pool of players looking for groups at all levels.  Here are some specific suggestions to help improve grouping:</p>

<p>- Allow group invites across zones and from within the "Looking for Group" tool.<br />
- Continue to focus on mission-based content.  Missions are the best thing to happen to Everquest.<br />
- Add missions for groups of three or four players instead of six.<br />
- Add an in-game group scheduling tool to help players find groups during certain play times.<br />
- Add better rewards to single-group encounters so raiders and non-raiders group together more often.<br />
- Do not rely on soloing to solve the grouping problem.</p>

<p>SOE may also consider more radical approaches for players to group such as allowing searching for players in other zones, allowing players to automatically join a group, and allowing for cross-server groups for instanced zones.</p>

<p>Beyond any other issue, SOE should continue focus on helping players find groups, build groups, and have fun.</p>

<h2>Add More Interesting Monsters</h2>

<p>Dragons of Norrath gave us some of the best game mechanics in a massive online game but the beasts left much to be desired.  In Dragons we met level 72 goblin kings unarmed and wearing loincloths, level 68 pumas that hit harder than Cazic Thule, and spiders - lots and lots of spiders.</p>

<p>I have watched gods die.  I have killed vampire lords with my bare hands.  I fought in the Ringwar of Thurgadin.  I have traveled to outer worlds and to the deepest pits of hell.  I shouldn't have to run from a puma.  I am a level 70 high priest; make me feel like it.  Add beasts worthy of my power and skill.  Examples include cyclopses, death knights, demons, devils, dire beasts, ettercaps, ettins, greater elementals, giants, golems, gorgons, hell hounds, hydras, liches, lycanthropes, medusa, manticores, mephits, minotaurs, mummy lords, nagas, ogre mages, rocs, spectres, titans, vampire lords, wights, wraths, and wyverns.</p>

<p>No more rats, bats, spiders, pumas, or loincloth goblins for level 70s.</p>

<p>Fun monsters are only one part of this topic, however.  The other part comes from varying the challenge of these encounters beyond hitpoints and melee damage output.  Fighting a lich and fighting a giant shouldn't be similar encounters.  Single-group monster challenges should have the same wide variety that raid encounters have.</p>

<h2>Add a Mentor System</h2>

<p>As Everquest gets older the average level of players gets higher.  As this average level increases, including methods so higher level and lower level players can hunt together, meet challenges, and receive rewards, becomes more important.  Add a method so lower level and higher level players can group together, face challenges, and receive rewards.  This will lead to a much larger possible player-base at any given level and allow friends who have different amounts of play time to continue to hunt together.  While level-based systems such as the Mentor system of Everquest 2 work well, it is not the only way to accomplish this.</p>

<h2>Rebuild the Plane of Knowledge</h2>

<p>More and more players, both old and new, use the Plane of Knowledge as their central gathering place.  Rebuild the Plane of Knowledge with new graphics, a new layout, new quests, and a new storyline.  Make the Plane of Knowledge the City of Adventure with a new government and new ties to existing content.  Build the city to prevent the video lag we receive in the current city.  While this is no doubt a monumental job, the heavy activity in Knowledge, now and in the future, warrants the update.</p>

<p>Massive online game competition is fierce this year.  Games begin to demand more and more of our time.  Everquest remains competitive with all of the newer games and expansions like Dragons of Norrath offer features unseen in existing MMOGs.  If EQ developers continue to improve grouping options, add new useful features, improve monsters, and update the core city, Everquest can continue to thrive for years to come.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
1 June 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The New Player Experience</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000061.html" />
<modified>2005-06-22T17:57:54Z</modified>
<issued>2005-05-29T14:33:13Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.61</id>
<created>2005-05-29T14:33:13Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we take an in-depth look at the new tutorial available on Test as the beginnings of the New Player Experience.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>How can SOE get more players playing Everquest?  This is a question we've asked since the release of Everquest 2 and World of Warcraft.  It's hard to bring new players to a six-year-old game when newer and shinier games appear right next to it.  This has been a question I've discussed often in these articles.</p>

<p>SOE has asked this same question many times as well.  Recent expansions have mostly focused on the game above level 50.  Newer features such as missions are given to players above 50 while those below 50 play the same sort of game we played six years ago.  While many small improvements were added to the level 1 to 10 game, they weren't cohesive and didn't compare to the newbie experience in newer games.</p>

<p>Last week on the Everquest Test server, SOE began testing an entirely new tutorial zone.  The original tutorial did a good job of showing new players the large array of strange Everquest commands and put them on a few quests but at level five or so, the game dumped the new player back in their old city and gave them little else.  I have heard new players speak their frustrations at that point.  No direction is given and no other players are in those towns.</p>

<p>The new tutorial extends the original by five more levels.  A player can hunt from level one to ten within this new and much larger zone.  New Kobold models were released and the zone uses new drake, spider, and goblin models from the Dragons of Norrath expansion.</p>

<p>Quests, about a dozen of them, use the mission window of Dragons of Norrath.  Quests have a wide variety of interesting jobs including blowing up Kobold mining operations and stealing the jailer's key.  There are even a set of group missions to defeat some of the larger boss mobs in the new zone such as the Kobold king, the spider queen, and some huge unnamed horror in the depths of the mines themselves.</p>

<p>The new tutorial is intended  to take players to level 10.  Players can leave the tutorial at any time and doing so drops them in the Plane of Knowledge.</p>

<p>Here is where controversy begins.  Many people want to continue the fight against Plane of Knowledge.  They think this city removes the soul of the original Everquest and removes their race identity that they had back when they hunted six years ago.  They're right, but there's more to it than race identity.  </p>

<p>Knowledge is often the most populated zone in Everquest.  If there is one place where a new player can really understand the difference between Everquest and Morrowind, it's in Plane of Knowledge.  The city has all of the practical features any city needs.  It has single-click access to sixteen newbie zones.  It is the one place where a new player can see how large the population of Norrath really is.  This also opens up the opportunity for SOE to rebuild Knowledge, a large job no doubt, into a new and shining city as technology and design understanding continue to grow.  Changing one city changes the city for every player.</p>

<p>After the tutorial players are directed to a new Plane of Knowledge Greeter.  The greeter gives a new set of quests to explore New Tanaan to find a banker, a spell vendor for their class, their local guildmaster, and a new NPC who begins sending players on a new set of armor quests.</p>

<p>At the time of this writing I was unable to start these armor quests (my little dwarven paladin was only level 7) but my understanding is that these new armor quests replace the original guildmaster armor quests using the new task window.  These quests should help lead a new player from levels 10 to 20.  At level 20, a new player should have a good view and understanding of the game and now has a path for even greater rewards.</p>

<p>These game updates are the first steps in a new push to bring new players to Everquest.  Only successful marketing can do the rest.  At the Fan Faire we will hear about a new expansion and then we may learn how SOE plans to market Everquest to a new and wider audience, an audience competed over by other massive online games such as Everquest 2 and World of Warcraft.</p>

<p>Now let's bust a common myth.  "There are no new players of Everquest.  Everyone's a twink."  I hear this a lot.  I also hear that the majority of EQ players are raiders and the majority of these raid MPG and above.  We always focus on the area we ourselves play.  There ARE new players, they just aren't hunting in Riftseeker's.  I spend a lot of time in lower level zones buffing and healing new players.  Many of them are indeed twinks, but quite a few are actually new players who either downloaded the trial or had a friend bring them in.  These new players are often pretty quiet and often hunt far away from other players, especially higher-level players.  No doubt there are less new players joining today than there was even a year ago, but they do exist and changes like these may bring in even more.</p>

<p>Will these tutorial changes and new quests indeed bring more players to Everquest?  That's hard to say.  There are a lot of variables unknown even to SOE.  In order to really grip a new player and drag them into a game as huge as Everquest, the newbie experience has to be smooth and clean.  The best newbie experience I have seen so far was World of Warcraft.  It focuses on a small town with very easy to accomplish quests.  I had little difficulty reaching level ten and I never got badly stuck.  As SOE continues to improve this level 1 to 20 segment of the game, it would do well to take lessons from WoW.  Much of what I see in the tutorial falls into this line.</p>

<p>Expect the new tutorial to be released to live servers after the Fan Faire but in the mean time, build yourself a level 1 test character and give it a try.  There are many good threads on this topic over at the Everquest forums and the developers are actively seeking input on these new tests.  New players help improve the game for everyone.  The more players that play Everquest, the better the game will be for all of us.</p>

<p>Next week expect a brand new Evil Agenda for my trip to the 2005 Everquest Summit and Vegas Fan Faire.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
29 May 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Return to Unrest</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000060.html" />
<modified>2005-05-27T19:16:48Z</modified>
<issued>2005-05-14T15:38:11Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.60</id>
<created>2005-05-14T15:38:11Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">There&apos;s a lot of big news this week.  Today we will take a look at the new old-world missions, the veteran rewards, the results of server mergers, the EQ Live price increase, and a few juicy rumors of things to come.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>It's been a big week.  We've seen one of the more exciting patches since the release of Dragons of Norrath and a few interesting bits of news and even a nice juicy rumor crossed my great oak desk this week so lets dig right in.</p>

<p>SOE released four new missions this week taking us back to some favorite old zones including Befallen, Unrest, Qeynos, and the newer but underused Hate's Fury.</p>

<p>I only had time to try the Unrest mission but I enjoyed it enough to do it twice last night.  The mission is excellent.  I'm not a fan of time travel stories; they're a bit overused in fantasy and science fiction, but to see Unrest just as evil overtakes it is quite a treat.  The mission's story is quite deep and interesting.  The mission mechanics take you through some of your favorite haunted spots in Unrest.  The mission can be finished in about an hour if you know what you're doing.</p>

<p>The mission only rewards a single random item upon completion including 100 hitpoint and mana items and a 65 hitpoint and mana augment for the uberfolk.  It does not reward any shards or LDON points.  There are some who would like to see all of these missions and adventures share a common currency but I think its fine to offer random rewards for some, crystals for another, and LDON points for a third.  It gives us reason to do them all instead of farming the easiest one.</p>

<p>These missions show a great way to improve old-world zones and give us a way to recapture fond days of hunting in these old-world dungeons.  They also focus a party on a single goal within these old zones.  We get a nice bit of story and a nice reward along the way as well.  I think this is the best way I've seen to revamp a zone.  I like these a lot more than the recent Mistmoore or Paw revamps.  </p>

<p>Missions in general are my favorite feature of Everquest.  It is the one feature that keeps me continually returning to Everquest after playing games like Everquest 2 and World of Warcraft.  They help focus a single group of players on a single goal; they help reward players for their effort; and they break up hunting sessions into nice manageable time periods.  I hope to see a lot more of these in the future.</p>

<p>The in-game email system got a lot of added features this week.  A new address book, an ability to send email guild-wide, new sound effects and text messages upon new mail arrival, and most importantly, an ability to forward in-game email to an out-of-game email address.  These changes make Everquest's email system the most robust email system of any MMOG.  All it lacks is an ability to send items along with an email.</p>

<p>This week we finally saw the release of the Veteran rewards.  Now Bristlebane Puppets turn all those people hanging around the front of the big bank in Knowledge into all sorts of stramge things.  Last night alone I used five of my seven veteran rewards and found every one of them useful.  The Bristlebane pet especially is quite a wacky experience.</p>

<p>Veteran rewards are a great way to bring people back in the game and reward those of us who have played since the beginning.  Some folks had problems receiving their rewards with a mixture of strange account time calculations including time unsubscribed and transferring characters from one account to another.  Some of these problems were fixed later that day.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, these great new features didn't come without cost.  This week John Smedley announced that in June the <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50010">Everquest subscription cost will go up</a> to $14.99 a month.  It's hard to understand a subscription cost increase like this for a game that's been out for six years now but the other changes this week give us a good idea of what we pay for.  For the next month we have the option to buy year-long subscriptions for $100, just over eight bucks a month and nearly half of what we would have to pay monthly.  This is the plan I chose myself.  </p>

<p>Even with the increased cost, Everquest continues to be a value compared to other forms of entertainment.  I just paid $15 to see "Kingdom of Heaven" and I wish I had my three hours back.  Even great games like God of War end up costing about $50 for eight to ten hours of entertainment.  Only the cost per hour of a paperback book runs lower than my Everquest subscription costs.</p>

<p>Time for a Mobhunter exclusive.  On June 9th at the Las Vegas Fan Faire, SOE will announce the new and latest Everquest expansion.  We already heard a few clues and rumors out of the last developer chat including words like "Werewolves" and "Drachinds", both words I like but not as much as "Vampires" and "Demons".  With their typical six-month schedule, I would prepare for an expansion release sometime in August.</p>

<p>This week, my home world of Quellious and the fine friends of Rodcet Nife merged together into a new world.  The merger went quite well, I didn't notice the change until I went into Knowledge and saw an extra one hundred people milling about.  The LFG list was thick with players to pick up for groups and my guild got in four or five new recruits within the first couple of days.  While I don't think server mergers are the perfect solution to problems like waning guild numbers or difficulty finding groups, I think they can help keep Everquest healthy and alive.  I'm enjoying the experience with my new friends of the Nife.</p>

<p>It's been an exciting week.  With the larger player-base on my server, the new veteran rewards, and the new excellent missions in old-world zones, we get to see a new side to Everquest.  Price increases might put a frown on our faces, but these new features help dullen the pain.  It's an exciting time to play.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
14 May 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Allure of Augments</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000059.html" />
<modified>2005-05-27T19:16:48Z</modified>
<issued>2005-05-02T14:58:21Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.59</id>
<created>2005-05-02T14:58:21Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today we discuss the most recent dev chat, a tiny peak at a brilliant article on disturbing trends, some interesting threads on the EQLive forums, and a few other odds and ends.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>The aftermath of the shocking news that SOE would open <a href="http://stationexchange.station.sony.com/">Station Exchange</a>, a service that will facilitate the sale of in-game items, characters, and money for out-of-game cash, came to an interesting conclusion.  An <a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive.vm?id=466&section=News&month=current">additional posting</a>, written a day after the <a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive.vm?section=News&id=457&month=current">original announcement</a>, stated:  "There will be no current live servers switched to the Station Exchange ruleset."</p>

<p>This makes a pretty big difference.  For the most part, Station Exchange will have little effect on most players.  The person next to you wielding that shining prismatic sword probably won't have bought it and if they did, it wasn't from SOE's Station Exchange.  If you don't want to buy or sell in-game resources or if you don't want to play with players that buy or sell in-game resources, you simply avoid those servers.</p>

<p>Station Exchange probably won't push out companies like IGE if they don't facilitate sales on existing servers.  Players have friends or characters on existing servers that they'd like to improve with some hard cash rather than in-game effort.  IGE will remain in business for a while and those same problems mentioned in Smedley's first letter will probably continue to exist.</p>

<p>It is very unlikely Station Exchange will migrate to EQ1.  Considering that SOE already began merging existing servers, it is unlikely they plan to stand up any new ones not to mention setting up a whole process and interface for the transfer of EQlive gear.  For now, I don't see a future for Station Exchange in EQLive and thats fine with me.  I am no longer concerned about Station Exchange.</p>

<p>A few days ago, the developers and producer of Everquest <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=109#M109">answered questions over on the EQ Stratics House of Commons chat</a>.</p>

<p>My favorite bit of information came early on in the chat.  Zajeer, the EQ itemizer, announced that Dragons of Norrath vendor items would include a new type 9 augment slot in addition to the existing type 7 slot.  The DON vendors will also carry type 9 augments priced at twice the cost of a base item at that level.  He doesn't mention the power of these augments but I imagine they will be lower in power than the existing type 7 augments.  It should be just enough to give DON gear a nice edge over previous LDON gear and other single-group drops.</p>

<p>A couple of articles ago, I mentioned that <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000057.html">high level single-groupers needed access to higher-power gear to progress through high level single-group content</a>.  Gemdiver wrote something very similar in his <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=8587">state of the game part 2</a> article on Caster's Realm.  This started a lengthy and heated thread on EQLive called <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=78190">Some feedback based on the latest Mobhunter post</a>.  It had a lot of interesting views on single-group equipment progression and I believe many of the concerns for both Gemdiver, myself, and others in that thread may be alleviated with these new DON augments.</p>

<p>I have two questions on the subject of these augments.  Can a DON equipped level 70 hunter with somewhere between 150 and 300 AAs expect to hunt and survive in the Muramite Proving Ground trials, Riftseekers, Ikkinz, and The Accursed Nest?  I think the answer to this is "yes" but I'd like to see actual proof.</p>

<p>Second, will the cost of these new augments push the total cost of a nice piece of DON gear so high that most people won't bother to acquire it?  SOE can always lower the cost if they see that no one is purchasing it but at a cost of roughly 1270 (340+250+680) for a single item (roughly forty missions worth of crystals), it doesn't seem likely that anyone will deck out every slot with nothing but DON gear.  However, it is realistic to expect that these new DON items and augments may help fill out the lower power slots of single-group hunters.  I'm planning on a new set of boots myself.</p>

<p>We'll have to see exactly what these augments are like and whether the cost is low enough to make them a practical upgrade when they come out in a couple of weeks.  This is an exciting improvement.</p>

<p>Zorillius mentioned that they are not looking at the EQ2-style adventure packs for EQLive.  While I liked the idea of D&D style modules for EQ, there's enough new content with each new expansion that I don't think they need to put out a few more zones.  Besides, I'm already spending enough on massive online games, I don't need another $10 a year for adventure packs.</p>

<p>Level 69 and 70 spells came up again recently, both in the dev chat and <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Necromancers&message.id=7297">over on the Forums</a>.  Rytan recently doubled the drop rate for 69 and 70 runes in both MPG and Riftseekers.  For all practical purposes, however, Riftseekers and the MPG trials is the only place to receive 69 and 70 runes with any reasonable chance.  With somewhere between eleven and twelve runes per spellcaster in the 69 and 70 range, I still don't think drops in one zone is a reasonable solution for such a huge amount of classes.  For some classes, these runes are required to operate against higher-level mobs, yet they are nearly impossible to receive except for camping named beasts in a single uninstanced zone.  Some other solution for 69 and 70 runes needs to be considered.</p>

<p>Last week I wrote an article for Caster's Realm called "<a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=8633">Disturbing Trends in Massive Online Games</a>" that mentions the recent trend on focusing on solo content as well as other instant-gratification changes such as out-of-game purchases.  This focuses on a problem I've had with Everquest 2, Worlds of Warcraft, and last week Guild Wars.  All three of these games seem to focus highly on solo-quests.</p>

<p>I've written a lot about solo content before.  I find solo content to be counterproductive to a massive online game.  I've received a lot of email over the last week.  Many players agree with me and give examples of how their playtime in solo-friendly games like Worlds of Warcraft and Everquest 2 are not as rich as the social connections they make in games like Everquest.  Those that argue for soloing usually bring up the LFG problem.  Currently, in most games, players spend too much time looking for a group.  Adding more solo content could make this problem worse.  The more players are able to progress alone, the less likely they are to group.</p>

<p>Rather than find new ways to let players solo, all of these game companies should use all of their skills and all of their powers to find easier and faster ways for players to group.  I've offered up a few suggestions such as game-wide invites, a mentor system, improved friends lists, and alt tracking, but I am sure there are many others I have not yet thought up.</p>

<p>With the Fan Faire and Summit coming up in about two months, I am beginning to ponder issues for my next "Evil Agenda".  The LFG problem will probably be number one on my list.</p>

<p>More than anything else, it is important that both game developers and players remember exactly why they play these games.  Gear, progression, zones, and levels aren't nearly as important or as lasting as the friendships we build.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
2 May 2005</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Breaking News: SOE to broker the selling of Items, Money, and Characters in EQ2</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000058.html" />
<modified>2005-05-27T19:16:48Z</modified>
<issued>2005-04-20T01:37:47Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.58</id>
<created>2005-04-20T01:37:47Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">We interrupt our weekly Mobhunter article for the most important update since our time here at Mobhunter (I love referring to myself in plural).  Tonight SOE announced that they will begin selling in-game money, items, and characters in Everquest 2 on selected servers.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>I thought my <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000057.html">last article</a> was a good one and I was hoping to let it sit and gather some good thoughts.  It had some of the best posts I've read in some time.  Tonight, however, John Smedley made an announcement that forced me to push that article down a notch and cover a new topic.</p>

<p>Tonight <a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive.vm?id=457&section=News&month=current">SOE announced that it will facilitate the selling of money, items, and characters on specially flagged Everquest 2 servers</a>.  This is perhaps the largest announcement of a feature or trend since I've started writing for Mobhunter.</p>

<p>The letter does not speak at all about doing something similar in Everquest and it is clear from the few folks I spoke to that they are only planning on considering this for EQ2 for the moment.  One wonders where it may lead if successful.</p>

<p>There are a thousand facets to this topic.  I can't begin to cover them all and hope to get this article out while the news is still hot so I will say this:</p>

<p>I think it's a mistake.</p>

<p>This is basically a trade between time and money.  I play Everquest 2 and progress because I want to see new places.  Now I, an employed yuppy with too much time on my hands, have justification to simply trade in a few bucks for the time it would take me to earn my progression.  It completely changes the investment in EQ2.  It also begins to show a disturbing trend towards quick fixes and direct response to player requests rather than considering the whole problem and where it can go.</p>

<p>It is important to understand that SOE is not creating these characters, money, or items but instead offering a safe transaction system so that players can sell among themselves.  I had a much stronger reaction until this point became clear.  It isn't like SOE is selling a level 30 any time they want, but I can buy a level 30 if someone is willing to sell it.  SOE will not be establishing the price. Still, this adds a level of authority and validation to a practice that so far had been considered sleazy.</p>

<p>Everyone knows how much I support SOE as they move forward in Everquest.  Lately, with the shift towards solo play and now this shift towards item, character, and money purchasing, I worry for the result to the social bonding of players in this game.</p>

<p>I don't play EQ for items or money or levels.  I play this game to meet other players and go on adventures.  I understand clearly the investment of spending time to earn levels to see new places and hunt in new lands.  Now that line becomes gray.  Should I spend my time leveling to 30 or should I just buy a level 30 and go read a giant George R.R. Martin tome instead?</p>

<p>There's a thousand facets to this subject and I have a feeling we're going to see a lot of them on the forums over the next week.  Before you place judgment, make sure to read the letter a few times and sit and think about the issue.  May Tunare watch over us.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
19 April 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>

<p>Here's a thread round up including quite a few posts by Smed and the other devs:</p>

<p><a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=pround&message.id=2674#M2674"> John Smedley Discusses Station Exchange</a><br />
<a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=stex&message.id=3#M3"> On the subject of Station Exchange</a><br />
<a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=stex&message.id=76&view=by_date_ascending&page=1"> Comments after reading the first round of posts</a><br />
<a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=stex&message.id=176#M176"> WTH?</a></p>

<p>Update:  This was posted last evening on a thread called <a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=stex&message.id=5022#M5022">Update: Existing Servers Will Not Be Converted to Station Exchange</a>:</p>

<p>To restate: Next week's polling will be used to determine how many new servers we need to start up at the service's launch. It will not be used to determine whether any existing servers should be converted. <strong>There will be no current live servers switched to the Station Exchange ruleset.</strong> (bolding from the original post, not added later)<br />
 <br />
Later, if the popularity of the service grows and it becomes apparent that we need more than the two planned servers, it will be because people have moved from other servers, which means those servers' populations will have gotten smaller. If that occurs, we may merge lower population servers together if any have gotten below the point of remaining a healthy community.</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Reign of Zorillius</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000057.html" />
<modified>2005-05-27T19:16:48Z</modified>
<issued>2005-04-18T15:02:35Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.57</id>
<created>2005-04-18T15:02:35Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week&apos;s article discusses the latest EQ Producer&apos;s, veteran rewards, Gemdiver&apos;s State of the Game Part 2 article, and an excellent post over on the EQ Live forums.  Enjoy!</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Things haven't slowed down in recent days.  This year alone we've seen the War of Dreadlands, the release of Dragons of Norrath, the sixth year anniversary events, and the first class re-envisioning.  It doesn't appear things will slow for some time.  Today we will take a look at a few pieces of news, a few articles, and speak a little about "fun".</p>

<p>It appears our friend Robert Pfister has moved off to new horizons and Craig Knapp, also known as Zorillius, has become the Producer of Everquest.  <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=107">Craig's first Producer's Letter</a> has a lot of interesting pieces of information.</p>

<p>SOE plans to instance the Plane of Time.  We spoke about this at the first <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000017.html">EQ Summit</a> nearly a year ago and it was on their larger to-do list.</p>

<p>Time is popular because it drops a large amount of powerful gear in a single raid.  It is a bottleneck not only for raiders but for just about everyone above level 65.  There is no other way to acquire gear of that power in that short amount of time.  Many argue that the work to reach Time is the cost of that reward but with the 85/15 rule in place, anyone can get into Time without any previous effort as long as they know the right people.</p>

<p>There is a lot of content tuned around Time level gear, not just raid content but single-group content.  Once you hit a certain stage in the game, Time becomes the only viable place to upgrade your equipment to the point that you can hunt in places like Riftseekers, the Muramite Proving Ground Trials, or the Nest.</p>

<p>Offering equivalent gear elsewhere is a better alternative to instancing Time.  I would rather see another revamp, perhaps a revamp of an instanced zone, that offers equivalent gear for a similar effort.  I would also like to see Time-level gear become available to single-group hunters at the same rate it is received by Time raiders.  We will discuss this more when we speak of Gemdiver's State of the Game article.</p>

<p>Based on long-standing raid rotations, the server merges have changed.  Karana will now merge with The Rathe and Bertox will merge with Tholuxe Paells.</p>

<p>Due to popular demand, the names of merging servers will come from a vote rather than simply based on population.  Depending on how they handle the vote, I would expect the results to be the same.  If the original choice of the server title was based on active population, say the number of unique players who logged in within a week, and now they replace that with a vote over a week period for all unique players, one would expect the results to be the same.  Anything can happen, however, and depending on what period of time the vote occurs, it could change the results.</p>

<p>Craig's letter also mentions plans to revamp the newbie experience and upgrade the look of some of the original EQ zones.  This is something I think is critical to bring in new players and keep Everquest competitive with newer massive online games.</p>

<p>The key to this success comes from proper marketing.  I outlined a few ideas in my "<a href="http://mobhunter.com/000028.html">Five Steps to One Million Subscribers</a>" article including offering the game on a free CD or DVD like AOL, and improving the initial user interface.  Proper marketing of Everquest and selling it alongside Everquest 2 and Worlds of Warcraft could help fill in a lot of empty seats since last November.</p>

<p>I am happy to see new content for new players.  The quest and mission system of Dragons of Norrath holds a lot of potential for all players of Everquest, not just the 50 to 70 crowd it currently targets.</p>

<p>SOE announced new <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50003">Veteran Rewards</a> last week.  These seven features, one for each year a subscriber has remained active, include some shockingly good abilities.  It appears that every player who has either played for a year or who will subscribe for a year to come will receive a 30 minute a day double experience bonus.  This is a direct benefit to just about all players who play regularly, though it really helps players who only play for short bits of time every day.</p>

<p>Other abilities include a 100% res and corpse summon; a full mana and hitpoint refresh; two crazy buffing pets; short duration resist, statistic, and run speed increases; and a boost to heals and blasts.  We will spend more time discussing each of the abilities once they go live in May.</p>

<p>My friend and debating partner (one might call him a master-debater *snicker*), Gemdiver,  wrote an excellent article called the "<a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=8587">State of the Game, Part 2</a>".  Gemdiver outlines two specific problems with the existing game: the focus on clerics and the equipment gap between raiders and non-raiders.  </p>

<p>I agree with his detailed assessments on these two topics but I don't necessarily agree with the scope.  I don't think the average active Everquest player, who I believe to be below level 60 has a continual requirement for clerics or sees the problem with high-end gear progression.  I don't think fixing these problems will make or break Everquest for most players.  I do, however, agree that both of these problems are large enough to warrant addressing.  I think both of these problems far outweigh the problem of instancing Plane of Time.</p>

<p>At levels above 65, I think there is a large focus on groups requiring clerics.  Places like Riftseekers, most of the Dragon missions, The Nest, MPG, and the MPG trials require a cleric in order to survive.  In most places below these high-end zones, however, groups can probably get away with a druid or a shaman.  We don't know exactly how the healing improvements to druids and shaman will play out but hopefully it will allow for a wider variety of successful groups.</p>

<p>Gear progression between raiders and single-group hunters has been a hot topic for me for nearly two years now.  I have a few philosophies on this matter:</p>

<p>No single-group content should require raiding to access.  This includes flagging but more recently includes equipment gaps.  Riftseekers, the MPG Trials, and The Accursed Nest  are single-group zones that require raid-equipped players.</p>

<p>All players should be able to improve their equipment through single-groups.  This includes raiders.  If raiders find the gear on the DON vendors to be underpowered, SOE should offer higher-end rewards that get all players excited about these missions.  Likewise, single-group hunters should always have further avenues for equipment progression.  There should always be higher-power gear for them to receive through single-group methods.</p>

<p>This topic could easily fill up an entire article so I won't dig into the problem here, but expect an article soon called "The Bloodwar" about the continuing war between raiders and non-raiders.</p>

<p>One last point, however.  When guys like Gemdiver agree with guys like me on a topic like this, its probably time SOE began to listen.  Something needs to be done to close the vast gaping chasm between single-group equipped players and raiders.</p>

<p>The gap must close.</p>

<p>When my mind begins to turn around this giant wheel of a topic, however, I always return to one thing: how does this relate to fun?</p>

<p>A recent post over on the EQ Live boards entitled "<a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=76563&view=by_date_ascending&page=1">Thoughts of a... resting... EQ player</a>" got me thinking about the larger scope of this topic:  What is fun and what is not?</p>

<p>Believe it or not, I recently picked up and began playing World of Warcraft.  I've barely scratched the surface of the game and I have no idea how it ends up in later levels, but it does give me another view of what makes MMOGs fun.  While I won't get into specifics about "fun" now, I will ask that we, as players of Everquest, should continually focus on what we enjoy instead of worrying about statistics or re-envisioning or gear or class balance.  </p>

<p>What matters is that we enjoy our time.  What can we do to enjoy it more?  What do we like? What do we not like?  These are the questions that matter and it is this feedback that will really improve Everquest.  Adding another 20 hitpoints onto an item won't make the game more fun.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
18 April 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The No-Patch Day News Roundup</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000056.html" />
<modified>2005-05-27T19:16:48Z</modified>
<issued>2005-04-06T20:58:53Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.56</id>
<created>2005-04-06T20:58:53Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today&apos;s article discusses some of the more recent news items floating around the EQ community including server mergers, class re-envisoning, the Fan Faire, next week&apos;s patch, and some other brilliant thoughts by Sai Loral. (note: News Roundup Trademark Loral Industries 2005; by reading the words &quot;News Roundup&quot; you fully consent to the Mobhunter End User License Agreement yet to be written.  For details, contact Moorgard.)</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>I had hoped to post an article shortly after the latest patch would stream across our servers but a delay until next week forces my fingers to the keyboard a little early.  There's been quite a bit of large news most of which we have already discussed at length.  So today, we will see where all of these big changes stand.</p>

<p>A week ago, SOE announced the official dates for server mergers across all servers.  Both my girlfriend and my friend, editor, and grandmaster-diaper-changer believed I was pulling their leg when I told them about SOE's announcement that all servers will be merging into half the number.</p>

<p>I was surprised to see the sudden announcement for all servers, but it makes sense.  I always felt that the rip-off-the-bandaid-fast-so-it-hurts-all-at-once approach is a good one for something like this.</p>

<p>I would be lying if I said I read the <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=71743">1400 posts about server mergers</a> after the announcement of this topic, but a brief glance brings up a few common thoughts.  1.  Servers are merging so Everquest is dead.  2.  Servers are merging and we're losing our identity.  3.  Servers are merging so how will I get my ph4t T1me l3wt.</p>

<p>Merging servers don't show the death throes of Everquest.  A lack of new content, new expansions, or a lack of attention by SOE would show those death throes.  The merging of the servers itself shows SOE's continued support to keep Everquest healthy.  As long as new expansions come out, as long as new patches fix bugs and add features, as long as every class argues that they are the slapped-in-face red-headed step child of Everquest, the game is alive and well.</p>

<p>Identity is an important point in these mergers, however.  I, myself, could not exactly say how I would feel if my server name were lost.  It would be a pain to change my signatures and web sites all over the web from Quellious to Rodcet Nife, that's for sure.  Server identity is important, though the real spirit is held within each member of that server.  That isn't going away.  I am reminded of flag-burning debates when I read about this.  Is the symbol of the server name more important than the community it represents?</p>

<p>SOE clearly stated a couple of times that server mergers were based on active population, though many wanted a variety of other solutions to decide including the age of the server, the power of one god over another (Veeshan could kick Luclin's a55!!), and even barbaric duels in the arena.  It was bad enough that I depended on uberguilds to open up the Nest, much less decide the fate of my server.  Total population makes the most sense.</p>

<p>So what about Ph4t T1me l3wt?  One solution brought up at the Summit a year ago, is to instance Time.  I don't support this solution.  The rate of dropping equipment in Time is based on a non-instanced zone, not an instanced one.  Instancing Time would make it a tighter knot in the center of equipment progression.</p>

<p>Offering Time level loot in other areas, areas huntable by non-Time equipped hunters, solves this problem.  For example, a second tier of loot on the Dragons of Norrath mission vendors with increased hitpoints, mana, foci, skill increases, and higher damage weapons, helps remove Time as a single dependency for equipment progression.</p>

<p>Such a solution helps raiders who wish to gear up but don't want to go back five expansions to do so; it helps close the huge power gap between single-group hunters and raiders; and it helps offer multiple paths for raid progression for up-and-coming guilds.  It will remove the single required dependency on Time for progression both for raiders and single group hunters wishing to reach places such as Riftseekers, the MPG trials, and The Nest.</p>

<p>Needless to say, the topic of server mergers brought up thousands of conversations but if anything, the huge amount of activity shows that players care a great deal for such a big move.</p>

<p>Next week, SOE will release the first wave of class re-envisioning changes.  A quick glance over to <a href="http://lucy.allakhazam.com/">Lucy</a> shows the details of many changes to a lot of spells, mostly in direct damage spells.  Many classes will see an increase in overall damage to mana ratios if not a direct increase in damage per second values.  Clerics, for example, saw a nice boost in magic blasters and a bigger boost to undead blasters.  Now if I could only find some undead to blast.</p>

<p>Shaman picked up their pitchforks and torches in another wave of angst against a change that added a 30 second recast time to their new DON proc buff spell.  Supposedly, the change helped prevent a single shaman from adding significantly to the overall damage of a raiding force, but with a one minute duration and a high mana cost, I don't know how big a threat this really was.  In the mean time, adding a 30 second recast hurts its use in a group.  The latest postings from Rytan on this topic offer a few possible alternatives including a group version of the spell or a version with a lower damage proc rate.  The group version makes the most sense to me.</p>

<p>There's a lot of other interesting changes in next week's patch mentioned in the <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=testing&message.id=5585#M5585">Test server patch message</a>.  It looks like we'll see some new Dragons of Norrath missions.  New hotspots were announced, although they look strangely like the existing hotspots if my fading memory serves.  Dragons missions will have their crystal rewards fixed - I'm betting the Gimblax mission will be worth about 10 crystals now.  That poor goblin needed a vacation.  There's a bunch of other smaller changes as well; it should be a nice patch.</p>

<p>On Thursday evening, <a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive.vm?id=440&section=News&month=current">John Smedley posted a letter</a> on the state of all of SOE's games.  He mentions that Alan Crosby, our own Brenlo, was promoted to Director of Community Relations.  Looks like Moorgard got a new boss!</p>

<p>SOE will host the next <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Fanfaire&message.id=5441">Everquest Fan Faire</a> on June 9th to June 12th.  Again, I will re-envision the Loral Evil Agenda, decide what areas I feel SOE needs to concentrate on, and bully for it among the other summit representatives doing the same.  I expect we will hear about the next Everquest expansion before this Fan Faire so there will be a lot to see.  Now where did I leave my spock ears?</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
6 April 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Other Worlds Than These</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000055.html" />
<modified>2005-05-27T19:16:48Z</modified>
<issued>2005-03-23T21:09:24Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.55</id>
<created>2005-03-23T21:09:24Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">The Overlord falls and the people rejoice. Today&apos;s update falls back to the more traditional news roundup, covering the fall of Mata Muram, the class re-envisioning, the anniversary, a couple of new features, and other bits of interesting news from the field.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Time for an old-fashioned news roundup!</p>

<p>On the evening of 23 March, 2005, the powerful armies of Cestus Dei confronted and defeated the Overlord Mata Muram. This final boss of Omens of War marked a huge step in the progression of high-end Everquest raids. Cestus Dei is also responsible for the first defeat of Tunat Muram, the final boss of the Gates of Discord<br />
expansion. I can't imagine the number of cross server recruitment requests they receive, but I bet it's a lot.</p>

<p>The strategy for defeating Mata Muram went quite far outside the traditional CH rotation / DPS strategies we grew used to in the times when raiding was young. Dei's description of the event paints the picture of a very unforgiving encounter that, while still requiring good equipment, requires extreme attention by every member of the raid force. No matter what your gear, this raid sounds like a nightmare of coordination.  Here's a quote from <a href="http://www.cestusdei.org/news.php">Cestus Dei's website</a>.</p>

<p>"On the surface, he's a pretty standard boss. He does damage that's more or less appropriate for a target at his stage of the game, and has two large instant-respawn minibosses with similar damage that must be controlled. Smaller adds spawn periodically that multiply themselves the longer they stay alive. Not all that bad on the face of it. His trick comes in the form of probably the most punishing mechanic that's ever been tried in this game: periodically, a single person on the raid gets an emote that only they can see. They have a few seconds to react to it and cast a spell just for the encounter- if they succeed, he's somewhat weakened. If they fail, he powers up the point where it might not guarantee a raid wipe, but in the few seconds that it even takes for everyone to realize someone has screwed up, probably everyone near him is dead."</p>

<p>"Mata Muram is a boss about pure disruption and chaos. He silences, knock-backs, stuns, fizzle-curses, slows cast time, mana drains, snares, and that's just getting started."</p>

<p>The Overlord's last words?  "There are other worlds than these...".</p>

<p>Last week, SOE posted the infamous <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=64032">Class Re-envisioning document</a>.  Feedback, as you can imagine, was mixed.  A few more interesting changes, like the Druid's state feature that switches between healer or blaster, got people quite excited.  A lot of the agenda-wielding class voices will never be happy until their beloved class rises to the top of the 16.</p>

<p>A patch scheduled for early April will bring many of these changes to first light and then we can begin to see the true results, but a lot of the suggested fixes should be well received.  Some, however, will never be happy no matter what SOE does.</p>

<p>For a long time, I felt that all classes at most levels should have some method to return quickly to safety when real life rears its ugly head.  Newer games such as Worlds of Warcraft, Everquest 2, and Everquest Online Adventures give new players some method to return home.  In the beginning of April, so will Everquest.</p>

<p>24 hours [update: it's been <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/updates/upcoming_updates.jsp?id=64010">changed from 24 to 6 hours</a> - even better!] after one logs out from Everquest, a "return home" button will appear on your character select screen.  Pressing it returns your character safely home no matter what horrible place you camped out at.  This meets the needs of players who, for many reasons, have to leave very shortly and don't have a good method to get home.  Some bring up gate potions or the Origin AA as an argument against such a change, but those features are not available except to the rich or the powerful.  Something had to be given to the level 35 ranger of Kaesora who had no other way out.  This is a great change.</p>

<p>The change to six hours lets players return to play within a day of their previous play session.  Six hours is long enough to make sure people don't replace real porting, but short enough to let players return home at 6pm when they logged out at 11pm the night before.</p>

<p>Another less useful feature restores a character to full hitpoints and mana after a character has been logged out for one hour.  Considering most characters can restore much faster than that, even twice as fast now that we have the guild hottub, I don't see much of a purpose, but it will do little harm.</p>

<p>Last week began the month-long celebration for Everquest's sixth year.  A new scavenger hunt quest across Kunark rewarded many with a new ten-charge 30-minute experience doubling potion. I'm convinced I will spend five clicks accidentally sitting in the hottub and another five just before my group wipes out.</p>

<p>With the anniversary comes fabled mobs.  Over a hundred mobs, many in Kunark, grew greatly in powered and earned the title Fabled.  Fabled Venril Sather tore down his opponents with a melee attack for somewhere around 5100.  The Fabled Overking in Chardok dropped a 250 hp and mana breastplate with a clickable invis that had most clerics drooling like St. Bernards.  A few players pontificated that six years from now, the Fabled Mata Muram will hit folks for somewhere in the 10 million range.</p>

<p>On 22 March, <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=64036">SOE began merging</a> four of the blue servers down to two.  Antonia Bayle and Kane Bayle merged down to Antonia Bayle.  Solusek Ro and Bristlebane merged down to Bristlebane.  I expect we will see more of these mergers in the future but  the severity of such changes warrant a slower approach.</p>

<p>Time for a shamless plug.  Over on Caster's Realm, I wrote an article called "<a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=7668">Class, Equipment, and Encounter Balance</a>" that discusses the complex balance between these three variables.  My main conclusion is that class balance alone isn't a factor to be considered without levels, equipment, and encounters coming into play.  Anyone who reads my pompous prose won't be surprised by the article.  I expect to write a couple more articles for CR soon including "Why Soloing is Evil" and "Why Play Everquest?", a rewrite of an <a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001076.html">older article</a> of mine that still makes the rounds once in a while.</p>

<p>And with that shameless plug out of the way, I leave you to enjoy this month's festivities and look forward to the changes coming soon.  Remember: All things serve the beam.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
24 March 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>

</feed>