<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Everquest news, editorials, and commentary.</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<copyright>Copyright 2005</copyright>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2005 08:02:12 -0500</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2005 17:23:52 -0500</pubDate>
<generator>http://www.movabletype.org/?v=3.01D</generator>
<docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs> 

<item>
<title>News After the Fall of Gukta</title>
<description>Today we have a short update on the latest happenings in our constantly changing world of Norrath including the fall of Gukta, more on the Boar, and some interesting articles and rumors on the internets.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000070.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000070.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2005 08:02:12 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Riddles in the Depths</title>
<description>In this week&apos;s news roundup we look at the progression of the War of Antonica and dig into some of the clues given at the most recent EQ Stratics Developer Chat.  Learn the secrets of the Clockwork Boar!</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000069.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000069.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2005 00:23:28 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Rising of the Trolls</title>
<description>This week we offer up a news roundup of the latest happenings in Norrath including the most recent patch, a couple of news articles of note, and the most recent War of Norrath.  Enjoy!</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000068.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000068.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2005 10:52:45 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Patch that Changed Everquest</title>
<description>This week SOE released a patch that forever changed the face of Everquest.  While some of the features may seem subtle to some and even annoying to others, when one digs into what these changes mean, one sees a much more usable game and a tighter community.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000067.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000067.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2005 10:35:44 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Equipment Gap</title>
<description>Things have gotten a bit too cozy on Mobhunter recently.  Today we take a look at that most popular of topics, high-end equipment balance.  Let the fun begin.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000066.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000066.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2005 12:24:18 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Depths of Darkhollow  Preview</title>
<description>We have a sneak preview of the Depths of Darkhollow expansion.  See how this expansion may tackle mentoring, class archetype issues, and unused content in a feature that may be the coolest feature ever added to EQ since Project M.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000065.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000065.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2005 03:32:32 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Notes from the West</title>
<description>Loral finds a few moments to post some notes from the Community Summit and the Las Vegas Fan Faire.  Read on for some exciting up-to-the-minute news and comments including information on the new expansion: Depths of Darkhollow!</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000064.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000064.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2005 13:47:35 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda - Las Vegas, Summer 2005</title>
<description>Next week Loral travels west to the shining lands of pyramds and pirate ships armed with the following Evil Agenda.  Read on to see what areas SOE should focus on to continue to improve Everquest.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000063.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000063.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2005 11:28:04 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The New Player Experience</title>
<description>This week we take an in-depth look at the new tutorial available on Test as the beginnings of the New Player Experience.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000061.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000061.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2005 09:33:13 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Return to Unrest</title>
<description>There&apos;s a lot of big news this week.  Today we will take a look at the new old-world missions, the veteran rewards, the results of server mergers, the EQ Live price increase, and a few juicy rumors of things to come.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000060.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000060.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2005 10:38:11 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Allure of Augments</title>
<description>Today we discuss the most recent dev chat, a tiny peak at a brilliant article on disturbing trends, some interesting threads on the EQLive forums, and a few other odds and ends.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000059.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000059.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2005 09:58:21 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Breaking News: SOE to broker the selling of Items, Money, and Characters in EQ2</title>
<description>We interrupt our weekly Mobhunter article for the most important update since our time here at Mobhunter (I love referring to myself in plural).  Tonight SOE announced that they will begin selling in-game money, items, and characters in Everquest 2 on selected servers.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000058.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000058.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2005 20:37:47 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Reign of Zorillius</title>
<description>This week&apos;s article discusses the latest EQ Producer&apos;s, veteran rewards, Gemdiver&apos;s State of the Game Part 2 article, and an excellent post over on the EQ Live forums.  Enjoy!</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000057.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000057.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2005 10:02:35 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The No-Patch Day News Roundup</title>
<description>Today&apos;s article discusses some of the more recent news items floating around the EQ community including server mergers, class re-envisoning, the Fan Faire, next week&apos;s patch, and some other brilliant thoughts by Sai Loral. (note: News Roundup Trademark Loral Industries 2005; by reading the words &quot;News Roundup&quot; you fully consent to the Mobhunter End User License Agreement yet to be written.  For details, contact Moorgard.)</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000056.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000056.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2005 15:58:53 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Other Worlds Than These</title>
<description>The Overlord falls and the people rejoice. Today&apos;s update falls back to the more traditional news roundup, covering the fall of Mata Muram, the class re-envisioning, the anniversary, a couple of new features, and other bits of interesting news from the field.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000055.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000055.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2005 16:09:24 -0500</pubDate>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>