<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:atom="http://purl.org/atom/ns" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">

<channel>
  <title>The Safehouse News</title>
  <link>http://www.thesafehouse.org</link>
  <description>The Rogue Community site for all your MMORPG news!! </description>
  <language>en-us</language>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 May 2006 09:37:18 PST</lastBuildDate>
  <copyright>(C) 2005 The Safehouse Network</copyright>
  <managingEditor>aidden@thesafehouse.org</managingEditor>
  <webMaster>hostmaster@safehousenet.net</webMaster>
   <ttl>5</ttl>

  <image>
  <title>The Safehouse News</title>
  <width>144</width>
  <height>31</height>
  <link>http://www.thesafehouse.org</link>
  <url>http://www.thesafehosue.org/rss.gif</url>
  </image>

<item>
<title><![CDATA[AMD launches Socket AM2 ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/tech/news_275.php</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2006 08:36:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Today AMD launched their new unified desktop socket format, Socket AM2.
Socket AM2 is set to replace AMD's socket 939 which will be EOLed (end
of life) at the end of this year, and will support both AMD's high end
Athlon 64 X2 and FX processors as well as their low end Sempron
processors. Socket 754 is set to remain in AMD's lineup throughout the
end of 2007 as a way to mantain an inexpensive single channel DDR based
platform.<br><br>Socket AM2 marks AMD's change from DDR memory to DDR2 memory, as well
as the move of their Sempron value lineup from single channel to a dual
channel memory format.<br><br>Here are several reviews from around the web:<br><br><a href="http://www.anandtech.com/cpuchipsets/showdoc.aspx?i=2762">AnandTech</a><br><a href="http://www.xbitlabs.com/articles/cpu/display/amd-socket-am2.html">X-Bit Labs</a><br><a href="http://enthusiast.hardocp.com/article.html?art=MTA2NSwxLCxoZW50aHVzaWFzdA==">HardOCP</a><br><a href="http://www.hothardware.com/viewarticle.aspx?articleid=822&amp;cid=1">Hot Hardware</a><br><a href="http://www.extremetech.com/article2/0,1697,1966062,00.asp">ExtremeTech</a><br><a href="http://www.firingsquad.com/hardware/amd_athlon_64_fx_62_5000/">FiringSquad</a><br> ]]></description>
<category>Ruccus</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/tech/news_275.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[E3: SOE Out of the Box ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_274.php</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2006 12:26:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[



<p class="MsoNormal">For the past few years Sony Online Entertainment has
basically had the same sort of display at E3. A large rectangular black box,
one side with windows giving you a tease of the demos and goodies inside, while
other sides showing game signage and videos but lacking proper demo boxes. This
year they finally broke that model and had several public demo stations outside area
as well.<br><br>No wonder, you might say, because SOE is now a co-publisher
for former rival, Sigil Games Online’s upcoming gem, <span style="font-weight:bold">Vanguard: Saga of Heroes</span>.
Add them to <span style="font-weight:bold">Gods and Heroes</span> plus the ongoing SOE titles of <span style="font-weight:bold">EverQuest</span>, <span style="font-weight:bold">EverQuest
II</span>, <span style="font-weight:bold">Star Wars Galaxies</span>, <span style="font-weight:bold">Planetside</span>, etc and the Black Box is just about
bursting.</p> ]]></description>
<category>Fricka</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_274.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Progression Server to launch in June! ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/EQ/news_273.php</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2006 21:55:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[<p>SONY ONLINE ENTERTAINMENT ANNOUNCES EVERQUEST PROGRESSION SERVER <br></p>
<p>"The Combine" Progression Server will allow all players to start on a level playing field as they explore the online world of EverQuest as it was in the beginning</p> ]]></description>
<category>ShadowCross</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/EQ/news_273.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[E3 2006 – Overview and Fricka Awards ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_272.php</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2006 00:20:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[<p><font face=Arial color=#ffffe0 size=2>E3 2006 has just ended so it must be time to give out awards.&nbsp;Fricka&nbsp;&nbsp;tells a bit about her E3&nbsp;experience and gives out her own Awards.</font></p> ]]></description>
<category>Fricka</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_272.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[E3 2006 Photos for Wednesday ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_271.php</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2006 23:28:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[<a href="http://www.thesafehouse.org/mugshots/">First batch of photos</a> are up from Fricka's E3 meetings and meanderings.<br><br><br><img alt="e32006" src="http://www.thesafehouse.org/mugshots/albums/e32006may10/IMG_2546.thumb.jpg" align="" border="0"><br> ]]></description>
<category>Fricka</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_271.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Quick Note - WoW New  Alliance Race: Draenei ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_270.php</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2006 12:09:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[<p>Blizzard finally showed off the new Alliance race named the Draenei.&nbsp;They are&nbsp;satyr-like creatures with&nbsp;hooves but have a reptilian looking tail.</p>
<p>Not much detail was given about this new race as everything is "not set yet". Classes are not announced though the demo allowed you to choose a warrior or paladin to play. There was also a hunter trainer I spotted in the starting city of Ammen Vale.</p>
<p>High resolution pictures will be coming tonight as well as official screenshots.</p>
<p>If you must have something to ponder, here's a very blurry camera picture of one log in screen model:</p>
<p><font size=2>     <table border=0 cellspacing=2 cellpadding=0 width=640 align=center>
      <tr><td><img src="http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/uploads/draeneiphonepic_001.jpg" height="480" width="640" border=0></td></tr>
     </table>
   </font></p>
<p>Here's one of the model at the booth display:</p>
<p>&nbsp;     <table border=0 cellspacing=2 cellpadding=0 width=640 align=right>
      <tr><td><img src="http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/uploads/144154312_3a1a71bbcc_o.jpg" height="480" width="640" border=0></td></tr>
     </table>
   </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p> ]]></description>
<category>Fricka</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_270.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Vanguard using EMotion FX Character Animation System at E3  ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_269.php</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2006 09:41:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[<font size=2>
<p align=left>Highly anticipated Vanguard: Saga of Heroes MMORPG using the EMotion FX Character Animation System at E3 </p>
<p align=left>ROTTERDAM, NETHERLANDS </font><font face=Tahoma size=2>–</font><font size=2> May 10, 2006 - Mystic Game Development, a pioneer in real-time character animation middleware, today announced that Sigil Game Online's Vanguard: Saga of Heroes was built using Mystic's EMotion FX real-time character animation technology as a core component. The MMORPG game, which received coverage in all 3 major US PC magazines recently, is being shown at E3 in LA this week. </p></font> ]]></description>
<category>Aidden</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_269.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[VANGUARD: SAGA OF HEROES FINDS A NEW HOME ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/Vanguard/news_268.php</link>
<pubDate>Fri,  5 May 2006 18:14:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[<p>VANGUARD: SAGA OF HEROES FINDS A NEW HOME</p>
<p>- Sigil Games Online and Sony Online Entertainment In Talks To Co-Publish Sigil’s Ground-Breaking New Game -</p>
<p>May 5, 2006&nbsp; Carlsbad &amp; San Diego, CA&nbsp; Sigil Games Online and Sony Online Entertainment LLC (SOE), a global leader in the online games industry, today announced that Sigil is working with Microsoft Game Studios on an arrangement to acquire the rights to its highly anticipated massively multiplayer online (MMO) game, Vanguard: Saga of Heroes.&nbsp; These efforts have resulted in a tentative agreement for Vanguard to be co-published by both Sigil Games Online and SOE. All three companies will be showing the game at the upcoming Electronic Entertainment Expo (E3) as they work closely together for a successful transition. Vanguard: Saga of Heroes is scheduled to launch this winter.</p> ]]></description>
<category>Aidden</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/Vanguard/news_268.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Sony to raise Station Access rate ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SOE/news_267.php</link>
<pubDate>Thu,  4 May 2006 19:20:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Starting June 1st, SOE will be raising their Station Access fee by $3/month, as noted <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50138">here</a>:<br><br><span style="font-style:italic"><span style="font-weight:bold">Station Access™ subscription
  price increase</span>
										  
										  
											</span><br style="font-style:italic"> <p style="font-style:italic">We
will be increasing our Station Access subscription rate in June.
Effective June 1, 2006, the new monthly subscription rate will be
$24.99/month, up $3.00 from its current price $21.99/month. We have
added significant value to the Station Access subscription since its
inception including two games, The Matrix Online and Star Wars
Galaxies, as well as incorporating the Adventure Packs for EverQuest II
at no additional fee, (including The Fallen Dynasty due out this
summer). In addition, the cost of operating the game service for the
games included in the Station Access subscription package has increased
significantly since we launched Station Access. This change will help
us achieve our goal of seeing that every player has a consistently
enjoyable experience in our game worlds and we intend to continue to
add value to this all-in-one subscription package. Current subscribers
don't have to do a thing; you will automatically be migrated to the new
billing structure under your current subscription plan when your
current subscription plan expires. Subscription rates are subject to
tax and value-added taxes, as applicable. <br><br> For more detailed information on the Station Access subscription package, please go to www.stationaccess.com.</p> ]]></description>
<category>Ruccus</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SOE/news_267.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Allakhazam sold ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_266.php</link>
<pubDate>Thu,  4 May 2006 18:28:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Yesterday Allahkazam.com made this announcement:<br><br><br><span style="font-style:italic">Allakhazam is pleased to announce that we have added several new sites
to our network and have joined them together to form the Zam.com
Network which is now instantly the leading content destination for all
MMO gamers. </span><br style="font-style:italic">
<br style="font-style:italic"><span style="font-style:italic">The new Zam.com Network will consist of newly expanded and improved
versions of Allakhazam.com and Thottbot.com. In addition, the assets
and content of OGaming.com (and the interface sites) and L2Orphus.com
will be integrated into the existing Allakhazam network. This will add
multiple new games to our site, more than double our personnel and give
us the flexibility to add more features, better service and expanded
coverage. </span><br style="font-style:italic">
<br style="font-style:italic"><span style="font-style:italic">In the coming months, we will be upgrading our server
infrastructure, expanding our news and editorial coverage, adding sites
for more games, and designing even better database services. We are
committed to making this the premier destination for the entire MMORPG
community.</span><br><br>Since the announcement the story has become a bit more complex. <span style="font-weight:bold"></span><strong></strong> ]]></description>
<category>Ruccus</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_266.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   

   
   

               
     
     

          
     
     
     

     
     
     

</channel>
</rss>