<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>Sunshadow wrote:Removing the &quot;No Trade&quot; would just mean I would be forced to buy upgrades </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Sunshadow wrote:Removing the &quot;No Trade&quot; would just mean I would be forced to buy upgrades in the Bazaar at inflated prices and raiders could then go farm the stuff to sell in the bazaar when they are not actually raiding. Yes, it would close the gap but it would kill a lot of the enjoyment I get out of the game.

---

I agree 100 percent I get joy out of knowing that I can attain gear on my own without the need for the bazaar I dont wan</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The equipment gap, the gap between becoming a raider for non-raiders, the lock out issue of zones.  </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The equipment gap, the gap between becoming a raider for non-raiders, the lock out issue of zones.  All of that goes away in a three part process.

1) Remove the no-drop flag from any item that is not 100% needed to be no-drop for quest reasons (epic&apos;s and maybe a limited handfull of others), from any expansion more than 18 months old.

2) Remove the flag process for any zone entry that is more than 18 months old.  Leave the flags as optiona</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Outstanding post by SomeoneThat AbsorHates. Very well thought out and offers alot of suggestions tha</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Outstanding post by SomeoneThat AbsorHates. Very well thought out and offers alot of suggestions that are excellent IMO. Well done.  

What I don&apos;t get at all are the 2 posts above it:

Sunshadow said --&gt;Removing the &quot;No Trade&quot; would just mean I would be forced to buy upgrades in the Bazaar at inflated prices and raiders could then go farm the stuff to sell in the bazaar when they are not actually raiding. Yes, it would close th</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Instead of saying &quot;removing the NO TRADE tag&quot; I would amend it to &quot;changing NO TRADE </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Instead of saying &quot;removing the NO TRADE tag&quot; I would amend it to &quot;changing NO TRADE tag to ATTUNEABLE&quot;.  I don&apos;t think you&apos;ll get anywhere by simply removing the NO TRADE tag.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Once again, this is about older raid gear, not the current stuff, so there&apos;s still plenty of se</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Once again, this is about older raid gear, not the current stuff, so there&apos;s still plenty of seperation between current raiders and groupers.

Making old raid gear tradeable is a pretty easy change to make, doesn&apos;t impact the fact that monsters still need to be killed for the items to enter the game, and will help quickly close the gap between groupers and raiders.

Moving forward, subsequent expansions can be created with a smaller dif</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I&apos;ll grant removing the no drop tag from older raid gear has some advantages. It really would r</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I&apos;ll grant removing the no drop tag from older raid gear has some advantages. It really would reduce the gear gap, and by tying the gap to the pace of raid progression (something SOE is good at controlling) it makes sure the gap stays reduced. It&apos;s easy to do. And giving raiders a new source of income reduces their opposition. But we should carefully consider what else it would do to the game.

A lot depends on the supply of raid items </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Dear Krylax,

Of course no-one is forced to buy in the Bazaar. But as this is a discussion about clo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Dear Krylax,

Of course no-one is forced to buy in the Bazaar. But as this is a discussion about closing the GAP it is relevent. As a group geared player I am unable to take down old raid mobs so how does the GAP close by making their drops tradable if I don&apos;t buy them in the bazaar. It doesn&apos;t. So again making those items tradable is useless to me. It forces me to buy them, if I choose to close the gap. What I and a lot of other people</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Well said Teremar and Sunshadow. Every expansion they create group items that don&apos;t close the g</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Well said Teremar and Sunshadow. Every expansion they create group items that don&apos;t close the gap. If they ever wanted the gap closed they would have done so already. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Sunshadow,

Thanks for the second post. I can see that changing the no - drop flag wouldn&apos;t hel</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Sunshadow,

Thanks for the second post. I can see that changing the no - drop flag wouldn&apos;t help you in your situation. Myself, I always liked wheeling and dealing in the bazaar, using my alchemy skill to make pp, etc. It added another dimension to the game for me. So buyable upgrades would help close the gear gap for me and the people I group with.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always be better than s</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always be better than single-group gear in the same expansions, or even up to three expansions back, but level 65 Tacvi gear shouldn&apos;t be better than the best single-group level 75 gear this far into the game.

Narrowing the gap would help the game out a lot.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral said --&gt;I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Loral said --&gt;I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always be better than single-group gear in the same expansions, or even up to three expansions back, but level 65 Tacvi gear shouldn&apos;t be better than the best single-group level 75 gear this far into the game.

Narrowing the gap would help the game out a lot


I agree with this completely. When i said &quot;close&quot; the gear gap I should have sai</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>[quote = Loral]I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always b</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>[quote = Loral]I don&apos;t want the gap closed. I want the gap narrowed.

Raid gear should always be better than single-group gear in the same expansions, or even up to three expansions back, but level 65 Tacvi gear shouldn&apos;t be better than the best single-group level 75 gear this far into the game.

Narrowing the gap would help the game out a lot.[/quote]

I think I would put the gear from the hardest, best designed, complex group missions</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I have come to point i believe where I can no longer play and enjoy this game. I dont have the time </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I have come to point i believe where I can no longer play and enjoy this game. I dont have the time to raid so I&apos;m screwed. I&apos;m in a small family guild, Screwed. I play a Melee and if group not on i sit LFG for 3+hours, Screwed. 

I thought the push to 75 was good for the game but after getting there I now believe otherwise. I cant solo or Duo anything that would produce a decent drop for me. And now im too high to get decent XP in the </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I agree the gap is huge now, but I think you overstate what is required to get the TSS armor, and I </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I agree the gap is huge now, but I think you overstate what is required to get the TSS armor, and I don&apos;t think it should be easier to get, as many of the camps are trivial (ie light blue trash) at 75.  The power sources drop almost every time you kill a named in Vald for example, and both together require a similar overall effort as past armor quests.

What surprised me most when I returned was that my gear was still pretty good, even after</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>(quick reply: Raiders shouldn&apos;t fuel the gear for a server.  Players should be able to go out O</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>(quick reply: Raiders shouldn&apos;t fuel the gear for a server.  Players should be able to go out ON THEIR OWN (either 1 or 2 groups) to get their major upgrades.  Sure make a few soloable to make it a little easier.)

I think &quot;The Gap&quot; can&apos;t be discussed in terms of HP/MANA anymore.  (I don&apos;t know if it&apos;s just the terminology we use for this topic??)

There are really lots of subgroups for the itemization: weapons (rati</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>