<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Mobhunter</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/" />
  <modified>2007-12-08T16:09:00Z</modified>
  <tagline></tagline>
  <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7</id>
  <generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="3.01D">Movable Type</generator>
  <copyright>Copyright (c) 2007, Loral</copyright>
  <entry>
    <title>Mobhunter 2007 Holiday Buyers Guide</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001557.html" />
    <modified>2007-12-08T16:09:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-12-07T22:41:50-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1557</id>
    <created>2007-12-08T03:41:50Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we look at all the great gamer gifts one can give or receive this year. It&apos;s a great year to be a gamer!</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The holidays literally fell upon us here in the north east. While the gaming scene last year focused primarily on systems such as the release of the Playstation 3 and the Nintendo Wii, this is the year for games. It usually takes a year before console games really start to match the power of the hardware and this year was no exception. Nearly every week since the beginning of October, excellent games have been released for all of the top gaming platforms.</p>

<p>Today we will take a look at some of the better gaming gifts this year.</p>

<h2>Systems</h2>

<p><strong>Top Choice: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Nintendo-DS-Lite-Onyx-Black/dp/B000I10PY2/mikesheanet-20">Nintendo DS</a></strong></p>

<p>The Gameboy sold 118 million units in its fifteen year lifespan and now the Nintendo DS looks to leap over it. The Nintendo DS could very likely be the most popular game system ever made. It accomplished this feat in the following ways: it is priced well at $130, it has a large library of very good games, and it is easy to play. It isn't uncommon to see many non-gamers playing games like Brain Age and Pokemon every spare minute. If Xbox Live Arcade and the Nintendo Virtual Console show the popularity of casual gaming, the Nintendo DS manifests it completely.</p>

<p>The Nintendo DS is the best of all game systems on the market. Unlike the Wii's Wiimote, Nintendo and other third parties clearly understand how to use the touch screen of the DS. While not all of the top games on the DS use the touch screen, others, like Zelda Phantom Hourglass and Brain Age, use it completely.</p>

<p>For strong Nintendo DS games, look for the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Nintendo-NTR-P-A2DE-Super/dp/B000ERVMI8/mikesheanet-20">New Super Mario Brothers</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Legend-Zelda-Phantom-Hourglass/dp/B000FRV2UK/mikesheanet-20">Zelda Phantom Hourglass</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Konami-24128-Contra-4/dp/B000UZVL58/mikesheanet-20">Contra 4</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Brain-Age-More-Training-Minutes/dp/B000QUYHIK/mikesheanet-20">Brain Age 2</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Nintendo-Planet-Puzzle-League/dp/B000OAOJ12/mikesheanet-20">Planet Puzzle League</a>, and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sierra-72742-Geometry-Wars-Galaxies/dp/B000RWV12W/mikesheanet-20">Geometry Wars: Galaxies</a>.</p>

<p>The Nintendo DS will make an excellent gift.</p>

<p><strong>Top Console: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000W91YTA?ie=UTF8&tag=mikesheanet-20&linkCode=as2&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B000W91YTA">Xbox 360</a></strong></p>

<p>Of all the current home consoles, the Xbox 360 is the best one. The controller is simple and elegant, a single device with enough buttons and controls to control some complicated games but ergonomic enough to make it easy to play some of the simpler Xbox Live Arcade games. Unlike the Wii's required classic controller and nunchuck, the 360's single controller is all that is needed for any of the 360 games save Guitar Hero or Rock Band for obvious reasons.</p>

<p>Technically the 360 is very strong. It includes in-game Dolby Digital sound and high definition graphics up to 1080p. If you want your new HDTV to look great, try out one of the better looking 360 games.</p>

<p>Xbox Live is an excellent online system and probably the biggest strength of the 360. One can buy the Xbox 360 basic system for $350 and immediately download ten game demos and maybe a hundred Xbox Live Arcade demos. Unlike the Wii's online store, a 360 owner can try out any of these game demos for free without any additional cost. Xbox Live also includes one of the best persistent player reputation systems. If you pay the 360 tax of $50 every six months, you can play games online with your friends as well. This multi-player tax is one of the drawbacks of Xbox Live, but it's a small one when you consider what you get for free.</p>

<p>Of all of the top systems right now, including the Wii and the Playstation 3, the 360 has the strongest line up of good games, the best characteristics, the best online mode, and at a decent cost. Save your money from the PS3 and save your time from the Wii; get the 360.</p>

<h2>Games</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Blizzard-Entertainment-World-of-Warcraft/dp/B000067FDW/mikesheanet-20">World of Warcraft</a> + <a href="http://www.amazon.com/World-Warcraft-Expansion-Burning-Crusade/dp/B000BWZY7Q/mikesheanet-20">Burning Crusade</a></p>

<p>The empire of World of Warcraft continues to grow with nearly ten million subscribers and generating over five hundred million in profit every year. For a game that requires staying power, WoW has it.</p>

<p>WoW continues to be one of the best, if not the best, massive multiplayer online game available. With beautiful graphics, a huge world, excellent solo, group, and raid play; the game has something for just about everyone. WoW can point its success to playing well on lower end systems, extremely accessible gameplay, and tons of polish. WoW itself can be purchased for $20 while Burning Crusade runs another $20. For forty bucks and $15 a month, it builds one of the largest and most beautiful virtual worlds ever to exist.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sony-EverQuest-Secrets-of-Faydwer/dp/B000WCUNNK/mikesheanet-20">Everquest: Secrets of Faydwer</a></p>

<p>World of Warcraft isn't for everyone. While it appeals to the masses, others seek the worlds off of the superhighways of gaming. Everquest continues strong into its eighth year with the release of Secrets of Faydwer, a single package that contains the core game and all fourteen expansions. While not as newbie friendly or clearly accessible as World of Warcraft, Everquest contains years worth of content. Not bad for $25 on Amazon. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Microsoft-9UE-00001-Halo-3/dp/B000FRU0NU/mikesheanet-20">Halo 3</a></p>

<p>It's probably not worth mentioning considering the popularity but Halo 3 is the game to own on the 360. A strong single player campaign, excellent co-op play, and a deep reward system for the wide range of multi-player competition modes all combine into a game that will likely remain active for years to come. Halo 3 is the strongest 360 game available.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Electronic-Arts-9849-The-Orange/dp/B000R0PLK2/mikesheanet-20">Orange Box</a></p>

<p>Half Life 2 on its own is an excellent game. The two expansion packs are each strong, although short, diversions back into the world of Black Mesa. Combine this with Team Fortress, a class based first person shooter, and then throw a 3d platform game in the mix and you have a lot to do in a single box. If you have only one game to buy, this might be the one.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/MTV-Games-SEP-Special-Edition/dp/B000TT4GBG/mikesheanet-20">Rock Band</a></p>

<p>Guitar Hero 2 changed how I understood video games. I have never had as much fun playing a game as I did nailing "Freebird" on Hard. I hosted "Dress Like A Rock Star" Guitar Hero 2 parties and played until my fingers went numb. Guitar Hero reminds us that the core of gaming is fun. The closer to fun the game keeps you, the better game it is. Rock Band appears to take Guitar Hero to the next level with new songs, additional instruments, and new modes of play. I've got a fever and the only prescription is more cowbell!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/UBI-Soft-Assassins-Creed/dp/B000P46NMK/mikesheanet-20">Assassin's Creed</a></p>

<p>Though I have not yet played it, Assassin's Creed appears quite strong. Some reviews point to repetitive gameplay as a failing but made up for with visual beauty and a very strong protagonist. This one appears to be a good one.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Microsoft-M59-00033-Mass-Effect/dp/B000OLXX86/mikesheanet-20">Mass Effect</a></p>

<p>Though the top Xbox 360 seem to focus on first person shooters, Mass Effect may break the mold. A powerful story and character driven dialog seem to be the strengths of this game with a solid RPG engine within. I'm looking forward to this one.</p>

<p>The wild shot: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/OTT-LITE-TrueColor-Original-Grey-Floor/dp/B000140KE6/mikesheanet-20">The Ott-Lite TrueColor Floor Lamp</a></p>

<p>For the big reader in your life, nothing beats a good strong natural light. The OTT-LITE floor lamp brings out the pure color of a good graphic novel and makes sitting and reading a book over hours a true pleasure. It may look expensive but Michael's usually has them on sale for 50% off. I love mine.</p>

<h2>Avoid the Wii</h2>

<p>Everyone either has a Wii or wants a Wii. Though it's been out for over a year, Wiis are still nearly impossible to get. I've had a Wii nearly since its release. I waited in line at four in the morning to get one. I've played through Zelda and Metroid. It is with this experience that I can say the following:</p>

<p>Don't bother.</p>

<p>Though Zelda, Mario, and Metroid are all strong titles, they are at the top of a small narrow hill. There aren't a lot of games for the Wii and very few have used the Wiimote in any strong or positive way. Though sold as a system for non-gamers, the Wii is surprisingly complex with two main controllers, a classic controller, and a game cube controller all required to play across all the games the system can play. I can't see how non-gamers will ever be able to figure out the complex controls of Zelda or Metroid. Even as an experienced gamer with 10 hours of time into Metroid, I still pressed the wrong buttons. Though far more classical, I found the Xbox 360 controller to be a lot simpler and a lot more intuitive for the games that use it properly.</p>

<p>The Wii also lacks Dolby Digital sound and high definition resolution. While some may point out that few people have HDTVs, they are a lot cheaper now than they used to be and all the HD consoles will still play on normal TVs. The time for low resolution gaming is over. With every Wii game I play, part of me always wishes that I could play the game in HD.</p>

<p>Nintendo's Virtual Console game download system also trails behind Xbox Live for one clear reason: no free trial version. While I can try out every 360 game before I buy it, it will cost me ten bucks to remember how much I hated Contra 3. People shouldn't have to pay just to try out the first level of a game they paid for 10 years ago.</p>

<p>When all is said and done, the Xbox 360 is the strongest console out there. The Wii, while very popular, has clear shortcomings and, until it has a stronger library, can be easily missed.</p>

<p>So there we have this year's Mobhunter Buyers Guide. This is a great year for gaming on nearly all fronts. With the initial battles of the console wars behind us, now the publishers focus on delivering the best games we've ever played. Now is the time to enjoy them.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
7 December 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Secrets of Faydwer Preview</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001554.html" />
    <modified>2007-12-08T03:45:52Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-11-04T21:17:30-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1554</id>
    <created>2007-11-05T02:17:30Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Loral goes on a preview tour of Secrets of Faydwer and shares his observations and opinions.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The world of Everquest moves ever onward. Last week, under the careful guidance of Rashere, Everquest's lead designer, I was able to preview the strange new worlds found in the Secrets of Faydwer, Everquest's fourteenth expansion. Overall the expansion looks strong. It contains many new zones, over thirty missions, multiple tiers of equipment progression, five new levels, and a focus on single group hunting. The clockwork theme may either excite players or leave them cold, but the design looks excellent. Whether it includes enough to hold players for an entire year, especially in this post WoW world, remains to be seen.</p>

<p>The story of Secrets of Faydwer involves the gnomish necromancer, Meldrath the Malignant, who unveils a floating fortress over the lost lands of Faydwer. Were-orcs, powerful undead, brownies, and the mechanical creations of Meldrath all threaten those who enter the lost lands. Secrets of Faydwer also continues the story of the Sleeper, the dragon Kerafyrm lost since the last days of Velious.</p>

<p>Graphically, the new expansion looks excellent. The brownie village and the new Crushbone-like dungeon of were-orcs feels like something you would see in Everquest 2, not Everquest. This game has come so far since the low-resolution flat textures of the original release in 1999. Like other expansions, Secrets also upgrades one of the older zones, this time Steamfont Mountains. The graphics of the new draconic zone is beautiful but still remains true to the artwork and architecture of previous draconic zones such as Skyshrine and the Sleeper's Tomb.</p>

<p>SOE chose to remain conservative with the expansion of Everquest. This is a smart move considering the <a href="http://www.wired.com/gaming/gamingreviews/news/2005/12/69816">general negativity of the massive changes to Star Wars Galaxies</a>. Everquest has evolved quite a bit over the years, but each evolution is a small change to the larger and consistent game built eight years ago. Secrets of Faydwer includes many refinements implemented in previous expansions including single group instanced missions and a tiered spell system. Secrets of Faydwer doesn't include any specific new gameplay features, but rather chooses to focus on enough zones, missions, equipment upgrades, and character level improvements to keep players busy for the next year.</p>

<p>Remaining conservative with Secrets of Faydwer is a good move considering the recent radical inclusion of a collectable virtual card game in both Everquest and Everquest 2. Attempts at revolution can still take place, but with as much hanging on the line as there is for Secrets of Faydwer, it is best to focus on the areas that have clearly worked and keep the radical ideas in the incubator a while longer.</p>

<p>Secrets of Faydwer marks the end of the six month development cycle for Everquest expansions. Instead of continual progression every six months, we now have a twelve month period of time until the next large set of content comes out. Secrets of Faydwer is built to give enough content for both raiders and non-raiders to, hopefully, fill those twelve months. Five new levels and a multi-tiered equipment progression system are two ways they hope to keep people playing over this period.</p>

<p>While The Serpent's Spine was intended to rebuild the lower and mid-level game of Everquest, Secrets of Faydwer focuses on the high level game. Secrets includes four tiers of content for players who prefer single-group hunting and high-end raids beyond the power of the current highest power raid zone, Solteris. While most Everquest expansions offered zones, encounters, and equipment for both raiders and single group hunters, the lead designer's description of Secrets of Faydwer focuses on high level single group play.</p>

<p>However, Secrets will contain twenty eight new high-end raids many above the current top raid zones for those few guilds who have cleared such areas. Secrets of Faydwer includes two raid zones with multiple progressive raids all above the Solteris level.</p>

<p>Equipment progression is one of the few main differences between Secrets of Faydwer and previous expansions. Equipment power will go up in large amounts in order to build tiers that require a certain power of equipment before one can proceed. In order to ensure players cannot jump a tier, the power of this gear will have to be high. No specific numbers were mentioned, but expect to see much higher power equipment than in previous expansions which leaned towards more conservative gains. This tiered equipment power level is a cornerstone in ensuring that Secrets will keep players busy for a whole year.</p>

<p>This expansion also marks a turning point in SOE's marketing for Everquest. Rather than releasing a single stand-alone expansion, SOE will release only a compilation pack that includes the basic game and all expansions. This is a dizzying amount of content in a single box; over four hundred unique zones and instances. If one considers the cost of the original game and $30 for each expansion, it includes over $400 worth of expansions for $40. However, for those of us who actually bought every expansion, this $40 pack is the only way to purchase it. That's a $10 price jump over the traditional expansions. Given the amount of time people spend in game, that's still not a lot, but at this price point one must consider it against the equally priced Burning Crusade expansion for World of Warcraft.</p>

<p>One sure way to ensure the success of an expansion is to include a character level increase. Secrets of Faydwer takes characters from level 75 to level 80 including all of the spells, disciplines, and alternate ability increases included with any level increase. These levels should take roughly the same amount of time as leveling from level 70 to level 75. Each time the level limit increases, older spells and equipment falls out of power. Focus effects on previous high-end raid equipment will become reduced or go out completely. All of this helps to push players forward into newer and more powerful areas but sometimes not without complaint.</p>

<p>Secrets of Faydwer has a lot to offer and, with the need to keep players involved for a year, it better be good. SOE took the best pieces of previous expansions and built it into a single large expansion with a focus on high-end single group play. Multiple tiers of loot, five new levels, and new high-end raids should keep players busy but, with a new Warcraft expansion on the horizon and the strength of Warcraft overall, SOE has an uphill battle to keep what players it has and to bring any new players in. From everything seen in the preview, however, Secrets of Faydwer looks to be a strong expansion.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
4 November 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Secrets of Faydwer Q&amp;A Answers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001553.html" />
    <modified>2007-11-09T15:50:29Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-10-24T14:51:50-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1553</id>
    <created>2007-10-24T19:51:50Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we look at SOE&apos;s answers to the Mobhunter reader submitted questions.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Below are the answers to the reader-submitted questions I received in my last article.</p>

<p>Except where noted, the answers came from Travis "Rashere" McGeathy, EverQuest Lead Designer  </p>

<p><strong>Is there any intent to change the rate at which characters earn experience or AA experience?</strong> </p>

<p>There are two areas concerning experience where we are looking at making changes.   </p>

<p>First, we’re going to smooth out the bonus experience you get for killing a creature close to your level.  Currently, when you kill a creature that is dark blue to you, you get double the creature’s base experience. If you kill a creature that is even one level below dark blue, you just get the base experience.  We’re going to change it so that you continue to get double experience at dark blue, but the bonus will slowly fall away as the NPC gets further below dark blue instead of going away immediately.  This will be happening in the near future. </p>

<p>Second, I’m looking at smoothing out the experience requirements from level 51 to 60 so it’s a more gradual transition from the easier experience levels prior to level 51. </p>

<p><strong>What will the flagging system be like in Secrets of Faydwer? </strong></p>

<p>There are two different flagging systems in Secrets of Faydwer, the single group flags and the raid flags.</p>

<p>The two most powerful "dungeons" in the game, Meldrath’s Mansion and Crystallos, require players to complete a single-group quest in order to gain access to those zones. </p>

<p>For raiders, there is a progression of raids that they will need to defeat, similar to previous expansions.  They will fight their way through raids in the base zones, then take on Meldrath in his mansion, and, finally, confront Kerafyrm in Crystallos.  Each area gets progressively more difficult. The majority of this is pure raid completion flagging, but you’ll obviously need access to Meldrath’s Mansion and Crystallos as well through the access quest before you can take on the raids in those zones. </p>

<p><strong>After the release of Secrets of Faydwer, will SOE open up or reduce the flagging restrictions for older content? If so, when?</strong> </p>

<p>We have no plans to change entry requirements for old content.  The content was built with those requirements in mind and we want people to experience the content flow as it was designed.  As the game advances and characters become more powerful, it naturally becomes easier to meet these requirements. </p>

<p><strong>What is the plan for new player models?</strong> </p>

<p>We don’t have any definite timeframe for releasing new player models.  Right now, we’re doing iterations on the new human based on player feedback.  Once that’s done, we’ll get the new versions up on test server so people can see them.  The plan is to continue to do these feedback cycles until we are happy with the state of the models, at which point they’ll be released to live servers. <br />
 <br />
<strong>Does Secrets of Faydwer include any improved solo hunting areas or solo quests?</strong></p>

<p>EverQuest is a group-based game, so we don’t specifically design content for soloing.  Instead, the ability to solo happens naturally due to player abilities and power progression.  That being said, there are several areas in the new expansion that beta players have had a lot of success soloing.  Also, the majority of quests in the expansion are available as a solo player, though you may require help to finish them if you’re taking on content that is difficult for you. </p>

<p><strong>Can you describe any changes to tradeskills or quests? In particular, high-end tradeskills required raid-level drops to grow; will there be any new ways for tradeskillers to reach high-end rewards without raiding?</strong> </p>

<p>Ngreth: Jewelry Making will be undergoing a redesign.  Jewelers will make base items that can have a gem inserted. The Jewelry making skill will be required to cut the gem.  The metal that the base item is made of will affect how much of the gem’s power is focused and given to the player wearing the ring.  This system will allow players to customize their jewelry to fit their needs. </p>

<p>Existing trade skill quests have not been altered.</p>

<p>Raid level rewards will continue to require participation in raids.  This is a paradigm that is not likely to change.  That said, certain trade skill quests with large time investments may give rewards near to raid level rewards. </p>

<p>With this expansion a new long trade skill quest will be introduced.  This quest does not require raiding in any part of it, but will be a significant time investment.  Additionally, it is in some rather difficult zones and is likely to require grouping in order to complete the quest.  One of the zones this quest uses definitely requires a minimum three person group.  This reward item will be a piece of jewelry that can fit in finger, ear, wrist, neck, or face slot.  Additionally it will have at least two versions: a melee focused version and a caster focused version.  I have hope that it may even have some attraction to raiders to fill an odd slot they may need to upgrade. </p>

<p><strong>How will the content in Secrets of Faydwer be balanced against level and AAs? What amounts of AAs are players expected to have at what levels?</strong></p>

<p>The first tier is approximately the same as The Buried Sea, so is balanced against that.  For the second tier, the first real jump in power, we did a query of all the players in EQ and found that the majority of players have less than 500 AAs.  We then created testing character that are in top-end casual-level gear (full praetorian armor, basically) and gave them 500 AAs to use.  These characters were used as the tuning point for the second tier of zones.  From there, the following tiers are based off the equipment you get in the previous expansion tiers and we kept the 500 AAs the same. </p>

<p><strong>Is there an attempt to bring new players into EQ with Secrets of Faydwer or will that be left to future expansions?</strong> </p>

<p>Secrets of Faydwer is built mainly for high level characters, but the actual box for the game is all-inclusive so a new player coming into the game can pick up the expansion and have everything EQ has ever released immediately!  The SoF all-in-one pack is scheduled to be available at participating retail stores and via digital download on November 13th and will include original EQ and all previous EQ expansions. </p>

<p><strong>What changes are you making to the general philosophy of itemization in Secrets, if any? Will the item power jumps be significant? How many tiers will it include? What gear and power level is required to acquire the lowest tier? Part 2: How will SOE address changes to itemization after the release?</strong> </p>

<p>With the shift to one expansion per year, we’re returning to the old itemization paradigm used up to around Planes of Power where player power rose significantly with each expansion.  This allows the expansion to have multiple tiers of difficulty to progress through even for top end casual characters.   </p>

<p>With SoF, there are essentially 4 tiers of difficulty and, correspondingly, 4 tiers of items.  The expansion starts at around the same difficulty as the easier mission instances in Katta Castrum (Atiiki missions, for instance) and the rewards are similar.  This provides an entry point for players who haven’t completed TBS.  From there, content and items scales upwards over the tiers with each tier built to be a challenge for players who have geared up in the previous tier. </p>

<p>Post-launch changes will be addressed as they always have been.  We keep a close eye on the live game at all times and make adjustments as needed. </p>

<p><strong>Is there any attempt in Secrets of Faydwer to increase gear rewards for high-end players in single groups?</strong> </p>

<p>Definitely- One of the things that the longer expansion cycle allows us to do is have larger increases in player power over a single expansion, so both group players and raid players have significant improvements to look forward to.  We’re also making some shifts to bring certain aspects of group gear (such as AC) closer to raid level gear.  This is being done to facilitate the ability for non-raid players to successfully group with raid level players. </p>

<p><strong>Will there be any new content released between expansions?</strong></p>

<p>We haven’t locked down our post-expansion plans at this point, but our goal is to add more live content over the course of the year leading up to the next expected expansion in the fall of 2008.  We would like to address adding new events, quests, missions, and potentially even zone revamps, new raids, and a supplemental release of AAs.  </p>

<p><strong>Are there any new monster missions in Secrets of Faydwer? If not, is there any plan to add any in the future?</strong></p>

<p>Secrets of Faydwer does not include new monster missions although we certainly plan to use them again in the future- they just didn’t fit into our plans for this expansion. </p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Your Questions About Secrets of Faydwer</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001552.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-10-06T13:02:25-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1552</id>
    <created>2007-10-06T18:02:25Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week, Loral solicits questions for submission to the Everquest development team regarding the upcoming Secrets of Faydwer.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>We're going to try something different today. Post comments with your questions to the Everquest development team regarding the upcoming Secrets of Faydwer and, after editing and choosing among them, I shall submit them and hopefully receive responses for a future article.</p>

<p>Class specific questions, questions focused on a narrow scope of the game, and pompous jackassery will not be submitted.</p>

<p>Thank you,</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
6 October 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Gencon 2007 Report</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001550.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-08-26T11:49:27-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1550</id>
    <created>2007-08-26T16:49:27Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Loral returns from his four day adventure in the midwest at this year&apos;s &quot;best four days in gaming&quot;, Gencon 2007.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>I began playing Dungeons and Dragons in high school in the 1989. Back then we played 2nd edition which, in retrospect, lacked a lot of the power of the original and current versions of D&D but managed to keep all of the complexity. Somehow we muddled through the rules of Thac0s, the lack of any demon princes and devil lords, and unique stat bonuses for every stat and still have a good time. I remember fondly the time when we battled Lord Manshoon and one of my players swallowed a spider in his big glass of lemonade at the same time.</p>

<p>Since then I've been playing D&D on and off for the past eighteen years, all of it as a DM. I love the low technology of a tabletop role playing game. I love working out the math and the stats myself. I love building a dynamic story at the table based on some themes, plot seeds, and characters I develop beforehand. I love having a group of friends laughing, rolling dice, eating Doritos, and having a good time.</p>

<p>This year my wife and I decided we would go to Gencon, the biggest tabletop gaming convention in the world. What follows is my account of the best four days in gaming. Everquest players take note that only a part of this article will discuss the lands of Norrath so skip ahead if you care not at all for the rest of it.</p>

<p>Stepping into the Indiana Convention Center on Thursday after lunch, I knew I was in trouble. Immediately I became aware that there was no way I would be able to pack in everything I wanted to do in four days. Looking through the phonebook-sized convention guide, one finds thousands of games going on. My wife, having the clearest head of the two of us, had pre-signed us up for a number of excellent events so we didn't have to scramble too much. Knowing what we know now, however, gives us a great idea about how to handle it next year.</p>

<p>Sometimes, while working at our day jobs, watching popular television, and walking around the malls, one forgets just how many geeks and nerds there are in the world. Walking into a convention hall with thousands of people who all know how to calculate a fighter's attack bonus is a wonderful thing. For a brief four days I learned what it would be like to live in a world of geeks and what a wonderful world it would be. Like the EQ Fan Faires, you get to hang out with thousands of people who all share a passion for a hobby that few in the outside world understand at all. Being this passionate about things like gaming, science fiction, and fantasy is a wonderful thing. It defines us when most people are defined only by their job, their family, or their in-depth knowledge of the political subtleties of American Idol.</p>

<p>Going to a tabletop gaming convention in a post MMO world is an interesting experience. The market is still very strong but one can see how the strengths of an MMO shine through. Throughout my eighteen years of D&D the hardest part is finding a good group. I've had about four or five groups in that time and all of them came to me by sheer luck. There has yet to be a good, efficient, and comfortable way to meet new players for a D&D game. This is where MMOs have such a clear advantage. I can log in, hang out in the Plane of Knowledge, and, though it may take some time, find a group of people who want to adventure. That's a pretty amazing thing compared to the trouble it takes to find a good D&D group.</p>

<p>Within the ocean of events and games, we did get to see a couple of interesting things related to EQ. Our first stop was to SOE's <a hre="http://legendsofnorrath.station.sony.com/"Legends of Norrath</a> room. Here SOE employees ran demos of their latest in-game collectable card game. Years ago at the first Fan Faire, I talked to one of the other players on our bus ride to the airport. He mentioned that Smed had asked him what he thought of a Magic: The Gathering style game built into Everquest with certain rare cards as loot drops from in-game monsters and certain rewards that carried over to your character. I hadn't heard anything since but apparently that idea solidified.</p>

<p>Legends of Norrath is a beautiful card game, though much of the rules still escape me. If you've ever tried Magic Online, you'll be familiar with the interface. The artwork and mechanics are very strong. The game can be played within Everquest and Everquest 2 as well as with a stand-alone windows interface. Unfortunately there is no flash-based web version, something I would have loved to play on my Mac.</p>

<p>How much impact a game like this will have on EQ is a good question. If the game is too good, we may see hundreds of zombie "AFK: playing Legends" players in the Plane of Knowledge. Not good enough and it will have as much impact as Gems. Still, it is a strong move for SOE and likely to be one of the bigger gameplay shifts in EQ we're likely to see.</p>

<p>Of special note, I asked both an Everquest developer and an Everquest 2 developer what they thought of Legends. I had wondered whether there was any mistrust of a game that was being wedged in by management into the worlds they develop. Both, without hesitation, said "I love it." Both of them talked about a shaky start to the game but both also mentioned that they and their co-workers have been caught staying after hours at work just to play a little more Legends.</p>

<p>I had the honor to meet Mr. Alan Vancouvering, also known as Absor, at the SOE booth a few times over our weekend at Gencon. Absor gave me a nice walkthrough of some of the new zones for Secrets of Faydwer. When I asked Absor what he best liked about the expansion, he said "clockworks". Given what I saw, there is a lot for Absor to like. The theme of the expansion borders on steampunk with huge roaming mechanical constructs walking across the new lands. Dynamic zoning points will keep players chasing the doorways to the next land of adventure. Given the length of time it can take to get a party together and actually into a dungeon, I am a bit apprehensive about making it already more difficult.</p>

<p>And yes, there are working gnomish catapults.</p>

<p>The expansion is still early but there were some excellent looking NPC models and some beautiful zones. One thing Absor mentioned that sunk my heart a little; the raids in Secrets will be starting at Solterius level and going up in at least two tiers of power. Whatever hope I had about skipping Demiplane has been crushed. SOE still seems to hold on to a philosophy of running players through very old content in order to fully explore the newest expansions, a cycle that has repeated itself since Planes of Power. By the time many players climb through the flagging and gearing requirements to get there, even Secrets may be old and out-dated.</p>

<p>Shifting back to my Dungeons and Dragons passions, Thursday night Wizards of the Coast announced the development and 2008 release of Dungeons and Dragons 4th edition. More and more over the past few months I have frequented the D&D forums and seen what the hard-core D&D players think of a new edition of D&D. Most of these players have all but memorized the current rules and feel very comfortable with 3.5. They have also spent a lot of money on 3.5 rulebooks which, as they see it now, will become obsolete with the release of 4.0.</p>

<p>My own gaming group, much like my Everquest and Warcraft groups, are not as hard core. We play monthly with the players spending little if any time in between games worrying about the rules or their characters. We like getting together, throwing some dice, shouting when we get a critical hit, and having a good time.</p>

<p>However, over the past three years, our characters have grown to level 16. The game begins to get much more bogged down at the higher levels than it does early on. We have gone from five encounters a game in the earliest levels down to two encounters at the higher levels due to the amount of time it takes to make decisions and verify all the rules.</p>

<p>When I heard what 4th edition would be doing, I smiled. They saw the exact same problems I saw. The typical wizard casting system, known as the Vancian system, is being heavily modified into "at will", "per encounter", and "per-day abilities". Watching wizards throw all their spells away in the first couple of battles is no more. Complicated combat systems like Grapple are also being reworked along with, I hope, the complex Cleric Turn Undead rules.</p>

<p>Combat in 4th edition is supposed to return to high speed, fast and fun dice rolling instead of continually referencing the Players Handbook.</p>

<p>My excitement for 4th edition mimics my excitement whenever I hear about new features for Everquest or Warcraft that help bring the game to the level of the hobbyist gamer. Wizards could have focused on developing more and more complex rule-sets for the current batch of gamers, or they can redevelop the system to help bring new players in. It appears they chose the latter.</p>

<p>Chatting with a couple of the Wizards game designers, it became clear that recently published D&D rulebooks like Book of Nine Swords, the warlock in Complete Arcane, and the three spellcaster classes in Tome of Magic all point towards the thinking in 4th edition. The recent D20 Star Wars Saga Edition roleplaying game also hints at some of the streamlining we will likely see in 4th edition. For my own glimpse at 4th edition, I came up with my own set of 4th edition-style house rules for my newest campaign.</p>

<p>One of the people I met at Gencon stated that they schedule in a whole day just to visit the dealer room and, after spending about four hours in there and still not feeling like I got to see everything I wanted, I can understand why. The dealer room is the heart of Nerd Heaven. Game demos are going on constantly. The costumes, ranging from Darth Vader to a very creative Beholder, add a wonderful atmosphere. Bring your wallet, however. I spent about $50 on dice, $50 on other accessories, and about $150 on various D&D miniatures that I just had to have. One disappointment, I had heard wonderful things about the Wizards of the Coast Dungeon Delve, a one-hour full D&D game hosted at the Wizards booth, but with only three tables, it was almost impossible to get a seat and play. I finally rushed their booth at the beginning of the last day and got to play only to be wiped out in the first room by some water elementals. I wish they had run a lot more tables of that. It was too much fun to have so little time playing.</p>

<p>Instead we played a lot of the RPGA dungeon delve, a 20 minute rapid rolling D&D adventure which, should you win, awarded you tokens with which to purchase dice or select minis. I came home with the biggest bag of dice I ever had.</p>

<p>I consider my first run to Gencon to be our recon run for our future years. Here are my recommendations for future visits to Gencon:</p>

<p>1. Sign up early for the True Dungeon. It was absolutely awesome, worth every penny of the high cost, and very hard to get into if you don't get in early. Don't miss it. Make it the first thing you sign up for.</p>

<p>2. Try to sign up for events outside of the dealer room hours. The dealer room is only open 10am to 6pm but the games go on early morning to late at night. If you leave a day open, leave Thursday open since the best wares will be out with the fewest people.</p>

<p>3. RPGA D&D games are a little bit dry but they are consistent. Sign up for some RPGA games to fill in slots of full RPGs.</p>

<p>4. I heard the Paizo Dungeon Crawl Classic games were a good time. I didn't get to go through any of them but I would like to next year.</p>

<p>5. Make a good list of the minis you want to purchase before you go and add to it as you see ones there. Shop around since the prices on the same mini can change a lot depending on the dealer.</p>

<p>6. Bring lots of food and drinks. You'll find yourself with very little time to buy food while you're running around. Bring something that can tide you over for half a day if you find yourself in a four hour game. Go to a Subway early in the day and get yourself a sandwich you can carry with you.</p>

<p>7. Arrive Wednesday night instead of Thursday so you can get all day Thursday, Friday, Saturday, and half of Sunday. You'll use up all that time without any problem.</p>

<p>8. For a quick and fun minis game, try Red Shirt Monster Mash. It's a one-hour game with about ten players all duking it out in a big dungeon. It costs about a dollar fifty but it's a great time.</p>

<p>Going to Gencon reminded me how much I love this hobby, how much the hobby means to me and defines me, and I can't wait to go back next year.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
26 August 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda, Summer 2007</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001548.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-08-11T10:49:56-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1548</id>
    <created>2007-08-11T15:49:56Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week Loral writes up his latest Evil Agenda with a plan to deliver it to Sony Online Entertainment at Gencon 2007.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>It has been 3 years since I first began writing Evil Agendas. It seemed the best way to clarify and simplify the areas I felt would best help Sony improve Everquest. The game has changed greatly since then. Five other Evil Agendas have come out since then. Sometimes the items presented are addressed, sometimes not. Today we look again at the elements that would best help Everquest improve this year.</p>

<p>There are a few factors to consider before attempting to define what might best improve the game. For one, for who are these improvements meant to help? Is there an attempt to bring in new players? Is there an attempt to draw from those who no longer find World of Warcraft satisfying? Is the intent to help keep hard core players continuing to play? Should Everquest continue to refine and polish their high-end raid game? Without knowing the exact strategy SOE employs towards Everquest, I can only guess at what improvements might best help the game meet its goals.</p>

<p>The five areas of improvement listed below assume a desire to bring old players back in, keep existing players playing, and bring in new players where possible. I have stated many of these items before, but I feel they are important enough to keep currently in mind.</p>

<p>1. Rebuild the Plane of Knowledge.</p>

<p>The Plane of Knowledge continues to be one of the top three, if not the most popular, zone in Everquest. The current architecture for the zone is six years old. While SOE has attempted to make new city zones since then such as Abysmal Sea and Crescent Reach, none of these zones has drawn any significant number of players.</p>

<p>Rebuild the Plane of Knowledge and continue to use it as a hub zone for Everquest players of all levels. Build neighborhoods that remind players of the heritage of their characters. Add quests and instances for short duration events at all levels. Make it look good enough and perform well enough to remind us that this game isn't suffering from an eight year history.</p>

<p>2. Add new Player Models.</p>

<p>The existing player models continue to be a legacy from the Everquest of old. The poorly performing and graphically broken Luclin models end up pushing many players back to the original Everquest models developed in 1998. Although we saw a lot of board traffic discussing a new human model, that model, originally discussed a year ago, has not yet been released. Find a faster and more efficient way to release high performance and good looking player models.</p>

<p>3. Focus on 30 to 60 minute events.</p>

<p>With so many newer games out, the tolerance for long-duration events including single group quests, missions, and raids, has gone down. Many players no longer accept long duration 90 minute to two hour events from the older expansions. Shorter events let players get in, have fun, progress, and leave within a time period that is more acceptable to the rest of their lives. Newer games have shown these durations to be possible, rewarding, and fun. Tune these events towards the bulk of the players who go through them, not to those who are able to do them the fastest. Tuning content around the highest power and fastest players ends up hurting the event for everyone else.</p>

<p>4. Reduce flagging restrictions and Remove flags for zones older than two years.</p>

<p>Flagging high-end zones is intended to increase the amount of time it takes high-end raiding guilds to reach the end of any given expansion. When the flags are put in place and tuned, they are tuned towards guilds who raid five to seven days a week for four to six hours. When those expansions become forgotten by those high end guilds, a new tier of guilds, guilds who play fewer nights a week for less hours, then have to overcome those flagging restrictions only with less actual play time.</p>

<p>Remove flag restrictions on end-zones two years after the expansion is released. This will add new life to these zones and help guilds with less time or lower powered players progress quick enough to enjoy the higher-end content in newer expansions. Making a three day raiding guild go through the same steps as a seven day raiding guild strictly because that seven day guild got through content so fast doesn't make sense. Flagging continues to be considered nothing more than a burden to overcome; not something fun and enjoyable.</p>

<p>5. Reduce filler and focus on fun.</p>

<p>Recent expansions revealed more and more content containing large amounts of unentertaining and time consuming encounters. Both single group missions, flagging requirements, and raid zones have become filled with creatures strictly to slow players down. They do not add to the enjoyment of the event. While a certain amount of such encounters are required, they should be reduced from their current number. Going from Tacvi to Anguish to Demiplane have shown an increase in filler mobs. Single group missions also show a large amount of filler mobs before reaching the climax of an adventure. Instead of offering interesting encounters before a climactic battle, it becomes drudgery. Kill X minions to kill 60 minutes before we reach the event we actually intended to play. Reduce tedium and increase fun.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 August 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Are Portable MMOs the Future?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001545.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-07-22T11:29:27-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1545</id>
    <created>2007-07-22T16:29:27Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral pontificates the future of MMOs in the portable gaming world. Could it be the next big leap in massive online gaming.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>In my last article I talked about three gross stereotypes in gamers: the true casual gamer, the hobbyist gamer, and the hard core gamer. I spent most of the article focusing on the attitudes and drive of the hobbyist gamer when compared to the powerful hard core gamer. However, the market for the casual gamer stands to be far greater in number and profit than either the hobbyist or the hard core gamer. Games built for hobbyist or hard core gamers may sell up to ten million copies worldwide for the most popular games released such as Halo 2 and World of Warcraft. Casual games, however, have the potential to sell to everyone else.</p>

<p>World of Warcraft changed the market of MMOs by many orders of magnitude. With its simple gameplay, low system requirements, extremely accessible quest system, and fast level increases; World of Warcraft brought in ten times as many players who had never played massive online games as any previous game published in the U.S.</p>

<p>It is unlikely another game will make as significant an impact on the PC as World of Warcraft. Other games may, in time, achieve the same numbers but it will require an incredible amount of work, a powerful infrastructure, and a lot of luck. Lord of the Rings Online had the most popular fantasy world, a tested infrastructure, and a lot of development. It came out strong and will do well for a long time, but it has no where near the numbers of players that World of Warcraft has. No doubt developers and publishers look at the market for MMOs and realize they have no way to make a dent.</p>

<p>Fertile lands lay open for those with the money, experience, and drive to seed it. The latest generation of gaming consoles all include the infrastructure for successful online games. Microsoft showed how successful a market built around online console gaming can become with Xbox Live. Yet no massive online game has successfully penetrated this market. Publishers have released a few MMO titles on consoles in the past but none have hit enough sales or subscribers to push the market forward. While this is likely due to poor marketing, a poor subscription model, or simply a poor game; publishers no doubt point to these few titles as an example of how MMOs overall would perform on consoles. Doing so is akin to pointing at the first few first-person shooters on consoles and saying a game like Halo can never work.</p>

<p>MMOs will likely make a significant impact on consoles in the next two years. It will only take one or two well done MMOs to push consoles into the realm of powerful massive online gaming. This doesn't, however, impact casual gamers. In order to tap into the market of massive online games for casual gamers, an entirely different platform must be considered.</p>

<p>There are over forty million Nintendo DS portable consoles in the world today. Even three years after release, the Nintendo DS outsells all other consoles. The top selling games on the Nintendo DS are often games with very simple mechanics, very little story, and often on focused game world. Games like Brain Age, Planet Puzzle League, and Nintendogs are hardly considered games by most gamers, yet they successfully tap into markets that games like Halo and Everquest can never touch.</p>

<p>The Nintendo DS has all of the hardware requirements needed for massive online gaming. It has voice input and output. It has built-in wi-fi. It has enough controls, including the touch screen, to accomplish a relatively complex game. Nothing prevents a publisher from releasing a MMO on the Nintendo DS except business and marketing decisions.</p>

<p>Even with 40 million consoles available, the Nintendo DS is dwarfed by a much larger infrastructure of inter-connected platforms: cell phones. There are over one billion cell phones in the world today. They cross all classes and all cultures. They have no pre-defined demographic. Release a game for a cell phone and you can reach just about anyone.</p>

<p>Not all phones have the capability to play games at all, much less network games. The platform varies so greatly that designing any game for all cell phones might prove impossible. However, as very popular phones proliferate like the Motorola Razor and the iPhone, this platform may stabilize.</p>

<p>A MMO for cell phones would hardly resemble any MMO we've seen so far. They'd be more like an online chat program or SMS client than they would a game. People may have avatars that represent them and might be able to engage other players in very simple games, but a full fledged roleplaying game is unlikely. Given the successes of casual games on the PC, game consoles, and portable systems, it is unlikely a casual gamer wants a traditional role playing game anyway. They are more likely to gravitate towards social networking and simple gaming. Over time, however, these games may become richer and richer, letting casual gamers escape into online worlds that shift from the abstract worlds of online chat to more defined worlds like Middle Earth, the worlds of Harry Potter, or more likely Poke'mon.</p>

<p>Now for some predictions.</p>

<p>I predict that in 2008 Microsoft will announce a Halo massive online game for the Xbox 360. The game will be released in 2009 and sell as many copies as Halo 2 and Halo 3. It will have as many if not more subscribers than World of Warcraft and it will begin a new age of massive online gaming on game consoles. Dozens of other console MMOs will be released within 2009 and 2010 but none of them will do nearly as well. All of the articles we've seen about World of Warcraft wrecking the MMO market on the PC will be rewritten to address Halo ruining console MMOs.</p>

<p>I predict that Nintendo or a third-party publisher will release a simple social online game with a persistent world for the Nintendo DS. The game will be similar to Poke'mon Diamond and Pearl except with persistent online play. Most hobbyist and hard core gamers will dismiss the game as overly simple but the sales will outstrip any PC-based MMO. It will also be the first online MMO to capture male and female non-gamers over the age of 30.</p>

<p>I predict that Apple will build an in-house game development team for the iPhone. As iPhone sales continue to increase, Apple will begin to release small and simple games designed for the iPhone. In late 2008, one of these games will include multiplayer and in 2009 Apple will release a massive multiplayer environment akin to online chat mixed with casual games. Again hobbyist and hard core gamers will dismiss this as a rich AOL chat client rather than a game yet it will outsell computer MMOs by a factor of ten.</p>

<p>I predict that computer MMOs will continue to be released but with decreasing sales and decreasing numbers. By 2010 most gamers will have gravitated towards console games for massive online games.</p>

<p>By 2020 over a billion people will be interconnected through portable massive online communities. Hundreds of different games from dozens of different players will let people interact and interconnect in the worlds and environments they find most comfortable. Such environments may be as sterile as an AOL chat room or as rich as Middle Earth. Portable systems will include enough resolution, enough control, and enough bandwidth to let people interconnect in text, voice, and image anywhere on the planet.</p>

<p>By 2030 we'll all be driving across a desert wasteland in supercharged muscle cars in search of gasoline. Our rugged off-road tires will crunch over the billion portable devices that have long since gone dark.</p>

<p>By 3051 robotic alien probes will land on earth and harvest all of the silicone and broken glass to build intergalactic starships.</p>

<p>Or perhaps that is just a MMO I'm about to play.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
22 June, 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Barriers of Online Gaming</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001544.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-06-24T22:19:51-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1544</id>
    <created>2007-06-25T03:19:51Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week Loral takes a look at the difficulties faced by game developers on game focus for those lost in the chasm between hard core gamers and part-time casual gamers.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last week I spent a few hours playing the new Shadowrun demo for the Xbox 360. It is a very interesting evolution in first person shooters (FPSs). Rather than the standard run, jump, and shoot we find in most FPS games these days, Shadowrun adds "new verbs" as the marketing guys like to say. You can run, jump, glide, teleport, blast back, see through walls, resurrect, and heal. You can combine magic, technology, and firepower all as fast as you can hit your bumpers and triggers. It's a pretty amazing game but I'm not going to buy it.</p>

<p>It isn't the game itself that steers me away but the knowledge that I am never going to be good enough to compete with those who will have more time, more skill, and more dedication to it than I will have. Shadowrun focuses exclusively on online play and with an online game, there is no option for me to enjoy it in my own way. Other games like Halo 2 at least had a single player campaign but even those disappointed me when I knew how much energy went into the multiplayer portion of that game, a portion I would rarely play and never enjoy.</p>

<p>I've pontificated at great length on the difficulties of the non-raider in Everquest. For six years I played Everquest dozens of hours a week without ever reaching into the depths of Everquest's high-end raid content. Though I spent extensive time in Everquest, I never broke into the inner circles of high-end raiders until recently. Some players in Everquest, and also now in Warcraft, complain about the lack of support for those who have not the time, skill, or dedication to achieve the highest rewards. This problem isn't exclusive to these games. Recently, on the most excellent <a href="http://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3?http://zdmedia.vo.llnwd.net/o1/Podcasts/051807.mp3">1UP Yours podcast</a> (43 meg MP3 file link), they discussed the barrier of entry for gamers who want to play competitive online games but cannot break into that circle of hard core elite gamers.</p>

<p>Building quality games for hobbyist gamers is extremely hard to do. Most games either focus on hard core elite gamers or focus on extremely short-duration gaming with little room in between. This has been a problem as long as gaming has existed but as games become more and more social, as more players interact with one another within these games, the problem becomes much more apparent.</p>

<p>Simple solutions cannot solve this problem. Adding features that automatically balance difficulties to even out the battleground will clearly show themselves as artificial. Hard core gamers won't like seeing their power limited and the victories of hobbyist gamers will feel hollow.</p>

<p>Before we dig too deep into this discussion, let us lay out some definitions. </p>

<p>Hard core gamers are gamers who have both the skill and the time to become the elite within any particular game. These are the high-end raiders in massive online games like Everquest and Warcraft. These are the guys who have ten times as many kills as the next highest player in Halo 2. These are the guys who make magic in Shadowrun really look like magic. These are the guys who post Youtube videos of themselves playing Freebird on Expert at 95% in Guitar Hero 2. </p>

<p>It would be easy for us to stereotype hard core players as jobless pimply teens hiding in their mother's basement but we'd be wrong. These can, and often are, adults with jobs and kids who just manage to have the time, skill, and dedication to be one of the best in their chosen battleground. Now that video games have hit an age where adults remember playing them throughout their lives, just about anyone can be a hard core gamer.</p>

<p>We can define casual gamers, a term I myself demanded to be tossed into the fires of the nine hells for its constant misuse, as gamers who play for very short periods of time, have little skill for more complex games, and who care little for the games themselves other than as a way to kill a few minutes. Casual gamers play solitare, they play flash games, and they play freecell when their boss isn't looking. They might play a Nintendo DS once in a while. They're the masses of people who still fawn over the bowling game for their Nintendo Wii. Any gamer who would take the time to read a message forum, read an article, or listen to a podcast about gaming spend very little time considering true casual gamers. We don't even consider them gamers. The marketing groups for the big gaming companies consider them constantly, however. They're building hundreds of new cell phone games a year just for this market.</p>

<p>hobbyist gamers is a new term for me. It defines those gamers who still consider themselves gamers but, either due to a lack of time, a lack of commitment, or a lack of skill, cannot break into the ranks of hard core gamers. Unfortunately for them, however, they know what a hard core gamer is. They know what the hard core gamers possess. These hobbyist gamers are the ones with one, two, or even three level 60 World of Warcraft characters but without a single piece of raid gear. They're the gamers who get destroyed dozens of times in an hour of Halo 2. Their corpses litter the battlegrounds of Azeroth.</p>

<p>hobbyist gamers didn't have much trouble in the past. It might take them twice as long, but on single player games, a hobbyist gamer could still complete it. Only on games with extreme difficulty or extreme time requirements would a hobbyist gamer simply quit. Online, however, these gamers face different problems. Instead of running at their own pace, they are in a race with some of the best and most dedicated gamers in the world. They may have done well against automated opponents but against real players they get destroyed over and over again. They feel as though they will never be as good as the hard core gamers and, when competing with them, either directly in combat or indirectly through content progression, they simply want to quit.</p>

<p>What can game manufacturers do to help? The companies that figure this out stand to make a lot more than the companies that focus on either the hard core or the casual gamers. There are no easy solutions, however. Everything must be carefully balanced. Double experience bonuses, instanced adventures, high-end loot purchasing systems; all of these have helped steer massive online games towards hobbyist gamers. Everquest and World of Warcraft could both reduce the amount of time it takes to complete meaningful group encounters such as the dungeon instances in WoW and the missions in Everquest. </p>

<p>Thirty minutes is all that can be expected when it can, for both of these games, take nearly that long to form a group capable of completing such an event. For player versus player games, there is no clear solution. Ranking systems don't seem to work. Equipment matching doesn't help make up for player experience. Dynamic difficulties are unrewarding for both types of players. Any game that is good enough to get the attention of a hobbyist gamer would likewise get the attention of a hard core gamer so there is no way to focus an entire game directly for hobbyists without also attracting hard core gamers.</p>

<p>The companies that find the right balance stand to make a lot of money. Right now that continues to be primarily single-player games like Zelda Twilight Princess, Crackdown, Grand Theft Auto, and the single player Halo campaigns. The designers of World of Warcraft made some smart decisions early on by keeping leveling fast even when hard core gamers hit maximum character levels in very short periods of time. Games like the multi-player Halo, Shadowrun, Battlefield, and Everquest will continue to reward those who put in the most time, have the most skill, and the highest focus. Many players would say this is as it should be. People trying to sell the games, however, realize the large number of players they're cutting off.</p>

<p>Breaking through the barrier of online gaming for hobbyist gamers is the greatest current challenge of gaming today. There exists a lot of potential for those who seek to break it.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
22 June 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Does a Yearly Expansion Cycle Mean for Everquest?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001540.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-05-05T12:59:14-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1540</id>
    <created>2007-05-05T17:59:14Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week Loral takes a look at the repercussions from SOE&apos;s announcement that it intends to release expansions yearly instead of twice-yearly.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>On 30 April 2007, Everquest's current producer, Clint Worley, announced that SOE would begin a yearly development cycle for Everquest expansions beginning this November and taking place every November thereafter. Today we discuss the possible impact of this large strategic change in Everquest's development.</p>

<p>During the original Everquest Community Summit SOE stated that predictable population drops occurred between expansions. The population would also predictably rise every time a new expansion was released. SOE argued that six-month development cycles helped keep the population more steady than the peaks and valleys seen in yearly expansions. Now SOE moves back to the yearly expansions, a release cycle we haven't seen since the release of Planes of Power.</p>

<p>This recent change brings up many more questions than answers. For example, what will this do to the development team itself? Will SOE reduce the amount of money spent over the year? Will the same number of developers remain on the staff throughout the year-long development cycle? How does this affect the developer's salaries? If it lowers the amount of money they earn, will they be more likely to find other projects?</p>

<p>What will this do to the product itself? Will the cost increase? Some players speculate that the cost will likely go up to $40 per expansion. A yearly release of the entire Everquest collection including all previous expansions and one new expansion could be another strategy. With the strength of competing MMO expansions such as Blizzard's Burning Crusade expansion for World of Warcraft, SOE may have a hard time selling an Everquest expansion for the same cost.</p>

<p>What will happen to the in-game population over the year? Will the lands of Norrath become barren during the summer months? Video and computer game releases often relax during the summer months, hoping to focus attention closer to the holidays. The number of people playing Zelda: Twilight Princess during the summer matters very little to the overall health of any single player's experiences, but a reduced population in an MMO affects each player who wishes to play - especially in a game with a very clear focus on group and raid encounters.</p>

<p>What caused SOE to make this radical change? The quality of expansions released in the spring has always lagged behind the quality of expansions released in the fall. What happened recently to make them decide that a yearly release was a better idea? Was it the clear lack of quality in spring releases or some other decision based on player metrics and business trends?</p>

<p>What will SOE do with those extra months? Will we see larger expansions like Omens of War, The Serpent's Spine, or even Planes of Power? Will SOE return to a multi-tiered model where even high-end raiders need to progress through multiple sets of end-zones in order to complete all of the raids in a single expansion? Will SOE use the time to debug, tune, balance, and polish the release? We can certainly hope.</p>

<p>Why would SOE tell us this now? Perhaps they tell us to help quiet the voices that complain about the current twice-yearly release cycle or perhaps they are setting us up for future changes yet unheard.</p>

<p>It will be nearly nineteen months before we see the true result of this change. The November release this year gives SOE two more months to improve this fall's expansion but we won't see the full result of a yearly development cycle until fall 2008. That's a long way off and a lot can happen. With the recent release of Lord of the Rings Online and the upcoming Age of Conan, the competition for massive multiplayer online role playing games gets thick. Blizzard will no doubt release another expansion for World of Warcraft in that time. Rumors speak to a new Blizzard MMO release as well, possibly announced in May. This is also the first full year with consoles being able to fully support massive online games without any hardware modifications or additions. What will the population in Everquest be like when the MMO universe has many alternate worlds to explore and half a year before Norrath sees changes to its landscape?</p>

<p>The console market is ready for a good powerful console-based massive online game. All of these things may drastically change the landscape between now and the first full-year expansion release for Everquest since Planes of Power.</p>

<p>We will end this discussion with a few predictions and a few things to monitor over the next year.</p>

<p>First, I predict the next expansion will be a large one with a level increase, possibly even to 85, and multiple tiers of single-group and raid progression. The expansion will have to include a large amount of progressive encounters and rewards to keep people playing throughout most of 2008. It may also include a large amount of solo content, and may need to if the populations do begin to lower over the summer of 2008. I hope we begin seeing more regular releases of new player models. SOE cannot include new models in an expansion if they plan to change them for everyone, but it is clearly the most outdated feature of Everquest right now. Overall, I expect this year's expansion to be a big one, on the order of Omens of War, The Serpent's Spine, and maybe even Planes of Power.</p>

<p>Over the next year we should continue to watch the population of Everquest. I expect we may see a server merger in the spring of 2008 to off-set the reduced amounts of players over the summer. We should also keep an eye on the development staff itself. If we start to see some of the bigger names moving on to newer projects, that could bode poorly for the game overall. Eventually Everquest will make that transition from a fully developed and marketed product to one of maintenance and upkeep. This next year may be the time we see this switch.</p>

<p>At this time we have far more questions than answers. We can keep our fingers on the silk strands of our web, feeling for the vibrations that will tell us more of what may come to pass, but for now, the web remains still.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
5 May 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Is SOE Abandoning Everquest?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001538.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-04-21T10:01:40-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1538</id>
    <created>2007-04-21T15:01:40Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral answers a question on the minds of many current Everquest players. Is Everquest dead yet? Is it dying? Has SOE forgotten the face of its father? Is SOE abandoing Everquest? Let us ponder the matters at hand.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Almost since its birth, players have been asking about the possible death of Everquest. Any game requiring a company's commitment as much as a massive online game will put doubt in the minds of the players. What  happens if the company loses its motivation to maintain the game before the players lose the motivation to play? The remaining players of Asheron's Call 2 found out when it closed down shortly after an expansion's release.</p>

<p>Let's take a look at the current status of Everquest.</p>

<p>Is Everquest dead? That requires a personal definition for a dead MMO. For the sake of this article, I will define MMO death as the lack of any support at all. Only when the servers are shut down, when all the developers are moved off to other projects, when all the support shuts down, and when players are unable to play; only then is a MMO really dead. Everquest is a long way from dead.</p>

<p>Is EQ dying? As long as new expansions continue to be produced and released and as long as there are enough players to allow groups and raids to face existing encounters, a MMO isn't dying. By this definition, Everquest is not dying.</p>

<p>But back to the original question: Is SOE Abandoning Everquest?</p>

<p>This is a harder question to define but let us consider a few known variables.</p>

<p>SOE is a different sort of company than other massive online game producers. While other MMO companies might focus on a single title, SOE has built a business around running multiple games with the same back-end infrastructure. They act as a MMO service provider. Not only do they run games with few actual players but they even pick up games that might be struggling. Matrix Online is one such example.</p>

<p>One element easily used to gauge the health of Everquest is to watch Everquest Online Adventures. EQOA has a lot of difficulty to overcome. It is a console title for an older system. It required specialized hardware, a wired network adapter and keyboard, to run. It had very little expansion or patch potential since patches had to fit within a Playstation 2 memory card. How EQOA ever got out the door is somewhat of a miracle. It isn't a bad game but it required a lot of work from the player to even get started.</p>

<p>Everquest Online Adventures still operates today, four years after its original release. With the release of the Playstation 3, it would still seem that EQOA's future is even more bleak but still it hangs on.</p>

<p>EQOA is the MMO we should watch to see just how long SOE will keep a MMO alive before deciding to pull the plug. Right now it would appear that any loss SOE accepts in relation to EQOA is low enough to make it worth keeping around. They can lower this loss by tying it into the rest of the server, network, and support infrastructure used by all of the other games they support.</p>

<p>This broad MMO infrastructure means that any of the SOE-branded MMOs are likely to stay online for a very long time. EQ, as one of the more popular SOE MMOs, is no exception.</p>

<p>SOE continues to announce and release new expansions for Everquest twice a year. While some, like the Serpent's Spine, have more to offer than others, like Prophecy of Ro, a lot of new content gets released every year into a game now eight years old.</p>

<p>SOE recently made a strategic decision that had many questioning the health of the game. The Serpent's Spine, an expansion intended to bring new players into the game by offering a new player race and large hunting areas, quests, and encounters for levels 1 to 75, was released only digitally. They did not sell it retail and did not offer a boxed version. For an expansion intended to bring new players into EQ, this seemed a strange decision. This practice continued with the Buried Sea.</p>

<p>This shift to online only releases seems to dictate that SOE has changed its philosophy in relation to EQ. Rather than attempt to bring new players into EQ, SOE hopes to bring older players back to EQ and keep current players playing. Given the very stiff competition of World of Warcraft, this might be a smart move. In the mind of one pompous egotistical high elf, EQ cannot compete with World of Warcraft for new players.</p>

<p>SOE recently announced the release of a new compilation pack for Everquest called the Everquest Anniversary Edition. This $20 boxed package will be available retail and includes Everquest and every current expansion. That is an amazing deal considering that, for us old timers, the base game and all thirteen expansions cost about $400. The release of the Anniversary edition could do a better job of bringing in new players than the release of the Serpent's Spine. Only time will tell.</p>

<p>What of Everquest 2? How does it relate to SOE's attitude towards EQ? We cannot know what is in the minds of the management at SOE but we can make assumptions on their overt behavior.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 cost a lot of money and a lot of that money likely came from Everquest's profits. SOE put a lot into the technology and marketing of EQ2 going so far as to release an entirely new set of player models strictly to market to Asian gamers. One cannot help but wonder if the money spent on Asian-friendly player models might instead have been spent on new player models for Everquest. Since the first days players asked for new player models we heard that the costs were simply too high. Yet a short time later SOE announces the release of new player models for EQ2. It is possible that these models were financed by the Taiwanese developer of Everquest 2, Soga, but I could never get a clear answer when I asked this question to SOE.</p>

<p>While SOE chose to release The Serpent's Spine download only, they still released and heavily marketed Echos of Faydwer Everquest 2 expansion to retail shelves. Again one could speculate that this shows SOE's desire to market only one of these games to new players. We cannot know the exact resources SOE spends on one game over another but we can safely speculate that EQ2 takes up significantly more resources than EQ. When one company runs two games, or in this case even more, there are times when its resources have to go one way or another.</p>

<p>What does this all mean for existing Everquest players? Not much. As long as we desire it, Everquest is likely to continue. As long as expansions are profitable, we will continue to see them every six months. As long as SOE has a team of artists, designers, and programmers dedicated to Everquest, we should continue to see improvements in the game.</p>

<p>There are areas where SOE's focus on EQ2 hurts Everquest, however, and it is important that our voices are heard. Better quality control, new player models, better server and network stability, and improved exploitation prevention are all important topics to existing EQ players. These requests also require significant resources and only by speaking out can we clearly show SOE that it needs to spend the required resources Everquest deserves.</p>

<p>Is SOE abandoning Everquest? Only if we let them.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
22 April 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Late, Incomplete, and Pessimistic Review of the Buried Sea</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001536.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-04-02T23:23:09-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1536</id>
    <created>2007-04-03T04:23:09Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Loral takes a micro-slice of the Buried Sea, examines it in a little petri dish, and doesn&apos;t like what he finds.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>In the book "The Little Guide to your Well Read Life", Steve Leveen offers recommendation on choosing the right book to read. His first rule is simple. If you don't like a book after fifty pages, close the book and move on. Time is too valuable and there are too many good books out there to waste it on a book you don't enjoy. You may miss out on a book that gets considerably better after the past fifty pages but is it really worth slogging through material you don't like to find out?</p>

<p>I have a similar philosophy with console games. If a console game doesn't grab me in the first two hours of play, it's better to shelf it and play something I like. The only game I've played in the past few years that didn't follow this theory was Zelda: Twilight Princess on Wii. Zelda got considerably better after the first six hours or so and became the best console game I've played since God of War even with a very weak beginning. Gears of War, Crackdown, Elite Beat Agends, The New Super Mario Brothers; these games all grabbed me within the first ten minutes and never let go.</p>

<p>In my preview of The Buried Sea I talked about all of the basic features that the expansion had: sixty instanced group missions, two new sets of point-based loot, seven huge uninstanced zones and a whole variety of new mobs to fight. It all looked very exciting but given the preview alone, I had no idea if those sixty missions were actually any good.</p>

<p>I haven't played the Buried Sea nearly as much as previous expansions, but with the few missions I have tried, I found the answer to that question. They're not.</p>

<p>On a Sunday afternoon a few weeks past, myself and a group of friends tried out three of the missions involving the lost love of of some pirate. These are pirate missions, from the first set of missions one can acquire. These are supposed to be the easiest missions available, missions for sub level 75 low-geared characters and we were geared in Anguish level equipment.</p>

<p>Even getting to the instances proved a challenge. You talk to one NPC to receive the mission and then must purchase a ticket for one of two different boats (if they tell you which one you are supposed to take, I missed it) which will take you to the instance. Once you figure it out, you'll know it the rest of your days but it wasn't clear at all how the tickets worked until you actually got a mission and had someone point out the boat you need to take.</p>

<p>The missions themselves include a lot of the same "pick up 10 siren head" collection quests we've seen before. Each mission seems to have a conclusion, however, that takes you away from the standard. Unfortunately the drop rates for the collection quests are extremely chaotic - one time we received ten quest items out of ten within the first twenty kills, another time it took us two hours to get the same ten. Rather than focusing the missions on the exciting conclusions, the missions force you through tedius collection or kill X steps.</p>

<p>The third quest in line gives you two tasks: kill thirty sirens and collect ten siren heads. First of all, I can't imagine how a sirin won't have a head after we kill her, but more importantly, we shouldn't kill fifteen of our thirty sirens and only get one head. What is the point in having the "kill 30 sirens" if we'll need to kill ninety to get the heads we need? Well, it turned out that once you complete either step a ship wrecks and you must rescue the crew. Perhaps the ambushing sirens all have heads but we never found out because all ten to twelve sirens attacked us at once and wiped out our party. By this time we had enough. We quit the quest and called it a day. At least three of us planned to switch to Warcraft that afternoon.</p>

<p>Three missions out of sixty is probably not enough of a sampling to make a full judgement. The other fifty seven missions might all be wonderful dynamic stories and adventures. Perhaps it's only those three that are so poorly tested or developed. I should really spend more time playing through more of the missions before snapping to a judgement about The Buried Sea. What I have seen so far is a lot of running around in huge complex zones to hunt down instances and hope that something along the mission doesn't get fowled up along the way.</p>

<p>My time is the most important commodity I have. I only have a few hours every week to play these games. More and more hobbies take up that time and I have to decide exactly where my time is best spent. Should I keep trying to slog through poorly designed missions until I find the ones that are good enough, well tuned enough, and rewarding enough to spend my time? Or should I go somewhere where I know the sort of output I am likely to expect?</p>

<p>The Burning Crusade has some problems. Last weekend I made a spectacle out of myself in the general channel when my level 62 character had to collect owl feathers for a drunken dwarf. The feathers rarely dropped on big white owls that killed me faster than the demons of the Gate. What sad state in my hunter's career had I reached when my job as a Hunter of the Outlands is to collect feathers from owls? Needless to say, I dumped that quest and moved on.</p>

<p>That's not the only example of a poorly designed quest in WoW. It has lots of problems. However, per hour played I have more fun in WoW than I do in EQ. Granted it isn't doing what I prefer doing - grouping with friends - but it offers a better tangible and intangible reward for the time I spend. And the Burning Crusade only cost $10 more than the Buried Sea.</p>

<p>Tonight I went in with five of my guildmates to complete "Locating the Statue". We defeated the four statue guardians. We defeated Brendanus Riordan even with his billion hitpoints. We examined the statue of Prexus. I even took a screenshot. The transcript, however, never showed up in anyone's inventory. So now what, do the quest again? We spent our two hours. We finished the steps. Why should we have to do it again and hope that this time it isn't bugged? I wasted one evening, why waste another?</p>

<p>I'll likely get back into the Buried Sea and find some missions that I enjoy. At this point, however, I'm far more likely to have others slog through those painful poorly-tuned missions and tell me on the forums or in chat banter which ones are worth my time and which are not.</p>

<p>In the mean time, however, when ever asked by a new player which massive online game to play, I have little reason to point them anywhere else but World of Warcraft. It's a better game.</p>

<p>The Buried Sea has an excellent list of features but my first fifty pages makes me want to put the book back on the shelf.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 April 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Player Models in Everquest</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001535.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-04-01T11:21:25-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1535</id>
    <created>2007-04-01T16:21:25Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">After seven years, Everquest finally receives the new player models it so richly deserves. They may not look great but the performance should be spectacular!</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>It only took seven years (five if you count from Luclin) but we finally got our new player models.</p>

<p><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/mshea01/EverquestAprilFools">Be careful what you ask for...</a></p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
1 April 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Overhead of Social Gaming</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001532.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-03-10T08:58:22-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1532</id>
    <created>2007-03-10T13:58:22Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral goes on a bit of a rant, describing the inherant overhead and difficulty associated with multiplayer gaming. Sometimes it&apos;s good to be alone.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Three weeks ago I wanted to sit down, relax, and play Call of Duty 3 on my Xbox 360. I put in the disc, booted up the 360, began loading up my saved game, and within 30 seconds "Soandso invites you to a game". I don't want to play multiplayer, I want to play single player. I decline the invite, disconnect myself from Xbox Live, and start playing again. But now I feel guilty. The guy who sent me the invite is a friend I haven't seen in awhile. All he wanted to do was go around shooting some newbs. What sort of ass do I have to be to disconnect from Live and play a single player game? So now I'm playing single player Call of Duty 3, sitting through the same stupid movie sequence I've seen fifty times, and feeling like an ass because I just blew off a friend of mine. </p>

<p>When did this sort of guilt infect our game play? Why should I feel bad for not wanting to connect to online games? When did these feelings of remorse and duty move us to play games we don't really want to play?</p>

<p>Often in war we hear soldiers say they aren't fighting for some doctrine or political mantra but for the buddy next to them. They're there to protect the friend sitting in the trench at their side. Like the Greek Phalanx, their shield protects the man to their left. They may not want to be in the war in the first place. They may disagree with the politics or the doctrine or the strategy or the tactics, but they are there because if they weren't, their friend's flank goes undefended.</p>

<p>Perhaps it is this philosophy that guide us to play games when we don't really want to play. How many times have I played Everquest for three or six or nine hours when my only real reason for being there was that other people could use my help? I didn't enjoy it. Likely I had played through the event many times. For example in the Plane of Sky for example, but the only reason I was there was because I knew that some warrior needed his sword or some mage needed a crown. Tunare knows I asked the same from others.</p>

<p>I never booted up Final Fantasy 7 because I was afraid Red XIII wouldn't like me if I didn't. That same pressure doesn't exist in single player games. I am reminded of those old Japanese LCD keychains where one had to take care of a virtual dog. Leave the virtual dog in a desk drawer for a week and you'd see this little sad dog, ribs showing, and sitting in its own filth. Who needs to feel the pressure of care and feeding from a device powered from a watch battery? </p>

<p>Single player games have very little guilt associated with them. You might feel pressure to finish a game even if you're not really enjoying it. You might consider it a waste of money if you don't spend some time on it. Right now I feel the desire to play Final Fantasy IV on my Nintendo DS not because its so wicked fun, although I do enjoy it when I play, but because I spent $30 on it and it's not seeing a lot of use.</p>

<p>As I write this I turn 70 degrees to my left and ask my wife, who is helping out a group in Everquest kill some tentacled cyclopean horror, if she *wants* to be doing what she's doing. "I don't mind it," she said "But I wouldn't be doing it if I wasn't asked to help." For a Saturday morning gaming activity, that isn't exactly a rave review. Yet this isn't uncommon in our MMO gaming. At best, it's something to do. At worst, it's stealing our own free time to focus on the desires of someone else. It is our desire to help others that drives us to spend our time in a game doing things we don't really want to do. When will that madness stop?</p>

<p>Twice before I wrote articles about the true strength of massive online games lying with the other players. The games themselves aren't the most exciting games ever created. There are bosses in God of War that outstrip just about every creature battled in a thousand hours of content in Everquest. It's the excitement of working with a team of other players, using our character's abilities as a part of a great mob-killing machine that drives us to play.</p>

<p>That strength can also be a detriment. Playing games with other players adds an overhead to our gaming experience. For every player added to a game, a hunt, or an event, there is the difficulty of coordination, scheduling, training, skill, and group balance. Blizzard knew this and designed World of Warcraft so that most of the game can be played without any of that overhead. A player can solo his or her way from level 1 to level 70. A lot of the most exciting events require a group and the overhead of building and leading that group often moves us to go back and collect 8 owl feathers simply because it's a lot easier to do so. There's no overhead and no guilt if you decide to leave after only collecting one.</p>

<p>I've spent a significant piece of my life over the past six years playing massive online games - Everquest in particular. I have over 10,000 hours logged in to my primary character. I've had a lot of fun over that career. Most recently my guild defeated Vishimtar in one of the best, most stressful Everquest battles I ever faced. I don't think I recall feeling so good after a game battle as I did then simply because of the added complexity and added responsibility floating on top of the 53 other players at the event.</p>

<p>The designers of massive online games would do well to recognize the overhead of multiplayer gaming. They should strive to make it as easy as possible for players to gather and get into the action.</p>

<p>At the same time, saying that all games will eventually go multiplayer is nonsense. Games like God of War and Zelda, Twilight Princess show us that there is a lot of room left for games that let players just sit back and play without having to worry about the social overhead of multiplayer gaming. Massive online games have the wonderful ability to, beyond any game style in the past, bring people together, help us meet new friends, and enjoy cooperative and competitive games far more than we ever could before. Other times, however, it's nice to be alone.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 March 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Anatomy of a Quest</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001530.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-02-18T09:49:47-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1530</id>
    <created>2007-02-18T14:49:47Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral takes a look at the changes in quest systems over the years and helps clarify what separates a good quest from a bad one.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Though in many different formats and many stages of success, quests have always been a cornerstone in massive online roleplaying games. From the earliest hidden quests in Everquest to the constant continuing stream of quests in World of Warcraft, we have seen quests evolve and grow. Today we will pick apart a variety of quest systems and attributes, studying them, poking them, and understanding what makes a good quest and what makes a bad one. Let us begin.</p>

<p>In the early days, there existed little to the quest system in Everquest. Possessed items tracked progress through quests. One talks to quest giver A to receive a bag. Hand the bag to quest fellow B and receive a note to give to quest fellow C for a new shining sword. Lose the bag or the note and you lose progress. This changed during the Planes of Power where character flags could keep track of a character's progress through quests. The quest system did little to help characters track their quests.</p>

<p>During Lost Dungeons of Norrath, Sony added a new system called the "adventure" system. Now a group of players could receive a single quest for the party, enter an instance designed around that quest, and complete the task to receive adventure points for new gear. Though limited to four quest types; collection, kill X, kill boss, or rescue; this system would evolve into the mission system contained in Dragons of Norrath, Depths of Darkhollow, and the recent release of The Buried Sea. The adventure / mission system would be a quest mechanic that continues to elude Blizzard in World of Warcraft.</p>

<p>World of Warcraft completely changed how people thought about quests. From the first ten minutes of adventure, the quest system clearly becomes the game people actually play. A vast world of scorched earth, snowy peaks, and lush forests surrounds eight million players who stare at their quest log in a futile effort to get back to that first moment of pure bliss: an empty quest log.</p>

<p>The quest log for World of Warcraft BECAME the game people played. Quests went in, quest steps were followed, quests were completed, new quests came in. Quests moved players from city to city, showed them the lands around them, and showed them the variety of creatures to slay. Quests in World of Warcraft help level and equip characters from their first level to their last.</p>

<p>At the Austin Game Conference keynote, Rob Pardo of Blizzard explained how quests drove everything in World of Warcraft. They're used to show the player the variety of areas and encounters. They help new players fit right into the game and understand basic concepts that they'll hold throughout their career. World of Warcraft is a game driven by quests. The quests in World of Warcraft ensure that players always have a purpose and always have a goal.</p>

<p>What makes a good quest? A good quest should contain just enough story to motivate a character but not so much that the player simply skips it. Every quest takes attention away from every other quest. Players want to move forward, not spend time considering every plot shift in a detailed storyline that really comes down to "collect four glowing rocks".</p>

<p>Quests should clearly represent their scope. This is one where WoW fails. Players should clearly recognize the quests with long multi-step story arcs as something different from the one-time collection quests. While the first steps don't have to be the most exciting events in the game, it should be clear that those early steps will lead to a much greater reward. Currently in WoW, the only way to know that a quest is an arc is either to look it up on a website or learn about it from someone else.</p>

<p>Quests should bring players together, not set them apart. Everquest's mission system is currently the most advanced quest system for bringing players together, giving them all a single goal, and giving them the environment they need to accomplish it. Rewards from these group quests should be greater than anything they could achieve as an individual. If the intent is to strengthen the relationships between players in an MMO, soloing should not be more productive than grouping.</p>

<p>Consider the differences between World of Warcraft's instances and the mission system in Everquest. In World of Warcraft, players will decide on their own that it is probably within their interests to hunt in an instance. They might ask their friends along, ask nearby players, or use the "Looking for Group" systems to find other interested players. When they get together, they might share quests for that instance, although any player who has already accomplished a quest cannot repeat it nor can anyone share a quest from within a quest chain. Individuals may be at different parts in their quests. Player A might only need three more "silver ores" while Player B still needs seven. This drives a wedge between players. Instead of all players working on a common goal, each player is in it for himself or herself.</p>

<p>The Everquest mission system assigns a quest to every member in a group. If anyone in the group completes any of the steps, it is completed for the group. The group is treated as a single entity and this helps tie the group together. The goals of each member is the exact same as the goals for the group.</p>

<p>Quests should also empower a player, not drag them down. When players feel like their are doing menial chores, they feel like their only motivation to finish is the specific tangable reward. The term "grinding" becomes frequently attached to such quests. Collecting eight owl feathers at level 62 doesn't show a player how powerful they have become. It isn't worthy. If one offers such a quest, one better make it a quick one.</p>

<p>Quests should always reveal the reward and let the player decide if it is worthwhile. Both Everquest and World of Warcraft include this feature though neither does it well for quest arcs. If I am beginning a five-step quest arc, I should know what rewards I will receive for completing the whole arc.</p>

<p>While the high number of Warcraft quests helps players always walk through small tangible quests over their character's career, they do build in a frantic drive to get from Point A to Point B. It isn't easy to point out exactly why, but World of Warcraft is far from a relaxed game. The constant drive to find and finish quests takes away from the player's ability to find his or her own quest or path through the world. Though it is easy to say that the World of Warcraft system removed the desire to sit and camp in a single hunting spot simply to earn experience, some of the freedom of the game is lost in the process. No doubt the World of Warcraft system is an improvement, but there still remains room for further improvement.</p>

<p>Every two years we see a drastic improvement in how massive online games improve in gameplay. From the simple item-based retrieval quests in Everquest to the mission system, to the constant tracking and progress of quests in World of Warcraft, each generation seems to bring new and exciting ways to play in these online worlds. Who can tell us what the future holds.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
19 February 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Preview of the Buried Sea</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001528.html" />
    <modified>2007-10-24T20:11:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2007-02-01T06:31:08-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2007://7.1528</id>
    <created>2007-02-01T11:31:08Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week Loral takes an extended tour through the new lands found in Everquest&apos;s thirteenth expansion, the Buried Sea.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Earlier this week I had the opportunity to walk through the new lands found within the thirteenth Everquest expansion, the Buried Sea, available 13 February 2007. Today I will discuss my experiences and discoveries as I walked the lands of the Buried Sea.</p>

<p>The Buried Sea contains seven new overland zones as well as over 60 instanced missions. The overland zones are huge, with some reports that crossing from one side to the other can take fifteen minutes or longer. The expansion's namesake zone, The Buried Sea, has seven islands spread across a large sea. Each of these islands acts as its own adventuring area with large boats and player-controlled rowboats shuttling players from island to island.</p>

<p>The expansion is split into two major areas, the pirate sea-faring area and the underwater Combine city of Katta Castrum. While many spend much attention on the pirate aspect of the expansion, I found the combine city to be the richer of the two areas - with ties to Rathe mountains, Luclin, and even Planes of Power.</p>

<p>The overland zones include a newly revamped Toxxulous Forest, The Buried Sea, Katta Castrum, the Jewel of Atiiki, Thalassius, Zhisza the Shissar Sanctuary, Silyssar, and the ultra-high-end Solteris - the Throne of Ro. The single-group zones range in difficulty from level 55 through Direwind, Valdeholm, Frost Crypt, Ashengate, and post-Ashengate in difficulty. Unlike The Serpent's Spine, the entirety of this expansion's content will focus on level 55+ characters.</p>

<p>The zones range in geography from islands among a great sea, to small pocket-environments encapsulated in magical shells deep under the water. The Buried Sea contains Egyptian-style ruins, ancient temples of the Shissar, a huge combine city that reminds us of Sanctus Seru, and the scorched homeworld of Solusek Ro.</p>

<p>Instanced missions make up most of the content within the Buried Sea. These six-person events range in duration from 30 minutes for sea-battles to 60 to 90 minutes for missions similar to the ones we saw in Dragons of Norrath and Depth's of Darkhollow. The missions start with lower-powered level 65 missions in the pirate area and escalate to level 70 and 75 missions in the Combine city. The Shissar missions will prove to be the most challenging set.</p>

<p>Like Dragons of Norrath and Lost Dungeons of Norrath, The Buried Sea will contain a point-based loot system. Players will earn points on each successful mission and can use these points to purchase new equipment and items at loot vendors in the pirate and combine areas. While the power of this armor is still changing, it looks like the most powerful set of armor purchasable from single group missions, once powered up with an Energeian powersource described below, will rival Anguish-level equipment.</p>

<p>The point system will be split into three tiers: pirates, Combine, and raid. Points earned on pirate missions can only be used to purchase lower-power items while Combine missions reward points used to purchase higher-powered equipment. There is a little overlap between the highest power pirate rewards and the lower powered Combine rewards. </p>

<p>The point rewards for these missions will also shift as missions become more or less popular. This will avoid bottom-feeding for points on the easiest or fastest missions like we saw on Creator missions in Dragons of Norrath.</p>

<p>This point system will also extend into the ultra-high-end raids in Solteris. Very powerful equipment can be purchased with points earned from these very difficult raids.</p>

<p>The Buried Sea includes a new type of equipment, the Energeian power source. This new inventory slot can contain a power source that can affect any of the new armor acquired in the Buried Sea expansion through drops or vendors. It is these power sources that add unique effects to the somewhat generic point-based loot.</p>

<p>The raids contained within the Buried Sea will focus almost entirely on difficulties above that found in The Serpent's Spine. The one raid zone, Solteris, is intended to be extremely challenging for current players. Giant beams of focused sunlight are able to scorch characters for over 100,000 damage. Solteris is built into tiers much like the islands in the original Plane of Sky raid zone. According to SOE, a raiding guild that makes it half way will have major bragging rights.</p>

<p>There are no monster missions in this expansion but SOE hasn't given up on them. We will see new monster missions entering the game in the future.</p>

<p>During the preview, SOE revealed that they are planning to release a new human model based on their work with the Drakkin model in The Serpent's Spine. This model will be seen on human NPCs in the Buried Sea. After this expansion's release, SOE plans to test the models out with the players and release them once they feel they are ready.</p>

<p>Two other new features round out this expansion: Fellowships and Guild Banners. Each of these features is targeted to a different play style. </p>

<p>Fellowships will help smaller groups of players with less time available get together faster and begin hunting. The fellowships will let three players in a group summon the other three directly to a hunting area. Fellowships also dedicate a chat channel for each fellowship even if ungrouped. It isn't clear what advantage this gives over traditional chat channels or group chat, but we will have to see it in action to judge. Upgraded fellowship campsites can also offer offensive effects, defensive effects, and even illusions to the fellowship. SOE hopes to extend the concept of fellowships but not before the expansion's release.</p>

<p>Guild Banners can be customized by guild leaders and can help a small set of guilded players summon the rest of a guild to a raiding area. Upgraded guild banners can also add beneficial area effects.</p>

<p>My preview of the Buried Sea surprised me. While I expected to see a lot of missions and a new point-based loot system, I didn't expect to see such large overland zones. The artwork in this expansion is excellent and helps bring back memories of our days in Luclin, Planes of Power, and even in the original lands.</p>

<p>It's a hard time to release a new Everquest expansion with all of the attention paid to the Burning Crusade. SOE wisely focused this expansion on Everquest's strength: dynamic mission-based group content. World of Warcraft's unfocused instances don't have the same focus on group missions found in Everquest. As a contrast to the strong static content found in the Serpent's Spine, the Buried Sea has a lot to offer veteran Everquest players.</p>

<p>And now, the <a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/mshea01/BuriedSeaPreview">screenshots</a>.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 February 2007<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>

</feed>