<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://mikeshea.net/rss.css" type="text/css"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

  <channel>
    <title>Mobhunter: Latest Comments</title>
    <link>http://mobhunter.com//comments.xml</link>
    <description>Everquest news, editorials, and commentary.</description>
    <dc:language>en-us</dc:language>
    <dc:creator>loral@loralciriclight.com</dc:creator>
    <dc:rights>Copyright 2005</dc:rights>
    <dc:date>2005-02-28T09:05:08-05:00</dc:date>
    <admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.movabletype.org/?v=3.01D" />
    <admin:errorReportsTo rdf:resource="mailto:loral@loralciriclight.com"/>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>

    <item>
      <title>Solistic said: Extremely well put Horzek. I agree with you, </title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>Extremely well put Horzek. I agree with you, but I actually think Loral is right also.  In this situation SOE is listenning, as the examples of the summoner in the Guild Lobby, where everyone has access to, even if they do not have DoN. Now SOE is listenning, I believe, because they have to either &quot;evolve&quot; with the rest of the gaming industry or die.  To me this is a good sign in the fact that they must think the EQ is still a viable product and they can still make a proffit from it. Or another way to rephrase it, EQ is not dead yet. </description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>Extremely well put Horzek. I agree with you, but I actually think Loral is right also.  In this situation SOE is listenning, as the examples of the summoner in the Guild Lobby, where everyone has access to, even if they do not have DoN. Now SOE is listenning, I believe, because they have to either "evolve" with the rest of the gaming industry or die.  To me this is a good sign in the fact that they must think the EQ is still a viable product and they can still make a proffit from it. Or another way to rephrase it, EQ is not dead yet. </p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T19:53:23-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>direcway said:  mnsmartonlineshops.com &quot; you like somet</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000051.html</link>
      <description> mnsmartonlineshops.com &quot; you like something that in some sense http://directv.smartonlineshops.com/directv.html directv online  isn&apos;t really for you. (Yeah, I know, intentional http://directtv.smartonlineshops.com/directtv.html directtv  fallacy, but I think that&apos;s pretty unavoidable http://dish-network.smartonlineshops.com/dish-network.html dish network  in music, pop at least.) Take for instance http://satellite.smartonlineshops.com/satellite.html satellite  an adult who really, honestly likes the http://satellite-tv.smartonlineshops.com/satellite-tv.html order satellite tv  music of The Wiggles...there&apos;s a certain http://dishnetwork.smartonlineshops.com/dishnetwork.html dishnetwork  irony there, isn&apos;t there? Or imagine if http://direct-tv.smartonlineshops.com/direct-tv.html direct tv  the St Matthew Passion was Richard Dawkins&apos;s http://directway.smartonlineshops.com/directway.html directway  favourite piece of music (plausible enough--scientists direcway  smartonlineshops.comnm</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p> mnsmartonlineshops.com " you like something that in some sense http://directv.smartonlineshops.com/directv.html directv online  isn't really for you. (Yeah, I know, intentional http://directtv.smartonlineshops.com/directtv.html directtv  fallacy, but I think that's pretty unavoidable http://dish-network.smartonlineshops.com/dish-network.html dish network  in music, pop at least.) Take for instance http://satellite.smartonlineshops.com/satellite.html satellite  an adult who really, honestly likes the http://satellite-tv.smartonlineshops.com/satellite-tv.html order satellite tv  music of The Wiggles...there's a certain http://dishnetwork.smartonlineshops.com/dishnetwork.html dishnetwork  irony there, isn't there? Or imagine if http://direct-tv.smartonlineshops.com/direct-tv.html direct tv  the St Matthew Passion was Richard Dawkins's http://directway.smartonlineshops.com/directway.html directway  favourite piece of music (plausible enough--scientists direcway  smartonlineshops.comnm</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T19:48:48-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> said: And to finish the comment,

One man&apos;s ve</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>And to finish the comment,

One man&apos;s vette, is another man&apos;s yugo.</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>And to finish the comment,</p>

<p>One man's vette, is another man's yugo.</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T18:50:09-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> said: ////////////
I loved my 70 Camaro SS but you </title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>////////////
I loved my 70 Camaro SS but you know what I love my 2004 Corvette with AC, CD player, Bose Stereo, Cruise Control, Heated Recarro seats, electronic FI and more HP with better gas mileage much more. 
///////////


Yes but your 70 camaro is still a 70 camaro (excepting any personal modifications you&apos;ve done to it), and you &apos;04 vette is still an &apos;04 vette.

If your 70 camaro slowly evolved into an &apos;04 vette, I doubt you would have many complaints...

However if your 70 camaro evolved (or devolved) into a &apos;04 yugo, someone would be raising hell.
</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>////////////<br />
I loved my 70 Camaro SS but you know what I love my 2004 Corvette with AC, CD player, Bose Stereo, Cruise Control, Heated Recarro seats, electronic FI and more HP with better gas mileage much more. <br />
///////////</p>

<p><br />
Yes but your 70 camaro is still a 70 camaro (excepting any personal modifications you've done to it), and you '04 vette is still an '04 vette.</p>

<p>If your 70 camaro slowly evolved into an '04 vette, I doubt you would have many complaints...</p>

<p>However if your 70 camaro evolved (or devolved) into a '04 yugo, someone would be raising hell.<br />
</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T18:46:17-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Horzek said: I keep pounding on evolving game worlds, in p</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>I keep pounding on evolving game worlds, in particular death penalties as you have seen.  Let me review my experiences with on line games and death penalties.

My first on line game was Ultima Online.  I played for a year and death was horrible there.  Any time you went out of a safe area with guards to hunt or mine or forage you were always at some risk from both players and from the monsters.  If you happened to die, very often all your equipment would be rummaged through and by the time you got back you would be lucky if your sash was still there.  There were many exploits and the game engine would permit you to log out safely then come back on later to find yourself placed in some dungeon or on the steps of a Player Killers door step.

By the time EQ came along, the UO death was very old and annoying.  At the time, and my first look at EQ was back in Beta phase 1 in August of 1998.  During my first month of play I made it all the way to level 6 with a magician.  By todays standards that may seem quite amazing but in those days even at level 6 a single death would cost a full yellow bubble of experience or 20% of your experience.  The game was very very tough and for this amount of risk I was getting fire beetle eyes.  AS the game progressed the experience penalty was greatly reduced so that eventually up to level 1o there was no real death penalty at all.  Even at very high levels these days the death penalty is quite a lot less.  EQ has definately evolved and the game I once played back in 1998 with my over clocked celeron 300a and 16 meg video card now takes up a whole lot more processing power and video performance.  

I was on line one night back then when there was a server wide message that the total on line population of EQ had just hit 200 people.  It was a very different world.  I bet you cant even imagine what it must have been like to look up to level 20 and call those folks the high levels.

I cant say EQ has not evolved because it clearly has.  The evolution was based on player demand, and on improving the fun factor for people playing.  What I am saying is that I would like to see further improvements with the death penalties.  I suppose the other night when I managed to get my druid killed and in a brief death loop I could have taken steps to ress myself using my cleric account.  The cost for that would have been a bit since I have not yet purchased DoN.. I am now leaning towards the purchase though because I am getting all I have ask for.  People are telling me it is fun and the rewards are very nice.  Not having DoN at the time though made corpse recovery much tougher.

I wish to applaud the developers on the concept behind the graveyards in the PoP zones.  This was an idea that was very well received and without doubt appreciated.  You all will remember the Fear raids with the rediculuous death and recovery requirements and even the hate wipes that kept you up hours past your bed time.  For these there is some validity to the risk versus reward idea although not many people today would tell you that the purple grape breastplate I got from hate is worth much today.  

Do you remember the early days of Sol A when upon going into the dungeon you could fall between the steps and burn to death?  Not only would you die, but your corpse was not recoverable because no one could get close enough to ress or pull you out.  Because of a simple game mechanic bug you could die and lose not only your corpse and experience but also all your gear as well.  I remember once going into that zone and seeing one lady there who was in tears and several of her friends who had all died just trying to help her recover her missing body.  At the time the rules were such that a petition to the GMs would not even help because they were not permitted to assist in that sort of corpse recovery.  This could not only ruin  a night of play, it could also ruin a persons experience enough to send them packing.

Yes, EQ has evolved, not always for the best, but it has evolved.  I am merely suggesting another step in this evolution.  For those die hards who can not handle evolution I can only warn you to stay away from tar pits.</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>I keep pounding on evolving game worlds, in particular death penalties as you have seen.  Let me review my experiences with on line games and death penalties.</p>

<p>My first on line game was Ultima Online.  I played for a year and death was horrible there.  Any time you went out of a safe area with guards to hunt or mine or forage you were always at some risk from both players and from the monsters.  If you happened to die, very often all your equipment would be rummaged through and by the time you got back you would be lucky if your sash was still there.  There were many exploits and the game engine would permit you to log out safely then come back on later to find yourself placed in some dungeon or on the steps of a Player Killers door step.</p>

<p>By the time EQ came along, the UO death was very old and annoying.  At the time, and my first look at EQ was back in Beta phase 1 in August of 1998.  During my first month of play I made it all the way to level 6 with a magician.  By todays standards that may seem quite amazing but in those days even at level 6 a single death would cost a full yellow bubble of experience or 20% of your experience.  The game was very very tough and for this amount of risk I was getting fire beetle eyes.  AS the game progressed the experience penalty was greatly reduced so that eventually up to level 1o there was no real death penalty at all.  Even at very high levels these days the death penalty is quite a lot less.  EQ has definately evolved and the game I once played back in 1998 with my over clocked celeron 300a and 16 meg video card now takes up a whole lot more processing power and video performance.  </p>

<p>I was on line one night back then when there was a server wide message that the total on line population of EQ had just hit 200 people.  It was a very different world.  I bet you cant even imagine what it must have been like to look up to level 20 and call those folks the high levels.</p>

<p>I cant say EQ has not evolved because it clearly has.  The evolution was based on player demand, and on improving the fun factor for people playing.  What I am saying is that I would like to see further improvements with the death penalties.  I suppose the other night when I managed to get my druid killed and in a brief death loop I could have taken steps to ress myself using my cleric account.  The cost for that would have been a bit since I have not yet purchased DoN.. I am now leaning towards the purchase though because I am getting all I have ask for.  People are telling me it is fun and the rewards are very nice.  Not having DoN at the time though made corpse recovery much tougher.</p>

<p>I wish to applaud the developers on the concept behind the graveyards in the PoP zones.  This was an idea that was very well received and without doubt appreciated.  You all will remember the Fear raids with the rediculuous death and recovery requirements and even the hate wipes that kept you up hours past your bed time.  For these there is some validity to the risk versus reward idea although not many people today would tell you that the purple grape breastplate I got from hate is worth much today.  </p>

<p>Do you remember the early days of Sol A when upon going into the dungeon you could fall between the steps and burn to death?  Not only would you die, but your corpse was not recoverable because no one could get close enough to ress or pull you out.  Because of a simple game mechanic bug you could die and lose not only your corpse and experience but also all your gear as well.  I remember once going into that zone and seeing one lady there who was in tears and several of her friends who had all died just trying to help her recover her missing body.  At the time the rules were such that a petition to the GMs would not even help because they were not permitted to assist in that sort of corpse recovery.  This could not only ruin  a night of play, it could also ruin a persons experience enough to send them packing.</p>

<p>Yes, EQ has evolved, not always for the best, but it has evolved.  I am merely suggesting another step in this evolution.  For those die hards who can not handle evolution I can only warn you to stay away from tar pits.</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T18:41:44-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loral said: You would call Woody, the guy who said that J</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000051.html</link>
      <description>You would call Woody, the guy who said that John Smedley stole his wallet, a puppet?

http://www.gucomics.com/archives/view.php?cdate=20040526

You might enjoy the idea that the Summit reps are a bunch of puppets but trust me, they aren&apos;t.  I think you need to do a bit more research.

And yes, calling me a puppet borders on personal insult.  If you don&apos;t care for me or these articles, go elsewhere.</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>You would call Woody, the guy who said that John Smedley stole his wallet, a puppet?</p>

<p>http://www.gucomics.com/archives/view.php?cdate=20040526</p>

<p>You might enjoy the idea that the Summit reps are a bunch of puppets but trust me, they aren't.  I think you need to do a bit more research.</p>

<p>And yes, calling me a puppet borders on personal insult.  If you don't care for me or these articles, go elsewhere.</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T18:23:44-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> said: I&apos;ll take the word vs wordperfect analog</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>I&apos;ll take the word vs wordperfect analogy farther and most of you are too young to remember what I am going to talk about.

Wordperfect died due to refusal to change in the face of a changing computer world. Microsoft refused to embrace the web for years and suffered for it themselves. Well long before word was Wordstar it died because they refused to change and become more like Wordperfect, Wordstar was arcane with commands like ctrl-s to save, ctrl-k to exit, etc...but Wordstar superceeded Electric Pencil which was more arcane and refused to change. 

Now how does all this lead to modern MMORPGS? Simple the older products were painful to use but we didn&apos;t realize it at the time and stayed in a state of denial until the public voted with their pocketbooks and drove out the old stodgy imitator to the throne. 

Well lets replace some of those word processors with text muds, EQ1, EQ2, AO, UO, WoW whatever and take a look at the numbers. 

I loved my 70 Camaro SS but you know what I love my 2004 Corvette with AC, CD player, Bose Stereo, Cruise Control, Heated Recarro seats, electronic FI and more HP with better gas mileage much more. 

Same with games you evolve or die.</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>I'll take the word vs wordperfect analogy farther and most of you are too young to remember what I am going to talk about.</p>

<p>Wordperfect died due to refusal to change in the face of a changing computer world. Microsoft refused to embrace the web for years and suffered for it themselves. Well long before word was Wordstar it died because they refused to change and become more like Wordperfect, Wordstar was arcane with commands like ctrl-s to save, ctrl-k to exit, etc...but Wordstar superceeded Electric Pencil which was more arcane and refused to change. </p>

<p>Now how does all this lead to modern MMORPGS? Simple the older products were painful to use but we didn't realize it at the time and stayed in a state of denial until the public voted with their pocketbooks and drove out the old stodgy imitator to the throne. </p>

<p>Well lets replace some of those word processors with text muds, EQ1, EQ2, AO, UO, WoW whatever and take a look at the numbers. </p>

<p>I loved my 70 Camaro SS but you know what I love my 2004 Corvette with AC, CD player, Bose Stereo, Cruise Control, Heated Recarro seats, electronic FI and more HP with better gas mileage much more. </p>

<p>Same with games you evolve or die.</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T18:10:05-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> said: All I gotta say is, if I paid for word, then </title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>All I gotta say is, if I paid for word, then I want word.

If I paid for wordperfect, then I better get wordperfect.

I sure as hell ain&apos;t trying to change *your* word to wordperfect or vice versa, and I sure as hell ain&apos;t gonna let you change *mine* without a fight.
</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>All I gotta say is, if I paid for word, then I want word.</p>

<p>If I paid for wordperfect, then I better get wordperfect.</p>

<p>I sure as hell ain't trying to change *your* word to wordperfect or vice versa, and I sure as hell ain't gonna let you change *mine* without a fight.<br />
</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T16:29:15-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solistic said: Horzek states:
&quot;A few years ago there wa</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>Horzek states:
&quot;A few years ago there was a giant in the world of office programs and their flagship was called Word Perfect. It was hard to use and required a college semester just to be able navigate it well. Those who had put in the time and learned it would swear by it no matter how obviously cumbersome it was.&quot;

Actually it was several years ago that Wordperfect sold their corperation.  Wordperfect was the largest selling software in the world when it sold to Novell.  They had the best customer service and refused to change that.  Since they could not afford the customer service that is the reason they sold.  Novell then sold it to Corel and it is still way better than MicroSoft Word.  Word was designed so that anyone (I mean anyone) would be able to use it with in a couple hours. Word Perfect was designed for the Professionals and the people that wanted to take time to create professional like docuements. 

Two things can be seen from that.  

One, WordPerfect Corp. had the best ethics in the computer world and got out of it when they would have had to compromise their ethics, even though they were still the best seller in the world.


Two, WordPerfect was the best seller because it had a truely complete product (take it from a graphic designer that had to use the old glass disk and cantainer wordprocessors), and gave the customer support for the people that had questions or problems with the product.

Hmmm I could extract both good and bad from this, when compared to EQ.  I guess Sony is just like everyother corperation.</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>Horzek states:<br />
"A few years ago there was a giant in the world of office programs and their flagship was called Word Perfect. It was hard to use and required a college semester just to be able navigate it well. Those who had put in the time and learned it would swear by it no matter how obviously cumbersome it was."</p>

<p>Actually it was several years ago that Wordperfect sold their corperation.  Wordperfect was the largest selling software in the world when it sold to Novell.  They had the best customer service and refused to change that.  Since they could not afford the customer service that is the reason they sold.  Novell then sold it to Corel and it is still way better than MicroSoft Word.  Word was designed so that anyone (I mean anyone) would be able to use it with in a couple hours. Word Perfect was designed for the Professionals and the people that wanted to take time to create professional like docuements. </p>

<p>Two things can be seen from that.  </p>

<p>One, WordPerfect Corp. had the best ethics in the computer world and got out of it when they would have had to compromise their ethics, even though they were still the best seller in the world.</p>

<p><br />
Two, WordPerfect was the best seller because it had a truely complete product (take it from a graphic designer that had to use the old glass disk and cantainer wordprocessors), and gave the customer support for the people that had questions or problems with the product.</p>

<p>Hmmm I could extract both good and bad from this, when compared to EQ.  I guess Sony is just like everyother corperation.</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T16:17:49-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redcloud said: You both are exactly point out why I&apos;m s</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>You both are exactly point out why I&apos;m saying.

Neither of you described a practical way to have risk if you consider that the penalty has to be the same level of fun... Why care then?

See my point?</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>You both are exactly point out why I'm saying.</p>

<p>Neither of you described a practical way to have risk if you consider that the penalty has to be the same level of fun... Why care then?</p>

<p>See my point?</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T13:56:20-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Naladini said: &quot;Within reason, MMORPG manufacturers sho</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>&quot;Within reason, MMORPG manufacturers should seek the fastest path to get a group together, get them hunting, give them a challenge, and reward them for their effort in as short amount a time as reasonably possible. Many of the items in past and future evil agendas focus on this theory.&quot;

While at the same time, allowing players to be as productive as possible if the grouping opportunity doesn&apos;t present itself in fairly short order.
</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>"Within reason, MMORPG manufacturers should seek the fastest path to get a group together, get them hunting, give them a challenge, and reward them for their effort in as short amount a time as reasonably possible. Many of the items in past and future evil agendas focus on this theory."</p>

<p>While at the same time, allowing players to be as productive as possible if the grouping opportunity doesn't present itself in fairly short order.<br />
</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T13:40:51-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loral said: Maybe I&apos;ve lost the point.  SOE put in a</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>Maybe I&apos;ve lost the point.  SOE put in a corpse summoning alter in DoN.  They aren&apos;t about to take it back out and they&apos;d catch holy hell if they tried to up the cost in either cash or experience.

There is certainly a fine line between convenience and too-easy.  A lot of old timers who remember running across Karana with three pumas on your arse at level 10 without bind, gate, port, and a blinking SoW hoping to reach a boat that may or may not dump you in the ocean think the game is too easy now.  However, I&apos;d bet quite a few of them would complain if the knowledge stones turned into dust.

Newer games offered less severe death penalties than EQ1.  Level 50 hunts in Plane of Fear still often resulted in four or five hour chain rescue attempts.  Now we have a corpse summoner with reasonable plat prices and a return to your bind spot.  You can argue if you want that the cost is too low, but I bet new players won&apos;t think so, and a lot of us will grow used to it in the mean time.  I&apos;ve already used it to get out of some CRs that would have taken me an hour or two.  Regardless, it is there now, just like the knowledge stones, and it isn&apos;t going to be removed.  Like the bazaar, the nexus, the wayfarer magi, Knowledge, the PoP graveyards, and the soulbinders, new features get added to reduce the more painful parts of the game.

Within reason, MMORPG manufacturers should seek the fastest path to get a group together, get them hunting, give them a challenge, and reward them for their effort in as short amount a time as reasonably possible.  Many of the items in past and future evil agendas focus on this theory.</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>Maybe I've lost the point.  SOE put in a corpse summoning alter in DoN.  They aren't about to take it back out and they'd catch holy hell if they tried to up the cost in either cash or experience.</p>

<p>There is certainly a fine line between convenience and too-easy.  A lot of old timers who remember running across Karana with three pumas on your arse at level 10 without bind, gate, port, and a blinking SoW hoping to reach a boat that may or may not dump you in the ocean think the game is too easy now.  However, I'd bet quite a few of them would complain if the knowledge stones turned into dust.</p>

<p>Newer games offered less severe death penalties than EQ1.  Level 50 hunts in Plane of Fear still often resulted in four or five hour chain rescue attempts.  Now we have a corpse summoner with reasonable plat prices and a return to your bind spot.  You can argue if you want that the cost is too low, but I bet new players won't think so, and a lot of us will grow used to it in the mean time.  I've already used it to get out of some CRs that would have taken me an hour or two.  Regardless, it is there now, just like the knowledge stones, and it isn't going to be removed.  Like the bazaar, the nexus, the wayfarer magi, Knowledge, the PoP graveyards, and the soulbinders, new features get added to reduce the more painful parts of the game.</p>

<p>Within reason, MMORPG manufacturers should seek the fastest path to get a group together, get them hunting, give them a challenge, and reward them for their effort in as short amount a time as reasonably possible.  Many of the items in past and future evil agendas focus on this theory.</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T12:13:38-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> said: Horzek, to use your example...

Stop trying t</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>Horzek, to use your example...

Stop trying to make my WORDPERFECT into your MICROSOFT WORD.</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>Horzek, to use your example...</p>

<p>Stop trying to make my WORDPERFECT into your MICROSOFT WORD.</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T11:25:29-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teremar said: There absolutely have to be death penalties. </title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>There absolutely have to be death penalties. No question about that. But I do think it&apos;s time for game designers to get beyond &quot;the penalty is that you have to do something that isn&apos;t fun for half an hour.&quot; We are talking about games here, and the goal should be to make them fun all the time.

That doesn&apos;t mean the penalties can&apos;t be as severe as the game designer wants them to be. You can take away xp, money, gear, you name it. Yes, some people are still going to complain &quot;You just took away everything I accomplished in the last two hours!&quot; But the difference is you hopefully had fun in those two hours, and the things you&apos;ll do to regain what you accomplished in those two hours will hopefully be fun as well. Yes, losing something is frustrating. But it should be, or death is meaningless.

Of course if you&apos;re not having fun that just means there are bigger problems with the game than the death penalty.</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>There absolutely have to be death penalties. No question about that. But I do think it's time for game designers to get beyond "the penalty is that you have to do something that isn't fun for half an hour." We are talking about games here, and the goal should be to make them fun all the time.</p>

<p>That doesn't mean the penalties can't be as severe as the game designer wants them to be. You can take away xp, money, gear, you name it. Yes, some people are still going to complain "You just took away everything I accomplished in the last two hours!" But the difference is you hopefully had fun in those two hours, and the things you'll do to regain what you accomplished in those two hours will hopefully be fun as well. Yes, losing something is frustrating. But it should be, or death is meaningless.</p>

<p>Of course if you're not having fun that just means there are bigger problems with the game than the death penalty.</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T10:33:07-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redcloud said: Then go play WoW. That really boils down to t</title>
      <link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
      <description>Then go play WoW. That really boils down to that.

If the social aspect of the game is too much of a burden to you, go play a game that isn&apos;t or much less.

Unless a GM binds you in VP, it doesn&apos;t happen often that you end up into a bind loop anyway or you aren&apos;t very carefull with your bind spot...

We can keep using every amount of cliches from RL till hell freezes over without bringing one inch of valid point to the discussion...
Portraiting a part of the playerbase as soon-to-be extinct is maybe ok talking to toddlers, maybe fanbois, not normal people that don&apos;t particularly enjoy having their game spoonfed or its challenge removed because x or y find it more microsofish to iron out any kind of brain activity from the game.

I&apos;m grossly exagerating at times but the message is &quot;easier, faster, lazier&quot; isn&apos;t automatically better. Not for entertainments like EQ imho.

That said, what is the shape of risk that will be acceptable for the average player WHILE playing a progression game. We&apos;re talking about EQ after all.

If not losing any amount of experience or time, what&apos;s left as risk? If someone looses versus content and it doesn&apos;t matter. Why care at all.</description>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<![CDATA[<p>Then go play WoW. That really boils down to that.</p>

<p>If the social aspect of the game is too much of a burden to you, go play a game that isn't or much less.</p>

<p>Unless a GM binds you in VP, it doesn't happen often that you end up into a bind loop anyway or you aren't very carefull with your bind spot...</p>

<p>We can keep using every amount of cliches from RL till hell freezes over without bringing one inch of valid point to the discussion...<br />
Portraiting a part of the playerbase as soon-to-be extinct is maybe ok talking to toddlers, maybe fanbois, not normal people that don't particularly enjoy having their game spoonfed or its challenge removed because x or y find it more microsofish to iron out any kind of brain activity from the game.</p>

<p>I'm grossly exagerating at times but the message is "easier, faster, lazier" isn't automatically better. Not for entertainments like EQ imho.</p>

<p>That said, what is the shape of risk that will be acceptable for the average player WHILE playing a progression game. We're talking about EQ after all.</p>

<p>If not losing any amount of experience or time, what's left as risk? If someone looses versus content and it doesn't matter. Why care at all.</p>]]>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter.com: Comments</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-03-04T10:06:52-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>


  </channel>
</rss>

