<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>&quot;That is disengenous. They have some of the best and brightest raiders that are willing to beta</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;That is disengenous. They have some of the best and brightest raiders that are willing to beta test there content.&quot;

So why didn&apos;t they?  The beta had open slots for a long time.  Entire guilds were given access to beta.  If the Stormhammer community was so eager to help test high-end raid content, why didn&apos;t they do it?

&quot;Alright I probably misunderstood, sorry Loral. I think I had in my mind a previous comment from you</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral wrote: &quot;I am able to get a pickup group for a DOD mission every night I try.&quot;

You a</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Loral wrote: &quot;I am able to get a pickup group for a DOD mission every night I try.&quot;

You are a cleric (and a semi-celebrity one).  Of course you get DoD groups every night you try.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Well, I don&apos;t group with five other semi-celebrity clerics.  Most of the groups have no idea wh</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Well, I don&apos;t group with five other semi-celebrity clerics.  Most of the groups have no idea who I am which is fine with me.

I don&apos;t buy the &quot;you&apos;re just a cleric&quot; thing.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;That is disengenous. They have some of the best and brightest raiders that are willing to beta</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;That is disengenous. They have some of the best and brightest raiders that are willing to beta test there content.&quot;
&quot;So why didn&apos;t they? The beta had open slots for a long time. Entire guilds were given access to beta. If the Stormhammer community was so eager to help test high-end raid content, why didn&apos;t they do it?&quot;

That would be my question to. from what I understood stormhammer got beta access privelages above</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Just to throw another wrench in the works...

I want more 1/2 group stuff. :P

Half of our regular g</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Just to throw another wrench in the works...

I want more 1/2 group stuff. :P

Half of our regular group left for EQ2 when it launched (we tried it, did not like it, and came back to EQ).  We don&apos;t have any desire to make new friends, so we&apos;ve been doing things as a three person group.  Obviously, that limits us primarily to bottom feeding, and we have to accept that as the consequence of our choice... but I do wish there was more conte</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;don&apos;t have any desire to make new friends&quot;

yes, lets change the fundemental core of</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;don&apos;t have any desire to make new friends&quot;

yes, lets change the fundemental core of the game so that people can solo and progress with less because your too lazy, scared, or anti-social to &apos;make new friends&apos;.

/boggle</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>DoD included a couple of 1/2 group monster missions, so I think SOE understands that not everything </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>DoD included a couple of 1/2 group monster missions, so I think SOE understands that not everything needs to be targeted at the 6-person group.  I just want to see more of it, preferably outside of the monster mission concept.

Feel free to continue formulating your negative opinion of me.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I don&apos;t mind more 1/2 group content and content scaled lower power (for lower reward) than typi</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I don&apos;t mind more 1/2 group content and content scaled lower power (for lower reward) than typical missions.  I actually like the WoW five-person-group.

I&apos;d rather have 1/2 group stuff and stuff set for 30 minute or 45 minute gameplay sessons than more solo content.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;So why didn&apos;t they? The beta had open slots for a long time. Entire guilds were given acc</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;So why didn&apos;t they? The beta had open slots for a long time. Entire guilds were given access to beta. If the Stormhammer community was so eager to help test high-end raid content, why didn&apos;t they do it?&quot;

The /betabuff characters were considerably better equipped than the average characters on SH once Township Rebellion and Precision Strike left the server.

The community kept playing and enjoying the content, but normal expa</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;I don&apos;t mind more 1/2 group content and content scaled lower power (for lower reward) tha</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;I don&apos;t mind more 1/2 group content and content scaled lower power (for lower reward) than typical missions. I actually like the WoW five-person-group.

I&apos;d rather have 1/2 group stuff and stuff set for 30 minute or 45 minute gameplay sessons than more solo content.&quot;

Agreed.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Only an observation since SOE says it will continue to add more MMs.

They were (I say were) popular</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Only an observation since SOE says it will continue to add more MMs.

They were (I say were) popular not only because of the nice rewards, but because a small group could be assembled in a matter of minutes and usually finish a mission in less than half an hour.  Perfect for short log on sessions or to kill time when waiting for guilds or friends to log on and assemble for bigger missions.

The last patches nerfed them, reducing the rewards and i</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Besides forcing people to actually be &quot;in&quot; the mission to earn the experience, what did th</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Besides forcing people to actually be &quot;in&quot; the mission to earn the experience, what did they nerf?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I know the guk one was nerfed to be harder to train the goblins to the zone... and think I heard the</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I know the guk one was nerfed to be harder to train the goblins to the zone... and think I heard the clockwork one was nerfed so that you had a limited # of lives... but am not sure if there were global changes made to further nerf them.  (I don&apos;t consider having to be in the zone and looting the crystal a nerf... though I wish they could have just flagged you as having entered the zone, as looting an otherwise meaningless object seems like </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MM&apos;s pretty dead on my server too. I really cant understand why they want content that no one u</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>MM&apos;s pretty dead on my server too. I really cant understand why they want content that no one uses. I wish they paid attention to LDoNs they way they did MMs, maybe peeps would still be able to do em.  All I heard out of peeps was how GREAT this expansion was going to be. Well, the next one I think I&apos;ll pass on for 3 to 6 months so i wont know about what they nerfed and what is was like when it went live. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>One has to remember Everquest is a flowing game.  It changes over time.  I&apos;m sure people who go</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>One has to remember Everquest is a flowing game.  It changes over time.  I&apos;m sure people who got LDON and DOD are glad that they bought them and played them early, before the experience was nerfed.  I think the eventual nerfing is simply the fact that if it&apos;s too good no one will play anywhere else.  There are many threads in different forums that say MMs were ruining the game as no one could find groups to play any of the &quot;regular</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>