<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:atom="http://purl.org/atom/ns" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">

<channel>
  <title>The Safehouse News</title>
  <link>http://www.thesafehouse.org</link>
  <description>The Rogue Community site for all your MMORPG news!! </description>
  <language>en-us</language>
<lastBuildDate>Thu,  3 Aug 2006 12:04:36 PST</lastBuildDate>
  <copyright>(C) 2005 The Safehouse Network</copyright>
  <managingEditor>aidden@thesafehouse.org</managingEditor>
  <webMaster>hostmaster@safehousenet.net</webMaster>
   <ttl>5</ttl>

  <image>
  <title>The Safehouse News</title>
  <width>144</width>
  <height>31</height>
  <link>http://www.thesafehouse.org</link>
  <url>http://www.thesafehosue.org/rss.gif</url>
  </image>

<item>
<title><![CDATA[Flying Lab’s Pirate Party at the Penny Arcade Expo! ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_294.php</link>
<pubDate>Thu,  3 Aug 2006 11:53:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[<p><span style="FONT-SIZE:11pt; FONT-FAMILY:Arial"><font face=Verdana size=2>Flying Lab Software will be hosting an exclusive party to celebrate their Pirates of the Burning Sea MMORPG during PAX, the Penny Arcade Expo, on Friday, August 25th in Bellevue, Washington. Attendees will be able to play the game, have some grog, participate in a pirate costume contest, and enjoy other piratical activities.</font></span></p> ]]></description>
<category>Nocte</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_294.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[E3 Downsizing?  ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_292.php</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2006 05:26:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[From Ars Technica: <a href="http://arstechnica.com/news.ars/post/20060730-7382.html">E3 game trade show not cancelled, but will be downsized</a><br><br><blockquote>Contrary
to reports across the web, E3 has not been cancelled. Next-Gen had
hoped that they would blow the lid off of a hot story by revealing that
the show had been cancelled, but some quick fact checking shows that
they are simply incorrect.<br><br>Sources close to the Entertainment
Software Association (ESA) tell Ars Technica that the show can and will
go on, but that big changes are planned. The "Electronic Entertainment
Expo" (hence E3) started in 1995 as a small but interesting annual
convention for gaming, following roughly six months after the
once-popular annual COMDEX computer trade-show in Las Vegas. The show
has grown immensely in popularity, and that appears to be the problem.<br></blockquote><br>The
article goes on to talk of game companies trying to out do each other
by putting on a better "dog and pony show" and not getting enough
return. It also mentions floor folks not being able to speak freely and
of "the show in a show" system where one needs to get an appointment to
get the real scoop.<br><br>I went to E3 this year and to tell you the
truth, it was less crowded than last year. That doesn't mean it wasn't
crowded though, it was still a mass of industry geeks and there were
still hour long lines for some things, such as the Spore demo. I can also
attest to the existence of the "show in a show" system. I had
appointments with the folks I interviewed and they were held in areas
not accessible to the floor public. However, it has been like that for
a few years now and I don't think the system will go away entirely. It
just makes sense that the CEO of a company is not the one on the floor
doing the demos for the week.<br><br>One thing they did this year was
to have a press only time slot, if the game companies want a chance to
interact with the press more perhaps that time period could be
extended. As far as the expense goes, maybe a cap of some sort might
help. Of course that may fall prey to the old "only bring a $20 gift"
syndrome and companies will still try to push it.<br><br>I don't have
the answer but I do know one thing. E3 has taken on a life of its own.
It's true that information is dispersed more quickly than ever,
especially information geared towards a net savvy crowd like gamers,
but E3 is still a trigger for the industry and the gaming public.
There's still nothing that can compare to it that will get us to sit up
and take notice. A press release here and there is not the same as the
convenience of being able to play and see the games all at once, even
if it is in the cacophony that is E3.<br><br><font class="technoratitag"><font class="technoratitag">Ongoing Discussion Thread:<br><a href="http://thesafehouse.org/forums/showthread.php?t=25410">http://thesafehouse.org/forums/showthread.php?t=25410</a><br><br></font></font><font class="sociallinks">  </font> ]]></description>
<category>Fricka</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_292.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Comic Con 2006 ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_291.php</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2006 21:12:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Once upon a time,
in 1970 to be exact, Comic Con begain with 300 attendees in the
basement of the US Grant Hotel in downtown San Diego and centered on...
comics.<br>

<br>

Fast forward to 2006 and we're seeing the biggest presence of movie, tv and
game studios ever. It was a Geek Fest for the 21st century and of course, The Safehouse attends and hilarity ensues. Topics covered: Quentin Tarantino, Kevin Smith, Robotech, NeverWinter Nights 2, SOE Block Party.<br><br><img alt="Comic Con 2006" src="http://www.thesafehouse.org/mugshots/albums/comiccon2006/IMG_2746.thumb.jpg" align="" border="0"><br> ]]></description>
<category>Fricka</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_291.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Intel's revolutionary Core 2 Duo ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/tech/news_290.php</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2006 23:48:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[With the Core 2 Duo, Intel has done an about face in how their processors work.&nbsp; Gone is the Pentium's Netburst technology, replaced with a more efficient and powerful design.<br><br>Reviews of their new processor have begun springing up all over the internet, and the results have been impressive.&nbsp; Most of the reviews deal with the expensive (~ $1,000) Core 2 Extreme E6800 processor (their fastest initial Core 2 processor), and the 'power gamer' Core 2 Duo E6700 (~$530) and E6600 (~ $320), the but a few reviews also have results for the low end E6300 (~ $165).<br><br>Read on for several links to Core 2 reviews on various websites around the net.<br> ]]></description>
<category>Ruccus</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/tech/news_290.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Auto Assault Servers Merge ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_289.php</link>
<pubDate>Sat,  8 Jul 2006 12:10:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Recently NCSoft announced that starting July 13th, all of its Auto Assault servers will be merging into one.&nbsp; The North American servers (Apocalypse, Carnage, Breakdown, and Wastelands) and the European servers (Desolation, Cataclysme, and <strong style="font-weight:normal">Ödland) will all join into one server, named Nexus.<br></strong> ]]></description>
<category>Ruccus</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_289.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Anime Expo News ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_288.php</link>
<pubDate>Tue,  4 Jul 2006 09:14:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Anime Expo has proved once again to be the premier industry con each year. Many licenses manga and anime alike, announcements, etc. I will list all of the manga and anime that were licensed, and a description of most titles.<br><br>All in all, about 13 licenses this time around. Not a record, but still very high and a very good sign for the Anime industry as whole as it appears to be slowly crawling out of it's slump and finding moderation.<br><br>Read more for all the information! ]]></description>
<category>Stalk</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/SH/news_288.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Vanguard Artists Comment on New Targonor ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/Vanguard/news_287.php</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2006 19:40:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Yesterday we released a <a href="http://www.thesafehouse.org/mugshots/newtargonorjune06">nice set of screenshots</a> featuring Vanguard's New Targonor. Today we got some nice commentary from the artists involved.<br> ]]></description>
<category>Fricka</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/Vanguard/news_287.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[War Hammer Online Screens &amp; Community Event? ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_286.php</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2006 15:15:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Warhammer Online is moving right along and they've shared a trio of exclusive screenshots with us.<br> ]]></description>
<category>Fricka</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_286.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[New Vanguard Screenshots ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/Vanguard/news_285.php</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2006 18:59:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Several screenshots from Vanguard: New Targonor.<br> ]]></description>
<category>Fricka</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/Vanguard/news_285.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   <item>
<title><![CDATA[Electronic Arts to buy Mythic Entertainment ]]></title>
<link >http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_284.php</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2006 20:21:00 EST</pubDate>
<description> <![CDATA[Today Electronic Arts announced that it has entered into an agreement to buy Mythic Entertainment.&nbsp; Mythic Entertainment will become EA Mythic, a wholely owned studio dedicated to developing Massively Multiplayer Online Role-Playing Games.<br><br>The press release can be found in .pdf form <a href="http://info.ea.com/news/pr/pr786.pdf">here</a>, or on Mythic Entertainment's website <a href="http://www.mythicentertainment.com/press/06202006EAMythic.html">here</a>.<br> ]]></description>
<category>Ruccus</category> 
<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.thesafehouse.org/news/news_284.php</guid> 

 
</item>


   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   

   
   

               
     
     

          
     
     
     

     
     
     

</channel>
</rss>