<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>Those changes look awesome. Hopefully TSS is able to hold things together.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Those changes look awesome. Hopefully TSS is able to hold things together.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Some editing required (duplicate paragraphs):

Some players complain about the perceived forced requ</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Some editing required (duplicate paragraphs):

Some players complain about the perceived forced requirement to level and earn AAs. Without a level increase and more AAs, the game becomes stagnant. Players at the max level with large amounts of AAs don&apos;t bother to hunt in groups, and hence many players have more difficulty grouping.

Some players complain about the perceived forced requirement to level and earn AAs but without a level increas</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I had to make a hard decision about whether to go with this article or write about the new changes. </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I had to make a hard decision about whether to go with this article or write about the new changes. I figured the new changes were big news everywhere else and rather than stick my nose too far into it, I&apos;d cover this topic instead.

The big one is the downtime change. I&apos;ve seen it in action and its a huge huge change. I don&apos;t have any idea how much it will impact the game but it will be a lot. It probably warrants a new article bu</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I wanted to point out that saga skins is NOT necessary for either receiving your 70 spell/disc (you </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I wanted to point out that saga skins is NOT necessary for either receiving your 70 spell/disc (you can do the &quot;bring me 4&quot; quests from sverag to get this, and its MUCH easier and faster) or for getting your TOB key (my cleric does not have skins finished but does have TOB-- you need NRO 1-3, Skylance 1-3 and Samples of Corruption only).  (You do need one person with skins + preparing skins + beoming the vessel to get samples of corrupt</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Just wanted to say congrats to a couple of fellow server friends!

Bacchuss of Radiant</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Just wanted to say congrats to a couple of fellow server friends!

Bacchuss of Radiant</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral,

I am a long time reader first time poster here.  I have typically agreed with your sentiment</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Loral,

I am a long time reader first time poster here.  I have typically agreed with your sentiments in the past, but your take on the PoR expansion couldnt be more wrong.  

When DoDH was out, did you afk in undershore hoping a good group would pick you up?  Playing a cleric I suppose that would be a possibility, but thats not what other classes can rely on, nor should it be an expected means of progression.  All of your points about the raid g</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>well progression servers are doin fine. groups within minutes in every lvlrange. soe should start to</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>well progression servers are doin fine. groups within minutes in every lvlrange. soe should start to dev. a luclin caped server.

they went the wrong direction starting with pop.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;PoR has tons of content for single groups that is very fun, including Sverag names, Skylance a</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;PoR has tons of content for single groups that is very fun, including Sverag names, Skylance arc, Razorthorn heroes challenge, relic mini names&quot;

Almost every time I go there, these zones are empty.

Pickup groups are a very important part of the game. Not everyone can rely on a tight knit group of friends with the right classes, right levels, right equipment power, and right time frames to meet these challenges.  WOW solves this with </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pickup groups can be an important part of the game, but shouldnt be thought of as equal to hardcore </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Pickup groups can be an important part of the game, but shouldnt be thought of as equal to hardcore players in terms of where their power should be.

The barrier to raiding is pretty severe for most players, even some who play a lot.  Raiding requires a guild, and requires one to be able to adhere to a schedule set for a large group of players.  It is much more difficult for some players to mesh their schedule with 40 players than it is to find 5</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>A cleric having trouble getting groups!?!?!?
Eh? 
What on earth can you do in group that would stop </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>A cleric having trouble getting groups!?!?!?
Eh? 
What on earth can you do in group that would stop groups?  The MAIN group former is usually a cleric as pretty well anything else can be worked around if you&apos;ve got a good healer.  How many groups form with the question &apos;got a cleric?&apos; THEN &apos;got a tank?&apos; &apos;it&apos;s ok, the Ranger/zerker/monk/bard/necro will be tanking&apos;
I&apos;m kinda freaked out that a cleric eve</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The new race looks like Frankenstein.  Ugh.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The new race looks like Frankenstein.  Ugh.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>This is what you get when a game focus&apos; on one type of player for so long.  All the others leav</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>This is what you get when a game focus&apos; on one type of player for so long.  All the others leave.  So when they finally do create some content for other playstyles nobody is there to play them because they had been left in the cold for so long they all went on to other games.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>i am agree with loral but in some key points he is mistaken i find groups in many places i may not b</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>i am agree with loral but in some key points he is mistaken i find groups in many places i may not be as high in lvl but i try to group with 55 plus because it is good exp. now the PoR expansion i see very few things lower lvl people can do but they focuse more on high lvl charcters. for instance i have a friend lvl 28 mage cant really find places with out getting killed by something uber higher than him. i am a lvl 51 shaman i cant really find g</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The success of TSS will be determined by how repeatable the content is. This is where instances in D</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The success of TSS will be determined by how repeatable the content is. This is where instances in DoDH, and PoR failed. The tasks can be long and difficult and the reward is automatic for all group members on completion (be that an item or flag or spell), this contains little incentive to repeat any mission. OoW was sucessful reasonable zone layout and runes which every caster needs and are random drops. It also has some nice faction based items</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>http://www.next-gen.biz/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=3715&amp;Itemid=2

An arti</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>http://www.next-gen.biz/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=3715&amp;Itemid=2

An article entitled.. is it possible to surpass world of warcraft?

it has a pretty good break down of what world of warcraft has done right and puts some stuff into a perspective light that I didnt think about its a good read.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>