<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/">
   <channel rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>eq2.fohguild.org</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2/phpnews/eq2.fohguild.org.rss</link>
      <description>
         This RSS feed was generated out of the newsdatabase of
         eq2.fohguild.org website.
      </description>
      <items>
         <rdf:Seq>
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
         </rdf:Seq>
      </items>
   </channel>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Finally an update!</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         So there isn't much to update.  We raid each day and collect the loot that doesn't seem to improve all that much.  When you can walk up to Darathar with 13 people (17 actually but 1 was a bot and 3 were afk scouts) and beat the shit out of him w/o one casualty, things start to get older than re-runs of Seinfeld.  By no means does this mean we won't pharm whenever but at this point in EQ2 there is no huge pressure to gear everyone up in full raid loot for bigger power pools, hps, or dps.  Nothing remotely challenges us.  Sure it is nice to get some gear and metal boxes but we are not much for rubbing off to uber loot stats (since we already have most everything in the game).  All we can hope for is a mighty expansion that will once again bring the pain of being in debt and facing mobs that making you hold your breath, and not your dick, the entire fight.   Speaking of expansions.  The little adventure pack kept some of us busy for a few days but soon enough our boys here stood up and took the server 1st on the boss, another for the record books.Excuse the fucking white blob... leet strat bubble txt is how we win.  The fight was more challenging than anything in the game at the moment.  As you can see it was sweet to have the server 1st broadcast to everyone (nice touch devs).  One thing I need to find out is who would even THINK of a particle effect of purple smoke exhailing from the face?  Someone was smoking something when they decided this would be a good idea.   Thanks for the "raid" zone! A few encounters brought our priests back from AFK.  Still, raid mobs are just not configured right yet.  30 raid mobs that you have to clear (raid junk mobs - RJMs) that take 10 mins to kill and cannot hit the tank makes for 300 fucking boring minutes.  What part of this is fun or challenging?  No loot, no suspence, just AFK and and autofollow... STOP PUTTING SHIT LIKE THIS IN THE GAME.  Give raid mobs MORE power since the auto attack doesn't do shit and they are usually drained in 20 fucking seconds (good job Dave).  Take the hps down a notch since RJMs are just that, junk.  X4 shouldn't give them a right to have 4 million hps. X4 should mean it hits x4 more, x4 harder, x4 more power, not take x40 times longer to kill.  These raid mobs give me horrid flash backs of VT but take out ALL the risk of dying and add a smaller hit box.  Hi, please..... Right, so this is usually where I post some uber loot we got.  I am going to miss a few people/loots but Grats to the following........Kythik on a Vclaw, ring and something else.Stella on some cap, bp and other shit.Patho on fucking not going ld everytime we zone ... and some good shit.Van on ring and other lewts.Xminos on noobie junk since hez lzr!Mysti on rings....... Faille on neck, arms, boots, rings...loothoeSigon for lots of shit (arms, bracer, bp and more) 
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Darathar done</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         What a great fight this was!!  People were at the top of their game on this fight and we took this bitch down 2.67 times.  2.67 times??   At some point Darathar thought it would be funny to go from 1% health to full health.  We wont talk about what happened on the .67 (/wink Elkay).Courtesy of our guild photographers (IE people that go LD during raids 
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>More great kills tonight</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         Vision of Vox sleeps with the fishes...  Loot suckedThe Antonica instance was a bit on the easy side, but at least we got 4 WOODEN CHESTS out of it!!
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Getting shit done....</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         Can you be stopped?  This was a tough fight but you all buckled down and put this bitch in the ground.  Great job on a game 1st kill on this foo.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Things just keep getting better and better</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         King Zalak the AncientSince the Launch of EQ2 we have seen the world change a lot.  The developers work hard to fix issues at the same time release new and exciting adventures for players.  The last big patch, Live Update #3, made some well needed adjustments to the game.  The addition of 4 new dungeons has made it possible for us to have something to do everynight (see above our crack team putting the hurt on King Zalak the Ancient).  At the same time a few of our dragons (/wave Vox and Vene!) have been adjusted to reasonable encounters but still challenging.We toyed with the new zones for a bit (see above pic of us putting the hurt down on one of the new named, nice GFXs!) but nothing is like slaying a dragon.  Nearly a month ago we took down Venekor.  Ever since he got a hold of some crack, the chinese money farmers could not be saved from his tyranny of CT.  Since we love our Team Dugim, FoH put an end to Venekor's reign of Cazic Thule.Since we were stumped by this mob for so long, I thought I'd show everyone the Venekor strat from the FoH playbook - Priest Hex Pattern.  His loot wasn't great but Grats Nyco on ancient cedar wand !Of course, the usual x2 and x4 mobs were taken down.  Aphyxia, Vaz, Nagalik, Fist, Kar'thuk... etc etc all farmed down giving a few of our members some nice items.black ebon chainmail gloves - Grats MystiqueGloves of Madness - Grats PurrzephanySpiritbound Chain Coif - Grats SkorgeAncient Ancestral Gloves - Grats AlloriaUber BP I have no pic of - Grat Linyen (pst him for link)Now usually there is no "Quotes" section on these News Updates.  Due to people bugging me to put up some funny shit I have taken a few SShots to display.  More will come later when people actually say funny or stupid shit.-Noah Notfuror
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>The crap you get raiding at 50.....</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         So you get to 50 and hope to have some shit you can raid.  Yeah, you know, those big ass mobs you see in zones with lvl 55 x8324 ++++++ above their name and 18 adds, WUWU shit to do!!  You get 24 of the best players around, drag these people into the depths of Sol Eye and other places, and what do you get??  Oh yes, the infamous WOODEN BOX!!!......... never heard him say that before.  Little did we know what to expect when Mezmith disarmed the trap successfully but still did the puke emote.It is NO WAY acceptable that a mob that is in the middle of east bumF*#@ x4+++ 55th lvl drops 8 pieces of shit that you will vendor for 2gp.  It is bad enough that you get ONE piece of decent loot in a metal chest from a x4 mob.  But to get a wooden box of shit is just absurd!   Now you can see we might be a bit pissed about this... it probably has to do with the fact that this was the THIRD raid mob in a row to drop a steamer.  Hear us now: EVERY x4 MOB NEEDS TO DROP A METAL BOX EVERYTIME.  You don't raid to get a bunch of shit loot.  You don't spend hours upon hours of strat discussion to get a TEAK CUDGLE and some crap Adepts that some noob has set for 20gp on the broker.  You raid the big stuff to get the big stuff.  Since we killed everything that can be raided in a matter of 2 days (oh yes, 7+ days or more before anything will pop...yay harvesting here I come /hug Dave), I have had some extra time on my hands to do a theraputic comic to make light of our woes.I am sure the fellas from the BBurrow, Unrest, Grobb and Najena servers that I chat with will get a good laff.  Just know you're not alone.~Noah Notfuror
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>DNS works now</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         http://eq2.fohguild.org will now actually work to get to this site.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Farm farm farm ....</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         As you can see the site is back up and in full action again.  All you fanbois can relax now and feel free to hit the website 47 times an hour hoping to see some uber loot update.  This update will make even your bookmarked pornsites seem boring.  Lets start off with the tweaks made from the big patch.Armor Tints - Red storm trooper, clamshell, then black.  Im in favor of just having a /random for the color and look of your armor at this point. Rating: 4HOs - Ahh yes, hos.  Now made practically retard free!  The new animations are a bit rough on the system, but everyone loves playing on Atari mode anyways (hugs Nvidia)  Rating: 9Armor Class - Hurray for big numbers.  Numbers make me happy.  Bigger numbers are the uberer I r.  Rating: 9New Heritages - GEBs and Tranix.  If you love Lavastorm (yay trains and lava ports!!) then enjoy lagtastic hours of running everywhere in this zone.  Lets not forget you need to know 12 different languages (including Chinese and Spanish) to even get half way done.  Rating: 6Metal Chests - Wooden box with 2 41st lvl adept dropped from a groupx4 epic mob after spending 40 mins beating on 100 million hps... awesome way to spend friday night.  Now with the adjusted loot on these mobs, we have something to look forward to dragging 24 people to the depths of Sol Ro.  Thank you for this adjustment.  Rating: 8Venekor - Saved the best one for last.  Yes, the uber creation of Moorgard.  Before the tweek it was a good fight.  Challenging and some strat needed for success.  Someone felt it necessary to change this encounter from exciting to absurd.  If you are going to make some AE raid wide, think about putting in resist checks, toning down the 4k per tick dot, or make it have a managable range. I am sure your testers did great against him before you released it to the Live servers (/hug).  Rating: 2With all the glorious changes we have enjoying farming the metal boxes from x2 and x4 mobs.  Even though they made mobs hit harder (Hi2u 6k nukes)... Agi boost work for crap... these fellas just cowboy up and get it done.  Heres the spoils of their hard work.Grats Pathogenn!Grats Mystique!Grats Insognito!Grats Endalmir!Grats Poyzin!
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Jan 29th, 2005 Noah Update</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         YS~~Quick update to show off a very nice piece of gear we got from the Fist of Solusek (20% Haste 4tw)THX FIST!!
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Another day, another dragon</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         So a couple days ago we talked to Nagafen, and I guess that after 500 years of being cooped up in the bottom of Solusek he's ready to get some booty.  He sent us to the crypt in Permafrost to get Vox all ready for him, but she wasn't in a particularly cooperative mood.  Common decency reared it's ugly head yet again, and we killed the insolent bitch.Noah was kind enough to provide this image.It took me 2 days to get around to making this update, but I was working on the site.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>And so it begins....</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         Now I could have posted loot from some gay 50th lvl quest in Cazic Thule (omfg, Blood Fire!11one)... but I think people need to see what is truly out there on these x4 epic mobs.  Here is some "soccer mom" loot for you to wish for....THX VENE!!     THX KRA'THUK!!And of course everyone needs to post their "I've seen Naggy and got the uber quest" pic... so here you go...~Noah Notfuror
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Site Launched!</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         eq2.fohguild.org is launched... Halfway.  The main page still isn't done, and the dns isn't set up for it to be eq2.fohguild.org yet, but the rest of the site is operational.  More news and a mainpage update coming soon.  The gallery uses the forum users.  Mouseover @ to upload.
      </description>
   </item>
</rdf:RDF>
