<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>While I think Raalf&apos;s idea is not a bad one, it is an unfortunate fact that Stormhammer is now </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>While I think Raalf&apos;s idea is not a bad one, it is an unfortunate fact that Stormhammer is now officially dead.  Any speculation on the role Stormhammer could have (I think should have) played in such things is, again unfortunately, moot at this point:(
     </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Announcement today:

EQ TITANIUM

EverQuest®: Titanium, an all-inclusive collection consisting of Ev</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Announcement today:

EQ TITANIUM

EverQuest®: Titanium, an all-inclusive collection consisting of EverQuest Classic and the first ten expansions. EverQuest Titanium carries a suggested retail price of $19.99 and will be available at retail beginning January 11, 2006. In addition to the release of EverQuest Titanium, SOE will launch EQ Players, a website that will enhance the services provided to EQ players. 

EverQuest Titanium offers the origina</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I am not a high end raider, but I have been around a while, so I have still had a chance to see the </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I am not a high end raider, but I have been around a while, so I have still had a chance to see the development of raids. I&apos;ve just got into Time, and find it really fun so far. To get their our last EP encounter was TRC. Many in the guild are not yet Time Flagged. The difference between the two sort of highlights the problem with the newer raids, of which you speak. TRC, you have an hour, if you are lucky of organisation, followed by an hou</description>
</item>
<item>
<title> Glormane you at least can now will people into PoTime and get them flagged a few each week. During </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description> Glormane you at least can now will people into PoTime and get them flagged a few each week. During PoP we had to do TRC 3 or 4 times not to mention the countless failures. TRC&apos;s reward was Time not a couple of drops though so that is why we did it.

 The PoP god raids were certainly fun and different and the time altough most people certainly didn&apos;t do Xegony or TRC more times than they needed. And I do think the major reason was the a</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I really think that the posters have hit on a very relevant point in terms of raid design, 2 solid u</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I really think that the posters have hit on a very relevant point in terms of raid design, 2 solid unbroken hours is very draining on even the most devout eq-worshipper, some kind of scripted intermission, break or a design which enables a short break each hour would be a major step imho, some encounters a break can be &quot;manufactured&quot; (for example kiting some key mobs awhile while resses/rebuffs/afk&apos;s/bio breaks are done is one way)</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>That&apos;s why 30min clearing tops + 15min fight is ok.

And raid locking at start with no trash is</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>That&apos;s why 30min clearing tops + 15min fight is ok.

And raid locking at start with no trash is not.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;If you can demonstrate to me how it&apos;s possible to get 54 end-game raiders on Beta to beha</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;If you can demonstrate to me how it&apos;s possible to get 54 end-game raiders on Beta to behave exactly as they would on a Live server, I will send you a whole box of fudge cookies. :)
-Prathun&quot;

Suggestion:

Identify an end-game raiding guild that is appropriate to attempt the new content in beta.

Copy their characters to beta.

Offer EACH AND EVERY ONE OF THEM a reward for BEATING the content.  For example:  Offer a reward for part</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;Identify an end-game raiding guild that is appropriate to attempt the new content in beta.&quo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;Identify an end-game raiding guild that is appropriate to attempt the new content in beta.&quot;

First, I can only hear the screaming from the casual end about this.  However, as a casual player who has no issues with raiders in general, the only thing I would suggest is never to use the same guild twice.  In other words, don&apos;t let one raiding guild have a monopoly on learning new content to the exclusion of all other raiding guilds.
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Adding to the previous poster&apos;s suggestion, it might be as simple as being allowed to have an i</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Adding to the previous poster&apos;s suggestion, it might be as simple as being allowed to have an influence on the story or just on the names of something.  It&apos;s difficult to do this to get a full 54 people, since you&apos;re not able to give all of them an addition.  But, allowing the 54 people to suggest a name, and then use one of those might do it.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title> As someone who has been in several of the beta&apos;s (but not in a good while) I can attest to the</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description> As someone who has been in several of the beta&apos;s (but not in a good while) I can attest to their being a difference between beta raids and raids on regular servers. First it is very hard to get a large group of people committed to fully testing things. Betas start off fun since you get to see all the new content etc, but after awhile you really start debating how much time and effort you want to put in for something in the end gives you no </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I agree with Mitcheypoo...Sendaii is wearing me out too.  It is a great and fun raid, but the adds a</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I agree with Mitcheypoo...Sendaii is wearing me out too.  It is a great and fun raid, but the adds at 25% are just to much.  It burns people out when you can only get that close and still get nothing after a long long fight.  It is to long, most times if you fight to the 25%, it is to late to make more than two runs at the thing in a night.
As far as the beta testing, I beta&apos;d on GoD, it was just to intense on the machine I had at the time s</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The naming thing is a good idea as well.  It has it&apos;s own issues but I suspect that those could</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The naming thing is a good idea as well.  It has it&apos;s own issues but I suspect that those could be overcome (for example you might say name some zone after the guild in question - But then Bunny Ninjas on my server would be an issue IMO).

The naming idea is easy as well - no itimization etc.  Simple to implement.  I still like the trophy idea though.  Stand around in POK with your flaming sword of beta ownage - Lots of folks would like that</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Verant had it right once in time, I&apos;m talking about breaks in long raids ;)

Back in the days, </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Verant had it right once in time, I&apos;m talking about breaks in long raids ;)

Back in the days, Plane of Sky was a monster to raid, but they had breaks after each isle.
After clearing one place, the &apos;event&apos; continued when the players handed their key to the NPC. It was possible to get in a bio break, to get something to drink, eat.
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>In regards to beta testing raid content there is rewards to those who do it.

First of all you get a</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>In regards to beta testing raid content there is rewards to those who do it.

First of all you get a solid knowledge of the encounter(s) you are testing, which most likely mean you will have it easier when you get to it, and thus start getting loots from it sooner. The guilds that did extensive testing in DoDh got 20 AAs each on a toon on the accounts they used as well, not that AAs really matter, but its still a reward no matter how you put it.
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Any feedback re: eqplayers.com.  I does not seem to display some chars - guilds etc. correctly.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Any feedback re: eqplayers.com.  I does not seem to display some chars - guilds etc. correctly.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>