<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>Firstly apologies to Maitreya, as I said its hard to pick up someone from just a few lines.

I don’t</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Firstly apologies to Maitreya, as I said its hard to pick up someone from just a few lines.

I don’t expect an expansion to come out and not have a few teething troubles. The post expansion patch is normally the same day or the day after a new release. Some problems don’t manifest themselves until they hit live and sometimes all the testing in the world cant stop that. The problems I mentioned I don’t think fall into this category. Whole items mi</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>SOE is rushing out expansions every 6 month to milk the cash-cow. The timer on EQ is running down, n</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>SOE is rushing out expansions every 6 month to milk the cash-cow. The timer on EQ is running down, not fast but it is.

The new expansion PooR is not finished on release, there&apos;s major content missing, there are classes with half assed/non working spells/abilities, and on and on.

It&apos;s just another nail in the coffin for a once great game.

Sony has lost the touch with reality, with the customers - they are losing on other fronts too.

</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Where anyone gets the idea the LoD helps close the XP gap bewilders me. A regular player gets 5-7 Lo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Where anyone gets the idea the LoD helps close the XP gap bewilders me. A regular player gets 5-7 LoDs per week. The casual players gets 1-2 per week or less. Please remind me how this would allow to similar characters to keep in touch?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;Would an XP modifer based on time played be of any use in this game. I am thinking in terms of</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;Would an XP modifer based on time played be of any use in this game. I am thinking in terms of the less you play the Higher the bonus/modifier.&quot;

You wanted a system that would provide bonus xp, but offer diminishing returns the more you play, correct? This is EXACTLY what LoD does.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Um, clarification please:

&quot;As Theater of Blood is instanced, all of this will happen in one pl</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Um, clarification please:

&quot;As Theater of Blood is instanced, all of this will happen in one place.&quot;

&quot;This design is not without risk. Already representatives from high-end raiding guilds question the logic of non-instanced keyholders.&quot;

Was that first sentence supposed to have a &quot;NOT&quot; in it?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>No, I want an XP modifier that lets a person who plays infrequently to earn similar xp as those who </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>No, I want an XP modifier that lets a person who plays infrequently to earn similar xp as those who play every day. LoD does not allow this because 5 times double xp for half an hour is much more than 1 times double xp for half an hour. 
Instead if it was 1 lot of ten times xp for half and hour then it would be more reasonable.
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Hmmm ... Tier 1 armor = 150 hps and Tier 2 = 200 hps?  Correct me if I am wrong here but isnt this a</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Hmmm ... Tier 1 armor = 150 hps and Tier 2 = 200 hps?  Correct me if I am wrong here but isnt this a massive jump backwards?  I mean, Qvic armor is 200-220 base hps and its 3 boxable now.  I would think Blood armor would be 250 tier 1 and 350 tier 2 minimum in terms of progression.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nobody actually knows the gear dropped in Theatre of Blood yet, so until we see, this really is spec</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Nobody actually knows the gear dropped in Theatre of Blood yet, so until we see, this really is speculation.
From the difficulty of the zone though, it should be a step up from Qvic by a fair bit.  3 groups that would sleep through M&apos;sha kills will get torn to shreds here.  Unless they&apos;re ALL totally on the ball, we&apos;re going to see alot of people popping back at bind point when exploring this place.  And this is before the mini-rai</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I fixed the typo.  Theater of Blood is NOT instanced.  Given the high rewards on unnamed mobs, the h</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I fixed the typo.  Theater of Blood is NOT instanced.  Given the high rewards on unnamed mobs, the high rewards on the powerful named mobs, and the high-end raid mobs required for progression to Deathknell, this should end up being a popular place.

You&apos;re probably right about the power of the Theater of Blood armor.  It will probably be higher than Qvic level and should be given that it takes two to three groups to get it.  One difference, </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>To be realist, non raiders will not get into Theatre, at least the vast majority won&apos;t. Dreadsp</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>To be realist, non raiders will not get into Theatre, at least the vast majority won&apos;t. Dreadspire had an access quest of 4 missions, yet it&apos;s a deserted place except when raiders meet up to raid DP. Theatre will be a much longer and harder quest since there are much nicer things dropping in that zone, so even less non raiders will get in. Also you say non-raiders will get into 2-3 groups, or non-raiders will get into larger groups. Exc</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>As a high-end raider myself I am concerned about &quot;bottle-necks&quot; hopefully any &quot;cockbl</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>As a high-end raider myself I am concerned about &quot;bottle-necks&quot; hopefully any &quot;cockblocking&quot; will be seen as very bad sportsmanship &amp; once over the initial rush for deathknell keys the highest &amp; fastest progressing guilds won&apos;t deliberately hold up each other or the guilds right beind them but rather concentrate their competition within progress inside an instanced deathknell itself, though i rather suspect to del</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral Wrote:Theater of Blood is NOT instanced. Given the high rewards on unnamed mobs, the high rewa</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Loral Wrote:Theater of Blood is NOT instanced. Given the high rewards on unnamed mobs, the high rewards on the powerful named mobs, and the high-end raid mobs required for progression to Deathknell, this should end up being a popular place.

Not to be rude, but didnt you say the same thing about Dreadspire? :) I dont know about your server. but I dont see too many single groups forming in dreadspire on mine.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>If you play infrequently, why should you earn as much xp as those who play every day?</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>If you play infrequently, why should you earn as much xp as those who play every day?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>P.S.: Before you label me as some arrogant high end raider who&apos;s level 70 with max AAs and simp</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>P.S.: Before you label me as some arrogant high end raider who&apos;s level 70 with max AAs and simply wants to keep the poor &quot;casual&quot; players down, let me tell you something: I have been playing for four and a half years and my highest character is 56 with 8AAs. I play less than that guy with 1200AAs, so I get less xp. I have no trouble accepting that I am going to get xp much slower than those who play a lot more. Why is it such a pro</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>http://hgamer.blogspot.com

Damn if you&apos;re still playing EQ after all these years and are not i</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>http://hgamer.blogspot.com

Damn if you&apos;re still playing EQ after all these years and are not into raiding... wtf are you playing for?</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>