<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rdf:RDF
 xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
 xmlns="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/"
 xmlns:taxo="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/taxonomy/"
 xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:syn="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
 xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
>

<channel rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/">
<title>Allakhazam.com News (full)</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/</link>
<description>allakhazam gaming news rss feed</description>
<items>
 <rdf:Seq>
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13572" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13570" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13569" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13568" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13567" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13563" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13562" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13560" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13559" />
  <rdf:li rdf:resource="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13558" />
 </rdf:Seq>
</items>
</channel>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13572">
<title>The Friday Grab Bag! [Dark Age of Camelot]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13572</link>
<description>It&#39;s time for the weekly &lt;a href="http://www.camelotherald.com/news/news_article.php?storyid=3566" target="_blank">Q&amp;A session&lt;/a> over on the Camelot Herald, check out this weeks Grab Bag below:&lt;br />&lt;blockquote>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Q. I have a question about the new patch note for housing.  Owning a large house has always been a mark as a status in the game.  With the new price changes a lot of people who have money invested in  their homes. A question comes to mind for people like me who now have a  house we paid 40 plat for it. If I upgrade once the patch goes live to  the new 25 plat Mansion, will the deed to my current house sell back  for the 40p I paid for it, or is it going to sell back for the new  lower price? I would hope my 40p deed would still be worth the 40p it  cost me to purchase.&lt;br />       &lt;br />   &lt;/strong>A. I asked the Bearded Wonder this very popular question and he knew the answer right away: &lt;em>The deed will sell for the current market price.&lt;br />   &lt;/em>&lt;br />   &lt;strong>Q.  I have started compiling detailed feedback on quests that I get stuck  on.  I have suggestions for changes that could be made to quest text to  make the quests easier for a new player to figure out.  I&#39;m doing it in  Word. Who can I send these documents to?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   A. Straight from the depths of the Quality Assurance department, The Hooded One has an e-mail address for you: &lt;em>Please send your bug reports to: &lt;/em>&lt;a href="mailto:cambugs@darkageofcamelot.com">&lt;em>cambugs@darkageofcamelot.com&lt;/em>&lt;/a>&lt;em> (Please note that we investigate all issues reported, but unless we  require more information, we are not able to respond to your report.)&lt;br />   &lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>&lt;a name="pause" title="pause">&lt;/a>&lt;blockquote>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   &lt;strong>Q. I have noticed that several of the new keeps designs do not have any of the half circle windows used to show where a trebuchet breach point is (Specifically the Sursbrooke and Berkstaed designs). Do those keep designs have trebuchet breach points or are they just not marked with the half circle window at the breach point?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   A. Having breached a few keep walls in his time, the Bearded Wonder explains: &lt;em>The keeps were designed to have different strategies available for keep capture. Some will have more &#39;breach&#39; points, some will have more &#39;siege tower&#39; spots. All &#39;breach&#39; points will look the same.&lt;br />   &lt;br />   &lt;/em>&lt;br />   &lt;strong>Q. There is supposedly a ring called Gem of the Deepest Darkness. I wanted to know if this was correct and what mob drops it. I found the reference on a website, but didn&#39;t know if it was correct.&lt;br />   &lt;br /> &lt;/strong>A. A question about a gem? Well the Lady of the Jewels was the one to ask: &lt;em>There is both a Ring of Deepest Darkness and a Gem of Deepest Darkness. They have a chance to drop from several named demons, such as Marquis Halphas and Earl Serapis. All the demons that drop these items can be found in the Brimstone Caverns, Halls of Helgardh, and Cave of Crauchan zones.&lt;/em> &lt;strong> &lt;/strong> &lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;br /> Q. My question is, If a guild house ends up repossessed can any guild member with a guild rank of 0 go to the item reserve guys to get the trophies and other items or are they lost forever? &lt;/strong>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   A. The Bearded Wonder has your answer: &lt;em>Guild houses can&#39;t be condemned. If a house is repossessed (guild or otherwise) from failure to pay rent, the trophies or other items not in a vault or consignment merchant are not saved. They are only saved for personal houses condemned based on account inactivity. If the guild house is going to be repossessed from failure to pay rent, it would be advisable to have someone with the ability to remove those items do so before the house is repossessed or they will be lost.&lt;br />   &lt;/em>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   &lt;strong>Q. I was wondering if you could shine a little light on how items affecting you is determined, in particular Spellcrafted items. I bought a bunch of player made dragonsworn armor, put it on without any Spellcrafting and the armor effected me. However after I Spellcrafted a piece and put it back on it no longer worked. How can I tell before I spellcraft something if it will work?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   A. The Lady of the Jewels blinked once or twice and then had this to say: &lt;em>The &quot;bonus level&quot; of an item is determined based on the amount of bonuses imbued into that item, so it is possible that an item with no bonuses will effect a character, but once those bonuses are added it no longer effects them. Unfortunately, there is no way at this time for us to place set bonus levels on crafted items since any combination of Spellcrafting would cause that number to change.&lt;br />   &lt;/em>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   &lt;strong>Q. From what I have heard from other people, the Alb dragon and Mid dragon are considerably easier to farm than the Hib dragon. Is this intended? &lt;/strong>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   A. After some conferring, both the Bearded Wonder and the Lady of the Jewels agreed: &lt;em>They were designed for the same number of players and should not be any more difficult an encounter in any realm. &lt;br />   &lt;/em>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   &lt;strong>Q. I was wondering how does the resists of someone with full resists differ from those who have little or none? Does it only effect how often someone resists an attack or is it much more?&lt;/strong>&lt;br />   &lt;br />   A. When it comes to resisting, the Balancinator could not resist to answer this question: &lt;em>Your resist percentages displayed on the paper doll do not affect your out right resist rate. So no, you will not see more total resists for having a higher resist percentage. It should reduce the damage taken by a greater amount than a person with lower resist percentages. Please see last week&#39;s grab bag which addressed the issue in more detail.&lt;/em>&lt;/p> &lt;p>&lt;br />   *******&lt;br />   ANNOUNCEMENTS&lt;/p> &lt;p>All of the dates for the Road Trips have been confirmed! Here is a list for those of you who need to plan ahead to attend one of these events:&lt;/p> &lt;p>San Diego, California - July 26th&lt;br />   Seattle, Washington - August 30th&lt;br />   Austin, Texas - September 13th&lt;br />   Chicago, Illinois - October 18th&lt;/p> &lt;p>There will be free snacks, prizes and of course get a chance to ask your questions to the Developers. Please remember to &lt;a href="http://www.darkageofcamelot.com/roadtrip/" target="_blank">RSVP&lt;/a>! We look forward to seeing you there.&lt;/p> &lt;p>Have you ever said to yourself, &quot;Self! I know all about my class and I want to help improve it.&quot; Well, have a look at the &lt;a href="http://www.camelotherald.com/teamleads/tl_available.php" target="_blank">Team Lead Positions&lt;/a> that are currently available and send in that application today!&lt;/p> &lt;p>If you haven&#39;t had a chance to take our New Server Type Poll, time is running out! We need your input if you would like to see a server that includes the Old Frontiers! &lt;a href="http://www.camelotherald.com/polls/" target="_blank">Go vote now&lt;/a>.&lt;/p> &lt;p>If you are out on the roads this weekend, please be safe. If you are out in the Frontiers, make sure to remember to look behind you - just in case. Have a great weekend.&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13570">
<title>Technical and Billing Support Closed Monday [Dark Age of Camelot]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13570</link>
<description>Note from the &lt;a href="http://www.camelotherald.com/news/news_article.php?storyid=3565" target="_blank">Herald&lt;/a>:&lt;br />&lt;blockquote>Our tech and billing guys are getting Monday, May 26th off work for the Memorial Day holiday. They will return to the phones on Tuesday at 11:00am EDT. As always, In Game support will remain at their desks, ready to assist you with your appeals.&lt;br />&lt;/blockquote></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13569">
<title>All good things... [EverQuest II]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13569</link>
<description>Not only is it a super cool TNG episode, but it&#39;s also the end of Zam&#39;s Permadeath Contest!!&lt;br /> &lt;br /> Saturday May 24th at noon central time!&lt;br /> &lt;br /> As of right now (9:40pm central time and past my bed time) the top 7 are as follows (assuming that my info is totally accurate):&lt;br /> &lt;br /> Keyasai&#160;&#160;&#160; Warden&#160;&#160;&#160; 61&lt;br /> Methuselah&#160;&#160;&#160; Bruiser&#160;&#160;&#160; 52&lt;br /> Aidolon&#160;&#160;&#160; Paladin&#160;&#160;&#160; 46&lt;br /> Nistia&#160;&#160;&#160; Fury&#160;&#160;&#160; 44&lt;br /> Caeleyne&#160;&#160;&#160; Necromancer&#160;&#160;&#160; 40&lt;br /> Malarra&#160;&#160;&#160; Warden&#160;&#160;&#160; 38&lt;br /> Zoenne&#160;&#160;&#160; Bruiser&#160;&#160;&#160; 38&lt;br /> &lt;br /> I&#39;ll be double checking the final info before posting the winners next Friday.&lt;br /> &lt;br /> Thanks everyone for participating.&#160; It was a lot of fun and I hope you all enjoyed it!</description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13568">
<title>SOE Podcast #36 [General News]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13568</link>
<description>&lt;div style="text-align: center">&lt;img src="http://eq2.allakhazam.com/images/Random%20Images/SOEpodcast.jpg" border="0" />&lt;br />&lt;br />&lt;div align="left">According to &lt;a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive_content.vm?id=1697&amp;section=News&amp;locale=en_US" target="_blank">EQII Players&lt;/a>, Podcast #36 is available for your listening enjoyment!&lt;br />&lt;blockquote>&lt;span class="postbody">&lt;p>Official SOE Podcast #36 is live!!! Craig &#8220;&lt;em>Grimwell&lt;/em>&#8221; Dalrymple delivers the news while Pex takes a vacation. Take a listen and meet Brad Wilcox Executive Director of Customer Service, and we chat with Emily &quot;Domino&quot; Taylor Game Designer, &lt;em>EQII&lt;/em> Tradeskills! Timmy stops in to update us on what&#39;s going on with him. Brenlo and Ashlanne talk about their trip to Seattle and class is in session so listen in to learn how to pronounce the &lt;em>EQ&lt;/em> Server Name.&lt;/p>&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;strong>So tune in!&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> You can get your Podcast goodness two different ways head over to&lt;a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.station.sony.com/podcasts.vm" target="_blank"> the Podcast&#8217;s official site&lt;/a>, and click on your preferred bandwidth or if you have iTunes installed select iTunes store, type SOE into the search box and click Subscribe! Your feedback is always welcome either on &lt;a rel="nofollow" href="http://forums.station.sony.com/station/forums/show.m?forum_id=120" target="_blank">the Station forums&lt;/a> or via email to &lt;a rel="nofollow" href="mailto:Brenlo@soe.sony.com" target="_blank">Brenlo@soe.sony.com&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>&lt;/span>&lt;/blockquote>&lt;span class="postbody">These are always fun, tune in!&lt;br />&lt;/span>&lt;/div>&lt;/div></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13567">
<title>SOE Customer Support Job Opportunities [General News]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13567</link>
<description>Gnobrin &lt;a href="http://forums.station.sony.com/eq2/posts/list.m?topic_id=418619" target="_blank">posted:&lt;/a>&lt;br />&lt;blockquote>&lt;span class="postbody">&lt;p>Now is your chance to get in the game!&lt;/p>&lt;p>SOE has immediate openings for Free Realms, Vanguard, and international Subject Matter Experts in the Customer Support division. For more detailed information about the available positions, please follow the links below and submit your resum&#233; today!&lt;/p>&lt;p>&lt;a rel="nofollow" href="http://careers.vurvexpress.com/jobprofile.cfm?szWID=16059&amp;szCID=72267&amp;szSiteID=1574&amp;szOrderID=495779&amp;szStart=1" target="_blank">International Customer Support SME&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;p>&lt;a rel="nofollow" href="http://careers.vurvexpress.com/jobprofile.cfm?szWID=16059&amp;szCID=72267&amp;szSiteID=1574&amp;szOrderID=497686&amp;szStart=1" target="_blank">Customer Support Subject Matter Expert - Vanguard&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;p>&lt;a rel="nofollow" href="http://careers.vurvexpress.com/jobprofile.cfm?szWID=16059&amp;szCID=72267&amp;szSiteID=1574&amp;szOrderID=497106&amp;szStart=1" target="_blank">Customer Support Subject Matter Expert - Free Realms&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;/span>&lt;/blockquote>&lt;span class="postbody">&lt;p>If Customer Support is your bailwick and games your passion, now&#39;s your chance!&lt;a rel="nofollow" href="http://careers.vurvexpress.com/jobprofile.cfm?szWID=16059&amp;szCID=72267&amp;szSiteID=1574&amp;szOrderID=497106&amp;szStart=1" target="_blank">&lt;br />&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;/span></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13563">
<title>Challenging the Changes [Vanguard Saga of Heroes]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13563</link>
<description>&lt;div align="justify">On May 13th Allakhazam posted an interview conducted with Thom Terrazas, a Producer on the Vanguard: Saga of Heroes team. In this interview Thom discussed the changes that have been made to the performance of Vanguard. He stated that the changes to the game&#8217;s optimization are night and day compared to the launch product, going so far as to say &#8220;I&#8217;ll even flag your account for free for a period of time if you want to go in and prove me wrong.&#8221; I decided that I&#8217;d take Thom up on this offer. &lt;br />&lt;br />My first task was to contact SOE to see if indeed this claim would be backed up. I submitted a ticket to customer service, citing the article on Allakhazam and what Mr. Terrazas had said. Within a few hours I received an update to my ticket saying that customer service would indeed honor Thom&#8217;s word and grant me a 3 day flag to play the game again. After a quick email back confirming my Station account info I was granted my access.&lt;/div>&lt;a name="pause" title="pause">&lt;/a>&lt;div align="justify">&lt;p>I fired up the Launcher and began the process of patching my installation. During the download I took time to read through the major Game Updates and changes, each one making a point to note fixes to crash bugs and performance. Once I was patched I entered the world of Tellon for the first time in nearly a year. Much to my surprise my characters that I created were still there, as was a heap load of /claim rewards for my account (18 months of time accrued). Now it was time for me to challenge Mr. Terrazas and see if indeed the changes were real and noticeable. &lt;br />&lt;br />Allow me to give you a quick back story before I dive into my findings. I participated in the last two betas for Vanguard prior to the official launch. On launch day, with my collector&#8217;s edition in hand, I added my serial number to my account and began the formal journey into the game. Sadly for me (and many others) the final product that was released to the public was anything but final: numerous crashes, performance hitches, broken quests, faulty textures, and overall sluggish game play plagued the launch of Vanguard. It is important to note that my computer is no slouch but it is also not a Cray. My system specs at the time of the launch (and today for that matter) are:&lt;/p>&lt;ul>&lt;li>Pentium 4 3.2 GHz &lt;/li>&lt;li>2&#160;GB RAM PC3200&lt;/li>&lt;li>400GB HDD (2x 200GB) on RAID0&lt;/li>&lt;li>Geforce 8800 GTS 640MB on PCI-e&lt;/li>&lt;li>Creative Audigy 2&lt;/li>&lt;li>Windows Vista Ultimate&lt;/li>&lt;/ul>&lt;p>Again certainly not a super computer but very much able to handle most any game I&#8217;ve thrown at it. At launch Vanguard suffered from sub-standard frame rates on my computer. This was especially noticed whenever I was traveling through an Outpost or if I attempted to group. I also had issues with crashing whenever I traveled through a &#8220;chunk&#8221; (a.k.a. loaded zone area) on the map, sometimes even falling through the world to my death during the chunking (switching between the current area into the newly loaded area). Frequently I&#8217;d hitch in combat situations causing many deaths from simply not being able to participate in the battle. I lasted maybe 2 months at most after launch before I switched back to Everquest 2 and said goodbye to Vanguard. This was sad for me as I was very much excited for Vanguard and what it promised. &lt;br />&lt;br />Flash forward to today: Skeptical though I was after logging in for the first time I found that the performance of the engine was significantly improved. I found my level 14 Cleric in Three Rivers Village, right where I left him all those months ago. I will admit I scoffed at first as the world around me loaded in pieces at a time. My initial frame rates hovered under 10 fps for the first 20 seconds or so. In the back of my head all I could think was &#8220;no changes here.&#8221; However once I actually began to move around the area things picked up quickly. I found that while still somewhat lower than I&#8217;m used to in other games the FPS were indeed greatly improved overall. In open areas I achieved an average of 30 FPS. Indoor areas (inside of cabins, houses, even the castle in Leth Nurae) I found my FPS pushing over 40. The only low points came from Outposts, but even these were acceptable given the level of detail the engine is designed to deliver. &lt;br />&lt;br />Combat hitching seems to be eliminated. I opened my quest log and started running a handful of quests to see how the engine would fair in combat. Indeed Thom had it right when he said it was night and day from the launch. Even more to my delight is that again the FPS during combat maintained a steady rate, even with multiple targets pummeling me. &lt;br />&lt;br />The major concern I had was the chunking. Now I must say that while I am pleased with the changes made here I believe that the Vanguard team does need to focus on continuing to make the process seamless. I intentionally passed through chunks aimlessly just to see how well it would perform and if it would cause a crash. I experienced some hitching during the chunking, sometimes up to 10 seconds of hanging, but nowhere near what I experienced at launch. Never once did I crash or fall through the world. I never passed through a chunk only to be surprised by an already engaged target forcing my death rattle. Though still not quite seamless the chunking process is very much stable and smooth enough to satisfy any player that quit the game shortly after launch because of the aforementioned issues. &lt;br />&lt;br />I wish I had more time during my 3 days of play to see more of the game, but alas the real world always takes priority over video games. However I can honestly say that Thom Terrazas spoke the truth during his interview on Allakhazam. The performance optimization that the team has been working on has greatly improved the game play experience. If the development team continues to improve upon the changes they&#8217;ve already made I believe that Vanguard could stand a strong chance of being a late life surprise to the MMORPG market. However it will take more than just technical improvements to sway those who were lost along the way and encourage new players. &lt;br />&lt;br />SOE and the Vanguard team need to finish the &#8220;trial isle&#8221; that has been rumored for months on end and actually release it to the world along with an actual ad campaign. Also an invitation should be extended to former Vanguard players, granting free access to former account owners so that they too can see what has changed. And personally I&#8217;d like to see an expansion to the game sometime in the next year or so. After all the current level 50 cap will prove to be standard fare for any MMO player. &lt;br />&lt;br />Overall I have to commend SOE and the Vanguard team for continuing to support and improve a game that many in the industry assumed left for dead a long time ago. With continued effort in both the technical and marketing ends Vanguard could indeed live a second, more successful life. I encourage anyone who left the game early on to take another look&#8230; you&#8217;ll be pleasantly surprised. &lt;/p>&lt;/div>&lt;br />&lt;p align="right">&lt;em>&lt;font size="1">David &#8220;Griever&#8221; Anderson &lt;br />Freelance Writer&lt;/font>&lt;/em> &lt;/p></description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13562">
<title>City of Heroes/Villains Reactivation Weekend [City of Heroes]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13562</link>
<description>&lt;p>Played City of Heroes/Villains in the past, and thinking about making a comeback? Now&#39;s your chance to take a look at everything that&#39;s been added, all gratis!&lt;/p>&lt;blockquote>&lt;p>Just in time to try out all the new features included in &lt;a href="http://www.cityofheroes.com/game_update12.html">Issue 12: Midnight Hour&lt;/a>, it&#8217;s a free Reactivation Weekend! From Thursday, May 22nd starting at 11 AM Pacific (1 PM Eastern) and continuing through Sunday, May 25th at 8:59 PM Pacific (11:59 PM Eastern) all inactive accounts in good standing have free access to City of Heroes and/or City of Villains! &lt;/p>&lt;p>If you haven&#8217;t played in a while, be sure to read through the press release for the launch of Issue 12: Midnight Hour: &lt;a href="http://www.plaync.com/us/news/2008/05/ncsoft_covers_n.html">&#8220;NCsoft Covers New Ground in City of Heroes&#8221;&lt;/a> and visit the Official Message Forums for &lt;a href="http://boards.cityofheroes.com/showflat.php?Cat=0&amp;Number=10822043&amp;an=0&amp;page=0#Post10822043">a wealth of information about Issue 12&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>&lt;p>We&#8217;ll see you in game and have a great &#8220;City of&#8221; weekend! 					 						&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>    </description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13560">
<title>ArchLord Celebrates Milestone with Bonus Weekend [Archlord]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13560</link>
<description>In order to celebrate their recently announced milestone of half a million users, &lt;a href="http://www.archlordgame.com/" target="_blank">ArchLord &lt;/a>is thanking the loyal players with a bonus weekend.  &lt;blockquote>&lt;p>&#160;&lt;/p>&lt;p>Double the Fun Weekend!&lt;/p>&lt;p>&#160;&lt;br />This weekend from 16:00 (GMT+1) on Friday to 08:00 (GMT+1) on Tuesday we will be running a double the fun weekend.&lt;br />&lt;br /> Both experience and drops will be double throughout the whole of this weekend across all three servers!&lt;br />&lt;br /> We hope you enjoy this event in the world of Chantra.  &lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>    </description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13559">
<title>Zu Online: New Client &amp; Patch Released  [Zu Online]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13559</link>
<description>&lt;p align="justify">Zu Online has a new patch that should help improve PvP.&lt;/p>&lt;blockquote>&lt;p align="justify">The &lt;a href="http://zu.igg.com">Zu Online&lt;/a>  Team&lt;a href="http://zu.igg.com/" target="_blank">&lt;/a> announced that the new 1.4.06 Patch had been  released on May 21st with an adjustment to class balance and improvement  of the PVP system. &#160;&lt;/p>&lt;p align="justify">Please visit  the official site to download either the latest client 1.4.06 or the  complete patch for updating any previous version to &lt;a href="http://1.4.06./" target="_blank">1.4.06.&lt;/a> &#160;&lt;br /> &lt;/p>&lt;p align="justify">The Latest  Client 1.4.06&lt;/p>&lt;p>Zu Online Game Client  &lt;a href="http://us-ca-d1.iggcn.com/zu/20080519/zu_setup_1.4.06.exe " target="_blank">Link&lt;/a> &lt;/p>&lt;p align="justify">Zu Online Game  Complete &lt;a href="http://us-ca-d1.iggcn.com/zu/20080519/zu_Up_1.4.02-1.4.06.exe " target="_blank">Patch&lt;/a>&lt;/p>&lt;p>For more download choice please  visit &lt;a href="http://zu.igg.com/news/newscon.php?aid=747 " target="_blank">here&lt;/a>.&lt;br /> &lt;/p>&lt;a href="http://zu.igg.com/news/newscon.php?aid=747" target="_blank">&lt;br />&lt;/a>&lt;/blockquote>        </description>
</item>

<item rdf:about="http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13558">
<title>Angels Online Newbie Guide [Angels Online]</title>
<link>http://www.allakhazam.com/story.html?story=13558</link>
<description>For everything you&#39;ve ever wanted to know about starting Angels Online, but were afraid to ask:&lt;br />&lt;blockquote>&lt;p align="center">Angles Online:  Newbie Guide  ＃1 &#160;&lt;/p>&lt;p align="justify">The new Eden  expansion has successfully attracted a large number of new players to  register, so the &lt;a href="http://ao.igg.com/main.php" target="_blank">Angles Online&lt;/a> team wants to teach newbie players all  the basics about the Angel Lyceum and the new version. &#160;&lt;br /> &lt;/p>&lt;p align="justify">For more information  please visit us &lt;a href="    http://ao.igg.com/guide/chapters.php" target="_blank">here&lt;/a>.&lt;br /> &lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote></description>
</item>

</rdf:RDF>

