<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>I don&apos;t mind more 1/2 group content and content scaled lower power (for lower reward) than typi</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I don&apos;t mind more 1/2 group content and content scaled lower power (for lower reward) than typical missions.  I actually like the WoW five-person-group.

I&apos;d rather have 1/2 group stuff and stuff set for 30 minute or 45 minute gameplay sessons than more solo content.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;So why didn&apos;t they? The beta had open slots for a long time. Entire guilds were given acc</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;So why didn&apos;t they? The beta had open slots for a long time. Entire guilds were given access to beta. If the Stormhammer community was so eager to help test high-end raid content, why didn&apos;t they do it?&quot;

The /betabuff characters were considerably better equipped than the average characters on SH once Township Rebellion and Precision Strike left the server.

The community kept playing and enjoying the content, but normal expa</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;I don&apos;t mind more 1/2 group content and content scaled lower power (for lower reward) tha</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;I don&apos;t mind more 1/2 group content and content scaled lower power (for lower reward) than typical missions. I actually like the WoW five-person-group.

I&apos;d rather have 1/2 group stuff and stuff set for 30 minute or 45 minute gameplay sessons than more solo content.&quot;

Agreed.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Only an observation since SOE says it will continue to add more MMs.

They were (I say were) popular</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Only an observation since SOE says it will continue to add more MMs.

They were (I say were) popular not only because of the nice rewards, but because a small group could be assembled in a matter of minutes and usually finish a mission in less than half an hour.  Perfect for short log on sessions or to kill time when waiting for guilds or friends to log on and assemble for bigger missions.

The last patches nerfed them, reducing the rewards and i</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Besides forcing people to actually be &quot;in&quot; the mission to earn the experience, what did th</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Besides forcing people to actually be &quot;in&quot; the mission to earn the experience, what did they nerf?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I know the guk one was nerfed to be harder to train the goblins to the zone... and think I heard the</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I know the guk one was nerfed to be harder to train the goblins to the zone... and think I heard the clockwork one was nerfed so that you had a limited # of lives... but am not sure if there were global changes made to further nerf them.  (I don&apos;t consider having to be in the zone and looting the crystal a nerf... though I wish they could have just flagged you as having entered the zone, as looting an otherwise meaningless object seems like </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MM&apos;s pretty dead on my server too. I really cant understand why they want content that no one u</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>MM&apos;s pretty dead on my server too. I really cant understand why they want content that no one uses. I wish they paid attention to LDoNs they way they did MMs, maybe peeps would still be able to do em.  All I heard out of peeps was how GREAT this expansion was going to be. Well, the next one I think I&apos;ll pass on for 3 to 6 months so i wont know about what they nerfed and what is was like when it went live. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>One has to remember Everquest is a flowing game.  It changes over time.  I&apos;m sure people who go</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>One has to remember Everquest is a flowing game.  It changes over time.  I&apos;m sure people who got LDON and DOD are glad that they bought them and played them early, before the experience was nerfed.  I think the eventual nerfing is simply the fact that if it&apos;s too good no one will play anywhere else.  There are many threads in different forums that say MMs were ruining the game as no one could find groups to play any of the &quot;regular</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>My real life groupmates were not using the MM&apos;s to Level....but to catch up on the huge gap we </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>My real life groupmates were not using the MM&apos;s to Level....but to catch up on the huge gap we have as casual players AA wise. I would never want to level much in a MM do to the lack off skill increase. But it is nice to be over the 200aa mark now, which I would not be at if no MMs.

As for the wait on the next Expansion. For me, I would rather not know what im missing. I was playing when you got 2aas per MM and now its 75-80% of one. If I j</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Aye, and now with the lock out timers on all the missions and the lower reward it looks like I&apos;</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Aye, and now with the lock out timers on all the missions and the lower reward it looks like I&apos;m back to grinding the Creator. I can almost get AAs as fast in DON content as I can in MMs now. This may be the intent of nerfing them this way. 

As a game of this scope ages the emptiness of old content and old zones grows more and more. What happened to LDON, will happen to DON, and will happen to MMs.  One has to wonder what they will do with </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Someone I know went from 52 to 70 only grinding in MMs. They have no gear, no skills but my god can </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Someone I know went from 52 to 70 only grinding in MMs. They have no gear, no skills but my god can they play a fairy well! Gone are the days where u need skills and hard work to progress...now it&apos;s about learning how todo 2 MMs quickly so you can just chain them to get max exp.

6finger Discount
Assmuncher of 
Quellious</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>When the DoD expansion went live, the MMs were bugged and needed to be fixed.  It was possible to be</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>When the DoD expansion went live, the MMs were bugged and needed to be fixed.  It was possible to be grouped and never enter or accept the mission and still gain exp and AAs.  With practice, some of the MMs could be soloed while the other group members were /afk.  I know one person who went from 67 - 70 and 20 AA - 100 AA in the Werewolf MM in a couple of days.

After the first patch, the exp and AAs were adjusted and later the addition of an ite</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>They should add a MM variant to each LDON which would reward you with some LDON points as well as so</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>They should add a MM variant to each LDON which would reward you with some LDON points as well as some XP. The points can replace the item reward. This might help those of us who still want some things in LDON but can never find a group willing to go there.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Personally I dont like most of the lore coming out of monster missions. the only one I would realist</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Personally I dont like most of the lore coming out of monster missions. the only one I would realistically try would be the one in Overthere, and I dont even think that is worth its time.

Monster missions were ill tuned forceing several wipes because the monsters were undertuned for the content. 

you could never take tradeskill/cash drops out of them. and now that experience is not there MMs are not a very appetizeing thing</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>There is a reason why the adds that spawn during Sendaii event only have 10-12k hitpoints, ae them d</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>There is a reason why the adds that spawn during Sendaii event only have 10-12k hitpoints, ae them down as they spawn and you will have no problem whatsoever..</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>