<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Everquest news, editorials, and commentary.</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<copyright>Copyright 2005</copyright>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2005 16:09:24 -0500</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2005 20:48:05 -0500</pubDate>
<generator>http://www.movabletype.org/?v=3.01D</generator>
<docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs> 

<item>
<title>Other Worlds Than These</title>
<description>The Overlord falls and the people rejoice. Today&apos;s update falls back to the more traditional news roundup, covering the fall of Mata Muram, the class re-envisioning, the anniversary, a couple of new features, and other bits of interesting news from the field.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000055.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000055.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2005 16:09:24 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda of Spring 2005</title>
<description>Today Loral releases another infamous Evil Agenda focusing on improvements to Everquest since the release of Dragons of Norrath.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000054.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000054.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2005 14:01:49 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Chipped Tooth of the Dragon</title>
<description>Dragons of Norrath adds many new and popular elements to Everquest, proving that Everquest continues to be a progressing and exciting game.  Not everything in this expansion shines so brightly, however, and this week we take a look at some of the problems in Dragons of Norrath and make a few suggestions.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000053.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000053.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2005 19:41:05 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>On the Wings of Dragons</title>
<description>This week we look at a couple of developer chats, Brenlo&apos;s World, feedback on the new bazaar, more server merger announcements, and the announcement of the Mentor system for Everquest 2.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000052.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2005 09:05:08 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral&apos;s Declaration of Principles</title>
<description>We take a quick break from the busy times since the opening of Dragons of Norrath to take a closer look at the purpose and promise of Loral&apos;s articles on Mobhunter.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000051.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000051.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2005 22:09:20 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Results of Gnomish Curiosity</title>
<description>Never failing to turn over the rock best left unturned, enterprising gnomes break open the wall of Lavastorm and once again change the face of Norrath.  This week we look at the release and some recently revealed features of Dragons of Norrath.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000050.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000050.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2005 08:31:57 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Dragons of Norrath Preview</title>
<description>On 15 February 2005, Sony Online Entertainment releases the ninth expansion for Everquest.  With new story-based missions, a new point-based loot system, instanced guild halls, beautiful graphics, and excellent user interface features, this may be the best Everquest expansion yet.  Read more to find out why.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000049.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000049.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2005 21:12:27 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Of Wing and Fang</title>
<description>This week we saw a new patch and a detailed interview with the developers of the Dragons of Norrath expansion.  This week&apos;s article discusses the new Mistmoore and Paw zones, the change to LDON&apos;s adventure selection, and touches on the exciting Dragons of Norrath mission system.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000048.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000048.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2005 09:05:58 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The World Has Changed</title>
<description>Dark clouds black out the frosted skies of Iceclad.  Iron boots crush into the eternal snow of Dreadlands.  Whispers of an ancient evil sift through the lands of the north.  The world changes.  This week we look at the historic moments we now face in the lands of Norrath.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000047.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000047.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2005 08:33:13 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Breaking News:  Dragons of Norrath</title>
<description>The coming of the Dragons of Norrath is upon us.  Read on for detailed information and commentary on this new Everquest expansion and a note about Everquest 2&apos;s announced Adventure Packs.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000046.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000046.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2005 23:30:07 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Topics of the New Year</title>
<description>This week we look at the current hot topics of Everquest including more class balance goodness, server consolidations, the life of Everquest, and the delayed guild summit.  Loral also officially eats crow.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000045.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000045.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2005 20:18:43 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Refunds, Mergers, and Flags</title>
<description>Today we comment on the most recent patch, talk a little about the forum traffic, and give an exclusive scoop on the subject of server merges.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000044.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000044.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2004 19:37:46 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Everquest Patch Message, 15 December 2004</title>
<description>Today SOE released the first large patch for EQ since before the Fan Faire.  The patch included backflagging changes, Gates AA refunds and changes, revamps of Paw and Mistmoore on Stormhammer, and new hotzones.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000043.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000043.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2004 10:26:23 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>News of the Winter&apos;s Moon</title>
<description>This week we look at the state of the game this holiday season and make a few wild and uninformed predictions.  We also take a look at what we hope to see in the coming December 15th patch.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000042.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000042.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2004 21:44:09 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Everquest 2 Review</title>
<description>Today Mobhunter offers a double-sized article: a full review of the first two weeks of Everquest 2.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000041.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000041.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2004 11:14:46 -0500</pubDate>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>