<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>The big problem with EQ is that it is now all about equipment, augs and levels and nothing about hav</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The big problem with EQ is that it is now all about equipment, augs and levels and nothing about having fun with friends, and adventuring. </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Did Robin Laws have a hand in the development?  The combat &amp; monster system sound like they were</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Did Robin Laws have a hand in the development?  The combat &amp; monster system sound like they were lifted directly from his mid 90&apos;s game, Feng Shui.

Having played D&amp;D since the white boxed set, I don&apos;t want to hear people griping about having to invest in a new system.  Been there &amp; done that multiple times.  I know of two groups that still play AD&amp;D because they didn&apos;t want to reinvest in new a new system.  Nobody </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>My big problem with it is that it has become less generic with this new edition.  D&amp;D 3.5 was al</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>My big problem with it is that it has become less generic with this new edition.  D&amp;D 3.5 was already starting to merge the fluff and the crunch together to the point where you had little things that would appear in your game that (as a GM) you might not approve of.

I saw more and more classes gain minor abilities that could only be explained as &quot;magical.&quot;  I had a setting in mind where the magic and the martial were separate, but </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Disappointing 4th edition really is.  Casters have been reduced to almost nothing.  The Spell Compen</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Disappointing 4th edition really is.  Casters have been reduced to almost nothing.  The Spell Compendium from 3.5 is now ash.  There really is no ability to control how a mage learns spells.

All classes have, in essence, become the same.  The simpler learning curve of fighters compared to the advanced study of the mage is no more.  It makes it hard to use the imagination.

For instance:  a first level mage versus a first level fighter.  That mag</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I haven&apos;t played D&amp;D for years (let&apos;s just say that when I last played we didn&apos;t </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I haven&apos;t played D&amp;D for years (let&apos;s just say that when I last played we didn&apos;t have any fancy &quot;editions&quot;) but I remember all too well the leveling curve Magical Tim describes. At low levels magic-users were practically a liability (&quot;Come on guys, protect the magic-user. He&apos;ll be useful someday.&quot;) while at high levels everyone else is relegated to filling space while spells decide the course of the bat</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I can honestly say I&apos;ve been playin D&amp;D even longer than you - I still have all of the old </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I can honestly say I&apos;ve been playin D&amp;D even longer than you - I still have all of the old 1st edition AD&amp;D books, played second, played third, played 3.5 - picked up 4th and really wanted to like it.  Unfortunately it&apos;s just not D&amp;D anymore - it&apos;s too pigeon holed, the mechanics and powers are sub-Diablo 2 level of interest.

This isn&apos;t a case of fear of change... it&apos;s a case of Wizards putting out a dud... a</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I&apos;ve been a DM/GM for 20+ years.  I&apos;ve played a variety of different RPG&apos;s.  I&apos;v</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I&apos;ve been a DM/GM for 20+ years.  I&apos;ve played a variety of different RPG&apos;s.  I&apos;ve also read through the 4th Ed books, made a few characters, and ran a few mock combats.

I considered listing the pluses and minuses, but it really isn&apos;t worth it.  You are a DM, it&apos;s your house, change it to suit your needs.

My final analysis is this: no matter how you play it, the game was designed to emulate MMO&apos;s to some extent</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I played D&amp;D for a long time.  Basic and 1st are my favorite.  But I have enjoyed 2E, 3E, and 3.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I played D&amp;D for a long time.  Basic and 1st are my favorite.  But I have enjoyed 2E, 3E, and 3.5E.  But for me, I don&apos;t enjoy 4E.  I find it bland and the magic is just wrong for me and my group.  I have played 4E a few times now.  For my group it&apos;s back to the earlier editions.

I think one of the problems is that they are trying to make the classes balanced against each other instead of building a party that is balanced against w</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Well having just read reviews on 4th edition and not actually reading them myself i must say that th</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Well having just read reviews on 4th edition and not actually reading them myself i must say that the general feeling i get is that the game has been &quot;streamlined&quot; for simple conversion into a video game which would make sense given todays MMO game popularity. It would make sense (marketing) to launch a Pen and Paper game and identical MMO video game online to bolster the ranks of D&amp;D players.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I guess I just don&apos;t see how the video game metaphor holds up. If we&apos;re saying it uses the</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I guess I just don&apos;t see how the video game metaphor holds up. If we&apos;re saying it uses the best of other roleplay systems that video and computer games use, sure, I suppose that&apos;s true. But the important differences between a video game and a tabletop game are still there. The DM still builds the world, the players still have a huge degree of freedom in their characters and in the world. It&apos;s still a bunch of people sitting ar</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Hi there.  I go way back to 1E and the original basic rules, then I played a lot of 2E in my day.  H</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Hi there.  I go way back to 1E and the original basic rules, then I played a lot of 2E in my day.  However, my group of friends that played broke up years ago when 2E was the latest version out there.  I felt that 2E was a worthy successor to the original AD&amp;D, and we enjoyed it very much.  My only complaint back then was that they just flooded the market with too many different campaign worlds and optional rules booklets, to keep track.  I n</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Did you guys even look further into the game? 4E books and gameplay, i agree has went down in qualit</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Did you guys even look further into the game? 4E books and gameplay, i agree has went down in quality. The hole point of the 4.0 is to make it easyer for there new online table top game to be understood and used by the younger people. I have been playing d&amp;d from when 3.0 came out but i started in 2.0 ( i even still have the old books) 4E is enjoyable on its own, but you guys seem to forget that its not the original dnd, every E has changed t</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I used to DM when I was in high school and at one point I had a campaign with about 13 players. Keep</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I used to DM when I was in high school and at one point I had a campaign with about 13 players. Keeping that many people entertained to the point where they were kicking me awake every sunday to play in my world I thought was a pretty good endorsement of my skill in the area of extemporaneous fiction.

However, as a DM, I felt AD&amp;D was broken because of its turn basis (let me stand around and watch other people move until it&apos;s my turn, t</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I have played D&amp;D from Basic when I was 7 years old back in the early 80s until just buying 4th </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I have played D&amp;D from Basic when I was 7 years old back in the early 80s until just buying 4th ed the other day.  I must say that I am really apprehensive with this system.  I am sure the proof will be in the pudding, in both the gameplay as well as convincing my gaming buddies to actually play the game.

It is hard to completely identify my concerns, but much of them I believe have to do with what everyone nowadays seems to call the &quot;f</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>i&apos;ve read all of these review and im irritated. first and foremost im not gonna say how long i&</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>i&apos;ve read all of these review and im irritated. first and foremost im not gonna say how long i&apos;ve played D&amp;D and whatnot... all that crap doesn&apos;t really matter IMO... i like all the editions, for different reasons for each

what matters is this, they came out with a new system to use for the game, but the game is forever the essense of the creativity coming from the DM and the characters playing it... If you want WoW on a table</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>