<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>This is an extremely angry article and it&apos;s kind of upsetting for me. I would have much rather </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>This is an extremely angry article and it&apos;s kind of upsetting for me. I would have much rather you say &quot;EQ is long past me, I don&apos;t really have a comment on this.&quot; than your angry, uncharacteristic rant. Also the Living Legacy promotion doesn&apos;t just effect EQ but EQ2 as well and the latter has me back hook line and sinker after a good run with WoW.

Regardless, what this promotion says to me is &quot;Norrath is here to st</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Yeah, wish you&apos;d actually played it for a short time before coming out with the &apos;here&apos</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Yeah, wish you&apos;d actually played it for a short time before coming out with the &apos;here&apos;s what you need todo to save EQ&apos; post that we see every day in the vet forums.
XP gain rate is HUGELY increased.
Gear is, if anything,too easy to get.

It&apos;s never been easier to get a group, play the game, enjoy it having fun.  If you can&apos;t put in more time playing the game than it probably took to write the article, then I&apos;m a</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;It&apos;s never been easier to get a group&quot;

I find that very hard to believe.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;It&apos;s never been easier to get a group&quot;

I find that very hard to believe.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Login, hang around a hotzone and see for yourself.

I&apos;ve left my alts of various levels in the </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Login, hang around a hotzone and see for yourself.

I&apos;ve left my alts of various levels in the level appropriate hotzones and have groups (with different players) within a minute or so of logging in.  I don&apos;t use /lfg, I run up, see if there&apos;s a spot, and offer my services.  If full, move to next group.  
TBH, this has been my method since I started playing and it&apos;s worked well for me so far, just seems really easy to get a gr</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>How about simply lowering EQ&apos;s system requirements?  </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>How about simply lowering EQ&apos;s system requirements?  </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;It&apos;s never been easier to get a group, play the game, enjoy it having fun.&quot;

This is</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;It&apos;s never been easier to get a group, play the game, enjoy it having fun.&quot;

This is actually the hardest time to find a group unless your a raider or personally know other people in the game.

just because its easier does not mean they should be resting, plenty of people who left feel the same way as Loral and do not want to play a game that requires their life as payment to be able to do anything in game.

and its really only en</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I will try(no promises) to get time this weekend to log into EQ, and do an experiment, seeing how lo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I will try(no promises) to get time this weekend to log into EQ, and do an experiment, seeing how long it takes to put together a pickup group.  Again, no promises, but I will try.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Here&apos;s my two cents for what it&apos;s worth.  Fascinating reading y&apos;all&apos;s posts, btw</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Here&apos;s my two cents for what it&apos;s worth.  Fascinating reading y&apos;all&apos;s posts, btw.  =) 

Some of us left EQ simply because the graphics requirements exceeded our video capabilities, and we couldn&apos;t afford to upgrade our notebooks every six-twelve months.

After switching to Mac, I discovered to my delight the EQ download is free, so I tried it again.  Unfortunately, SoE doesn&apos;t really cater to Macs (boo-hoo!) as there</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>4 hours to be level 2 as a melee?

Uhm, if you play the tutorial, you get level 2 by the time you ev</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>4 hours to be level 2 as a melee?

Uhm, if you play the tutorial, you get level 2 by the time you even reach the adventure area and hail the NPCs.  Total time, probably about 5 minutes.

Maybe the Mac version does not have the tutorial, but the PC version does. :)</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>For returning players, there are simply too many AAs that were originally put in place to slow peopl</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>For returning players, there are simply too many AAs that were originally put in place to slow people down or address for quirks in the interface.  Many of these should be eliminated and refunded outright or addressed through simple quests from your GM . Some examples:

Battle Ready. 5AAs for extra bandoleer slot. Players should not have to pay AAs because of user interface design. Possible to just do this manually, but why make it harder on play</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I’m going to start t his by disagreeing with Loral on his first point: “It wasn&apos;t armor power o</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I’m going to start t his by disagreeing with Loral on his first point: “It wasn&apos;t armor power or the cost of the expansion or the lack of raids that pushed many players over to World of Warcraft; it was the lack of entertaining battles and encounters and a feeling of helplessness when it comes to progression.”

There are many reasons people left EQ, as varied and personal as there are people that left, and the longer the player has been away</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>In addition with my post, I want to share an annoying/funny story.

I am a Bard; I have the mask tha</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>In addition with my post, I want to share an annoying/funny story.

I am a Bard; I have the mask that allows me to cast Dark Elf illusion on myself. It was a bit of a hobby of mine to wonder around Neriak, and I was curious if it was on the list of revamped zones so I went there. Now, I do remember that illusions faded with zoning so once in I recast my illusion. Everyone is dubious, since I follow Erolissis Mar, and rare guards are KoS. I  bump </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Long time EQer from way back. I stopped playing EQ in 05, they are right.. i left because it was bur</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Long time EQer from way back. I stopped playing EQ in 05, they are right.. i left because it was burned out and tired. Played WoW till a few months ago and retired that game.. again.. raiding BT / HJ gets boring and tiring.. need something new.. or something different. I went back to a old fallback, AO, I had so much fun playing a old familiar friend.Played some AoC but now i see this promotion.. going to walk around check out how EQ has changed </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Well, I logged back in this weekend to meet up with some old friends and dust my characters off once</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Well, I logged back in this weekend to meet up with some old friends and dust my characters off once again.  I have to say the game is looking tired indeed and the graphics left a lot to be desired.  I guess there&apos;s no going home again.  However, I&apos;ll continue to post here because I always enjoyed talking about EQ much more than actually playing it.  Look for another article from me soon titled &quot;Ten Changes SOE Should Make That Sti</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Oh Red, you&apos;re such a girl.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Oh Red, you&apos;re such a girl.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>