<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/">
   <channel rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>eq2.fohguild.org</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2/phpnews/eq2.fohguild.org.rss</link>
      <description>
         This RSS feed was generated out of the newsdatabase of
         eq2.fohguild.org website.
      </description>
      <items>
         <rdf:Seq>
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
            <rdf:li resource="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2" />
         </rdf:Seq>
      </items>
   </channel>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Farm farm farm ....</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         As you can see the site is back up and in full action again.  All you fanbois can relax now and feel free to hit the website 47 times an hour hoping to see some uber loot update.  This update will make even your bookmarked pornsites seem boring.  Lets start off with the tweaks made from the big patch.Armor Tints - Red storm trooper, clamshell, then black.  Im in favor of just having a /random for the color and look of your armor at this point. Rating: 4HOs - Ahh yes, hos.  Now made practically retard free!  The new animations are a bit rough on the system, but everyone loves playing on Atari mode anyways (hugs Nvidia)  Rating: 9Armor Class - Hurray for big numbers.  Numbers make me happy.  Bigger numbers are the uberer I r.  Rating: 9New Heritages - GEBs and Tranix.  If you love Lavastorm (yay trains and lava ports!!) then enjoy lagtastic hours of running everywhere in this zone.  Lets not forget you need to know 12 different languages (including Chinese and Spanish) to even get half way done.  Rating: 6Metal Chests:  Wooden box with 2 41st lvl adept dropped from a groupx4 epic mob after spending 40 mins beating on 100 million hps... awesome way to spend friday night.  Now with the adjusted loot on these mobs, we have something to look forward to dragging 24 people to the depths of Sol Ro.  Thank you for this adjustment.  Rating: 10Venekor - Saved the best one for last.  Yes, the uber creation of Moorgard.  Before the tweek it was a good fight.  Challenging and some strat needed for success.  Someone felt it necessary to change this encounter from exciting to absurd.  If you are going to make some AE raid wide, think about putting in resist checks, toning down the 4k per tick dot, or make it have a managable range. I am sure your testers did great against him before you released it to the Live servers (/hug).  Rating: 2With all the glorious changes we have enjoying farming the metal boxes from x2 and x4 mobs.  Even though they made mobs hit harder (Hi2u 6k nukes)... Agi boost work for crap... these fellas just cowboy up and get it done.  Heres the spoils of their hard work.Grats Pathogenn!Grats Mystique!Grats Insognito!Grats Endalmir!Grats Poyzin
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Jan 29th, 2005 Noah Update</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         YS~~Quick update to show off a very nice piece of gear we got from the Fist of Solusek (20% Haste 4tw)THX FIST!!
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Another day, another dragon</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         So a couple days ago we talked to Nagafen, and I guess that after 500 years of being cooped up in the bottom of Solusek he's ready to get some booty.  He sent us to the crypt in Permafrost to get Vox all ready for him, but she wasn't in a particularly cooperative mood.  Common decency reared it's ugly head yet again, and we killed the insolent bitch.Noah was kind enough to provide this image.It took me 2 days to get around to making this update, but I was working on the site.
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>And so it begins....</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         Now I could have posted loot from some gay 50th lvl quest in Cazic Thule (omfg, Blood Fire!11one)... but I think people need to see what is truly out there on these x4 epic mobs.  Here is some "soccer mom" loot for you to wish for....THX VENE!!     THX KRA'THUK!!And of course everyone needs to post their "I've seen Naggy and got the uber quest" pic... so here you go...~Noah Notfuror
      </description>
   </item>
   <item rdf:about="http://www.fohguild.org/eq2">
      <title>Site Launched!</title>
      <link>http://www.fohguild.org/eq2</link>
      <description>
         eq2.fohguild.org is launched... Halfway.  The main page still isn't done, and the dns isn't set up for it to be eq2.fohguild.org yet, but the rest of the site is operational.  More news and a mainpage update coming soon.  The gallery uses the forum users.  Mouseover @ to upload.
      </description>
   </item>
</rdf:RDF>
