<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>pbktzh zfxbuj zexqyoc ezfm qkwe envpq ifqpjn</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>pbktzh zfxbuj zexqyoc ezfm qkwe envpq ifqpjn</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>New models are being worked on, &quot;elves&quot; are in the pipeline.

Jourdian (Clint Worley) has </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>New models are being worked on, &quot;elves&quot; are in the pipeline.

Jourdian (Clint Worley) has a new &quot;EQBlog&quot; up and running.

http://eqdev.wordpress.com/</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>New models in the pipeline &quot;Elves&quot;.

http://eqdev.wordpress.com/</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>New models in the pipeline &quot;Elves&quot;.

http://eqdev.wordpress.com/</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Also in regards to EQ, from this source:  http://forums.station.sony.com/eq/posts/list.m?topic_id=12</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Also in regards to EQ, from this source:  http://forums.station.sony.com/eq/posts/list.m?topic_id=128186  Zatozia wrote the following:

&quot;Greetings,

At the beginning of the year, I mentioned that changes would be happening with the correspondent program. The changes are close on the horizon.

The existing correspondent program and the current community leader group (from previous summits) will be phased out.  Instead, I will be implementing </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Redhenna,

All good news this month from SOE, and as you posted on the SOE forums, SOE is making som</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Redhenna,

All good news this month from SOE, and as you posted on the SOE forums, SOE is making somewhere between 1,495,000 to 2,990,000 per month on EQ still.  So while not a IP that SOE is looking to reinvest into, they certainly have every reason to keep the IP performing, perhaps even to see somall expansion on as they move more and more into housing a catalog of MMO titles with micro-transaction system boosting the bottom line.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I enjoyed reading the article and I look forward to more.  It is quite clear that EverQuest must con</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I enjoyed reading the article and I look forward to more.  It is quite clear that EverQuest must continually improve in order to meet the needs of the players who log in.  I am delighted to hear that part-time players (less than 40 hrs/week) are progressing in the game.  I think the decision to slow down the expansions was a good one.  This gives some rest time for the guilds at the top as well. They can farm until everyone in the guild has upgra</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&gt;&gt; One issue I have is while non-devs (Nolrog) have mentioned multiplies in the 3x range,

Any</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&gt;&gt; One issue I have is while non-devs (Nolrog) have mentioned multiplies in the 3x range,

Any multiple that I mentioned were for use in the example in my post, and not meant to represent anything that acutally may happen (since we won&apos;t know until it goes live.)

N
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Moreau, thank you for your kind words.  I wanted to quickly comment on one thing you said that I sor</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Moreau, thank you for your kind words.  I wanted to quickly comment on one thing you said that I sorta did not like though.

&quot;This gives some rest time for the guilds at the top as well. They can farm until everyone in the guild has upgraded gear in all 22 slots and then enjoy real life for a bit or farm gear for alts for the hardcore collectors.&quot;

There is this complete falacy that hardcore raiders do not have a life.  Raiders I have k</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The thing is that the old world is getting updated with hot zones, and the WoW ticketed on itemizati</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The thing is that the old world is getting updated with hot zones, and the WoW ticketed on itemization will never sell. The &quot;gear gap&quot; is something that will continually exist and perpetuate the game&apos;s difficulty level.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>With regards to the gear gap... one of the major stumbling blocks is for the devs to let go of this </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>With regards to the gear gap... one of the major stumbling blocks is for the devs to let go of this &quot;raid gear&quot; attitude on much older expansions.  A good example was the Eron&apos;s jewelry quest where the caster version got a weaker version of maelin&apos;s meditation which is obtained very easily from a single group MPG trial. Another example is AC levels on tank gear stagnating for groupers. They refuse to budge because &quot;once a</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Omega, old world zones are not being updated, just given a higher ZEM and some(I think) temporary ne</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Omega, old world zones are not being updated, just given a higher ZEM and some(I think) temporary new named mobs and drops(do the new named/drops stay beyond the hotzone timeframe?).  I think more could be done, without taking up a whole lot of dev time.

&quot;the WoW ticketed on itemization will never sell&quot;--I am not following that statement at all.  What do you mean by that?

The gear gap will stay around forever, but I do not see what it</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Yes, any changes made (beyond ZEM) for hot zones stay even after the zones lose their hotzone status</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Yes, any changes made (beyond ZEM) for hot zones stay even after the zones lose their hotzone status.  For example, you can go, right now, to Seb, and eventually get an unmasked changeling to pop and drop you a decent aug, even though that was from 3-4 hotzones ago. :)</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thanks xsi.  That does not change the idea that more can be done(quests omg) with hotzones.  By the </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Thanks xsi.  That does not change the idea that more can be done(quests omg) with hotzones.  By the way, the unmasked changlings where awesome though.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I want to expand on a thought Redhenna mentioned.  I think that one of the biggest injustices that S</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I want to expand on a thought Redhenna mentioned.  I think that one of the biggest injustices that SOE did to EQ was to tie the group gear to a percentage of the mythical &quot;average raider.&quot; I know why they did that, but I don&apos;t think they even had a clue as to it&apos;s impact on the game over an extended period of time.

The goal, of course, was to keep a separation between the average raider and the top end grouper, making raiding</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Great post Keisa &amp; I agree with you on your gear balancing viewpoint.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Great post Keisa &amp; I agree with you on your gear balancing viewpoint.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>