<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- generator="Movable Type/2.62" -->
<rss version="0.91">
  <channel>
    <title>LoralCiriclight.com</title>
    <link>http://loralciriclight.com/</link>
    <description>Tales and adventures of Loral Ciriclight in the online role playing game, Everquest.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <webMaster>mike@mikeshea.net</webMaster>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2003 04:18:11 +0000</pubDate>

    <item>
      <title>Drundor</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000113.html</link>
      <description> &quot;The warriors of Zek are not finished with you. The fires of War are eternal. I shall return.&quot; The...</description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Lxanvom</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000103.html</link>
      <description>It is with a quivering hand that I write my last words. At my feet lies my lord, the thirteenth...</description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Nightmare</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000093.html</link>
      <description>Breath burned through Loral&apos;s lungs as he raced across the land of Nightmares. He could hear the pursuing hobgoblins getting...</description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Disease</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000092.html</link>
      <description>Loral looked with revulsion into the pit that led into the Plane of Disease and the giant pipe that eternally...</description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The Godslayer</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000091.html</link>
      <description>Since the dawn of Norrath, pain, torment, and horror all paid homage to the Plane of Fear. Dark demons and...</description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Light</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000090.html</link>
      <description>&quot;And what of the heroic paladin lost to the Shissar? What ever happened to him?&quot; Loral had told his son...</description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Darkness</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000089.html</link>
      <description>&quot;It was a dark moment, my boy. Perhaps darker than any I had faced before. The ancient serpents paralyzed me...</description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Ssraeshza</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000088.html</link>
      <description>For one hundred twenty years Yylis had been a slave of the Shissar. For seventy of those years he had...</description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The Grey</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000087.html</link>
      <description>Jolain Goldenleaf stared out over the wastelands of the Grey. The vacuum of the land pulled his skin tight against...</description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>A brief history of the Iksar</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000086.html</link>
      <description>Understanding a species requires an understanding of its history. This parchment discusses the main turning points of the great Iksar...</description>
    </item>

  </channel>
</rss>