<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://mikeshea.net/rss.css" type="text/css"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

  <channel>
    <title>LoralCiriclight.com</title>
    <link>http://loralciriclight.com/</link>
    <description>Tales and adventures of Loral Ciriclight in the online role playing game, Everquest.</description>
    <dc:language>en-us</dc:language>
    <dc:creator>mike@mikeshea.net</dc:creator>
    <dc:rights>Copyright 2005</dc:rights>
    <dc:date>2005-06-01T05:01:37+00:00</dc:date>
    <admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.movabletype.org/?v=3.01D" />
    <admin:errorReportsTo rdf:resource="mailto:mike@mikeshea.net"/>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>

    <item>
      <title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda - Las Vegas, Summer 2005</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001305.html</link>
      <description>Next week I travel west to the Las Vegas Fan Faire and to the second Everquest Summit. Once again I...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1305@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Next week I travel west to the Las Vegas Fan Faire and to the second Everquest Summit.  Once again I will bring my recommendations to help improve Everquest.  Many of the items discussed in previous Evil Agendas have been addressed by SOE and it is my hope that these issues will be addressed as well.</p>

<h2>Help Players Find Groups</h2>

<p>This is by far the number one issue in Everquest today.  SOE developers should do anything they can to help players find groups, build groups, and get groups off and hunting as fast as possible.  Players below 60 have much greater trouble finding groups than those above 60.  SOE should always look for ways to increase the pool of players looking for groups at all levels.  Here are some specific suggestions to help improve grouping:</p>

<p>- Allow group invites across zones and from within the "Looking for Group" tool.<br />
- Continue to focus on mission-based content.  Missions are the best thing to happen to Everquest.<br />
- Add missions for groups of three or four players instead of six.<br />
- Add an in-game group scheduling tool to help players find groups during certain play times.<br />
- Add better rewards to single-group encounters so raiders and non-raiders group together more often.<br />
- Do not rely on soloing to solve the grouping problem.</p>

<p>SOE may also consider more radical approaches for players to group such as allowing searching for players in other zones, allowing players to automatically join a group, and allowing for cross-server groups for instanced zones.</p>

<p>Beyond any other issue, SOE should continue focus on helping players find groups, build groups, and have fun.</p>

<h2>Add More Interesting Monsters</h2>

<p>Dragons of Norrath gave us some of the best game mechanics in a massive online game but the beasts left much to be desired.  In Dragons we met level 72 goblin kings unarmed and wearing loincloths, level 68 pumas that hit harder than Cazic Thule, and spiders - lots and lots of spiders.</p>

<p>I have watched gods die.  I have killed vampire lords with my bare hands.  I fought in the Ringwar of Thurgadin.  I have traveled to outer worlds and to the deepest pits of hell.  I shouldn't have to run from a puma.  I am a level 70 high priest; make me feel like it.  Add beasts worthy of my power and skill.  Examples include cyclopses, death knights, demons, devils, dire beasts, ettercaps, ettins, greater elementals, giants, golems, gorgons, hell hounds, hydras, liches, lycanthropes, medusa, manticores, mephits, minotaurs, mummy lords, nagas, ogre mages, rocs, spectres, titans, vampire lords, wights, wraths, and wyverns.</p>

<p>No more rats, bats, spiders, pumas, or loincloth goblins for level 70s.</p>

<p>Fun monsters are only one part of this topic, however.  The other part comes from varying the challenge of these encounters beyond hitpoints and melee damage output.  Fighting a lich and fighting a giant shouldn't be similar encounters.  Single-group monster challenges should have the same wide variety that raid encounters have.</p>

<h2>Add a Mentor System</h2>

<p>As Everquest gets older the average level of players gets higher.  As this average level increases, including methods so higher level and lower level players can hunt together, meet challenges, and receive rewards, becomes more important.  Add a method so lower level and higher level players can group together, face challenges, and receive rewards.  This will lead to a much larger possible player-base at any given level and allow friends who have different amounts of play time to continue to hunt together.  While level-based systems such as the Mentor system of Everquest 2 work well, it is not the only way to accomplish this.</p>

<h2>Rebuild the Plane of Knowledge</h2>

<p>More and more players, both old and new, use the Plane of Knowledge as their central gathering place.  Rebuild the Plane of Knowledge with new graphics, a new layout, new quests, and a new storyline.  Make the Plane of Knowledge the City of Adventure with a new government and new ties to existing content.  Build the city to prevent the video lag we receive in the current city.  While this is no doubt a monumental job, the heavy activity in Knowledge, now and in the future, warrants the update.</p>

<p>Massive online game competition is fierce this year.  Games begin to demand more and more of our time.  Everquest remains competitive with all of the newer games and expansions like Dragons of Norrath offer features unseen in existing MMOGs.  If EQ developers continue to improve grouping options, add new useful features, improve monsters, and update the core city, Everquest can continue to thrive for years to come.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
1 June 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-06-01T05:01:37+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caster&apos;s Realm: The Encounters of Everquest</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001301.html</link>
      <description>We spend a lot of time talking about class balance, equipment issues, the bloodwar between ubers and casuals, spell and...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1301@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>We spend a lot of time talking about class balance, equipment issues, the bloodwar between ubers and casuals, spell and item number crunching, and a thousand other topics that seem really important. When you step back and look at Everquest, especially in the light of newer massive online games such as World of Warcraft, EQ2, and Guild Wars, we begin to see something else. Class balance isn't the reason some players moved on to other games. Nor was it how much damage their blaster does at level 68.</p>

<p>When it comes right down to it, Everquest is a game built around having fun with your friends. These friends might be people you knew when you were five or people you just met an hour ago. The fun part might be anything from hunting down a spider in Greater Faydark to cutting down Overlord Mata Muram with fifty of the mightiest heroes who ever walked Norrath.</p>

<p>It is ironic that we spend so little time looking at the encounters we face and so much time worrying about the hitpoints on our boots.</p>

<p>So today we look at the encounters themselves. What's fun? What's not? What can we hope to see in the future?</p>

<p>In the old days of Norrath, encounters were most often static camping near a zone line with a puller dragging in a mob at a time. The goal of such a hunt was often experience with perhaps a chance at a nice drop. When I think back to my earliest days in EQ, I remember hunting at the Aviak village seated about fifty yards from the ramp while our puller brought birds back to our camp.</p>

<p>I remember hunting at the Frontier Mountains zone line of Lake of Ill Omen pulling sabertooth tigers, sarnaks, iksars, and the occasional skeleton. I remember hunting at the giant fort of Frontier Mountains pulling giant after giant. The North Wall in Dreadlands, the giant fort in Burning Woods, the left or right corners of Karnor's, the various fungi camps in Fungus Grove, and the outer or inner cave groups in Plane of Valor; I have spent most of my time in Everquest at one experience camp or another. Some call call this experience farming.</p>

<p>Even today, with the wide range of raid encounters and the missions and adventures of Lost Dungeons and Dragons of Norrath, this experience camp is probably the most common sort of hunt. This is how players progress through their levels and earn AAs.</p>

<p>Many of our best memories can be found at one camp like this or another. These camps can last hours with nothing but conversation to pass the time from mob to mob. I met many of my best in-game friends at such camps. From an encounter standpoint, however, there is little excitement in such events. There is no real goal other than earning experience or perhaps seeing a rare loot drop.</p>

<p>Dungeon crawls were the original intent of the dungeons of Norrath. A group of six hardened adventurers would crawl from the dark entrance of a dungeon to its furthest depths. This rarely happened, however. Most often new camps would be established with colorful names such as ass/sup (my personal favorite) or blind/task or disco 1 or disco 2. A group would fight its way to a safe point and continue the experience grind from there. A good puller might keep two or three rare spawns cleared until the party emerged draped in riches or returned dead on their shields. It wasn't until Lost Dungeons of Norrath that the dungeon crawl could be enforced in-game.</p>

<p>Lost Dungeons gave us a purpose for the first time in our dungeon hunting. Instead of simply hunting for experience or loot, we hunted with a purpose in mind. The goal might be to slay an ancient vampire lord or rescue a poor fallen halfling. Most often, however, as they did with the dungeon camp spots, groups gravitated to the highest reward for the least work: collections and murder spree adventures. These two were the least interesting adventures from a story standpoint. There is no exciting climax when you kill the fifty third skeleton of Deepest Guk nor when you finally find that twenty fifth vampire tooth. Many considered LDON to be the punch-card blue collar job for the adventurer. Put in your time, earn your points, buy your gear.</p>

<p>Dragons of Norrath refined the direction of Lost Dungeons and began to wrap real storylines around our dungeon explorations. Now the plots aren't so simple anymore. You must pick a flower from a garden and find the pot before it decays. You must hunt down the elusive Kirin who's dirty paw prints mark every surface. You must slay the guardians of the Lair Mistress and then slay the ancient beast herself. Now we have purpose. Now we see true variety in our hunts. It's not all about killing the beasts now, your sword may be no good if you can't discover the pattern of the Kirin.</p>

<p>Again players gravitate towards the easiest encounters. I wish I had a silver piece for each slaying of the lord-of-the-loincloth, Gimblax. People like fun and challenging encounters but fun and challenge are not nearly as tangible as forty radiant crystals and two AAs worth of experience.</p>

<p>While challenging and fun encounters are what keep players playing, players always seek the most tangible rewards for the least effort.</p>

<p>I am skipping over a whole slew of encounter types including the Justice and MPG trials, the various challenges and trials of Gates of Discord, and the biggest ones of all, the raids. There are hundreds of different encounter types in Everquest and they are all important. Everquest is a vast game with wide variety. SOE must continue to refine every one of the encounter types, from camp-and-grind experience hunts to the largest raids against the largest foes. All of them are important and have a place.</p>

<p>So let us end with a few general pontifications, a few thoughts, and a few recommendations. Consider these Loral's Rules for Encounters:</p>

<p>- Players always gravitate to the highest reward for the lowest risk. SOE should place these highest rewards in the form of experience gain and loot, on the challenges to which it wishes players to gravitate. Use experience and equipment rewards as the bait to take adventurers into the strongest areas of Everquest. Use these rewards to take players to the encounters that are the most fun.</p>

<p>- The more steps in a mission that take players away from the traditional hunt, the less likely they are to succeed. While rotting flowers and pot-hunting add a nice change to a hunt, players may avoid it to aim towards the surest victory.</p>

<p>- Of the various mission types in Dragons of Norrath, the type I find the most entertaining are the minion / subboss / boss adventures. In these adventures, players hunt down a number of minions, a set of four or so sub-boss creatures, and a final boss creature. This story arc builds suspense over the hunt and builds to exciting climax. Use this model often.</p>

<p>- Encounters should vary in duration from 45 to 90. Shorter 15 to 30 minute trials with lockout timers might help players with limited time and still offer significant rewards.</p>

<p>- Any encounter intended for more than two hours should be clearly marked as a long encounter. Such encounters should be used with great care, if at all. Even if players wish to play more than 90 minutes, they can do an adventure more than once.</p>

<p>Everquest is a vast game with thousands of different activities. In recent days we have seen powerful tools and new directions for single-group hunting. All play styles and all encounter varieties are important but neither the players nor SOE should ever forget what this game is about: having fun with friends.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Caster&apos;s Realm Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-05-29T15:37:33+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: The New Player Experience</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001299.html</link>
      <description>How can SOE get more players playing Everquest? This is a question we&apos;ve asked since the release of Everquest 2...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1299@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>How can SOE get more players playing Everquest?  This is a question we've asked since the release of Everquest 2 and World of Warcraft.  It's hard to bring new players to a six-year-old game when newer and shinier games appear right next to it.  This has been a question I've discussed often in these articles.</p>

<p>SOE has asked this same question many times as well.  Recent expansions have mostly focused on the game above level 50.  Newer features such as missions are given to players above 50 while those below 50 play the same sort of game we played six years ago.  While many small improvements were added to the level 1 to 10 game, they weren't cohesive and didn't compare to the newbie experience in newer games.</p>

<p>Last week on the Everquest Test server, SOE began testing an entirely new tutorial zone.  The original tutorial did a good job of showing new players the large array of strange Everquest commands and put them on a few quests but at level five or so, the game dumped the new player back in their old city and gave them little else.  I have heard new players speak their frustrations at that point.  No direction is given and no other players are in those towns.</p>

<p>The new tutorial extends the original by five more levels.  A player can hunt from level one to ten within this new and much larger zone.  New Kobold models were released and the zone uses new drake, spider, and goblin models from the Dragons of Norrath expansion.</p>

<p>Quests, about a dozen of them, use the mission window of Dragons of Norrath.  Quests have a wide variety of interesting jobs including blowing up Kobold mining operations and stealing the jailer's key.  There are even a set of group missions to defeat some of the larger boss mobs in the new zone such as the Kobold king, the spider queen, and some huge unnamed horror in the depths of the mines themselves.</p>

<p>The new tutorial is intended  to take players to level 10.  Players can leave the tutorial at any time and doing so drops them in the Plane of Knowledge.</p>

<p>Here is where controversy begins.  Many people want to continue the fight against Plane of Knowledge.  They think this city removes the soul of the original Everquest and removes their race identity that they had back when they hunted six years ago.  They're right, but there's more to it than race identity.  </p>

<p>Knowledge is often the most populated zone in Everquest.  If there is one place where a new player can really understand the difference between Everquest and Morrowind, it's in Plane of Knowledge.  The city has all of the practical features any city needs.  It has single-click access to sixteen newbie zones.  It is the one place where a new player can see how large the population of Norrath really is.  This also opens up the opportunity for SOE to rebuild Knowledge, a large job no doubt, into a new and shining city as technology and design understanding continue to grow.  Changing one city changes the city for every player.</p>

<p>After the tutorial players are directed to a new Plane of Knowledge Greeter.  The greeter gives a new set of quests to explore New Tanaan to find a banker, a spell vendor for their class, their local guildmaster, and a new NPC who begins sending players on a new set of armor quests.</p>

<p>At the time of this writing I was unable to start these armor quests (my little dwarven paladin was only level 7) but my understanding is that these new armor quests replace the original guildmaster armor quests using the new task window.  These quests should help lead a new player from levels 10 to 20.  At level 20, a new player should have a good view and understanding of the game and now has a path for even greater rewards.</p>

<p>These game updates are the first steps in a new push to bring new players to Everquest.  Only successful marketing can do the rest.  At the Fan Faire we will hear about a new expansion and then we may learn how SOE plans to market Everquest to a new and wider audience, an audience competed over by other massive online games such as Everquest 2 and World of Warcraft.</p>

<p>Now let's bust a common myth.  "There are no new players of Everquest.  Everyone's a twink."  I hear this a lot.  I also hear that the majority of EQ players are raiders and the majority of these raid MPG and above.  We always focus on the area we ourselves play.  There ARE new players, they just aren't hunting in Riftseeker's.  I spend a lot of time in lower level zones buffing and healing new players.  Many of them are indeed twinks, but quite a few are actually new players who either downloaded the trial or had a friend bring them in.  These new players are often pretty quiet and often hunt far away from other players, especially higher-level players.  No doubt there are less new players joining today than there was even a year ago, but they do exist and changes like these may bring in even more.</p>

<p>Will these tutorial changes and new quests indeed bring more players to Everquest?  That's hard to say.  There are a lot of variables unknown even to SOE.  In order to really grip a new player and drag them into a game as huge as Everquest, the newbie experience has to be smooth and clean.  The best newbie experience I have seen so far was World of Warcraft.  It focuses on a small town with very easy to accomplish quests.  I had little difficulty reaching level ten and I never got badly stuck.  As SOE continues to improve this level 1 to 20 segment of the game, it would do well to take lessons from WoW.  Much of what I see in the tutorial falls into this line.</p>

<p>Expect the new tutorial to be released to live servers after the Fan Faire but in the mean time, build yourself a level 1 test character and give it a try.  There are many good threads on this topic over at the Everquest forums and the developers are actively seeking input on these new tests.  New players help improve the game for everyone.  The more players that play Everquest, the better the game will be for all of us.</p>

<p>Next week expect a brand new Evil Agenda for my trip to the 2005 Everquest Summit and Vegas Fan Faire.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
29 May 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-05-29T15:32:22+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Return to Unrest</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001302.html</link>
      <description>It&apos;s been a big week. We&apos;ve seen one of the more exciting patches since the release of Dragons of Norrath...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1302@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>It's been a big week. We've seen one of the more exciting patches since the release of Dragons of Norrath and a few interesting bits of news and even a nice juicy rumor crossed my great oak desk this week so lets dig right in.</p>

<p>SOE released four new missions this week taking us back to some favorite old zones including Befallen, Unrest, Qeynos, and the newer but underused Hate's Fury.</p>

<p>I only had time to try the Unrest mission but I enjoyed it enough to do it twice last night. The mission is excellent. I'm not a fan of time travel stories; they're a bit overused in fantasy and science fiction, but to see Unrest just as evil overtakes it is quite a treat. The mission's story is quite deep and interesting. The mission mechanics take you through some of your favorite haunted spots in Unrest. The mission can be finished in about an hour if you know what you're doing.</p>

<p>The mission only rewards a single random item upon completion including 100 hitpoint and mana items and a 65 hitpoint and mana augment for the uberfolk. It does not reward any shards or LDON points. There are some who would like to see all of these missions and adventures share a common currency but I think its fine to offer random rewards for some, crystals for another, and LDON points for a third. It gives us reason to do them all instead of farming the easiest one.</p>

<p>These missions show a great way to improve old-world zones and give us a way to recapture fond days of hunting in these old-world dungeons. They also focus a party on a single goal within these old zones. We get a nice bit of story and a nice reward along the way as well. I think this is the best way I've seen to revamp a zone. I like these a lot more than the recent Mistmoore or Paw revamps.</p>

<p>Missions in general are my favorite feature of Everquest. It is the one feature that keeps me continually returning to Everquest after playing games like Everquest 2 and World of Warcraft. They help focus a single group of players on a single goal; they help reward players for their effort; and they break up hunting sessions into nice manageable time periods. I hope to see a lot more of these in the future.</p>

<p>The in-game email system got a lot of added features this week. A new address book, an ability to send email guild-wide, new sound effects and text messages upon new mail arrival, and most importantly, an ability to forward in-game email to an out-of-game email address. These changes make Everquest's email system the most robust email system of any MMOG. All it lacks is an ability to send items along with an email.</p>

<p>This week we finally saw the release of the Veteran rewards. Now Bristlebane Puppets turn all those people hanging around the front of the big bank in Knowledge into all sorts of stramge things. Last night alone I used five of my seven veteran rewards and found every one of them useful. The Bristlebane pet especially is quite a wacky experience.</p>

<p>Veteran rewards are a great way to bring people back in the game and reward those of us who have played since the beginning. Some folks had problems receiving their rewards with a mixture of strange account time calculations including time unsubscribed and transferring characters from one account to another. Some of these problems were fixed later that day.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, these great new features didn't come without cost. This week John Smedley announced that in June the Everquest subscription cost will go up to $14.99 a month. It's hard to understand a subscription cost increase like this for a game that's been out for six years now but the other changes this week give us a good idea of what we pay for. For the next month we have the option to buy year-long subscriptions for $100, just over eight bucks a month and nearly half of what we would have to pay monthly. This is the plan I chose myself.</p>

<p>Even with the increased cost, Everquest continues to be a value compared to other forms of entertainment. I just paid $15 to see "Kingdom of Heaven" and I wish I had my three hours back. Even great games like God of War end up costing about $50 for eight to ten hours of entertainment. Only the cost per hour of a paperback book runs lower than my Everquest subscription costs.</p>

<p>Time for a Mobhunter exclusive. On June 9th at the Las Vegas Fan Faire, SOE will announce the new and latest Everquest expansion. We already heard a few clues and rumors out of the last developer chat including words like "Werewolves" and "Drachinds", both words I like but not as much as "Vampires" and "Demons". With their typical six-month schedule, I would prepare for an expansion release sometime in August.</p>

<p>This week, my home world of Quellious and the fine friends of Rodcet Nife merged together into a new world. The merger went quite well, I didn't notice the change until I went into Knowledge and saw an extra one hundred people milling about. The LFG list was thick with players to pick up for groups and my guild got in four or five new recruits within the first couple of days. While I don't think server mergers are the perfect solution to problems like waning guild numbers or difficulty finding groups, I think they can help keep Everquest healthy and alive. I'm enjoying the experience with my new friends of the Nife.</p>

<p>It's been an exciting week. With the larger player-base on my server, the new veteran rewards, and the new excellent missions in old-world zones, we get to see a new side to Everquest. Price increases might put a frown on our faces, but these new features help dullen the pain. It's an exciting time to play.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
14 May 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-05-14T15:40:39+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caster&apos;s Realm: The Story of 69 and 70 Runes</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001300.html</link>
      <description>With the release of Omens of War, SOE began a new system for delivering spells. This system offered many advantages....</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1300@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>With the release of Omens of War, SOE began a new system for delivering spells. This system offered many advantages. Spells rewarded by turning in runes came out in a certain order and ensured that a player never received duplicate spells. Runes for 66, 67, and 68 runes were dropable and, although expensive, cost the same price regardless of what spell was returned within each level. There was no price gouging for Conviction like there was for Virtue back during PoP. This resulted in a much more stable reward system for spells than previous expansions.</p>

<p>69 and 70 spells, however, have proved difficult to acquire. Unlike the others, 69 and 70 runes are no-drop. You must receive them in battle in a select set of areas within Omens of War.</p>

<p>It is important to understand the scope of this topic. The difficulty of acquiring 69 and 70 spells probably only effects a small group of players but only SOE can tell us exactly how many players this effects. SOE can take a look at the number of level 69 and 70 spellcasters who have level 69 and 70 spells and compare them to those who do not. If most casters have them, than this isn't as big a problem as it might appear. If, however, most casters do not have their spells, it is worth considering an alternative.</p>

<p>Often when this topic comes up, one statement pops up without fail: Spells are the same as the weapons and armor a non-caster must acquire and sometimes this armor is just as difficult to acquire.</p>

<p>Spells are not the same as weapons and armor. They are a different entity worthy of a different solution than simply labeling them "loot" and adding them to the same system as weapons, armor, and augments. Each spell is often vastly different than other spells.</p>

<p>Spells are but one element to a caster's upgrade path. Like all other classes, casters must improve their equipment with armor upgrades, mana upgrades, mana regeneration upgrades, and focus effects. While casters improve primarily with spell upgrades, gear matters for casters as much as it does for other classes.</p>

<p>But sometimes spells ARE loot. If we look at expansions like Ykesha, Lost Dungeons, Gates of Discord, and Dragons of Norrath, we don't see the base progressive spells we see in Kunark, Planes of Power, and Omens of War. We see new spells that improve us beyond the basic abilities of our traditional spells.</p>

<p>As spellcasters level up, they will find they require new spells in order to perform effectively. As we grow we need new blasts, new heals, new armor spells, new slows, pacifications, and mezzes. Without them, we are worse off than we were at the lower level since the battles in which we fight are balanced around the spells we are supposed to have.</p>

<p>The problem with 69 and 70 spells is in the sheer number of them. Most classes have ten to twelve spells above level 69. This isn't a matter of getting lucky on one or two drops, a caster must receive ten to twelve level 69 and 70 runes to receive all of the upgraded spells for their class. Looking back at the comparison for loot, no warrior has to loot ten swords in order to receive the one that makes him more useful.</p>

<p>The real problem with 69 and 70 spells is availability. 69 and 70 spells drop in five zones: Wall of Slaughter, Ruined City of Dranik, Muramite Proving Grounds, the MPG single-group trials, and Riftseekers. They also drop off of multi-group beasts in areas such as Bloodfields and Noble's Causeway but we will focus on single-group drops in this article.</p>

<p>The drop rate in Wall of Slaughter, Ruined City of Dranik, and the Muramite Proving Grounds is so low as to make it pointless to hunt there with the intention of acquiring 69 and 70 runes.</p>

<p>For example, in the Muramite Proving Grounds, one might see a 69 or 70 rune drop once every nine hours per named mob. Considering that groups often have at least four of their members seeking these runes and that a caster needs ten to twelve of these runes to reach the end of his or her spell lines, it might take 360 hours to get all of these spells. Assuming a group can clear two spawn locations, you're still looking at 180 hours. This doesn't include group downtime, travel time, recovery time, LFG time, or any other factor that will likely increase that time.</p>

<p>And that's the average.</p>

<p>Considering that this is a random drop off of a rare mob then awarded on a random loot roll with the other members, the odds are very low per drop. These odds also reset every hunt. You aren't earning points towards spell drops each hunt, you are just hoping that this time you might get lucky.</p>

<p>In a recent post on the topic, Rytan, SOE's spell guru, mentions that the MPG single-group trials have the best drop rate average at one rune per 90 minutes. However, with a two hour lockout per trial and a reported drop rate of one rune per three trials, the drop rate is more like one rune every six hours. Add that to the odds that at least two others in your group also require their runes and you're back to 180 hours of Trial hunting to get all level 69 and 70 spells.</p>

<p>This leaves Riftseeker's Sanctum. This zone drops runes on average of once every 2.66 hours per rare spawn location. If we assume two cleared spawn locations and the same three people per group requiring spells we come up with forty hours for the total spell line. That's a great improvement over the 135 in MPG and the 180 in MPG trials.</p>

<p>This leads to one conclusion. If you want your 69 and 70 spells, hunt in Riftseekers. It is the only reliable way to earn 69 and 70 spell drops with any reasonable return and even there it is based only on luck.</p>

<p>Let's step back a moment and talk about what SOE can do in the future to improve the spell drop situation. I agree that while spells aren't exactly direct loot, they are not to be handed out for no effort at all. On the other hand, new spells are one of the primary reasons people level up and to deny them those spells hurts their motivation to progress.</p>

<p>Here are a few recommendations to improve spell progression in the future:</p>

<p>Split spells up into "have" spells and "have-not" spells. "Have" spells are the base spells each class needs to do their primary job and are easier to acquire. "Have-not" spells include minor upgrades to the "have" spells, convenience spells like group buffs, and secondary spell lines for that class. "Have-not" spell are harder to acquire.</p>

<p>Only drop ancient spells on raids. Don't use raids as a path for non-raid spell progression. Come up with a set of spells that primarily benefit raiders on raids and don't unbalance group encounters. Hsagra's wrath and the giant bane spells of Velious are good examples.</p>

<p>Offer solo quests or single group missions that reward the "have" spells and make the rewards droppable. Offer alternative spell progression paths once newer expansions make older no-drop spells harder to acquire. Find a new way to distribute spells older than two expansions.</p>

<p>Offer at least one or two spells per level that are easily acquirable to help reward casters for leveling up. Spells are a primary reason casters level up. While not every spell should be available at every level, one or two spells per level would help motivate casters to level.</p>

<p>Spells are a complex topic. Most discussions try to oversimplify exactly what they are or how they should drop. There is no clear conclusion to these arguments. Each spell is unique and must be considered and balanced against other spells and other items not just in power but in acquisition. Time for me to get back to Riftseeker's.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
8 May 2005<br />
loral@loralcirlcight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Caster&apos;s Realm Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-05-08T15:34:06+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: The Allure of Augments</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001289.html</link>
      <description>The aftermath of the shocking news that SOE would open Station Exchange, a service that will facilitate the sale of...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1289@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>The aftermath of the shocking news that SOE would open <a href="http://stationexchange.station.sony.com/">Station Exchange</a>, a service that will facilitate the sale of in-game items, characters, and money for out-of-game cash, came to an interesting conclusion.  An <a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive.vm?id=466&section=News&month=current">additional posting</a>, written a day after the <a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive.vm?section=News&id=457&month=current">original announcement</a>, stated:  "There will be no current live servers switched to the Station Exchange ruleset."</p>

<p>This makes a pretty big difference.  For the most part, Station Exchange will have little effect on most players.  The person next to you wielding that shining prismatic sword probably won't have bought it and if they did, it wasn't from SOE's Station Exchange.  If you don't want to buy or sell in-game resources or if you don't want to play with players that buy or sell in-game resources, you simply avoid those servers.</p>

<p>Station Exchange probably won't push out companies like IGE if they don't facilitate sales on existing servers.  Players have friends or characters on existing servers that they'd like to improve with some hard cash rather than in-game effort.  IGE will remain in business for a while and those same problems mentioned in Smedley's first letter will probably continue to exist.</p>

<p>It is very unlikely Station Exchange will migrate to EQ1.  Considering that SOE already began merging existing servers, it is unlikely they plan to stand up any new ones not to mention setting up a whole process and interface for the transfer of EQlive gear.  For now, I don't see a future for Station Exchange in EQLive and thats fine with me.  I am no longer concerned about Station Exchange.</p>

<p>A few days ago, the developers and producer of Everquest <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=109#M109">answered questions over on the EQ Stratics House of Commons chat</a>.</p>

<p>My favorite bit of information came early on in the chat.  Zajeer, the EQ itemizer, announced that Dragons of Norrath vendor items would include a new type 9 augment slot in addition to the existing type 7 slot.  The DON vendors will also carry type 9 augments priced at twice the cost of a base item at that level.  He doesn't mention the power of these augments but I imagine they will be lower in power than the existing type 7 augments.  It should be just enough to give DON gear a nice edge over previous LDON gear and other single-group drops.</p>

<p>A couple of articles ago, I mentioned that <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000057.html">high level single-groupers needed access to higher-power gear to progress through high level single-group content</a>.  Gemdiver wrote something very similar in his <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=8587">state of the game part 2</a> article on Caster's Realm.  This started a lengthy and heated thread on EQLive called <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=78190">Some feedback based on the latest Mobhunter post</a>.  It had a lot of interesting views on single-group equipment progression and I believe many of the concerns for both Gemdiver, myself, and others in that thread may be alleviated with these new DON augments.</p>

<p>I have two questions on the subject of these augments.  Can a DON equipped level 70 hunter with somewhere between 150 and 300 AAs expect to hunt and survive in the Muramite Proving Ground trials, Riftseekers, Ikkinz, and The Accursed Nest?  I think the answer to this is "yes" but I'd like to see actual proof.</p>

<p>Second, will the cost of these new augments push the total cost of a nice piece of DON gear so high that most people won't bother to acquire it?  SOE can always lower the cost if they see that no one is purchasing it but at a cost of roughly 1270 (340+250+680) for a single item (roughly forty missions worth of crystals), it doesn't seem likely that anyone will deck out every slot with nothing but DON gear.  However, it is realistic to expect that these new DON items and augments may help fill out the lower power slots of single-group hunters.  I'm planning on a new set of boots myself.</p>

<p>We'll have to see exactly what these augments are like and whether the cost is low enough to make them a practical upgrade when they come out in a couple of weeks.  This is an exciting improvement.</p>

<p>Zorillius mentioned that they are not looking at the EQ2-style adventure packs for EQLive.  While I liked the idea of D&D style modules for EQ, there's enough new content with each new expansion that I don't think they need to put out a few more zones.  Besides, I'm already spending enough on massive online games, I don't need another $10 a year for adventure packs.</p>

<p>Level 69 and 70 spells came up again recently, both in the dev chat and <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Necromancers&message.id=7297">over on the Forums</a>.  Rytan recently doubled the drop rate for 69 and 70 runes in both MPG and Riftseekers.  For all practical purposes, however, Riftseekers and the MPG trials is the only place to receive 69 and 70 runes with any reasonable chance.  With somewhere between eleven and twelve runes per spellcaster in the 69 and 70 range, I still don't think drops in one zone is a reasonable solution for such a huge amount of classes.  For some classes, these runes are required to operate against higher-level mobs, yet they are nearly impossible to receive except for camping named beasts in a single uninstanced zone.  Some other solution for 69 and 70 runes needs to be considered.</p>

<p>Last week I wrote an article for Caster's Realm called "<a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=8633">Disturbing Trends in Massive Online Games</a>" that mentions the recent trend on focusing on solo content as well as other instant-gratification changes such as out-of-game purchases.  This focuses on a problem I've had with Everquest 2, Worlds of Warcraft, and last week Guild Wars.  All three of these games seem to focus highly on solo-quests.</p>

<p>I've written a lot about solo content before.  I find solo content to be counterproductive to a massive online game.  I've received a lot of email over the last week.  Many players agree with me and give examples of how their playtime in solo-friendly games like Worlds of Warcraft and Everquest 2 are not as rich as the social connections they make in games like Everquest.  Those that argue for soloing usually bring up the LFG problem.  Currently, in most games, players spend too much time looking for a group.  Adding more solo content could make this problem worse.  The more players are able to progress alone, the less likely they are to group.</p>

<p>Rather than find new ways to let players solo, all of these game companies should use all of their skills and all of their powers to find easier and faster ways for players to group.  I've offered up a few suggestions such as game-wide invites, a mentor system, improved friends lists, and alt tracking, but I am sure there are many others I have not yet thought up.</p>

<p>With the Fan Faire and Summit coming up in about two months, I am beginning to ponder issues for my next "Evil Agenda".  The LFG problem will probably be number one on my list.</p>

<p>More than anything else, it is important that both game developers and players remember exactly why they play these games.  Gear, progression, zones, and levels aren't nearly as important or as lasting as the friendships we build.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
2 May 2005</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-05-02T12:30:26+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caster&apos;s realm: Disturbing Trends in Massive Online Gaming</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001288.html</link>
      <description>Since late last year we have seen big changes in massive online games. On the surface, many of these changes...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1288@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Since late last year we have seen big changes in massive online games. On the surface, many of these changes appear to improve the game and open it up to a wider audience. Not all of these changes come without cost, however; and not just financially. Some of these changes miss the point of why we play massive online games in the first place.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 recently made most of its overland creatures soloable by all classes. Players can travel all over Thundering Steppes or Nektulos, and find hundreds of mobs killable by a single character regardless of class. World of Warcraft included large amounts of solo content since its release. The vast offering of solo creatures, quests, experience, and loot often proves too tempting an option when compared to the difficulty of finding a group with a bunch strangers. If options exist for a player to level from 1 to 50 without grouping with a bunch of strangers, players will follow it.</p>

<p>Those strangers, however, are the reason to play. Gameplay, evolving environments, and character advancement are important features of any game. There are many single-player games that involve the players in deep plot lines, offer fast and powerful progression paths, and have an important feature all massive online games fail to include: a pause button. It's the thousands of other players that make massive online games unique. Avoiding them ignores the one thing that sets these games apart.</p>

<p>The more solo content game designers add, the more they steer players away from the strength of massive online games.</p>

<p>The shift from Everquest's buffing system to the more rigid system in Everquest 2 made it much harder for players outside of groups to help one another. Buffing other players, while overpowering in many circumstances, created a social community of those who want to help people and those who seek help. Buffing in Everquest created contact between players who might never have met eachother before. In Everquest 2 it becomes much more difficult to establish that connection. The rigid combat and buffing system of Everquest 2 makes it not nearly as clear how one character can assist another.</p>

<p>Last week, Sony Online Entertainment announced that it would set up a new set of servers and facilitate the transfer of characters, equipment, and in-game money in trade for real life currency. The outside purchase of characters, equipment, and in-game money has gone on for a long time now, but this is the first time the company of the game validated the practice.</p>

<p>Players who purchase gear, in-game money, or characters completely miss the point. Massive online games aren't about gear or level or items, they're about meeting other people and going on adventures with them. Players cannot build friendships with other players if they continually shift from character to character or spend their entire play session seeking out the rewards that might offer the best cash on Station Exchange.</p>

<p>These changes points to a disturbing trend. Instead of longer and more enriching content meant to bring players together, we see games turning toward instant gratification with large amounts of solo content and validation for purchasing characters, gear, and in-game money outright rather than earning it in-game. This may lead to more subscribers for each game, but it will not help reinforce the main difference between massive online games and traditional single-player games: the other players.</p>

<p>There are things we, as players, can do to improve our own played time and help show others the strength of massive online games. Here are some examples:</p>

<p>- Go out of your way to group with people. Don't always seek the safest path for personal gain if it steers you away from other players.</p>

<p>- Remember that the game isn't about levels, gear, or money; its about the other players. Years from now you won't remember what the ratio was on your fancy sword or how many hit points your breastplate had. You will remember your friends and the adventures you shared. Your friends list is your greatest possession.</p>

<p>- Go out of your way to help new players and show them that not everyone is out for themselves. Institute a buffing-event or newbie adoption program for your guild. Set up contests or player-generated quests that don't just involve killing beasts for experience and coin.</p>

<p>Game producers can also improve the grouping aspects of massive online games rather than leaping to the easy fixes for solo-play, experience bonuses, or the real life purchase of in-game resources. Some examples include:</p>

<p>- Help get groups together faster. Allow group invites across zones. Focus group content around one-hour play sessions. Widen the level ranges on group content to allow for a larger pool of players looking for groups.</p>

<p>- Remove detrimental features of grouping such as group experience debt and add a significant experience bonus for players who choose to group instead of soloing.</p>

<p>- Add features that reinforce pickup groups and pickup raids. Reward all players in a group for their work, not just one player with random luck.</p>

<p>- Improve tools for social connections. Add a notes section to friends lists. Offer a method for alt tracking. Let players forward tells from one alternate character to another.</p>

<p>- Add in a system that lets low level players and high level players group together. Ensure both players earn experience and meet appropriate challenges. Don't get stingy with the experience they earn, make it worth while for a high level to group with their low level friend.</p>

<p>- Do not jump to soloing as a fix for short-time players.</p>

<p>Most importantly, find new ways to get people together in a group, get hunting, and having fun together in a short period of time.</p>

<p>Massive online games are seeing much greater popularity than ever before and this trend appears to continue. With a far greater number of players playing online games, the urge to make quick and easy changes that might bring in even more subscribers is strong. It is easy to give players what they ask for but not always easy to look deeper into why they ask for it and what the real problem is.</p>

<p>Sometimes players forget the real difference between these games and other RPGs. It is easy to get caught in item statistics or levels. Game companies should remind them what is important. Game companies should constantly and continually reinforce the biggest strength of their games: the massive amount of online players. Players should never forget why they play. Your greatest rewards aren't gear or levels or items, they're the people you meet in your adventures.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
24 April 2005<br />
Loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Caster&apos;s Realm Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-04-24T21:06:38+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 58: Dark Meetings</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001287.html</link>
      <description>Loral walked down the streets of Qeynos. Each step he took closer to the temple of Life added another weight...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1287@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Loral walked down the streets of Qeynos.  Each step he took closer to the temple of Life added another weight on his heart.  Cool winds blew over the city's stone walls from the northwest, whipping at Loral's green robes.  A circle of gold held his neat pony tail in place.  His eyes, eyes that had seen one hundred and twenty years of adventure, matched the light blue of the sky.</p>

<p>Loral turned the corner and the temple of life came into view.  The huge saucer-shaped temple floated and slowly rotated on a pillow of magical energy.  Loral stepped onto a runed plate of strange metal, a gift from the Erudites, and transported in a crack of magical energy into the core of the Temple of Life.<br />
	<br />
Loral smiled when he saw his friend and mentor, Ciric of Quellious, walking towards him but Loral's eyes spoke of great sadness.  The blue-robed Erudite embraced the Loral.</p>

<p>"How are you, my friend?"  Ciric's deep voice brought back old memories.</p>

<p>"As well as can be expected.  We fight on many fronts and I fear treachery within the Felwithe council, but other than that..."  Loral smiled but it fell quickly.  "How is my father?"</p>

<p>"Better."  The word took much of the weight off of Loral's shoulders, but not all.  "He gains weight.  He is not sick.  We do our best to prevent further weakening of his muscles and bones."  Ciric paused.  "He has not awakened."</p>

<p>"I would like to sit with him," Loral said.</p>

<p>"Of course."</p>

<p>Tarlin lay in a bed of goosefeathers and wool blankets.  He rested, eyes closed and breath steady.  Someone had cut his hair and it flowed neatly over his shoulders in rivers of silver.  The same person had shaved the old ranger's beard, making him look less like a prisoner of Torment and more like Loral's father.</p>

<p>Loral picked up Tarlin's hand and held it tight.  Though the demon, Xuzl, had showed Loral a peek of Tarlin's torment, Loral knew that even that painful glimpse was but a taste of the eternal torment and loneliness of the dark hells that Tarlin had faced for over 100 years.</p>

<p>What had Loral accomplished in those hundred years?  The priest traveled to Kunark and Velious and the moon of Luclin.  He had traveled to the outer planes and the depths of the lost crypts of Mistmoore.  He fought in two wars and saw the scorched lands laying in waste behind the armies of the Muramites.  What progress had he made?  A dark cloud hung heavy over Loral's city of Felwithe.  It seemed every rock unturned revealed a new horror.</p>

<p>He must regain perspective and learn what he must.  His life was unimportant.  His reputation was unimportant.  There were resources available.  Felwithe's council already found these resources questionable but their results were not.  Loral needed information and he knew where to get it.</p>

<p>Loral kissed his father's hand and left Qeynos that evening.</p>

<p>Rough waves rocked the large ship as it pulled into the gulf of Gunthak.  Dark clouds sent a cold drizzle on the ship's travelers.  Large tattooed ogres pulled thick ropes and drew the ship to the wide docks.</p>

<p>Loral stepped onto the docks of Gunthak.  His face hidden by his gray hood and flashes of his golden armor peeked from the folds of his cloak.  Narrowed eyes watched the elven cleric as he walked to the tavern.  Tattooed women wearing far too little clothing hid only their daggers under boots of leather and tiny swaths of silk.</p>

<p>Few patroned the tavern this wet afternoon.  Three gnomes in enormous hats roared in laughter at one another.  Two erudite women, not the nobles of Erud but hardened war wizards of the deep seas whispered two each other in a strange dark tongue.  In the corner, a lone dark elf sat relaxed and observant.  </p>

<p>The dull roar of confusion and indecision left Loral as he sat down at the dark elf's table.  Though surrounded by spies, thugs, and assassins, Loral felt a peace he had not known in some time.</p>

<p>Xarrak smiled one of his subtle smiles that hid a thousand secrets and ran a hand over his shaved dark head.  Without a word, Loral took a small leather pouch from his belt and slid it across to the dark elf.  Xarrak took the pouch without a word and tucked it into his own belt, not looking at its contents.</p>

<p>"Is it safe to speak here?"  Loral noticed that no one kept an eye on the pair of elves.</p>

<p>"This is a safehouse.  Anything that happens here stays here.  This is a house of business.  Those that violate this unwritten law end up in the shipwrecks one hundred feet below us."  Xarrak smiled and Loral shivered.</p>

<p>"Tell me what you have learned," said Loral.</p>

<p>"The lack of support from Felwithe drives a wedge between your home's council and the refugees from Firiona Vie.  The survivors moved north east to the ruins once possessed by Sather's lycanthropes, the Drolvarg.  They hope to keep pressure on Lanys's forces and make the witch pay for every inch she holds in blood.</p>

<p>"Felwithe sends adventurers west to Taelosia and through the Discord Rifts to Kuua but fewer and fewer adventurers meet their call.  They began to realize the futility of such a war.  The council is now locked in in-fighting.</p>

<p>"Some of Felwithe's generals and more progressive supporters broke away from the council and now act independently in th service of Norrath and Tunare.  They call themselves 'Norrath's Keepers'."</p>

<p>Loral pondered the dark elf's words.  "I believe I shall seek out these Keepers."</p>

<p>"I thought as much.  They hold their headquarters in the caves of north Lavastorm.  They investigate the new lands beyond the northern mountain walls discovered by the gnomes."</p>

<p>Loral stood to leave.  As he reached the door, the chaos returned to his mind.</p>

<p>WHAT DID YOU LEARN?</p>

<p>The voice of Xuzl crashed in upon Loral.  He began to replay the conversation with the dark elf but stopped.  Surely Xuzl had seen what occurred, why did he need it repeated.  Unless ... the demon never saw it.  Loral turned and sat back down with the dark elf.  Again the chaos left his mind.  Xarrak smiled.</p>

<p>"What magic do you possess that blocks telepathy?"  Loral tried his best to keep emotion out of his voice.  Xarrak slipped a thin leather cord from under his fine chain tunic.  A small shard of black shaped like a curved dagger hung from it on a tiny ring of steel.</p>

<p>"During the war of Fear, the Shissar came up with many new weapons and armor to protect against Thule's demons.  The mental powers of such demons is beyond even the Shissar to control so they chose to block it completely.  This is an artifact of that time."</p>

<p>"I must have it."  Loral's eyes blazed.</p>

<p>"It is not for sale.  I will keep my eyes open for another but it will not be cheap."</p>

<p>"I will pay any price."</p>

<p>"Be careful what you offer, Hand of Tunare."  Xarrak's smile left him.  "There are some prices you will not wish to pay."</p>

<p>Loral stood again and again the chaotic telepathic crush of Xuzl filled his mind.</p>

<p>WHAT DID HE SAY.</p>

<p>Loral did not answer.  He must never recall the information Xarrak relayed to him as long as Xuzl burned in his head.  He must focus and bury it like a treasure in a sea of sand.  He must focus on something even stronger.  Loral thought of his father.</p>

<p>A thousand miles east and north, across the seas, over the mountains of the Raithe and the plains of Karana and the ice flows of Everfrost, two gnomes changed the face of Norrath forever.  They giggled as their exploding mechanical spiders blew rock apart and further uncovered the enormous skull of an ancient dragon.</p>

<p>From deeper under the rock and molten metal, ancient beasts long asleep began to awaken, opening eyes of fire and baring teeth as long as swords.  The old wyrms of Norrath awakened.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-04-22T04:50:37+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caster&apos;s Realm: On Soloing</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001284.html</link>
      <description>Soloing has been a continuing topic of interest since the days Everquest first began. Newer games like World of Warcraft...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1284@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Soloing has been a continuing topic of interest since the days Everquest first began.  Newer games like World of Warcraft and Everquest 2 continually advertise new features and content for soloing.  Clearly many players desire rewarding solo content, but what dangers lurk in such desires?  What will happen to the rest of the game if soloing becomes the fastest and most reliable way of earning experience?  Put your wizard on AFK and sit back for an interesting read.</p>

<p>Soloing offers many obvious and clear advantages.  Soloers can often begin hunting right away.  They do not need to wait for other group members; they do not need to surf the LFG channel looking for that one last tank; they do not have to show each member how to arrive at a hunting ground.  Soloers can leave the keyboard when they wish without harming the rest of a group.  Soloers earn reliable experience over time because they only have to trust themselves.  They don't have to worry about getting that one bad bard who always overpulls and wipes out groups.</p>

<p>The clearest advantage to soloing is time.  Soloers can get hunting, earn experience, and get out quickly  sometimes in as little as ten or fifteen minutes.  Some players need this or they couldn't play.  Not everyone has a lifestyle that lets them play a game non-stop for hours at a time.  There is no pause button in Everquest.  For some, soloing is the only option.</p>

<p>Soloing has some disadvantages as well.  Everquest is built around grouping.  The other players are the only clear difference between a game like Everquest and a game like Morrowind.  If one solos all of the time, one will have a harder time meeting new friends, forming a network of allies, joining guilds, or get invited to hunts or raids.  One who spends his or her entire Everquest career soloing misses out on what makes Everquest such a great game.</p>

<p>In Everquest, not all classes solo equally.  Some classes such as wizards, druids, necromancers, and bards; have significant advantages in soloing.  Other classes such as warriors, rogues, monks and most classes without an ability to heal or kite, have significant disadvantages in soloing.</p>

<p>Some argue, including SOE, that this is acceptable.  On the EQLive website it clearly states which classes are better able to solo and which are highly sought after in groups.  Some argue that not every class is as desired for a group and thus should have equal advantage in soloing.</p>

<p>I argue a different case.  Every class should have equal advantage earning solo experience.  Groups should desire every class equally, though not always for every slot in a group.  Every class should have opportunities to earn similar experience to other classes alone if grouping is currently impossible. </p>

<p>I won't dig back into group desireability for every class.  It is easy to argue that warriors, clerics, and enchanters are desired more highly than other classes in a group and this is partly true, but each group wants only one of those classes and wants three or four of the other classes.  Just as every class should have reasonable chances for earning similar experience as other classes alone, they should have equal chances for getting into a group.</p>

<p>The way to fix soloing is to make grouping more desireable and easier to do.</p>

<p>Should every class quad kite in Fire?  No.  Not every class has to earn experience in exactly the same way but every class should have an opportunity to earn the same general amount of experience in the same amount of time; whether it is through the use of a instanced solo dungeon exploration, a task, a quest, or normal hunting.</p>

<p>What should that reward be?  This is a more difficult question, one with no clear answer but one thing is clear:</p>

<p>Players should earn significantly more experience grouping than they should soloing.</p>

<p>It often takes a lot time to form a group, get to a hunting zone and begin hunting.   One must consider this downtime when determining the experience reward a group should earn while hunting.  Other factors such as players getting lost, players dying, players going afk, players leaving and new players joining need to be factored in as well.  When we consider all of these factors it is clear that grouping experience shouldn't just be better than solo experience; it should be MUCH better.</p>

<p>What happens if it isn't?  Eventually, people will stop grouping.  If you think its hard to find a group these days, imagine how hard it would be if everyone earned more reliable experience soloing?  Why would anyone group?</p>

<p>People seek the most reliable experience over time.  Since soloing offers a much more reliable experience, the reward for grouping should be significantly increased to make up for its lack in reliability as well as the extra time it takes to form a group and get hunting.</p>

<p>What about players playing more than one account at a time?  They seem to gain the clearest advantages of both soloing and grouping.  Can or should anything be done about them?  No.  They count as a group just as everyone else does.  They pay for those extra accounts.  If designed properly, no one person should be able to efficiently play a game like Everquest with more than one character nearly as well as a full group of live players.  The efficiency of having a live player behind each keyboard should result in faster and more reliable hunts in more dangerous and rewarding areas.</p>

<p>What should SOE do in regards to soloing?</p>

<p>Improve the task system with tasks anyone can accomplish with any class and any level in an hour.</p>

<p>Add  more progressive solo tasks and quests that follow through a story line and offer good one-time experience and item rewards.</p>

<p>Ensure that grouping offers a significant advantage over soloing.  Players should always desire a group over a soloing activity.  Only in limited play-time or high AFK time situations should a player desire to solo.</p>

<p>Decide how much experience each player should earn soloing when compared to grouping and offer that experience reward equally to all classes.  It doesn't have to be perfect but it should be close. </p>

<p>Add improvements for the classes that have a harder time soloing such as tasks, quests, particular items or skills that help that class solo.</p>

<p>Add tasks that don't require killing lots of mobs.  Examples include exploration tasks, puzzle tasks, mini-game tasks, or spawned encounters designed for the class that spawns it.</p>

<p>SOE should improve grouping content instead of merely improving solo content. Many times players use the difficulty in finding a group as a reason for improving solo content.  Instead of bypassing the grouping process completely, there are clear ways to improve grouping and speed up the time it takes to form a group and get hunting.  Such improvements might include:</p>

<p>Let players invite other players into their group across zones.  Let /invite player work regardless of where that player is.</p>

<p>Add player characters to the 'find' button.  Help players track their groupmates more easily. Refund the points for the 'Find Group Member' group leader ability.</p>

<p>Add less demanding yet profitable hunts for non-ideal groups or groups with a mix of wide level ranges.</p>

<p>Add a mentor system similar to Everquest 2.  Let players of mixed levels hunt together and earn experience.</p>

<p>Add tasks, quests, and missions designed for three or four players instead of six.  Help bridge the gap between soloing and the perfect six-person group.</p>

<p>Players and game companies alike have embraced soloing nearly completely.  Both Everquest 2 and World of Warcraft offer nearly enough solo content for a player to go from level one to the highest level without ever having to group.  Continually improving solo content became the trend.  Improve it too much, however, and you may destroy the very thing that made Everquest such a unique and monumental game: the dependency on other players.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
12 April 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Caster&apos;s Realm Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-04-21T15:49:40+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobhunter: Breaking News: SOE to broker the selling of Items, Money, and Characters in EQ2</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001286.html</link>
      <description>I thought my last article was a good one and I was hoping to let it sit and gather some...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1286@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I thought my <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000057.html">last article</a> was a good one and I was hoping to let it sit and gather some good thoughts.  It had some of the best posts I've read in some time.  Tonight, however, John Smedley made an announcement that forced me to push that article down a notch and cover a new topic.</p>

<p>Tonight <a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive.vm?id=457&section=News&month=current">SOE announced that it will facilitate the selling of money, items, and characters on specially flagged Everquest 2 servers</a>.  This is perhaps the largest announcement of a feature or trend since I've started writing for Mobhunter.</p>

<p>The letter does not speak at all about doing something similar in Everquest and it is clear from the few folks I spoke to that they are only planning on considering this for EQ2 for the moment.  One wonders where it may lead if successful.</p>

<p>There are a thousand facets to this topic.  I can't begin to cover them all and hope to get this article out while the news is still hot so I will say this:</p>

<p>I think it's a mistake.</p>

<p>This is basically a trade between time and money.  I play Everquest 2 and progress because I want to see new places.  Now I, an employed yuppy with too much time on my hands, have justification to simply trade in a few bucks for the time it would take me to earn my progression.  It completely changes the investment in EQ2.  It also begins to show a disturbing trend towards quick fixes and direct response to player requests rather than considering the whole problem and where it can go.</p>

<p>It is important to understand that SOE is not creating these characters, money, or items but instead offering a safe transaction system so that players can sell among themselves.  I had a much stronger reaction until this point became clear.  It isn't like SOE is selling a level 30 any time they want, but I can buy a level 30 if someone is willing to sell it.  SOE will not be establishing the price. Still, this adds a level of authority and validation to a practice that so far had been considered sleazy.</p>

<p>Everyone knows how much I support SOE as they move forward in Everquest.  Lately, with the shift towards solo play and now this shift towards item, character, and money purchasing, I worry for the result to the social bonding of players in this game.</p>

<p>I don't play EQ for items or money or levels.  I play this game to meet other players and go on adventures.  I understand clearly the investment of spending time to earn levels to see new places and hunt in new lands.  Now that line becomes gray.  Should I spend my time leveling to 30 or should I just buy a level 30 and go read a giant George R.R. Martin tome instead?</p>

<p>There's a thousand facets to this subject and I have a feeling we're going to see a lot of them on the forums over the next week.  Before you place judgment, make sure to read the letter a few times and sit and think about the issue.  May Tunare watch over us.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
19 April 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>

<p>Here's a thread round up including quite a few posts by Smed and the other devs:</p>

<p><a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=pround&message.id=2674#M2674"> John Smedley Discusses Station Exchange</a><br />
<a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=stex&message.id=3#M3"> On the subject of Station Exchange</a><br />
<a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=stex&message.id=76&view=by_date_ascending&page=1"> Comments after reading the first round of posts</a><br />
<a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=stex&message.id=176#M176"> WTH?</a></p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2005-04-19T15:58:50+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>


  </channel>
</rss>

