<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>Krylax, what is it you like about WoW graphics?  I seriosuly found them to be worse than pretty much</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Krylax, what is it you like about WoW graphics?  I seriosuly found them to be worse than pretty much any other game(EQ1 included outside of player models).  Very cartoony, and nothing that really made you say &apos;wow, that looks great&apos;.  Color usage makes my head hurt in WoW.

I am not trying to ignite the great WoW vs EQ debate, not questioning that you like them, I am more just trying to understand.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Initially I found the WoW graphics way too cartoony for my tastes too, but I gradually got spoiled b</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Initially I found the WoW graphics way too cartoony for my tastes too, but I gradually got spoiled by the fluid motion accompanying them.  Now the EQ graphics look old and tired to me - not because of a lack of details but rather because every movement looks jerky and unnatural.

As far as the WoW community is concerned, with at least a couple of million active players, the community is what you make of it.  I have had no problems finding friendl</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;But I was playing for all of 3 minutes before I came across my first jumping pvp killing idiot</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;But I was playing for all of 3 minutes before I came across my first jumping pvp killing idiots.&quot; 

That comment alone shows you don&apos;t have a clue about WoW. There is no place in the game that a newbie of 3 minutes could run into a &quot;PvP Killing&quot; idiot that could have any effect on you at all. All the starting areas are NON-PVP unless you are a moron and attack the opposing faction player.

Yeah, EQ is still the best with</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I am surprised that Loral has not published an entry here to point out the significant damage that S</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I am surprised that Loral has not published an entry here to point out the significant damage that SOE is doing to EQ1 by neglecting the game.  Every day I log in there are bots spamming every channel with their plat selling websites.

Every day I log in I hear more and more about MQers, GKers and the exploitation of Solteris.  And SOE does not do a damn thing about any of this.  It is diluting the game.  It&apos;s hurting the game in a BIG way.
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Good Grief! 

You people think MMOG PvP is the only PvP out there.  Go get the Orange Box and play T</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Good Grief! 

You people think MMOG PvP is the only PvP out there.  Go get the Orange Box and play Team Fortress 2! Best PvP action game ever! Seriously.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Hedbonker wrote: I am surprised that Loral has not published an entry here to point out the signific</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Hedbonker wrote: I am surprised that Loral has not published an entry here to point out the significant damage that SOE is doing to EQ1 by neglecting the game. Every day I log in there are bots spamming every channel with their plat selling websites.

..

I would rather he do a entry about Legends of Norrath and why its probably a bad idea to dedicate so many game resources to giving LoN all the new illusions and familiars.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Redhenna, that&apos;s a very difficult question to answer. Graphics are essentailly an art form and </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Redhenna, that&apos;s a very difficult question to answer. Graphics are essentailly an art form and art is very personal and subjective. Why do I like a certain painting?  Why do i like a certain song?  Why do I like a certain movie?  I&apos;m not sure why I like the things I like, I just do.  Not trying to avoid your question I&apos;m just not sure how to explain personal taste exactly.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Why do the EQ models look like they&apos;re having an epileptic seizure whenever they run?  It&apos;</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Why do the EQ models look like they&apos;re having an epileptic seizure whenever they run?  It&apos;s embarrassing!  Not to mention the use of the same breastplate design from lvl 1 to 80.  At least I can dye it pink...</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Heh, gotta agree with the poster with the comment regarding the WoW community.  If you can&apos;t fi</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Heh, gotta agree with the poster with the comment regarding the WoW community.  If you can&apos;t find likeable players amongst a community of millions worldwide, I think that says a lot more about you as an individual than it does about the game.  I&apos;ve grouped with students, housewives, doctors, graphic artists, small business owners, programmers, engineers, members of the military, retirees, disabled persons, medical patients, car salesmen</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Krylax, you are right, that is a difficult at best question.  It&apos;s just something that continua</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Krylax, you are right, that is a difficult at best question.  It&apos;s just something that continually struck me with WoW.  People talk about the nice graphics, and yet I find them just horrid, and do not see what it is that people find so nice.  On the other hand, I find EQ2 graphics to be just breathtaking at times(Eve Online too, though in a completely different way), and yet I know some people do not like them.  Heh, different strokes and al</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Redhenna,

First, just wanted to say Happy Holidays.  That said, I wanted to drop my virtual 2cp int</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Redhenna,

First, just wanted to say Happy Holidays.  That said, I wanted to drop my virtual 2cp into the mix.

Redhenna, if your as old school as I was/am with EQ such that your first experiences included higher level characters getting consent to drag your corpse, then we share some history in EQ.

Thinking back on EQ of that era, a couple things come to mind.  At it&apos;s inception EQ was marketed as &quot;paper and pencil roleplaying&quot; b</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Ghost of Zek, I was not quite that old school.  I started playing midway between Velious and Luclin.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Ghost of Zek, I was not quite that old school.  I started playing midway between Velious and Luclin.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Once again I have to disagree with Loral&apos;s judgment on the Wii. If you can get one go for it, i</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Once again I have to disagree with Loral&apos;s judgment on the Wii. If you can get one go for it, it&apos;s a ton of fun with all the new games out for it like Mario, Metroid, Star Wars, NiGHTS, Sonic, and all the mini-game-games. If you&apos;re a hardcore console fps sorta guy it probably won&apos;t be your thing though there&apos;s still Resident Evil and the wii zapper to check out. Honestly there&apos;s so many games for wii I want right now</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>So just read that SOE is being bought out by an Indian company. ROFLMAO....adios EQ1, Matrix, Vangua</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>So just read that SOE is being bought out by an Indian company. ROFLMAO....adios EQ1, Matrix, Vanguard, LOLOLOLOL</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Smed&apos;s comment on the rumored sale(that you are two days late on btw):

&quot;This story is com</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Smed&apos;s comment on the rumored sale(that you are two days late on btw):

&quot;This story is completely false. We aren&apos;t for sale

No idea who made this up. We are in discussions with various companies in India about bringing our games to this growing market but that&apos;s it. We aren&apos;t for sale.

Smed&quot;

Even the most cursory glance at the original story would tell you that it is almost certainly false, as the supposed purchas</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>