<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>&quot;make two sets of spell missions. one with difficulty based on casual gear and one based on har</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;make two sets of spell missions. one with difficulty based on casual gear and one based on hardcore gear.(but the reward is the same) but people can do whatever mission they choose. and make it so the choices are recorded as statistics. now,honestly...do you think anyone would do the hardcore gear missions?&quot;

Why bother?  Why not just make a button you can push and get the same gear?  Then everybody is uber, and you don&apos;t have to </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>My guess: 

They don’t want to confuse the new user with expansions. I bet they will release this on</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>My guess: 

They don’t want to confuse the new user with expansions. I bet they will release this on the shelves ONLY as a full package, be that the full titanium + serpent&apos;s spine, or just the classic + serpent&apos;s spine.

Can you imagine how painful it may be for new players to be told “oh but you must buy these two boxes to play the game!” or being told in the counter “you want this expansion that’s cheaper or you want the full version</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Keisa said

&quot;Why bother? Why not just make a button you can push and get the same gear? Then ev</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Keisa said

&quot;Why bother? Why not just make a button you can push and get the same gear? Then everybody is uber, and you don&apos;t have to worry about how long you have to play the game.&quot;

Hey I like that idea. Its better than whats been going on. 

Ive been 70 for a year now still missing 3 69 spells and all my 70 spells. That is totally wrong. Ive been to the rune camps here and there but dont have the time to spend 10 hours doing it.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>It&apos;s just this.

Once, when I was playing Heroes of Might and Magic III, I came up against a re</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>It&apos;s just this.

Once, when I was playing Heroes of Might and Magic III, I came up against a really hard scenario.  No matter what I did, I couldn&apos;t seem to break it.  The starting position was really disadvantaged, and by the time I dealt with the first opponent, three others were storming in with massive forces.

I used a cheat code and poof, I had 5 black dragons, yay.  I played maybe 3-4 more turns before I realized that winning the</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>And what is the point if your stuck at that same spot forever and a day? You dont play anymore eithe</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>And what is the point if your stuck at that same spot forever and a day? You dont play anymore either! There has to be a happy medium is all im saying. Not everybody has 1k+AA&apos;s and groups with those 1k+ people.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>You are stuck?  Really?!?  There is nothing you can do to improve your character?  I don&apos;t have</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>You are stuck?  Really?!?  There is nothing you can do to improve your character?  I don&apos;t have all my 70 spells, but I am still able to improve my character.  I receive an upgrade of some kind almost weekly.  Surely there is something you can do to improve your situation.

The game isn&apos;t about getting all the top stuff.  It&apos;s about using the tools you have to enjoy the game and getting more tools that can help you to enjoy the gam</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>No use posting when peeps dont get it..

GL all</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>No use posting when peeps dont get it..

GL all</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;Comment Posted by: Hemdell on July 18, 2006 02:58 PM

No use posting when peeps dont get it..
</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;Comment Posted by: Hemdell on July 18, 2006 02:58 PM

No use posting when peeps dont get it..

GL all&quot;

I would say, from your comments that you are the one that doesn&apos;t &quot;get it!&quot; 

You are a casual, I am a hardcore raider....but I used to be in a casual family guild, so I do know where your coming from, problem is you need to ask yourself why you play Everquest &amp; what you want from it.

....if all you want are easy </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>no,these people get it. they know what is going on but they seek to debunk what others say to benefi</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>no,these people get it. they know what is going on but they seek to debunk what others say to benefit or validate themselves. but it dosent really matter because here is what cant be debunked and it pisses them off to the very core: eq has lost what seems to be half its subscription base in recent years. the more uber eq gets;the more people seem to quit.wow caters to the casual player and has a active playerbase in the millions! eq caters to the</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Phrank wrote:Just guessing? ROFLMAO guess you should get some facts straight before you post such in</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Phrank wrote:Just guessing? ROFLMAO guess you should get some facts straight before you post such inane comments.
Wishing the numbers higher for EQ won&apos;t make it true no matter how thick your rose colored glasses are.

----

they are just guessing, they dont have press release numbers, and even the press release numbers arent exact numbers. 

if anything its people like you who get off thinking of EQ failing.

the numbers may not be as high </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Simkine wrote: When I came back to play on the Progression server I checked out my old server for a </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Simkine wrote: When I came back to play on the Progression server I checked out my old server for a few weeks. Empty zones abound. Perhaps less than a group here or there, most higher levels than the zone farming items or powerleveling. Late at night, the raiders come online and do their instances and log off.

---
while it may be true many of the old zones you went to were empty.. there are alot of instanced zones in everquest now where people h</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Oh, we get all that, Concerned1.  Now, I&apos;ll tell you what you don&apos;t get.  I&apos;ll start </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Oh, we get all that, Concerned1.  Now, I&apos;ll tell you what you don&apos;t get.  I&apos;ll start with a story.

When I was a young lad, I had a conversation with my mother.  I told her, &quot;We are rich.&quot;

She was taken back by the statement, and she asked me why I thought that was true.  I told her that, &quot;We have everything we need and most things we want.  People who have a lot more money than we do will never be rich, because the</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Extremely well said Keisa.

I have been playing around in The Devastation trying to do a little ques</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Extremely well said Keisa.

I have been playing around in The Devastation trying to do a little quest and trying to learn how to bow solo in the zone. With all of the travelling packs of mobs and mob pops and random snaring mobs I have killed only slightly more of them than they have of me. No gear, no xp and a heck of a lot of fun.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Honestly, what everquest needs is a full overhaul of the death system and new animations. They don&a</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Honestly, what everquest needs is a full overhaul of the death system and new animations. They don&apos;t even need to change the SoL models if they don&apos;t want to just fix the shitty animations and make it neat.

Death though, always respawn with all gear and with spells memorized already. Tone down the huge exp cuts between 40 and 51 and keep the res system the same, leave a blank corpse that can be ressed for exp and to bring you back to w</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Yeah, come on casuals.  Quit whining if you don&apos;t have your rune drops.  All you gotta do is sp</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Yeah, come on casuals.  Quit whining if you don&apos;t have your rune drops.  All you gotta do is spend the next year or so /lfg or making pick-up groups that either last an hour or wipe on the first pull and disband.  The timesinks are insane in EQ, but casual players are not, and so move on when they see how bad it will be for them.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>