<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/" />
<modified>2005-02-02T16:19:13Z</modified>
<tagline>Everquest news, editorials, and commentary.</tagline>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2</id>
<generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="3.01D">Movable Type</generator>
<copyright>Copyright (c) 2005, Loral</copyright>
<entry>
<title>Of Wing and Fang</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000048.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T16:19:13Z</modified>
<issued>2005-02-02T14:05:58Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.48</id>
<created>2005-02-02T14:05:58Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we saw a new patch and a detailed interview with the developers of the Dragons of Norrath expansion.  This week&apos;s article discusses the new Mistmoore and Paw zones, the change to LDON&apos;s adventure selection, and touches on the exciting Dragons of Norrath mission system.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>SOE released quite a <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?article=7543">large patch</a> this week.  You can read the entire patch message here but I will highlight a few of the more interesting features.</p>

<p>Lost Dungeons received a much requested selection menu for one of the four mission types.  While this decision will certainly be popular for those who still adventure, it basically removes the assassination and rescue missions from the list.  The collection and murder spree missions are much easier than the assassination and rescue missions.  Few would ever select a mission that offers a harder difficulty for no gain in reward.</p>

<p>One of my problems with LDON is the lack of a story arc.  I actually prefer going on assassination missions because they are one of the only adventure types that has a building plot and a final confrontation.  Boss mobs and anti-heroes are important not only in video games but also in traditional fantasy.  Walking into a dungeon and killing 58 skeletons or collecting 28 bone chips doesn't have the same energy as going into a dungeon, killing 57 skeletons and then killing Ograth the Skeleton King.  </p>

<p>A better solution to the selection choice would be to make rescue and assassination missions offer up a higher reward for their difficulty.  Giving boss mobs nice loot or rescued NPCs offering up a reward for their return might have made the difference enough that people would once again select them. This change puts a band-aid on the problem of convenience.</p>

<p>SOE revamped two older zones this week including Mistmoore and Paw.  Both zones now harbor beasts above level 60.  Walking into Mistmoore at level 69, I was reminded of how I felt entering the dark castle at the young age of 30.  Mistmoore was always a very difficult dungeon and well known to eat even the heartiest of adventures.  It is nice to see it return to its former danger.</p>

<p>Part of that danger, however, came from some of the quirks of the dungeon.  Mob pathing was never very good and it wasn't uncommon to see enormous trains pour out of the castle and tear across the courtyard killing anything that moved.  That tradition remains today.  It isn't uncommon to see a mob run in the opposite direction and return with a couple of friends when you pull it.  From the item links floating through our network of channels, the loot supports the reward, but it would have been nice to have a zone whose danger didn't come from its unexpected bug-based behavior.</p>

<p>I have yet to step foot into the new paw but from the equipment I see, I imagine it is as difficult as Mistmoore was.  Paw always had one of the most difficult dungeon layouts that only the oldest old-world dungeons had.  Remember upper and lower guk?  How about Kedge Keep?  I am sure old timers wax nostalgia about the difficulty of old-world dungeons but few ever went deep into paw.   Most groups found a cozy corner near the zone and pulled what they could see.  Only adventures many levels above the zone population would dare to delve deep in and even then they had a gate potion at the ready.</p>

<p>One very small fix in this patch that had me cheering out loud was a fix to the font system.  I always preferred Verdana over Arial as a font but using such a wide font ended up breaking the item counts on stackable items.  This last patch fixed this problem.  It was a small but useful fix.</p>

<p>This patch did not implement the task changes I had hoped to see. We will not see these new tasks and task improvements until the release of Dragons of Norrath.  It would have been nice to see these new tasks before the release of the next expansion but improvements to the task system at any time will hopefully help those who prefer to hunt solo.</p>

<p>This week EQ Stratics hosted a <a href="http://eq.stratics.com/content/hoclogs/donhoc.php">developer chat</a> with Travis Mcgearthy and Ryan Barker of the EQLive design team to talk more about Dragons of Norrath.  This was the first time SOE discussed the details of the new Mission system with those outside of the Dragons of Norrath beta.  While a future preview of Dragons of Norrath will go into more detail on this system and the other features of DoN, I can make a few general statements on what we see so far.</p>

<p>Of all of the features of Dragons, none excite me as much as the Mission system.  The Mission system ties together the Omens of War task system, the Gates of Discord expedition system, and the Lost Dungeons adventure point system.  Players pick a particular mission, one with much greater variety than the four LDON types, and complete that mission in an instanced part of a larger dungeon zone.  Completing this mission awards a sort of currency that can be used to purchase new items.</p>

<p>There are a number of advantages to this system.  They have well-defined timeframes for completion, in this case, about an hour.  They reward every member of a group equally rather than favoring one lucky party member with random loot.  They offer gameplay variants other than sitting and hunting at a particular camping spot.</p>

<p>For those of us who thought LDON was one of the great improvements in Everquest, the Mission system answers our roar of requests.  Unlike LDON, however, Dragons features a lot of raid content (dragons!) and general overland and dungeon non-instanced zone exploration.</p>

<p>We had a busy week and I expect a few more in the future.  In the next couple of weeks I will write a preview of Dragons of Norrath that will go into further detail into these systems and the other features of this expansion.  In the mean time, lets hunt some vampires.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
2 February 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The World Has Changed</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000047.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2005-01-24T13:33:13Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.47</id>
<created>2005-01-24T13:33:13Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Dark clouds black out the frosted skies of Iceclad.  Iron boots crush into the eternal snow of Dreadlands.  Whispers of an ancient evil sift through the lands of the north.  The world changes.  This week we look at the historic moments we now face in the lands of Norrath.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>We remember the battles of Bloody Kithicor.  The older adventurers speak to the newer ones of the days when it was safe to cross the forest at night, the days before the wars came and tore the dead from the ground.  Now only the boldest adventurers dare to cross the unholy grounds of Kithicor at night.</p>

<p>We remember the fall of Grobb.  The ancient Guktans, children of Marr, crawled from the depths of Guk and marched upon Grobb.  The trolls were sent north to Neriak with an eternal fire in their eye for their homeland.</p>

<p>We remember the god-battles of Lesser Faydark.  The avatar of Tunare and the avatar of Cazic Thule battled upon the cursed lands of Lesser Faydark calling heroes of both light and darkness to their sides.  The outcome of this battle, different in each of our splinter worlds, changed the face of the Faydark for some time.</p>

<p>Dynamic events set Everquest apart from other traditional games.  We never watch the landscape of Final Fantasy or Baldur's Gate shift, grow, or collapse unless it is part of the linear story.  Everquest isn't a story, however.  Everquest is a world, and events like these prove it.</p>

<p>Two weeks ago, a knight of Tunare stood on the bridge of Felwithe and asked for aid in locating Firiona Vie.  Pieces of her cloak and evidence of her travel lay about the old lands.  Further investigation revealed a dark plot surrounding the Tower of Frozen Shadows in the Iceclad ocean.  Powerful beasts roamed the icy lands and a guardian barred all entrance into the dark tower.  Even the sky spoke of great evil.</p>

<p>Now dark elves spy over the Dreadlands.  Who knows where this will lead, but one thing is for sure; like Bloody Kithicor, the Fall of Grobb, and the god wars of Lesser Faydark; the world of Norrath will not remain the same when these times are over.</p>

<p>So now the future lies in our hands.  Will we at least witness these changes?  Of the three events mentioned above, I witnessed none of them personally.  I did hunt down and return pieces of evidence of Firiona's travel.  I helped the parties seeking to rescue Firiona from the tower by turning in pieces of evidence among the ruins of the Tower's beasts.  I have seen the scouts of Dreadlands.  Yet few others seem to see this.</p>

<p>So now we uncover another strange behavior I have witnessed for a long time.  A lot of players tend not to try anything new, instead preferring to hunt in commonly known and safe lands.  We lose sight of the forest through the trees.  Our chance for the safe acquisition of levels, AAs, and gear takes us away from some very entertaining one-time events.  Many will miss these events because they either do not hear of them, or do not care to witness them and leave their safe Wall of Slaughter group.</p>

<p>I noticed this same behavior at the beginning of each expansion.  People didn't seek out MPG and Riftseekers when Omens came out, they went to Fire and earned their levels and AAs there.  People continued working on LDONs and everyone wanted to finish their epic 1.5 as fast as possible rather than see some of the deeper lands of Kuua.  Perhaps my narrow view only sees these types of players, but sometimes it feels like we forget what we really seek.  We hunt down new higher numbers instead of seeking new adventures.</p>

<p>Over the next three weeks, we will see a great shift in Norrath.  If you seek it out, you can witness this change and fight alongside your allies in the battles ahead.  When these events are complete, you will never have the chance to see them again.</p>

<p>Speak to your friends, to your guild, and to your groups, and let them know of these changes.  Put together a small team of explorers and seek out these strange signs.  Take your raiding force that threatens the same beast you destroyed a dozen times before and attack the creatures you will never have a chance to see again.</p>

<p>Remember that this game isn't only about levels or AAs or gear.  It's about fun.  In this case, the fun has a lifespan and it will never come back again.  Don't miss it.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
24 January 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Breaking News:  Dragons of Norrath</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000046.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2005-01-11T04:30:07Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.46</id>
<created>2005-01-11T04:30:07Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">The coming of the Dragons of Norrath is upon us.  Read on for detailed information and commentary on this new Everquest expansion and a note about Everquest 2&apos;s announced Adventure Packs.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Early today rumors started spreading like wildfire of a new Everquest expansion.  This evening we finally have more details.  Most of your questions can be answered at the <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/dragonsofnorrath/index.jsp">Official Dragons of Norrath Website</a>.  Lets dig right into the main features:<br />
<blockquote><strong><br />
Everquest: The Dragons of Norrath, release on February 15th.</p>

<p>- New Zones, Creatures and Content - From Lavastorm to the Thundercrest Isles adventure in graphically enhanced zones with all new themes.  Brave challenging new quests, discover new treasures, and battle new NPCs including drakes, goblins, and fierce dragons.</p>

<p>- New Interactive World Map - A full-color interactive map of the world allows players to point-and-click from a world view, to a continent view, to a zone view of the traditional line maps.</p>

<p>- Player Barter System - Allows players to set up their own method of giving platinum or items for other items.  Players can now buy items!</p>

<p>- Potion Belt - Allows for quick use of consumable items, such as potions or food.</p>

<p>- Bandolier Equip - Lets your character have pre-arranged, multiple sets of weapons accessible by a single mouse click.<br />
	<br />
- New spells and Tradeskill Recipes</p>

<p>- All-New Guild Halls - Individual instanced Guild Halls for guild members to meet and prepare for playing. Includes the following features and benefits:<br />
	<br />
- Guild Bank - Bank slot for storage of items accessible by all (designated) members of a guild.</p>

<p>- Mana/health Regen Pool - Allows players to easily regenerate their mana and health in preparation for battle (available only at the Guild Hall).</p>

<p>- Mass Corpse Summoning Altar - Allows guilds to summon guild corpses en masse to the altar room after a wipe out.</p>

<p>- Guild Portal - Allows guild members to purchase the ability to have a persistent port to pre-determined areas around the world.<br />
	<br />
- Guild Tradeskill Objects - Various tradeskill tools are located in the guild hall for easy access by guild members.</p>

<p>- Guild 'Looking for Members' Tool - Allows guilds to recruit by placing persistent “ads” on bulletin boards, search for player characters who match guild criteria and send in-game emails to those members.</p>

<p>- Players 'Looking for Guild' Tool - Allows players to find guilds recruiting members.</p>

<p>- Buff Timers - In the Guild Halls buff times can be paused for Guild Members.</p>

<p></strong></blockquote></p>

<p>The front page also mentions a "In-game email system" when you highlight one of the crazy spires.</p>

<p>Loral's Comments:</p>

<p>The front page of the website mentions a release date of February 15th (Looks like I may owe Nanyea a drink).  I didn't expect it this soon but the schedule fits inside of the traditional six month delivery of new expansions since PoP.  While the boards already crawl with "but they haven't fixed all the doors in Freeport" comments already, and while many others feel that SOE is bringing this out too soon, history since PoP shows a six month delivery cycle.  Personally, I enjoy seeing the world shift and change as often and as radically as it does.  Change is growth and growth is good.</p>

<p>I love the mentioned guild features, however, I fear the associated in-game costs.  Hopefully the guild costs scale well for non-high end raiding guilds.  The mass summon corpse feature interests me the most.  While I feel SOE should give this feature to every player of the game in the form of a Shadowrest NPC, even in a guild hall this feature will help many players.  However, if the cost is scaled around guilds with 54 raiders of level 70, it won't scale well for a guild of 12 level 20 to 50 players.  The costs of guildhall features should scale well for guilds of all sizes in order to be a truly great feature.</p>

<p>In-game email, a guild recruitment service, and a player search of recruiting guilds will help people get together and find groups of friends with similar goals and play-styles.  I like that a lot.  Now if only we would see a "recruit" guild status to streamline the guild recruitment process.</p>

<p>The UI elements look to be nice additions.  One of these, the bandolier, was a feature asked for at the guild summit.  The world map should help new players but many of us who have the zone maps permanently laid over the neural paths of our brains will find little use in them.</p>

<p>The beta signup appears and disappears on the front page of EQLive.  If you don't blink at the wrong moment and you desire to betatest the expansion, keep watch the Everquest homepage.</p>

<p>In other news, John Smedley, president of SOE, posted an interesting note about Everquest 2 including this comment about a new form of $5 bit of content called "Adventure Packs":</p>

<p>"Adventure Packs are a new style of content that we are introducing to EverQuest II. You can think of them as being similar to "Modules" from traditional tabletop RPGs. They will be heavily story driven and themed adventuring areas. We will provide a part of each of these Adventure Packs, at no extra charge, to all of our players. This should give everyone the opportunity to see if a particular Adventure Pack is the kind of thing they are interested in. You'll be able to buy these at any time, since they will be delivered digitally. We plan on keeping the price point for these low... In fact, our first one will be just US$4.99."</p>

<p>Read the <a href="http://eq2players.station.sony.com/news_archive.vm?section=Headline&id=311">John Smedley's full EQ2 letter</a>.</p>

<p>Adventure packs interest me.  This is an opportunity for SOE to release mini-games or campaigns for EQ2 in a more traditional RPG sense.  I imagine modules like Temple of Elemental Evil and Queen of the Demonweb Pits.  I imagine single story lines that progress from beginning to end.  Where typical EQ2 expansions will focus on large scale world-based content, these adventures will offer a specific and focused story, gameplay element, zone, and quests.  So why not have this for EQ1?  The idea of paying another $5 every three months will turn some people off, but considering the time we get for our dollar, $5 for twenty hours of content is a pretty good deal.</p>

<p>Earlier today, Everquest Executive Producer, Robert Pfister, posted <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=TNZ&message.id=146526#M146526">The State of Everquest in 2005</a>.  In it he discusses many of the past and future points of interest for Everquest including possible server merges for the Zeks and a review of other servers after Dragons of Norrath, the class role review, and the release of Dragons of Norrath.  It is unclear when we may first see class changes occurring and I would bet it won't be until after the release of Dragons of Norrath.  That will surely vex some people.  Minor class tweaks don't excite me like a new expansion does, however, and I bet I am not alone.</p>

<p>Yes, I get all googly eyed when I see the glossy propaganda for a new expansion.  I know we still have class discussions ahead of us and new patches that update old-world content like the task system.  I know there are still plenty of bugs.  But I see a screenshot like <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/dragonsofnorrath/images/screenshots/EQ000099.jpg">this Frost Giant</a> and I can't help but get giddy.  I love Norrath and I love watching it grow.  I look forward to the days ahead.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 January 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Topics of the New Year</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000045.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2005-01-03T01:18:43Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://2.45</id>
<created>2005-01-03T01:18:43Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we look at the current hot topics of Everquest including more class balance goodness, server consolidations, the life of Everquest, and the delayed guild summit.  Loral also officially eats crow.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>With SOE's developers on vacation this week, life in Norrath has been quiet.  So let us sit back, relax, and enjoy our new year with a look at some of Norrath's most recent topics of discussion.  Four big topics continually seem to dominate the live forums:  EQ's lifespan, server consolidation, class balance (egads), and the summit.</p>

<p>Let us get the most painful one out of the way first.  For nearly the entire time I've written for Mobhunter, people complain about class balance.  I covered it a couple of times before, but let me step back from my own views on the matter and talk about what we see.  </p>

<p>Early on when the new EQLive forums stood up, Kytherea and Ashlanne began keeping track of the top ten class issues for each class.  Regardless of the continuing disclaimers on these threads, people assumed this meant these class issues would all be addressed.  Now even though many classes have had some of their issues addressed, people lean towards statements like "SOE isn't listening" and "none of our class issues are being met".  How easily we forget.  I had a conversation a couple of days ago with someone who stated that even though some of their class issues were met, they were things that should have been fixed anyway and didn't count.  </p>

<p>My head swam with the spiral I see people swimming down.  Then, my friend Boanerges from EQClerics linked a document called <a href="http://www.legendmud.org/raph/gaming/laws.html">The Laws of Online Game Design</a> gathered by Raph Koster.  Raph worked on a variety of online games including Ultima Online, and Star Wars Galaxies and now acts as the Chief Creative Officer over at SOE.  One of these rules shined like Frodo's Light of Earendil:</p>

<p>"<em>Hans Henrik Staerfeldt's Law of Player/Admin Relations: The amount of whining players do is positively proportional to how much you pamper them.</em> Many players whine if they see any kind of bonus in it for them. It will simply be another way for them to achieve their goals. As an admin you hold the key to many of the goals that they have concerning the virtual environment you control. If you do not pamper the players and let them know that whining will not help them, the whining will subside."</p>

<p>Another one might articulate this better:</p>

<p>"<em>Hal Black's Elaboration:</em> The more responsive an admin is to user feedback of a given type, the more of that type the admin will get. Specifically, as an admin implements features from user suggestions, the more ideas for features will be submitted. Likewise, the more an admin coddles whiners, the more whining will ensue."</p>

<p>We might argue that not listening or responding to player concerns ends their whining simply because they go away.  If you don't listen to your customers and address the issues that must be addressed, they will go away.  Sometimes, however, I wonder if badgering the developers into making changes has become its own progressive massive online game.  Why should I hunt for a new hammer when I can get the developers to make the one I have better?  Why fight so hard against the Luggalids in Nadox when I can convince SOE to make them easier?  It seems the EQLive forums became their own sort of meta-game.  I might receive more improved items and upgraded spells there than I will hunting in game.</p>

<p>This brings up a multitude of questions.  Should SOE have ever validated class issues by keeping track of them on an open forum?  Do those class issues really represent the whole set of players who play those classes?  Now that they have validated these concerns, what should they do to address them?  Will simply addressing them as-is result in breaking the game even further?  Do the players really know whats best for the whole of the game?  There are few easy answers and a whole lot of theory.</p>

<p>Let us shift paths and discuss server consolidation.  Recent threads reveal no official words on any move by SOE to consolidate servers although I stand by my rumor that they at least consider and discuss Zek consolidation.  It makes more sense for those servers with their wide variety of rule-sets on top of population issues.  While more and more threads pop up each day, I wouldn't expect SOE to make any other move to consolidate servers until after the release of the next expansion.</p>

<p>Shifting paths again we reach the Guild Summit.  SOE had originally planned a summit in January but announced that they pushed the date back to July.  The original January announcement started a series of interesting feedback threads on <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48581">soloing and tasks</a>, <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=48894">user interface</a>, and <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=50919#M50919">grouping improvements</a>.  While it would have been nice to get a deeper look at the next expansion, a June summit may hit at a more opportune time to offer feedback.  As far as the summit effecting the longevity of the game, I don't think opinionated egotists like myself have as much impact as we would like to think.  For all we know, Firiona Vie's hem-line has more to do with EQ subscriptions than any feedback found on a website.</p>

<p>Which leads into the last path we will walk today, the life of Everquest.  I wrote an article for Caster's Realm titled <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=7411">Is Everquest Dying?</a>.  Anyone who read any of my other articles already knows my answer but in case you have not, the answer is "no, it isn't".  When we look at the longevity of previous MMOGs and how few users can still finance new expansions, I think it is safe to say that Everquest has a long life.</p>

<p>This brought up an interesting question for me, however.  Can Everquest last the rest of our lives?  While it is obviously difficult to predict forty or fifty years of technology, we can assume that bandwidth and server costs will continue to go down. The value of continuing to maintain Everquest may be worth the bragging rights of maintaining a MMOG for ten, twenty, perhaps fifty years.  Will people still want to play?  People still want to play Pong, so probably.</p>

<p>For my last act, I would like to make a formal statement.  I was wrong.  Yes, I know it is hard to believe and I risk influencing the vast markets in the bazaar with my mere spoken word, but...I was wrong.  The prices of Muramite Runes still seem to fluctuate between 20 and 30k in the bazaars well after my Thanksgiving 10k prediction.  While I am confident that the prices will continue to go down, it would appear that more people are willing to pay for runes at that price to keep the market high. Shame on you.</p>

<p>Keep an eye out next week for a new article entitled "Loral's 2005 Predictions" for more lies, propaganda, and inaccurate financial outlooks.  In the mean time, enjoy the new year and all of the possibilities it brings.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
2 January 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Refunds, Mergers, and Flags</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000044.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-12-16T00:37:46Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.44</id>
<created>2004-12-16T00:37:46Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today we comment on the most recent patch, talk a little about the forum traffic, and give an exclusive scoop on the subject of server merges.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>This week we saw the largest update in some time. Wednesday's patch included pages and pages of changes covering everything from the long awaited backflag solutions to new hotzones and alternate advancement point refunds.</p>

<p>We discussed a these changes previously so I will only touch on a few things. The AA refunds, for the most part, seem to be very reasonable. SOE's goal was to make the point costs of Gates AAs fit better with the costs found in Omens of War. In a few days we should know how well this meets the desires of those it effects.</p>

<p>The backflagging solution should help guilds. While some guilds stayed at their current rate of power and delved deep into Anguish, other guilds began opening their doors wide open to new recruits since the release of EQ2 and WoW. These backflag changes help guilds continue to progress at the point they left off by using the 85/15 rule to bring in unflagged recruits. Because guilds won't have to backflag, they should be able to retain members rather than lose them. These backflag changes came at a good time for many raiding forces.</p>

<p>A few older zones had their experience modifiers increased including Shadeweaver's Thicket, Kurn's Tower, Unrest, Crystal Caverns, Solusek's Eye, Katta Castellum, Lower Guk, Nagafen's Lair, and Umbral Plains. These new hot zones should help get newer players into zones they might otherwise skip for newer content. I like the idea behind hotzones. Without too much effort, older zones become much more desirable than they once were.</p>

<p>Tacvi, the deepest and darkest corner of the Gates of Discord expansion, had a couple of nice changes for those powerful enough to reach it. It received a new zone in that doesn't require the weekly slaying of an ubermob to enter. This prevents guilds from simply waiting until another guild comes by and takes care of the large fellow. Tacvi also received a larger cache of new loot. I would expect this loot to be on par with the equipment we see coming from the depths of Anguish.</p>

<p>We saw our first wave of epic alterations this patch. These updates mainly handled the content required to receive the epic, but more than once we've heard that the epic effects themselves will be looked at. Expect to see some changes to epic 1.5s and 2.0s coming soon.</p>

<p>Both /autofire and /melody made it into this patch. Many archers and song singers rejoiced.</p>

<p>The two revamped zones, Mistmoore and Splitpaw made it to the Legends servers. I haven't yet heard what sort of content we can expect, but rumors speak to Elemental-level beasties worming their way through the infected paw of the Karanas. We shall wait and see. Expect these zones to make it to the live servers in about a month.</p>

<p>While we saw many good changes for the upper-end of the game, we didn't see that many that effected the larger group of players below level 65. Backflagging, epic 1.5 changes, and Tacvi matters to high-end raiders, but there wasn't much in this patch for the larger group of non-raiders and single-group hunters. At this critical stage, SOE must consider the low end and mid-level game a priority over these changes to high-end content.</p>

<p>Hopefully in January we should see the much-anticipated task changes we heard about at the Fan Faire.</p>

<p>A few different board postings offer some excellent advice that effects every player, not just raiders. Three interesting threads, one on soloing and task changes, one on user interface suggestions, and another on grouping and LFG changes, all have excellent suggestions and advice that effects a large majority of Everquest players.</p>

<p>Two topics seem to dominate the conversations over on the Live forums. Class balance continues to raise its ugly head, usually wrapped in "SOE doesn't listen!" Most of the time, the complaint isn't really that SOE doesn't listen, but that SOE doesn't agree. People don't seem to want to hear it when their ideas are shot down. In the meantime, to squash the rumors of lack of communication, continue to watch the dozen or so postings a day from various SOE employees over at the dev tracker.</p>

<p>One other topic became so prolific recently that threads had to be consolidated into one huge thread. I speak of server mergers. I think merging servers should be an absolute last resort for SOE. It is the sort of change that cannot be undone, once done. It breaks up of our identity within the community and it gives the (perhaps inaccurate) impression that EQ is on a steady decline without a chance of going back up. Yes, numbers have been low, although anyone who tells you they have real data to support specific trends is most likely lying. Nothing tells us that we won't see the continued trend of new players joining in and old players returning when a shipment of new shiny expansion boxes hits the shelf sometime between March and May.</p>

<p>Ok, time for the scoop....</p>

<p>Recently, a large group of players from the Zek servers, Tallon, Vallon, Sullon, and Rallos, got together with representatives from SOE to discuss their merger. These servers, being evil red PVP servers, have a much different demographic and player base than the other pansy huggy blue servers. They also, apparently, have many fewer active players.</p>

<p>My vast network of spies tells me that SOE is indeed considering consolidating all four of these servers. While they have no definite plans yet, there are discussions within SOE to consolidate these four servers together. It is easy to consider this a reactionary move, however SOE apparently considered this merger well before EQ2's release and the meeting with the Zek players.</p>

<p>Those same spies did not reveal what the rule set would be for this combined server, so they were all immediately put to death.</p>

<p>Many will use this to feather their giant "EQ is Dead" mardi-gras hats. Yet, these same people will continue to pay their $12 a month and visit sites like this one and the EQLive boards. People love to hate.</p>

<p>The MMOG business tells us otherwise. Many other MMORPGs continue to not only run but bring out new expansions even with nearly 1/10th of the population of EQ. I expect that the server numbers need to drop dramatically over a long period of time before SOE decides to pull the plug. In the meantime, I see those who never enjoyed the game go off to greener pastures and those of us who do enjoy the game will form a new, tighter, and stronger community than ever before.</p>

<p>The day I don't hear anyone shouting "EQ is dead" is the day I really begin to worry.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
15 December 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Everquest Patch Message, 15 December 2004</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000043.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-12-15T15:26:23Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.43</id>
<created>2004-12-15T15:26:23Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today SOE released the first large patch for EQ since before the Fan Faire.  The patch included backflagging changes, Gates AA refunds and changes, revamps of Paw and Mistmoore on Stormhammer, and new hotzones.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Here is the full context of today's patch message.  A commentary will follow later.</p>

<p>*** Update Headlines ***</p>

<p>----------------------------<br />
* Backflagging<br />
* Gates AA point refunding<br />
* New Hot Spots<br />
* Mistmoore & Splitpaw revamps going to Stormhammer</p>

<p>Backflagging *<br />
----------------------------<br />
As you know, when a guild gains or loses members, they often find themselves dedicating a large amount of time re-playing content that they have long since completed in order to gain access to zones for newer members. During our Community Summit this last summer, and in many subsequent discussions, we have heard the recurring desire to find a way to ease the frustrations associated with this backflagging.</p>

<p>While the issue is not as simple as removing flags altogether (we feel flags are necessary for the zones they are currently attached to), we have looked into ways that we can reduce the frustrations of backflagging and feel that we have arrived at a fair and equitable solution, which is detailed below.</p>

<p>- A new implementation of the 85/15 rule has been introduced into Planes of Power zones including the Plane of Time. This should resolve the outstanding problems that occur from time to time with the current 85/15 implementation.</p>

<p>- The new 85/15 has also been introduced for the locked zones in Gates of Discord.</p>

<p>- An alternate means of flagging guild mates for locked content in Planes of Power and Gates of Discord has been implemented that will allow you to flag raid members for the zone you are in by completing raid content within that zone. </p>

<p>The implementation varies slightly from zone to zone to fit the story and nature of the zone, but in general will involve killing a raid target within that zone, looting an item, and completing a single group quest to change that item into a zone flag. This only applies to zones that don't already have a single group task or system to gain access.</p>

<p>AA Changes<br />
-----------------------------<br />
- Reduced the cost of many Gates AAs. Players will receive a refund equal to the difference on AAs that now have a lower cost. *<br />
- Changed the monk AA Crippling Strike to an activated ability that does an eagle strike attack as well as a snare. <br />
- Changed the monk AA Stunning Kick to an activated ability that does a round kick attack as well as a stun.<br />
- Changed the monk AA Eye Gouge to an activated ability that does a tiger claw attack as well as reduces the targets offensive ability. <br />
- Due to major changes in how these work, AA points for Crippling Strike, Stunning Kick, and Eye Gouge have been refunded. <br />
- Reduced the reuse time of the Ranger AAs Frost Arrow and Flame Arrow to 3 minutes. *<br />
- Hobble of Spirits will now stack with the Beastlord's proc buffs. *<br />
- Fixed problem with the Beastlord AA Bestial Alignment where if you had maxed buffs this AA would not reset if it did not take. <br />
- Duration enhancement focuses and AAs should now increase the duration of pet buffs.<br />
- If your stored AA's go above 30, they will no longer be set to 30 when you zone. However, you should still not be able to gain more than 30 unless you get a refund, get the AA from a GM, or get an AA from a script. *<br />
- Fixed an issue with Half Elf Paladins of Tunare and the Origin AA. *<br />
- If your character was created before EQ started storing starting location data, when you log into the game you will now be prompted to choose your home city from a list of valid starting locations for your character. You will only need to do this once and once this has been set, it cannot be changed. This will correct the problems with the Origin AA not returning some characters to their expected home city.</p>

<p>Zone and NPC Changes<br />
-----------------------------<br />
- Hot Spots have been moved (level ranges are approximate): *<br />
Shadeweaver's Thicket 1-30<br />
Kurn's Tower 10-25<br />
Unrest 15-30<br />
Crystal Caverns 25-35<br />
Solusek's Eye 25-45<br />
Katta Castellum 30-60<br />
Lower Guk 35-55<br />
Nagafen's Lair 40-55<br />
Umbral Plains 50-60<br />
- Respawn time for the bosses in Tacvi has been increased from 3 to 5 days.<br />
- Some Tacvi loot has been upgraded. Bosses now drop more items per kill and some all new items have been added to the zone. *<br />
- An alternate entrance into Tacvi has been added in Txevu that will allow guilds to bypass the Zun'Muram after they have defeated him at least once. Guilds that have previously defeated the Zun'Muram will need to do so at least once more before they can use the new entrance. *<br />
- Gilipus of Ak`Anon has joined the Beta Neutral Faction. You will now be able to complete his quest without having to raise Gem Choppers Faction. <br />
- The 3 Tormentors in the Jelvan event now share hatelist when idle or aggro. Anyone that is on one Tormentor's hatelist, but not on the other 2 Tormentor's hatelist will be added. This should make it difficult (if not impossible) to avoid AOEs.<br />
- Modified the Warden Hanvar event, all guards should appear in their appointed places.<br />
- Fixed a bug in Anguish that could make Warden Hanvar unkillable.<br />
- Clicking on the door to Anguish while having the Seal: Mastery of All on your person will now prompt red text indicating your flag has been granted.<br />
- The respawn of Globes of Discordant Energy are now tracked on the event timer for Anguish. The method for obtaining the Globes has not changed.<br />
- The pile of stones that was used as a secondary zone between Dranik and Bloodfields has been removed. There is now an actual zoneline there.<br />
- Plane of Justice - previously, you could not click the red teleports to leave the Seventh Hammer's room unless the Seventh Hammer was dead (or not up). This has been changed so you can leave the room as long as it is not aggro. If you click on a portal while he is aggro, you should get a message and remain in the room. <br />
- Grennet Stormhand in North Qeynos is no longer a task master since he is part of a quest. His task master job has been taken over by Jorren Boxmover.<br />
- Increased the maximum duration for all Labyrinth Trials from 1 hour to 2 hours. When an event is successfully completed, the instance will shut down in 30 minutes. If it is failed, the instance will shut down in 5 minutes.<br />
- Changed the reclusive Girplan event in Bloodfields so that each NPC in the sequence stays up for 15 minutes instead of 3 minutes before depopping.<br />
- Elemental NPCs are once again Charmable in Bastion of Thunder.</p>

<p>Epic Alterations<br />
-----------------------------<br />
- Updated some text to clarify what is needed for the bard epic 2.0. *<br />
- Part of the rogue epic that could be skipped has been repaired as this was not intended to be possible.<br />
- The zonewide shout that occurs when killing base pop NPCs in the special instance of Vxed for the paladin epic has now been removed.<br />
- Added another check to the monk epic to make sure that the monk looting the item also has the Mark of Justice needed to access the 7th Hammer's area.<br />
- More details regarding the combine for the Beastlord Epic 2.0 have been added to the text. *<br />
- Fixed the hand in to Uisima for the Ranger Epic 1.5.<br />
- Added a hint to the Druid Epic 2. *<br />
- In the Hider Event in Frontier Mountains for the Druid Epic 1.5, the goblins should teleport a bit less frequently. *<br />
- Additional lore has been added to the rogue epic 2.0. *<br />
- Moved the Dark Huntress from Mistmoore to the Tower of Frozen Shadow. <br />
- Changed a few of Lirprin's dialogues to hint at where the last few steps are that players are missing. *<br />
- Arly Golyeck in Paludal caverns will now accept bribes from half-elves, or those that are in half-elven illusion while also wearing a Burnoose of the Halfbreed.</p>

<p>Tradeskill Changes<br />
-----------------------------<br />
- The Tradeskill window will now allow up to 500 favorites (up from 100). *<br />
- The drop rate of spiderling silk has been increased, as there are many new combines that require this item as a component. *<br />
- The Rune of Zephyr should now drop off of the appropriate level of NPC's. *<br />
- Several Tradeskill recipes have had their missing ingredients added to the game. These items will now drop off of appropriate NPC's. *<br />
- Increased the drop rate of Tae Ew Scales. *<br />
- Increased the drop rate of Putrescent Blood. *<br />
- Made several quest-related combines "Learnable". *<br />
- Fixed a few grammatical issues with the "Forge of Icewell Arms" book.<br />
- Fixed an issue with one of the Abysmal Sea tradeskill books (The Beauty of a Simple Stone). It should now be able to be read. <br />
- Fixed the recipe for the Imbued Northman Kite Shield (Rallos). <br />
- Fixed the research recipe for Malosini, it should now combine properly. <br />
- Fixed the recipe for Tuna Rice Surprise, it will now return the Wok on success. <br />
- Fixed the Large Sandblasted Steel Girth, it is now usable by the appropriate races. <br />
- Fixed the Sandblasted Ringmail Bracelet, it is now usable by the appropriate races. <br />
- Fixed the multiple-recipes for Vegetable Oil, they will now return the correct yields. <br />
- Fixed the disparity in between the cast-times on the various "Greater Elixir of Concentration" potions.<br />
- Added the Blood Treated Kaniz Hide to the game. <br />
- Added a recipe for players to create a package of vegetables. *<br />
- Added a "Fully Charged Gnomish Vanishing Device" to the game. *<br />
- Added LDoN Foraged items to the Interactive Objects in all LDoN zones (this includes the foraged alchemy components). *<br />
- Removed the lore tag from the Smithing Chisel. *<br />
- Taught Barbarians how to make Large Leather Gorgets and Pants. *<br />
- Evaluated the PoP Smithing disparity between plate and chain. *</p>

<p>1. One block of ore will now yield two sheets of metal. *</p>

<p>2. Removed the Chain Jointing requirement from the combine. It now requires one Superb Leather Padding instead. *</p>

<p>Item, Spell, Discipline and Skill Changes<br />
-----------------------------<br />
- Auto range attack implemented, no longer will it be necessary to range attack manually - /autofire is a toggle command that will fire your ranged weapon until you run out of ammunition, turn on autoattack to switch to melee combat, or use the /autofire command again. *<br />
- /melody ability implemented for bards - To use /melody, type /melody . The numbers are the same numbers you would use for the /cast command. The melody will repeat the songs in the specified order until a note is missed due to an interruption. *<br />
- Modified Mirrored Mask, so it is no longer no rent and poof on death, however the click effect only works inside Anguish.<br />
- Increased the chance on the Cleave effects to affect DPS as they were originally intended.<br />
- Fixed a bug with the Frenzy of Conquest benefit.<br />
- No-rent containers no longer poof on login if they contain items. They instead change into an unenchanted container with the same number of slots, and a chat message notifies the player. *<br />
- Changed the Mark of Justice to take the player's group instead of just the player when attempting to engage The 7th Hammer. *<br />
- Cryston, Staff of the Riftnow has the focus of Quickening of the Ikaav.<br />
- Dragorn Head Statue Piece and Dragorn Torso Statue Piece are now very large and can fit in bags. <br />
- Clear Rock and A Large Rock are now very large and can fit in bags. <br />
- Polished Stone of Renewal can now be used by berserkers. *<br />
- Berserker: Hastened War Cry has been fixed. <br />
- Bards will stop playing songs when feign death effects hit them (some NPC encounters do this). <br />
- Players are no longer able to have Form of the Great Bear and a mount on at the same time.<br />
- Holyforge will now increase your chance to slay undead, and if you have the Slay Undead AA you will have an even greater chance of a slay with Holyforge. *<br />
- The spell Nature's Blight was not increasing the damage as stated and should be working as intended now. *<br />
- Fixed a bug with haste items and haste augments. Their effects were stacking when they shouldn't have. It will now only take the greatest haste effect from the item including augments.<br />
- When combining the aegis of chaotic worship with the soul temper and a flask of water, you will receive the temper and the aegis of chaotic worship back if you don't have the correct flags instead of just the aegis back.<br />
- The Monk's feign death success rate has been improved. It was previously capped at 95% at 100 skill and now it ramps up the success rate for higher skill levels. *<br />
- Fixed several inconsistencies with pets affected by focus items.<br />
- Increased the mana regen gained by Elemental Simulacrum.<br />
- Touch of the Devourer was changed to allow partial damage when it is resisted. This is an increase in the overall damage of the spell.<br />
- New items are available on the PvP point merchants. *<br />
- Might of the Wild Spirits and Savage Wildcaller's Blessing should now stack better.<br />
- The effect on the Wristband of Secrets no longer works on other players.<br />
- Increased the focus % of the following effects: </p>

<p>Hastening of the Ikaav <br />
Quickening of the Ikaav<br />
Alacrity of the Ikaav</p>

<p>- Increased the potency of Pure Spirit. <br />
- Nature's Balance should now only remove beneficial spells from the target.<br />
- Removed the scaling focus mods from the following spells:</p>

<p>Force of Ikkibi<br />
Order of Trushar<br />
Sylvan Anger<br />
Taelosian Geomancy<br />
Burning Night<br />
Anger of Taelosia<br />
Sylvan Kindle<br />
Clear Fire</p>

<p>- The the class-specific quest chest armors from Omens of War now have a .8 second cast time.<br />
- The pre-nerf LDoN armor sets can now be sold back to the merchants, like other LDoN items. They are the versions with two type 2 slots and one type 3 slot (instead of one each of types 1, 2, and 3). These items are those with the following in the item name:</p>

<p>Royal Attendant * of Sand<br />
Incorporeal * of the Specter<br />
Mucus-Drenched *<br />
Immortal's Bloodied * </p>

<p>Miscellaneous<br />
-----------------------------<br />
- Multiple procs on a pet are now working properly. *<br />
- A resource leak in the graphics engine was corrected and we have seen a measurable improvement in client stability as a result.<br />
- The sky system now influences the ambient lighting.<br />
- Animated traps such as the ones in soldunga/b are now detected by the collision system and will cause a small amount of damage.<br />
- You can once again target things on the other side of a water surface and other passable surfaces.<br />
- Added code to check and validate specialization skills. If the values are not legal, the player will be informed why they are not legal and they are reset.<br />
- Added popup confirmation dialog when you attempt to give an augmented item to an NPC. *<br />
- Added optional parameters to /book command -- /book open, /book close. *<br />
- Fixed bug where a player who had more than 2 million plat in his inventory was unable to purchase anything from a vendor or trader.<br />
- /yell messages are no longer displayed if the yelling player is in your ignore list. *<br />
- Some models that were scaled dramatically could cause the collision system to fail, resulting in warps to ceiling and other strange side effects. For example the vases in dranikcatacombsa at 1000,-1011, 0 would always cause players to be pinned to the ceiling due to this bug.<br />
- Players standing on the lip of an edge should now slide down off them more smoothly. <br />
- There have been some optimizations to the collision system. You should see improved performance in zones with very large stationary objects (potimea, bloodfields, etc).<br />
- Fixed a number of small bugs in the zoom camera behavior. These fixes include removing the possibility of having the first mousewheel click causing the camera to bounce back into first person, a bug that could cause the camera to get stuck “one click” out of first person, as well as smoothing out the camera motion a bit.<br />
- Scrolling to third person and tabbing to another window should no longer cause the screen to bounce back and forth.<br />
- Summoning mounts in certain places should no longer cause players to fall through geometry. <br />
- Getting out of water should be much easier to do. *<br />
- Mounts are no longer dismissed when zoning. *<br />
- Spell scribe timers (putting a new spell into the spell book) now take only 1 second.<br />
- Players should no longer experience 20k falls when standing on cliff edges while suffering from low frame rate. <br />
- The bounding radius for small races was too tall, preventing them from accessing some areas. For example, gnomes couldn't enter the small huts in Steamfont. This was a global problem that is now fixed; that is just one example.<br />
- Weather effects are now working properly when the Wake of Karana spell is used. Additionally, sounds related to starting & stopping of various weather types due to zoning and Wake of Karana should be working correctly.<br />
- /who commands now display both class title and base class name for players over level 50, e.g. "Bedazzler (Enchanter)" *<br />
- Fixed a bug that caused a lot of writing to the dbg.txt file during a raid. </p>

<p><br />
Zone Revamps - Mistmoore (Legends)</p>

<p>-----------------------</p>

<p>In Mistmoore's Catacombs, the servants of the Trueborn, a sect of vampires with Mayong Mistmoore's blood flowing through their veins, grew tired of their masters throwing them into the fray against the Norrathian intruders. They came to desire more power for themselves. </p>

<p>It was not long before the first words of dissension crept through the catacombs on the will of whispers. The Trueborn servants congregated in dark, musty halls away from the eyes of their masters and over time their numbers grew along with their ambitions. Their time had come and soon they would rise up to claim their rightful place in Mistmoore Castle, gaining accolades from Lord Mayong Mistmoore himself for their brilliance and bravery -- or so they supposed.</p>

<p>Over several months, the Trueborn traitors recruited an army to their cause. On a black night as the moon was swallowed by a thick veil over Faydwer, they struck, killing their masters and leading their army toward Mistmoore Castle. They slaughtered all in their path and many masters of the Scions sect, the Trueborn's rival blood-children of Mayong, were destroyed that night.</p>

<p>The fierce wave of the lesser Trueborn rushed into the cellars of Mistmoore Castle without detection. Unbeknownst to all but the servants, Norrath's adventurers had uncovered winding caves beneath the surface that bypassed the castle's defenses. In a matter of hours, the castle was overrun and the servants of the Trueborn declared themselves the true Children of Mistmoore.</p>

<p>Since taking control of the castle, many Children have busied themselves repairing the damage from the battle while others continue to seek the magical ore that was uncovered in the catacombs. </p>

<p>They all prepare, waiting for the day their master returns to grant them glory.</p>

<p></p>

<p>Zone Revamps - Splitpaw (Legends)</p>

<p>-----------------------</p>

<p>Farsoth Mal, son of the Ishva Mal, leader of the Verishe Mal tribe, sat by his father's side watching him rule his minions in Splitpaw Lair. His father may have conquered this lair some years ago, but Farsoth believed they should rule far more than just one underground kingdom. He grew to despise his father for his lack of ambition and many hours were spent in bitter arguments between the two. The Ishva Mal grew tired and angry at the ceaseless challenges to his authority, gaining as much contempt for his son as his son had for him.</p>

<p>During a particularly heated argument of growls and grisly barks, the Ishva Mal reminded his willful son that his power was absolute and that he shared his throne with no one. With one quick motion, the Ishva Mal brandished his spear and sliced off his son's paw, determined that he would finally win the respect he deserved from his son. But the Ishva Mal's cruel methods would prove to be his downfall.</p>

<p>The Ishva Mal grew to be a greater tyrant each day, so much so that the Verishe Mal mages and warriors secretly formed the Council of Nine to challenge his rule. Farsoth saw the plans the Verishe Mal had in store for his father, but did nothing to stop them and instead chose to use them to his advantage.</p>

<p>Farsoth learned much from the council's mages and became obsessed with the summoning arts they practiced. His fascination eventually led to a plan that would secure the throne . . . for him. </p>

<p>Through all he'd learned from the Verishe Mal mages, he believed he could summon a powerful entity from the Plane of Fire itself. Farsoth thought with such power at his side, nothing could stop him from ruling the Splitpaw Lair and any lands he desired. </p>

<p>He prepared for weeks, researching and gathering the reagents he required and finally he set to work to summon a terrible beast to bring an end to his father's rule. </p>

<p><br />
Farsoth was distracted by his own anger, forgetting vital components as he wove the spell and the unthinkable happened. Flames shot out of the portal that Farsoth opened and, at the same time, rocks rained down upon the inhabitants of the lair. Then, the portal shifted its focus and water flooded into the corridors, extinguishing the flames and washing away the rocks. The portal shimmered once more and waves of all types of elementals poured into Splitpaw.</p>

<p>Farsoth certainly attained part of his goal. His father was killed, but so to were most of the gnolls he wished to lead to greatness.</p>

<p>Now he is a prisoner to the swarms of enraged elementals that have made Splitpaw Lair their new home.</p>

<p>* Denotes a change requested by the community.</p>

<p><br />
- The EverQuest Team </p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>News of the Winter&apos;s Moon</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000042.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-12-05T02:44:09Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.42</id>
<created>2004-12-05T02:44:09Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we look at the state of the game this holiday season and make a few wild and uninformed predictions.  We also take a look at what we hope to see in the coming December 15th patch.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>We've had a slow couple of weeks on the EQ front.  No doubt concern arises from the perceived drop in numbers and while we certainly cannot say what the future holds, it would be premature to follow in the same well-walked tread of picket sign wearing doomsday sayers.</p>

<p>A few factors all crashed together this year, more than any year previous that I can remember.  Instead of a holiday season with one or two new games coming out, nearly six must-have hit games came out at once.  In a discussion about EQ2 and its effect on some high end guilds, I heard guild leaders say that as much as they like the cross-game chat between EQ1 and EQ2, what they really need is cross-game chat to Half Life 2.  Now that may not be the case for everyone, but that is my point.  There isn't an easy conclusion to make about any of this.</p>

<p>I am an officer in a small guild built around helping the adventurers of Norrath.  During our regular weekly events Healers United travels around Norrath to popular hunting spots to offer our healing, buffing, resurrection, advise and gameplay help to those who need it.  Usually we had four to six people on during off hours and somewhere between fifteen and twenty during the core hours of 7pm to 1am EST.  Since Thanksgiving, our numbers dropped  closer to four to eight during prime time and one or two regular people on the off-hours.</p>

<p>Am I worried about this?  Yes.  What is my reaction to this worry?  Recruit newer members.  The game shifted for a lot of people in this time.  Some guilds wait to see what happens after the holidays and that's a smart move.  If a lot of folks really are playing Half Life 2, Halo 2, or Grand Theft Auto San Andreas, those games won't last forever and back to the doors of Anguish they will return.  Some are no doubt playing EQ2 and Worlds of Warcraft but those games won't be for everyone either.  Both are different enough from Everquest to turn away some long-time players of EQ.</p>

<p>I watch the larger guilds crash together and merge into new giant forms like huge floating balls of mercury.  I see others simply fall under the weight of their own lofty goals, lack of interest, and stubbornness to open their doors to new members or alliances.  The smarter leaders consider alliances with other individuals and organizations until they get a better feel for what sorts of numbers they require.  Once they see a solid trend, for example always having about 32 people online instead of around 54, they should begin to recruit new members.</p>

<p>None of us know what the true statistics are.  We only see what we see and we best react to what we know for fact.  It won't surprise me if we see a return to EQ in January and it certainly won't surprise me to see a larger surge of returning players when SOE announces and releases the next expansion.  At that point the new single-player games will be over, the shine of newer MMOGs will wear off, and people will fall where they have the most fun.</p>

<p>Over the last two weeks I balanced my time between both EQ and EQ2 and I noticed an interesting thing.  I like EQ2 a lot and I have fun hunting with little Pavlen the foppy roguish swashbuckler as he spies for Qeynos and slays vile stinking gnolls but when I return as the Venerable Loral Ciriclight, 68th cleric of Tunare, I have no less fun than I did before.  I still enjoy a heart-racing hunt in the Muramite Proving Grounds.  I still enjoy talking and meeting with my friends.  I still marvel at the look of Omens with its shiny skinned Dragorns and hideous glowing eyed Discordlings.  I still have a lot of fun playing Everquest.</p>

<p>SOE needs to focus on a few things to keep Everquest strong.  We need to see the world continue to change and shift.  We need to see new features for both new and existing players.  We need to continue to see new content meant to challenge and excite us and we need features to help us get together with friends and defeat these challenges.  I don't see them slowing down at accomplishing this at all.</p>

<p>So what sorts of improvements are we likely to see soon?  On December 15th a new patch will include a lot of new features that will help EQ continue to grow and evolve.  Stormhammer, the server for the cultural elite, will receive two revamped zones, Mistmoore and Paw.  The Everquest website includes descriptive lore about both <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=64379">Mistmoore</a> and <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=64380">Splitpaw</a>.  What Splitpaw really needs is a nearby Wayfarer camp or Knowledge stone.  Expect these zones to move to the proletariat servers in one to two months.</p>

<p>Both /autofire and /melody will move to the live servers.  These two long awaited features, mainly for rangers and bards, help players play those two classes with a bit more ease matching the other classes.  Positive changes to the way a player plays the game matter a lot more than any statistical change you might receive.</p>

<p>We should expect the task changes I heard about at the fan faire to move to the live servers in January.  Expect thousands more tasks with new task-types including things like fishing and foraging.  The more I look at the task system, the more I see the potential for an EQ2-like quest journal.  If SOE added some class-specific tasks, group tasks, and some item rewards to the task interface they already have, they would have a really strong new system for both new and older players alike.</p>

<p>Perhaps the biggest change we will see comes with the new backflag solution.  Ever since Planes of Power, backflagging has slowed down a lot of big guilds.  Guilds would fight their way past Rallos Zek, through some of the elemental planes, and, for a variety of reasons, lose enough players that they needed to reflag new members in order to continue.  This process, when you include Planes of Power and Gates of Discord flagging, might take up more time than actually hunting new content.  SOE hopes to fix this with a new backflag solution.</p>

<p>Nearly every flagged zone allows 15% of a raid to be unflagged upon entering it.   A small handful (perhaps two to six per zone-wide raid) of back-flag quest items drop per zone-wide raid.  These items lead unflagged attendees of these raids through a single-group quest to receive a flag for that zone only.  Now that raider is fully flagged for that zone.  The 85/15 rule will be applied to Time and to Gates of Discord flagged zones.</p>

<p>This solution will help guilds and high-end raiding alliances with their backflag woes.  As long as they have enough flagged people to get into and raid higher-tiered zones, they can help flag new members without sending most of their flagged members back to raid older content over and over.  </p>

<p>This solution will not help single-group hunters who desire these flags, but my favorite statement at the fan faire sums up the solution to this very well: The best way to fix the flagging problem is not to have progressive flagged content ever again.  In other words, expansions from Omens and on will hopefully only have a single flagged zone at the end of the expansion similar to Veeshan's Peaks, Sleeper's Tomb, Vex Thal, and Anguish.</p>

<p>Two new storyline entries whispered across the winds recently.  These stories begin to build better connections from the old world to the wars in the strange lands of Kuua and Taelosia.   I often complain that we have little understanding or in-game motivation to travel to these distant lands when threats such as the Rujarkian orcs, Mistmoore vampires, the horrors of Miragul the Lich, and the poisoned rivers of Guk pose much greater risks to our lands.  These stories, along with a few in-game changes (perhaps Muramites in Greater Faydark, Toxx Woods, the Commonlands or Qeynos Hills) would do a lot towards tightening up the loose storyline that ties Norrath to Taelosia and Kuua.</p>

<p>Strange shapes loom on the horizon.  While the doomsday heralds that plague New Tanaan's streets continue their cries to the gods of chaos about the end of days, I see a time for a new golden age.  I see a time of great wars and great victories.  I see lost friends returning home and new friends joining the ranks of the adventurers of Norrath.  Most importantly, I still have fun every time I log in and I plan to do so for a long time to come.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
6 December 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Everquest 2 Review</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000041.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-11-20T16:14:46Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.41</id>
<created>2004-11-20T16:14:46Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today Mobhunter offers a double-sized article: a full review of the first two weeks of Everquest 2.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Note: I wrote this review for both Mobhunter and EQ2 Caster's Realm. For bonus points, find four pop culture references!</p>

<p>Since the days I began playing Everquest I heard about the development of Everquest 2. It took form over the years becoming less of a dream and more of a reality. I've bought games for the last twenty years now and I learned not to pay attention to previews. Ever since the days the glossy game mags touted Sewer Shark as a revolutionary step towards interactive entertainment, I learned to ignore the hype and pay attention to the game itself when released.</p>

<p>I felt different about Everquest 2 than most new games. I looked forward to its release, but I felt trepidation instead of giddy excitement. I still love Everquest. I still want to play it. I don't want my friends to leave; I don't want my guild to fall apart. SOE doesn't want players switching games either, they prefer to drag in a whole new pack of angry wizards, but that doesn't mean it won't happen. While I knew I would buy EQ2 and I was pretty sure I'd play it for a long while, part of me didn't WANT to like it. So it was with this trepidation that I opened up the beautifully packaged EQ2 box and installed the two DVDs filled with Norrath's new world.</p>

<p>For the past two weeks, young Pavlen, my half-elf rogue, reached level 15. What I've seen impresses me a lot. So today I write a review of Everquest 2 from the eyes of a long-time Everquest player.</p>

<p>Character generation alone shows the depth of this game. What impressed me most was how different two characters of the same race can look. The variations between two half-elves were as extreme as the difference between high elf, half elf, and wood elf. The wide range of hair styles, hair color, skin color, and even physical size helps create a truly unique character. The details of cheek hight, chin size, eye slant, and mouth width probably went too far; few people will see your big goofy Bruce Campbell chin as you race around the city, but more detail is always better. (That's two pop-culture references so far, Moorgard.)</p>

<p>While graphics in a game like Everquest get people to ooh and ahh at magazines, demonstrations, and videos, they matter little when compared to gameplay. Massive online games have to pay close attention to steady yet limitless progression, class desirability, class interdependence, social connectivity, and encounter variance. Graphics are important but people pay less and less attention to them the longer they play. But yes, the graphics are stunningly beautiful.</p>

<p>EQ2 includes graphic settings so advanced that EQ2 will push machines to their limits five years from now. I had to set my machine, which screams through Doom 3's most advanced settings, to performance-level to achieve a reliable framerate. This thread on <a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/board/message?board.id=tech_support&message.id=3265&amp;jump=true">setting graphic performances</a> has a lot of good advise. One thing that will drastically increase your framerate is to set "complex shader distance" to "-1", all the way to the left, in your "Performance" menu under display options. It removes the pretty bumps from things but will result in sometimes a 20 FPS increase. It appears, however, that Everquest 2 graphics will scale well into the future. As hardware gets better, so will EQ2's appearance.</p>

<p>The quest journal is the core of Everquest 2. As I grew from a young adventurer on the Isle of Refuge to the seasoned hunter of Antonican Gnolls, I constantly added new quests into my quest journal. I didn't push to progress in levels or equipment. I pushed to find quests and complete them.</p>

<p>The quests in Everquest 2 follow a very wide range of tasks including delivery, collection, slaughter, exploration, completing tradeskills, and mini-zone clearing. Quests arrive from anywhere. Poke a wooden boat on the beach and find a strange rune inside that leads to a whole new quest. Get a brass key from a rat and discover a quest to unlock a room full of dark elf spies. Buy books in the library to learn of long lost treasures.</p>

<p>Quests follow every path of the game; whether you want to explore, hunt, tradeskill, or travel around a city. Quests drive you to find new zones and new places. Each quest is a small story for you to follow. The game doesn't force you down any one path; you choose which of these quests you wish to pursue; but there is little reason to hunt without having a quest to drive you.</p>

<p>The low-level quests from level 5 to 7, especially the collection and delivery quests, help you learn the layout of the huge cities of Qeynos and Freeport. These delivery quests frustrate people at first but once finished, it is far easier to find one's way around.</p>

<p>Quests lead you through all forms of progression. I spend little time worrying about my equipment or level. Instead, I watch my quest journal. What quests can I accomplish fast? Which ones are too old? Are there quests that other people have? One great feature lets you peek into your group member's quest books. If they have a quest you don't, you can learn where this quest starts and get it yourself.</p>

<p>It's far too early to tell if this will continue throughout Everquest 2. Much of what I describe is also true for Everquest 1 at this level. I do not know if quests become far fewer and less rewarding at the higher levels, forcing us to go back to camping in one spot and grinding experience.</p>

<p>So far it appears that Everquest 2 embraced its title. We may very well quest forever.</p>

<p>Now lets talk a little about the cities. After taking Pavlen up to level 15, I rolled up a dark elf enchanter and took him through level 7 in Freeport. The vast difference in atmosphere between Freeport and Qeynos astounded me. While Qeynos feels like Minis Tirith or Camelot, Freeport feels like H.P Lovecraft's version of planet Gidi Prime in Dune. Huge red tendrils of power hold a vast tower floating above the torn city. What horrors lie in that tower? What power could lift such a thing? Freeport is vast and scary. I love it.</p>

<p><br />
EQ2's combat system is another big change from Everquest. Efficient combat requires a lot of interaction. Combinations of moves, a wide range of skills, and situational requirements require that a player constantly pay attention to the battle and press the right attack at the right time.</p>

<p>As a 15 rogue, nearly all of my damage comes from my variety of bending and twisting stabs and slashes. If I were to set on auto-attack and go get a pop-tart, my efficiency in group would drop to less than 10%. I have to pay attention.</p>

<p>Heroic opportunities, a mix of fighting-game style combinations and the most graphically advanced version of Simon Says, offer a collaborative dimension to combat. Some groups seem to ignore them completely, but when they work they're very exciting.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 based class dependence around archetypes. Each player decides on an archetype in two steps before picking a particular class. Each class has the basic abilities of the archetype. All scouts can improve run speed, track creatures, and hide in shadows. All priests can heal and resurrect. This breakout of four archetypes should help keep each class useful in any group. We cannot yet tell how this will work out at the higher levels, but it seems to work fine at the low.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 focuses on trying to give people more content at each level. Leveling too quickly robs the player of a lot of opportunities. Some players will always drive as high as they can go as far as they can go, like Icarus trying to reach the sun, but the best way to play this game is to enjoy it at your own pace and let leveling and gear come as they come.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 built in a lot of tools to improve social interaction. Players can invite other players into a group anywhere in a zone. Players can directly invite others from the "Looking for Group" tool. Players can target other players in a group and see their name highlighted across the zone no matter how far away. There are world-wide channels for new players, classes, and cities.</p>

<p>SOE streamlined the actions of getting into a group, finding your group, following your group, hunting in your group, and leaving your group. Every class, upon achieving citizenship in the citizenship quest, receives a daily gate to your home city helping players leave the game quickly when real life rears its ugly head and demands a sacrifice.</p>

<p>It is too early to poke big holes in a game this big but a couple of things stick out as potential problems. While raiding doesn't require more than 24 people, a limit that may radically change the forming of the dreaded uberguild, a level system for guilds promising a new path for content could alienate guilds of lower power or lower membership. This may not be a problem as long as it doesn't become the only form of progression available. EQ1 seemed to drive players into uberguilds once they reached a certain level. At the high levels joining a raiding guild became the only way to increase one's power. Still, a guild-based level system seems to stretch outside of simple social interaction and into the realm of cliques and elitism; something I detest in massive online games.</p>

<p>Everquest 2's biggest problem is time. I don't plan on quitting Everquest 1. I already filled my day with work, writing, the dreaded Tivo, and my nightly hunts in Everquest. I have yet to successfully play two massive online games at the same time. Whichever game I happen to be in, I feel like I'm missing something going on in the other.</p>

<p>Everquest 1's numbers certainly dropped in the last two weeks. However, I hear other guild leaders say that Halo 2, Half Life 2, Grand Theft Auto: San Andraes, and the holidays in general take more players away from EQ than World of Warcraft or Everquest 2. While it looks like EQ numbers dropped in the last couple of weeks, we won't know its real impact until the worlds settle and we see where everyone ends up. I wouldn't count anything as fact until early next year.</p>

<p>It is easy to look at the release of Everqust 2 as an earth-shaking event. We play in a community where the decisions of a sword or a bow bring hundreds of angry rangers to the doors of SOE. From some of the passion we read on the EQ forums and even on the comments on previous Mobhunter articles, it would seem we traveled far outside the realm of a simple game.</p>

<p>But Everquest and Everquest 2 are games. We buy them, we install them, we play them, and we talk about them. Sure, these aren't like any other games before them. No couple ever met and got married over Ratchet and Clank. Everquest 2 is one of the best games I have ever seen. If my dollar is my vote, I bought two copies of the game, one as a gift, and signed up for a year-long subscription including all of the web features. The total price was over $200 but I expect a high entertainment reward for my investment. Everquest 2 is an amazing game and I look forward to watching young Pavlen progress through this vast world.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
22 November 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>November News Roundup</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000040.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-11-11T14:44:53Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.40</id>
<created>2004-11-11T14:44:53Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we take a look at some community news including the release of EQ2, some code changes, Caster&apos;s Realms&apos;s new administrator, and a few other odds and ends from around the net.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Everquest 2 hit the shelves on Tuesday and the world didn't end.  Few people know exactly what will happen over the next six months but numbers in EQ will no doubt be low throughout the next few weeks.  For the raiding guilds that require 54 people all night every night, this might end up causing a bit of trouble but for the single-group pickup hunters, life shouldn't be so bad.  There will be less groups overall but each group still needs six members.  Spots that were once over camped may open up.  The great hoards of treasure falling out of the  lands of Kuua should distribute to fewer people, giving each one a greater chance for a nice item or rune of power.</p>

<p>Not all communication methods are up and running yet between EQ and EQ2 but cross-game tells and EQ2 channel joining from EQ1 works.  From within EQ you can send a tell to your EQ2 friend by typing "[tell eq2.antonia_bayle.pavlen hail" where antonia_bayle is the servername he or she is on and pavlen is his or her character name.  You can send a tell from EQ2 to Everquest by typing "/tell eq.quellious.loral hello".  I hoped that this would be a little easier.  With all of the various / ; [ ways to send tells it is easy to get confused.  One would think, with the various server names, that we wouldn't have to put the game title in front to send a tell.  "/tell antonia_bayle.pavlen" has enough information to tell the vast self-aware machine farm at SOE that I want to send a tell to EQ2.  "[tell eq2.antonia_bayle.pavlen" makes me feel like I'm writing my own email headers.</p>

<p>Moorgard announced that you can also send tells to Star Wars Galaxies characters using the same method: "/tell swg.servername.charname message".  I don't know anyone playing SWG so I couldn't test it out.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 players cannot yet subscribe to EQ1 channels but you can subscribe to EQ2 channels within EQ1 by typing "[join eq2.servername.channel" (there's that stupid bracket again).  Hopefully we'll see EQ1 channel subscribing from within EQ2 soon.</p>

<p>I plan to write a full review and comparison of Everquest 2 during a slow news week but I love it so far.  It won't drag me off of EQLive any time soon, but the quest system is very rewarding and I hope we see a system like it in EQLive sometime soon.</p>

<p>SOE released the details of the backflagging solution this week.  Some mobs, like those in Plane of Time, drop items that let previously unflagged players become flagged.  Some zones require a single-group quest once an unflagged player acquired a quest piece from a raid-level mob inside the zone they wish to enter.  Most zones will soon have an 85-15 rule, allowing 15% of a raid to enter a zone without needing a flag.  There will be a variety of other quests to backflag people for lower-tier Planes of Power zones.  Read the full <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=7049">backflagging report</a> from my summit friend, Emil.</p>

<p>This is a fine solution for backflagging.  It will not help unflagged groups get flags, however.  At this point in the game's life, I don't know that that matters.  Unflagged raiding organizations now have a wide range of unflagged raids to conquer.  Gates and Omens offer a lot of unflagged raid-level content with rewards higher than Plane of Time.  I still see many guilds or raiding groups banging their heads on the walls of Time and losing members in the process.  With the probable drop in members due to EQ2, Grand Theft Auto, Halo 2, WoW, and the holidays in general, an enterprising raid force would be wise to try new targets with greater rewards.  It is also a good time to open your doors a little bit and let some typical non-raiders into your raids.</p>

<p>Grumbuk, SOE's resident coder at the Fan Faire, wrote a <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=development&message.id=1987#M1987">lengthy report on some current collision changes</a>.  We can expect a few performance tweaks in areas that previously gave us a bit of trouble and getting out of that chilly water should finally come a bit easier.</p>

<p>A series of strange new spells, all available to level 20 priests and casters, hit the dark pages of Lucy on the 9th.  These spells, called "blessings" each correspond to one of the known gods.  When cast, these spells summon a strange unknown item.  If I had to guess, and it is probably wishful thinking on my part, I would say they could summon a single-charge, no-rent gate device usable by typical non-gaters.  If it isn't, well, it should be.</p>

<p><a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/">Caster's Realm</a>, one of the more popular EQ websites, underwent a change of command.  Baelish, the previous administrator, moved on to help SOE develop the Station Players website for EQ2.  My friend Gemdiver, the previous administrator of the wizard community forum, Graffe's, now maintains Caster's Realm and <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=6885">plans</a> to take it to all new levels.  He recruited a few community writers to write content for the site including your favorite cleric who started with a <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=6966">Raidleader's Guide to Raiding</a> posted late last week.  Now if I can just convince Gemdiver not to burn Plane of Knowledge to the ground, I could make real progress.</p>

<p>It's been a slow couple of weeks since the Fan Faire but in December we can expect a patch or two with some exciting changes.  In the mean time, help save the Dragorns from the plight of their Muramite overlords and get some fine armor in the process.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight <br />
11 November 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>October 2004 Fan Faire Report</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000039.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-11-02T12:21:27Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.39</id>
<created>2004-11-02T12:21:27Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">We return from New Orleans full of strange visions and fine tales to tell.  Pull up a chair and listen to the stories of the future of Norrath.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>The following article was written for both Mobhunter and Caster's Realm.</p>

<p>I return from the Bayou, black notebook laden with facts, details, rumors and the philosophies from the silver temple of the west.  SOE put on a fine event, as entertaining as it was informative.  SOE developers and staff made themselves available throughout the three-night event, happy to discuss anything the fans could bring up.</p>

<p>If you care not to hear of the festivities, skip down right into the juicy morsels of goodness below.  If you have not been to a Fan Faire, however, it is quite a treat.  There's always a bit of nervousness going to such an event.  We all know each other in-game but to meet face to face can be a bit daunting.  Non stop contests, presentations, late-night gatherings, and panels filled out three days perfectly.  It wasn't uncommon to see three fellows walking down Burbon Street, hurricanes high, shouting "hail" at everyone they saw.  "Train to Zone" they'd shout as a pack of bikers drives by with grim looks on their bearded faces.</p>

<p>Your head swims with after-images as you fly back home.  Brenlo hurls sharp-edged boxes at the heads of players in the manifestation of his ultimate Community Relations dream.  Vannoth teaches players how to train zones ("OMGZ RUN") and Cyb3r barbarian females in Everquest 2 ("OMGZ YUO USED ME!").  The costumes, the contests, the dialog, the tales of adventure, the personalities; they all add up to a weekend packed with enough memories to last six months.  If you ever get a chance to go to a Fan Faire, take it.</p>

<p>Ok, now on to the juicy morsels of goodness.</p>

<p>A large amount of the Fan Faire focused on Everquest 2.  By now most people have heard of the November 8 release date.  SOE had planned on this date for some time; it was not a knee jerk reaction to the rumored simultaneous release date of World of Warcraft.  Who really believes those EBGames dates anyway? Shame on you.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 showed up everywhere.  A 24 hour Everquest 2 contest awarded an Alienware PC to the player with the highest level and experience.  Over 30 machines were open for Fan Faire attendees to play.  Every Fan Faire attendee earned an EQ2 beta account upon registration.  I will leave it to other reviewers to discuss the details of Everquest 2 but I will discuss a few interesting tidbits.</p>

<p>I finally met my predecessor, Moorgard.  During our discussion he mentioned that EQ2 went through a series of focus tests and usability tests for both new and veteran players.  I hope Everquest goes through such tests if it has not done so already.  Making the game easy to start and play is a key to bringing in new customers.</p>

<p>SOE demonstrated the new Station Players website for Everquest 2 players.  The website offers a wide range of excellent features including guild website tools, Magelo-like player profiles, web-based guild chat, and server community forums.  There's a lot to like and demonstrations are available on the EQ2 website.  SOE intends to implement these features for all SOE games including EQLive in the next six to eight months.</p>

<p>Now let us dig into EQLive news.</p>

<p>In the next patch or two, the task system will gain over one thousand new tasks including tasks up to level 70.  Tasks will include a variety of new actions such as foraging and fishing on top of the existing kill 10, collect 4, talk to an NPC, or visit a location.  SOE plans to balance many old tasks as well.  Kaikachi, the task developer, reinforced that he uses bug reports and feedback to balance tasks so make sure to /bug or /feedback them if you find a task that doesn't work.</p>

<p>Backflagging came up more than once this event and SOE appears to have a viable solution in the works.  SOE will extend the 85-15 flagging rule, the rule that allows 15% of a raid to enter a flagged zone without the flag, to Time and many Gates zones.  Raid mobs within flagged zones will drop one or two quest items that let unflagged members begin a quest to receive a permanent flag for that zone.  Flags achieved this way will not backflag characters for previous zones.  A Time flag quest, for example, will not award a Fire flag.</p>

<p>Rashere, the primary Alternate Ability developer, has a list of AAs to review.  He already wrote a spreadsheet of point cost reductions for Gates AAs.  A piece of code will soon let players receive AA refunds without losing AAs over 30 should they zone.  It will not let players store more than 30 new AAs, however.  Players who already purchased AAs at the higher cost will receive the difference; they will not get a full refund for abilities unless the ability itself changes.</p>

<p>During the "Maintain a Living World" panel a pompous jackass of a moderator brought up the Everquest's Economy. According to Lyndro, tributes helped take money out of the economy but targeted the wrong players.  High-end players hold most of the money in Norrath but rarely use tributes.  Items like horses only take money out of the economy once.  SOE designed systems like trade skills to take money out of the economy but SOE always considers new solutions.</p>

<p>SOE does not plan to add new LDON loot.  Like Kunark and Velious, SOE intends players who get through the content of LDON to travel onwards to expansions like Omens and Gates.  LDON is not intended to offer progression through the entire range of the game.  Now that Omens offers fine equipment to single-group hunters, I agree with their assessment.</p>

<p>SOE plans to continue changing hot-zones to get players traveling out to old world zones.  From time to time they may add Fabled-like items to old-world content like they did with the fifth anniversary.  These changes, on top of epic quests and tasks, help get new players to older world zones.</p>

<p>Rogue's Hour, the first in a series of four planned Everquest-based novels, hit the shelves a couple of weeks ago and Scott Ciencin signed books and discussed future publishing plans.  Each of the next three books will come out every three months including one by Elane Cunningham, the author of many fine Forgotten Realms books.  These books help add new depth to our world and I look forward to their continued release.</p>

<p>Class tuning came up many times and SOE has plans to address class issues.  SOE will release class descriptions, not full class definitions, which contain a lot of SOE internal statistics.  SOE community relations folk meet often with developers to help make sure the class issues get discussed and to make sure each class has a clear group role and is fun to play.</p>

<p>I spent a time far shorter than I would have liked speaking with Vahlar regarding lore and story progression.  I mentioned my desire to see the Muramites invading Norrath and she assured me that some big changes would hit Norrath in coming weeks.  SOE heard the player's cry for a more cohesive storyline, one built from original EQ lore and plans to improve this.  The return of Firiona Vie and the Lifeguide to the storyline begins this return to older lore.</p>

<p>SOE already began the design of a new EQLive expansion but details are scarce.  Lyndro stated clearly that expansions will follow the Kunark, Velious, and Omens trend for one single locked zone, not a series of progressive locked zones such as those we faced in Planes of Power and Gates of Discord.  SOE rebuilt much of Omens, far more than I expected, after the guild summit in June.  SOE hears what players ask for and they heard us very well with Omens.  I have high hopes and look forward to January's announcement.</p>

<p>The future looks bright.  We see many exciting changes on the way and every SOE employee I spoke to said many of the things I wanted to hear.  EQ2 presents a huge unknown variable but it is clear that no SOE employee on either team wants EQ players quitting one for the other.  I do not see EQ2 affecting EQLive's future in any way but for the better.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
2 November 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Loral&apos;s Evil Halloween Agenda</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000038.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-21T11:59:15Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.38</id>
<created>2004-10-21T11:59:15Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Next week Loral travels to the strange lands of New Orleans.  He travels with a satchel full of this Evil Agenda in the hopes of helping to manipulate Everquest to his own evil lands of darkness and horror.  Read on...if you dare!</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Next week I travel to New Orleans and join in the fun at this year's EQ Fan Faire.  As I did with the guild summit in March, I write the direction I would like to see EQ travel.  This article describes five areas for SOE to focus on and improve in the future.</p>

<h2>Add and Improve Quests</h2>

<p>Quests should be the cornerstone of Everquest.  Currently, however, most progression comes from killing beasts and getting occasional rare drops.  Many different types of events could spawn from quests, whether they are group hunts, raids, tasks, tradeskills, or soloing.</p>

<p>Add and update quests.  Consider developing a new quest system similar to the task system.  Update the Ro armor quests with valuable pieces.  Add level 30 and 40 armor quests.  Add a mid-level epic quests.</p>

<p>Everquest should include fun, powerful, and progressive quests at all levels.  Quest completion should offer significant experience bonuses, character flags, equipment upgrades, augments, new spells, and new disciplines.</p>

<p>Build a new quest interface that uses the "find" trail, compass marking, and a log-book to keep track of quests players currently follow.</p>

<p>Quests should return to the center of the game, especially a game titled "Everquest".</p>

<h2>Improve Grouping Options</h2>

<p>Add a /groupinvite keyboard command to invite players from outside the zone into a group.  Add "invite player" to the LFG window so one can send invites across the game.  Allow players to invite another by pressing the "invite" box on the group window and typing in a name.</p>

<p>Improve the "Friends" window.  Add a notes field for each friend.  Add a way to track alternate characters of a single player.  Add a way to forward tells from one character to another.  Make the "Friends" window more like the guild tool so we can track friends online, view notes, send tells, and perhaps send messages to off line characters.</p>

<p>Add short-duration tasks for groups of two or more people working on a single task.  Use the task system of Omens to give groups a short-duration quest tracking down evil bosses or hunting packs of loosed werewolves.  Tie it in with an improved quest system so groups can get together, pick a quest, and accomplish it within 90 minutes for experience and progress towards new gear.</p>

<p>Find a way for high level and low level players to work together.  Both should be challenged and both should receive an appropriate reward.  With the large amount of both high level and low level players, if methods can be found for these groups to work together, far more groups will gather together, run off, and have fun.  Gandalf and Frodo both grouped together and Frodo was totally g1mp.</p>

<h2>Focus on 90 minute events.</h2>

<p>While many Everquest players play for long periods of time, many cannot.  Everquest should focus around 90 minute game sessions.  Players should be able to progress in levels, AAs, and equipment in 90 minute intervals.  Camping for extended periods of time should not be the only way to progress in equipment at higher levels.</p>

<p>LDON offers a 90 minute point-based loot system that lets players earn new gear in smaller play-sessions but longer periods of time.  Use systems like this one to let players with limited time earn new equipment in other areas of Norrath.</p>

<p>Not every area or encounter should focus on 90 minutes, but many of them should.  Everquest needs to fit in better with our busy lives.</p>

<h2>Improve Encounter Variety</h2>

<p>Add more variety to single-group encounters.  Use instanced expeditions to tailor scripted encounters around groups.  Find new challenges for players other than straight damage.  Consider a lich that has very few hitpoints but many spells of protection that must be defeated before damaging the lich.  Consider beasts that only cast spells instead of melee, but with devastating effects!  Keep it fun, not frustrating.  No more chain complete healing mobs or mobs that gate only to earn back 30% of their hitpoints.</p>

<p>Use the experience gained from building excellent raid encounters to build fun new single-group events.  I understand the Muramite Provinground trials include events like this.  Continue this great work and build it for players of all levels, not just the highest high-end players.</p>

<h2>Make the Game Easier for New Players</h2>

<p>Everquest is a very difficult game to learn for new players.  Systems like the tutorial help but further refinements could help new players learn how to play and become slobbering addicts posting general substance-free negativity on the ranger forum in a few short months.  Here are a few suggestions:</p>

<p>Add a newbie chat channel autojoined at character creation.  Make it very easy for players to learn how to chat.  Give them a message that tells them how to send information and what the chat is for.</p>

<p>Streamline the interface for skills, disciplines, AAs, and other hotbutton effects.  Create a single window with all possible effects that we can drag over to our hotboxes. Auto-learn skills or notify players of new possible skills when they become available.</p>

<p>Add in an alternative to corpse recovery.  Add an NPC that summons bodies to Shadowrest for a high level-based cost.  Make the bodies he summons unressable to account for the easier corpse recovery.  As an alternative, add it as a necromancer and shadowknight spell.</p>

<h2>In Conclusion...</h2>

<p>Flexibility is the strength of Everquest.  Every year our world changes and every year it gets better.  The requests above will help Everquest continue to grow into an enjoyable and ground-breaking game for both old and new players.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
21 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Warts Under the Emperor&apos;s Clothes</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000037.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-18T16:32:45Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.37</id>
<created>2004-10-18T16:32:45Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">It is a month after the release of Omens of War and the world of Norrath changed forever.  While this expansion has many strengths, it also has a few weaknesses.  This week we peek underneath the beautiful and ornate exterior to examine a few of the expansion&apos;s weaknesses.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>A month passed since the release of Omens of War and there is much to love.  Excellent graphics, useful and fun zones, great hunting, and many new directions to progress all build one of the best expansions we've ever seen.</p>

<p>In previous articles we talked about the strengths of Omens.  This week we look at some of its problems in hope that SOE considers them for change in Omens itself or considers them in the design of future expansions.  Let us begin.</p>

<p>The Hollows, Sewers, and Catacombs expeditions in Omens include instanced content between levels 45 and 70 filled with experience mobs and the occasional rare beast holding a bag of shiny loot.</p>

<p>One thing lacking in these expeditions is any sort of plot, story, quest, or purpose aside from general hunting.  These dungeons could have included plots and story lines, boss mobs, point-based loot systems, or even Kael-like armor quests instead of simply being more experience content.  Add a quest, add a story or purpose, or add a new loot system and these dungeons become a lot more fun.  And please, no more rats, bats and spiders.</p>

<p>The Omens task system could be the future of quests in Everquest.  All of the tools are there to help players accomplish quests and travel across Norrath.  While the current quest options are limited, scripted encounters and continuing story lines could take players through exciting quests far different from what we're used to.  Add scripted and locked encounters, add an overarching story line, add more rewards than just cash and experience, and you will create a strong new quest system in Everquest for all levels.  Include quests for level 68 and above.  All players should have the option to perform tasks.</p>

<p>Omens brings a much improved spell system over Gates of Discord and Planes of Power.  The Muramite Rune system ensures players never receive duplicate spells.  Players may trade and sell level 66, 67, and 68 spell runes and already the obnoxious prices in the bazaar plummet.  I predict rune prices will hit the reasonable10k mark by the end of November.</p>

<p>While players can reach level 70 in dozens of areas, they must now travel to either Muramite Proving Grounds or Riftseekers, two very difficult zones for non-raid equipped players, and hope they get lucky on a drop and lucky again on a roll.</p>

<p>SOE can improve this in two ways.  Add in a quest that lets players receive their first rune at each level.  Make the quest more than just rare drops on rare mobs.  Remove the no-drop flag on 69 and 70 runes so players can sell these runes in the bazaar like the others.</p>

<p>When the whole focus-item quagmire hit a couple of months ago, we heard that Focus 5 items would be more available than the focus items we saw in Planes of Power.  While decent focus gear seems to drop regularly in Wall of Slaughter, the drops in Ruined City of Dranik and Muramite Provingrounds, both harder zones than the Wall of Slaughter, drop few items with focus or combat effects.  Add more focus and combat effects to equipment in Ruined City of Dranik, Muramite Provingground, and the Ruined City expeditions.</p>

<p>Now lets talk about a larger problem: Everquest's time requirements.</p>

<p>Lost Dungeons of Norrath changed the face of Everquest.  Instead of spending four to six hours at a time sitting in one place pulling the same mobs over and over, we now had adventures that forced us to crawl, gave us a goal to accomplish, and a time limit to accomplish it in.  It was not uncommon to get a group together, start an adventure, finish it, and camp out within a two-hour period.  The game went from camping the same spot for six hours to a game of fast and furious adventure.</p>

<p>With Omens  I hoped to see an improvement on this.  More quests, more adventure types, perhaps a new point based loot system that doesn't remind us of a cigarette vending machine ("Innoruuk curse it! My +40 hitpoint augment is stuck again!" *bang bang*).  Omens had the potential to combine our favorite overland hunting from expansions like Velious and Luclin with the powerful dungeon and loot system of Lost Dungeons.</p>

<p>Instead we took a step backwards.  We have expeditions but they are simply instanced hunting zones.  We sit, we pull mobs, we kill them, they respawn, and we repeat until we fall over into our own four hour old bowl of mulchy Coco Puffs.</p>

<p>In order to have any shot at new spells or gear in Omens, you have to hunt for at least four hours.  In that time you may see two to three named mobs and may have a 50% shot at winning something.  If you don't win, you are no closer to a new item or spell than you were when you started.  There is no loot or spell progression option other than random luck or spending cash in the bazaar.</p>

<p>More important than the loot system, however, is a sense of an urgent adventure, one that requires us to fight fast and hard towards a single goal.  These exist deeper in Omens with the Muramite Provinground trials, but few will see these Ikkinz level expeditions any time soon.</p>

<p>Omens is a great expansion with a lot of excellent content and features.  With a little more focus towards quests, events, and goals, and a 90 minute duration per adventure this expansion or future expansions will step outside the traditional Everquest four hour camp and into a more time-friendly and exciting game.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
18 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Myths of Class Balancing</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000036.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-12T04:09:52Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.36</id>
<created>2004-10-12T04:09:52Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we get away from some of the controversy surrounding our beloved game and go into the green pastures of a topic we can all enjoy and agree upon.  I kid, of course.  Lets roll up our sleeves and dig into the myths of class balance.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>A couple of weeks ago I wrote about five meaningless terms of Everquest.  One of these, Class Balance, is so overused that it now defines just about any problem one has with one's class.  There is no such thing as class balance and if there were, we'd have no defined classes.  There are nuggets of truth within this chaotic topic, however, and once we know what to ask for we can learn how to ask for it.</p>

<p>While there is no class balance, there is class tuning. Many of us focus on a particular class and with the time we've put in, we know bits and pieces of our class that under-perform.</p>

<p>Every class has advantages and disadvantages when compared to other classes.  This should always be true.  Adventurers depend on each other and always should.  If we could all solo our way to 70 with greater efficiency than in a group, we would.  Dependency forces us to group to progress and grouping is what makes Everquest different than any other single-player role playing game.</p>

<p>There are four main archetypes that current Everquest classes fall into.  Powerful efficient groups require each of these four archetypes in order to battle at the best of their ability.  These archetypes include healers, crowd controllers, tanks, and damage dealers.  </p>

<p>Groups should not depend on any one of the sixteen classes.  At worst, they should only require one from each of the four archetypes in order to group well.  For the most part, this exists today.  A group can earn excellent experience and a shot at some nice loot without any dependency on one class.</p>

<p>Now it is possible to have an ideal group.  It is possible to have a perfect combination of classes that outperform a group of a different makeup.  Again, this will probably always be true and even after extensive class tuning, will end up being true in some other configuration. Even if some sort of widespread class evaluation took place, equipment, AAs, and the skills of the players will always create imbalance between two different groups.</p>

<p>Here is one of Loral's Key to Happiness:  Forget about the numbers.  Throw away your damage per second parser.  Ignore the experience per hour you hear people acquiring in Fire.  Enjoy your class and your skills and go where you desire to hunt.  Constantly worrying about the damage per second of your character and only hunting in the most profitable zones leads to boredom and anger.  </p>

<p>This Key to Happiness is superseded by Loral's First Rule of Happiness: Have Fun.  If you like delving into the numbers, go ahead.  If they lead you to believe your class is worthless and weak and you end up spending days arguing with monks on the class boards, best to leave them aside.</p>

<p>When I brought up the topic of class balance with my editor, we decided we'd take a look at rangers.  He plays a wizard and I play a cleric so we had to go to his wife, the only one we know personally who plays a ranger.  When we asked what her top five ranger issues were, this is what she came back with:</p>

<p>- Rangers aren't big enough.<br />
- The starting city is too hard.<br />
- Rangers are a mishmosh class.<br />
- After years of playing she is only level 24.<br />
- Rangers get no respect.</p>

<p>I bring these up to show how perception changes our focus.  You may think you're the voice of all rangers when you argue that the Epic 1.5 should be a bow, but you really only focus on high-level rangers capable of accomplishing the quest.  The more narrow your view, the fewer people you help.  While focus is fine, we should not lose sight of the bigger picture.</p>

<p>For the class correspondents I have one piece of advise.  Always consider the class at all levels.  Don't focus on only the highest level of the game.  Classes have problems throughout their life and problems between level 30 and 50 effect more players than those at 65 and above.</p>

<p>So how can we help SOE improve our classes?  First, consider what we ask for.  If it bleeds into another class consider what impact it may have on them.  If the impact is little, perhaps it is a reasonable request.  If it impacts a lot, best to think about it further.  The best chance for change is to focus on skills that do not dramatically effect the class.</p>

<p>Second, use your class correspondent.  Find out who they are and what their issues are.  They work with SOE directly to make sure top class issues are known.  If your change is really as important as you think it is, you shouldn't have a hard time convincing them about it.</p>

<p>Third, speak in detail.  Don't complain about your classes overall grouping benefit.  Pick the abilities that require improvement and focus on them.  When I read over the class requests on the EQLive forums, I see mixes of specific requests (Turn Undead needs to work better) with general ones (Clerics need a secondary role).  Guess which one I'd fix first?</p>

<p>Like every other topic we bring up with SOE, avoid constant negativity, avoid threats, avoid woe-is-me statements about how your class is dead.  No class is dead.  Every class is still well represented on every server.  Every class has use.  Every class has advantages over others.</p>

<p>Above all, we should keep the whole game in mind when we consider changes.  Vast ranges of players, classes, levels, and zones remind us that we have a huge world.  SOE should always consider focusing on big changes first and smaller changes second.  While SOE cannot ignore class changes, it is the large changes that improve the game the most.  I would sacrifice Turn Undead in a minute if it meant we would see a new corpse recovery option.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Interview with Scott Adams</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000035.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-08T05:27:26Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.35</id>
<created>2004-10-08T05:27:26Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week it is my pleasure to interview Scott Adams.  Scott and Pasty Loral dicuss Scott&apos;s mark on the computer game world, Scott&apos;s Everquest career, and Scott&apos;s EQ Wishlist.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>This week I am honored to introduce Scott Adams.  Scott agreed to sit down with Mobhunter for a short interview.  Scott is a long-time Everquest player and a major icon in the computer gaming community.  Let us begin the questions:</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  For those who have yet to figure out the gnomish technology of "Google" could you please introduce yourself and your background?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I am credited with starting the Personal Computer Gaming industry in 1978 with the publication of Adventureland. I am also called the father of computer gaming. (Should be grandfather now, hehe) My company Adenture International was in business til aprox 1985 publishing primarily computer games for the micro computers of that era.</p>

<p>I had actually been writing computer games before this. I remember writing computer games at a radar station I worked at and using the radar monitors to play the games on. I later had a homebrew system my brother build from CPU bit slices that I wrote a simple arcade style shooter for. I had to entirely hand assemble and link it. Later I had a Sphere computer (kit computer) which I wrote an elaborate arcade tank war game complete with home made controllers. It won Sphere's first annual "What do I use my Sphere Computer for" contest. With the advent of "appliance" computers  (that is what we homebrewers called them back then) such as TRS-80 and Apple I saw my chance to write for a larger audience.</p>

<p>I understand I have inspired many of today's game designers and programmers. I still get allot of fan mail from the nice folks who tell me that my games were the reason they got into computers as a career. I am always happy to hear from folks like that and have made many new friends over the years because of it.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  How do you feel about the direction computer games took since you started the field?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I am actually very happy with modern day computer games. One of the reasons I started my writing computer games was there were none around to play. Now there is a wonderful surfeit of great games. I watch them evolve over the years from the simple single man generated effort to the small team built games to the industrial strength mega efforts of today.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  How long have you played EQ?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I started playing EQ in April 2001. I had heard about the game before when it launched but had the impression it was some sort of glorified chat room with folks pretending they were medieval people. Sort of like a Medieval reenactment world. Certainly nothing a real computer game player would ever be interested in.</p>

<p>Then a friend of mine told me he played and what it was really about. I decided to give a try and rolled up a halfling druid. I was instantly hooked.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong> What characters, classes, and levels do you play?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I have played almost all the classes and characters. My highest char is only 48 and is a druid. I have allot of 30-40 level characters as I would roll them up and play them to see how well they fit into my hydra.</p>

<p>You can see my current set and my others here:<br />
<a href="http://www.msadams.com/magelo.htm">http://www.msadams.com/magelo.htm</a></p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong> Could you explain your Hydra?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> I play 5 chars at one time. I use 5 discreet computers to do this. My center machine I run my Paladin. On my left is my enchanter, to my right is my druid. These machines are all on the same desktop. On a rolling cart to my left is my Bard and another cart on my right has my cleric.</p>

<p>I have many in game macros setup to assist me. For example when I bring in a mob I hit the 5 key on my setups. This will then do the assist the puller and start whatever normal attack its. The cleric will do a celestial heal and the bard will auto follow the puller to get in place then assist and melee attack.</p>

<p>My bard uses a keyboard macro to allow him twist 3-4 songs at time, normally he is using amplify and a manna song.</p>

<p>I remapped the F1-F8 keys to be the spell gems, so I can instantly fire off spells as needed on any of my characters. My 1-0 keys are all mapped to the normal hotkeys. I have an emergency bail out on the 8 key on all my chars. The druid has a Crucible of Escape and this on the 8 key, the other casters all have gate on 8.</p>

<p>I also use a 4rd party utility called EQ Watcher www.eqwatcher.com which reads the log files out loud. I have my own custom scripts I have written for it so I can be kept informed at all times what is going on my other chars. This one utility more than anything else makes my hydra MX5 possible!</p>

<p>http://www.msadams.com/EQWatcher/</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  What other MMOGs do you play and what do you think of them?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong>  I have played all the major MOGS and many of the minors ones too. Dark Age of Camelot, Anarchy Online, Neocron, Eve, Underlight, A Tale in the Desert are some examples of the MOGs I have played. Right now the only two I am playing are EQ and City of Heroes.</p>

<p>CoH is a MOG lite. Basically a pure fighting game with nothing added to get in the way of the fast furious battles. I have currently been in CoH since its launch this April.</p>

<p>Of all the MOGs I play EQ is the only one that I keep coming back to, I usually play a MOG for 2 to 4 months then return to EQ.</p>

<p>I am also beta testing EQ2 and will be in that big time when it launches. I won't play a hydra there. I also do not play a hydra in CoH, the game is way to fast and furious to really allow it.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  What are some of the things you like about EQ?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> Big world and lots of utility spells. The co-operative aspect of the game where it is you and friends against a hostile environment. The abilities you get at higher levels to teleport around quickly. The excitement of the drops and not knowing what may turn up.</p>

<p>I love the bazaar system and all the updates they did recently to improve it. No other game has anything even close to this. A one stop shopping mall is SO much better than tiny shops scattered over the whole game world.</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  What sorts of things would you like to see improved in the existing EQ world?</p>

<p><strong>Scott Adams:</strong> Quests. You really have no way to know if a quest is doable or not, what the reward might be and if it is worth even trying, maybe times the reward is simply not even usable. I, like many others, use the 3rd party web sites to determine which quests are even worth bothering with. This really stinks.</p>

<p>Content for non raiders. I don't raid and don't want to, but I want to see interesting sites and fight interesting mobs.</p>

<p>In game email. Some way to communicate with EQ only friends. My other mogs have this feature and it makes a big difference.</p>

<p>Sidekicking. This feature in City of Heroes allows one to play their friends no matter their levels. You can either choose to raise some else level to you or decrease yours to theirs. This alone would make an incredible difference in EQ to allow folks to join up.</p>

<p>Improved graphics. The current Luclin era character models certainly need work as do most of the old world zones.</p>

<p>Group oriented task system. The OOW task system should be expanded to allow groups to get them together and all reap the rewards. This is then like an outdoor LDoN spread across Norrath. Would be great fun. Currently I do tasks with my hydra but not all members of the hydra can always get the same tasks.</p>

<p>The ability to do LFG across zones. CoH just put that in and its a phenomenal idea. This way folks can invite others no matter where they are currently looking for group!</p>

<p><strong>Mobhunter:</strong>  Thank you for your time Scott!  You can read more about Scott Adams at <a href="http://www.msadams.com/">his website</a> and download some of <a href="http://www.msadams.com/downloads.htm">Scott's Grand Adventures</a>.</p>

<p>Interview conducted by Loral Ciriclight<br />
7 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Early October News</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000034.html" />
<modified>2005-02-02T15:03:07Z</modified>
<issued>2004-10-04T05:17:32Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.34</id>
<created>2004-10-04T05:17:32Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we relax from the onslaught of Lorals editorials for a more traditional look at the news.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>This week we take a look at some of the news appearing throughout the Everquest community.</p>

<p>On Halloween SOE hosts the <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/fanfaire/index.jsp">New Orleans Fan Faire</a>.  SOE posted the  <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/fanfaire/event_schedule.jsp">schedule</a> for this year's Fan Faire last week.  Your favorite cleric (that's me in case you forgot) will be in attendance armed with an all new agenda to stuff into the pockets of anyone with an SOE badge.  Like the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000016.html">summit agenda</a>, I will post this agenda here a week or two before the Fan Faire.</p>

<p>This week SOE announced <a href="http://soeworlds.station.sony.com/">SOE Worlds</a> a print magazine devoted to Everquest, Everquest 2, Everquest Online Adventures, Star Wars Galaxies, and the rest of SOE's army of massive online games.  The magazine includes strategy articles, general reviews, fiction, and interviews.  I expected something like this to come out eventually; I'm surprised it took as long as it did.</p>

<p>The largest buzz and attention in the last couple of weeks appears to focus on Epic 1.5s.  Every class board, hundreds of discussions on the EQ Live forums, and most of the developer and community feedback follows the progression of these quests.  Epic raids pour into most chat channels and even the non-raiders seem to have epic fever.  Why people seem to be more interested in epics than levels, AAs, spells, or other gear seems beyond me.  It may be the most popular Omens feature for high-level players.</p>

<p>A bit of nastiness hit quite a few people last week.  People's Omens accounts shut off without warning and sent level 66+ players back to their level 65 self.  At first rumors spoke of credit transaction problems but reports came in from people who bought their copy in the store.  Sony jumped on it and posted <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=63626">this statement</a>.  I heard of nearly half a dozen people losing their level in this manner but all of them seemed to get it back without too much of a hassle.  This seems to be the only major bug in an otherwise smooth expansion release; certainly smoother than Gates of Discord which suffered from random linkdeaths for nearly a week.</p>

<p>A new <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=testing&message.id=4617">feature on test</a> has bards cheering.  Bards will soon have the ability to auto-twist songs using a new "/melody" command.  Typing "/melody 1 2 3" will play each of the three songs in sequence.  The change helps bards become more social creatures, giving them the time to chat with friends and watch Tivo until their friends shout "Heal Me, Dolt!".  Some bard purists complain that it removes one of the great tests of skills for bards but most bards agree that the loss of challenge is worth the reduction in repetitive motion stress.</p>

<p>66+ spell costs dropped from 140,000 plat on the first few days to 60,000 plat today on Quellious.  I expect to see them drop to 10k before they meet the balance of supply and demand.  This should probably happen in a month or two.  I still know little about the location of 69 and 70 spells.  The no-drop requirement worries me.  Instead of living the twilight of my levels where I choose, I will probably have to hunt in Muramite Provingrounds and Riftseeker's in order to receive 69 and 70 spells.</p>

<p>People continue to migrate in long lines to the Wall of Slaughter.  Though better experience and loot awaits discovery in Ruined City of Dranik and its two sets of instances, people prefer the easier hunting ground and higher drop-rate of the Wall.  I cannot blame them and it is better to have one zone like the Wall than none at all, but it will be nice to see people spread out a bit more into the other lands.  In the mean time, for great fun and high adventure, travel to the Ruined City of Dranik through the Bloodfields.  If you are truly a band of hearty adventurers, attempt the Sewers and Catacombs expeditions.</p>

<p>One thing that definitely appears to be missing are random rare drops on normal mobs.  Instead of spending hours camping the same two spawn areas in the Hollows, I'd prefer to have a low chance (1/100) of receiving a rune drop or a loot item off of a normal beast.  Perhaps they haven't been found and reported yet, but so far I have seen none.</p>

<p>Expect a new system for the loading screens between zones.  People in beta had problems with the original one looking too much like a system hanging forever so they put in the loading screen.  The loading screen, however, breaks the flow of the game too much.  Sony builds a new system as we speak.  Perhaps we will see it in the mid-October patch.</p>

<p>I look with narrowed eyes to find problems for the single-group hunter in Omens and I find few.  Spell drops seem reasonable.  I received a piece of loot in a single-group battle I could immediately use, something that hasn't happened to me in a long while.  High level players can reach high level loot without required raiding.  We have so many useful zones that some excellent hunting areas like the Ruined City of Draniks sit empty.  Most of the problems I find and report are little more than nitpicks.  Overall I still give Omens a big thumbs-up.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
4 October 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>

</feed>