<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>These changes sound great, the only thing that I wonder is if I do decide to come back to my level 6</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>These changes sound great, the only thing that I wonder is if I do decide to come back to my level 61 Ranger with next to no AA&apos;s and no loot that&apos;s significant will I be able to find groups and guild and raids and progress? I&apos;m not saying get to level 80 fighting Meldrath or whoever in a week I mean hitting up some PoP or Gates content or getting EQ/AM3 and stuff like that... I&apos;m strongly considering giving this another shot </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>SOE removed many flagging requirements as of today&apos;s patch.</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>SOE removed many flagging requirements as of today&apos;s patch.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;it already feels like a console game.&quot;--The unintended humor of that line had me laughing</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;it already feels like a console game.&quot;--The unintended humor of that line had me laughing till I hurt.

Great article Loral, and a couple of your points hit on exactly why I dislike WoW(minus the playerbase, I met nothing but annoying people in WoW, with one exception).</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&gt;&gt;Weakness 1, A Focus on Solo Gameplay

Well I disagree with you on this point - I think that </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&gt;&gt;Weakness 1, A Focus on Solo Gameplay

Well I disagree with you on this point - I think that is the biggest strength of the game.  This is what allows new people to enter the game and still find the endgame accessable even if no one is around.

Have you tried to solo a Warrior to max level in Everquest - as a newbie - lately?  I think if you look at the endgame - while a lot of it is available for solo play - you will find that it does ind</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>This list seems contradictory to me, as if you&apos;ve got two ideal versions of WoW in mind. One is</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>This list seems contradictory to me, as if you&apos;ve got two ideal versions of WoW in mind. One is the game you&apos;d want to play, the other is the one some supposed audience of super-casual gamers would want to play. That&apos;s fine, but it&apos;s hardly fair to criticize WoW for not being both. I also have to disagree with most of your specific complaints.

Weakness 1, A Focus on Solo Gameplay: You do have a level 70 character, don&apos;t </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I realize a lot of my criticisms are contradictory to the strengths of the game. Being able to solo </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I realize a lot of my criticisms are contradictory to the strengths of the game. Being able to solo your way to the top is one of the great strengths of the game, but it also goes against the one thing that separates WoW from games like Grand Theft Auto or Elder Scrolls - lots of people.

Bartle shows that there are a few trends in games like WoW that make it very popular but make it equally difficult to build rich social relationships in commerc</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral...

Personally if you were to ask me what the failure is I would point to the raiding game...
</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Loral...

Personally if you were to ask me what the failure is I would point to the raiding game...

Currently you have a game you can solo to 70 in with relative ease.

You can start the 5 man dungeons without any specific gear requirement...

This is where the brick wall hits in game play (for non PvP action).

10 mana Kara runs can be done with 2 tanks and 2 healers - but the encounter learning curve picks up quite a bit here - nothing outrage</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;Being able to solo your way to the top is one of the great strengths of the game...&quot;

Dep</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;Being able to solo your way to the top is one of the great strengths of the game...&quot;

Depends on what you mean by &quot;the top.&quot; I definitely wouldn&apos;t call level 70 with no purple gear the top, and I just don&apos;t see the solo rep grinds after that as real progression paths (like I said, they&apos;re more &quot;something to do when you can&apos;t group&quot;). I do think being able to solo to max level such that you can ge</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I had soloed my way to a bunch of purple gear through daily quests. By &quot;the top&quot; I meant t</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I had soloed my way to a bunch of purple gear through daily quests. By &quot;the top&quot; I meant the top level.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Wow, if these are the weaknesses, no wonder its the number one game. I didn&apos;t want to level any</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Wow, if these are the weaknesses, no wonder its the number one game. I didn&apos;t want to level any other char than my first, but truth is I now have 2 lvl 70s and a lvl 60. After some time, you can get into the mood to lvl another char up.

I loved EQ. Best gaming experience of my life. Too bad I can&apos;t solo it like WoW or I would have lvld another char in EQ. Now my wizard is stuck at lvl 62. I did install EQ once again a few months back, </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral: I presume that means you&apos;re exalted with most or all of the factions can be soloed. If s</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Loral: I presume that means you&apos;re exalted with most or all of the factions can be soloed. If so congrats--that&apos;s a lot of dailies and/or turn-ins. I can certainly see why you&apos;d feel like WoW is focused on soloing.

I don&apos;t want to minimize what you&apos;ve accomplished at all, but I&apos;m pretty sure if you had been doing Karazhan every week over the same period you&apos;d have more and better purple items at this point. So </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I&apos;ve done Karazhan about three times now. Mostly I find it hard to get into a good enough group</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I&apos;ve done Karazhan about three times now. Mostly I find it hard to get into a good enough group to clear it. I&apos;m in a pretty big guild that has about three or four regular groups but all of them are filled up. Pickup groups are usually nasty in attitude and quick to break up.

So instead, when I want to play for under two hours, I work on dailies. I just got my epic flying mount and am working on the absolutely awful Netherdrake quests.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I have to agree with the general sentiment that this review seems inconherent, while at the same tim</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I have to agree with the general sentiment that this review seems inconherent, while at the same time contradicting your statements in previous articles.  

1. Focus on Solo Play

Richard Bartle is essentially only correct in one aspect: World of Warcraft has established a paradigm that no one will defy, and as failed games like Vanguard show, consumers exclusively prefer.  However, the notion that &quot;rich relationships&quot; were somehow an i</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I think I have to agree with Kaelon&apos;s diagnosis that your guild just isn&apos;t working for you</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I think I have to agree with Kaelon&apos;s diagnosis that your guild just isn&apos;t working for you, but let me suggest an alternative treatment: leave your 70 hunter in the guild, but level up a new character from a more group-friendly class. If what you want to do is play with other people, you&apos;ll have a much easier time doing so as a tank or healer. Then be sure to fight the temptation to follow the path of least resistance and spend you</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Come join my guild on Icecrown, you would be more than welcome!</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Come join my guild on Icecrown, you would be more than welcome!</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>