<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Gnomes Are Friends, Not Food</title>
    <description>All things EQ2 and even some that aren't</description>
    <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;BlogID=3</link>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>glen@headcasemods.com</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2005 11:41:14 GMT</pubDate>
    <docs>http://backend.userland.com/rss</docs>
    <generator>RSS.NET: http://www.rssdotnet.com/</generator>
    <item>
      <title>Posted by Raf on the Forums</title>
      <description>&lt;P&gt;Take a look at the patch notes below!&amp;nbsp; Seems that we'll have the ability to add procs and effects to your rare armor and weapons. While this is great news, we don't know if your going to be able to TRADE attuned items!!! So you may want to hold off on attuning rare armor and weapons untill this is sorted out. Otherwise&amp;nbsp;we might not be able to add effects since attuning makes it no trade and you may have to buy a new rares.&lt;/P&gt;
&lt;P&gt;&lt;STRONG&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ffcc00&gt;*** New Harvested Items and Recipes ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/STRONG&gt;&lt;/P&gt;
&lt;DIV&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/DIV&gt;
&lt;DIV&gt;- There are new types of uncommon harvested items to be found. They can be gathered from existing harvesting nodes and are identified as glowing, sparkling, glimmering, or luminous depending on their level range.&lt;BR&gt;- New recipe books are available for purchase at the camps of the Hand of Marr and Brethren of Night. Those wishing to buy the books will need to first earn favor with the merchants.&lt;BR&gt;- Using these new recipes and new harvested items, Alchemists can create magical extracts that other crafters can use to make new items or enhance existing goods.&lt;BR&gt;- Armorers and Tailors can combine the magical extract with certain pieces of pristine armor and make new types of enchanted armor. When the wearer is attacked, chest pieces have a chance to proc a heal-over-time spell and leggings have the chance to proc a damage spell.&lt;BR&gt;- Weaponsmiths and Woodworkers can combine the magical extract with certain types of pristine weapons and make new types of enchanted weapons. These weapons have the chance to proc a damage spell in combat.&lt;BR&gt;- Woodworkers can combine the magical extract with certain types of pristine shields and make new types of enchanted shields that have a chance to proc a damage spell during combat. They can also use the magical extract to infuse wands with an activated damage spell.&lt;BR&gt;- Tailors can use the magical extract to create hex dolls that cast a detrimental effect on an enemy. The dolls also provide a minor stat buff to the user.&lt;BR&gt;- Jewelers can combine the magical extract with certain types of pristine rings and make new types of enchanted rings that provide activated buffs to strength, agility, wisdom, intelligence, or stamina.&lt;BR&gt;- For weapons, armor, and shields, the quality level of the creation process determines the potency of the magical effect attached to the item. All quality levels of enchanted weapons, armor, and shields retain the stats of the pristine item used to make them.&lt;/DIV&gt;</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=22</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=22&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=22</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2005 11:40:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GINORMOUS PATCH DAY!!!!!</title>
      <description>&lt;SPAN class=headline&gt;Update Notes: March 8, 2005&lt;I&gt; 3/08/2005 6:00 AM&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt; &lt;BR&gt;
&lt;P&gt;*** Headlines ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Act as a Mentor for your lower-level friends with our new Mentoring system!&lt;BR&gt;- New treasure is available for solo players and small groups!&lt;BR&gt;- Grouping made even better with a reduction in shared XP debt!&lt;BR&gt;- Solo and small group XP increased even more, especially for players over level 30!&lt;BR&gt;- Artisans can let buyers know they're available with the new /LFW (looking for work) tag!&lt;BR&gt;- Quest coin and experience rewards have been increased!&lt;BR&gt;- Friends and guilds can now share housing more effectively.&lt;BR&gt;- Experience a new level 50 epic battle in The Deserted Mine!&lt;BR&gt;- Enjoy a new solo instance in the Commonlands: Valley of the Rogue Magi!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Mentoring ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Act as a Mentor for your lower level friends with the new Mentoring system!&lt;BR&gt;- When you right click a lower-level group member, you will see an option to Mentor them.&lt;BR&gt;- Selecting "Mentor" will set your level to that of your lower-level friend, and you will operate at the same effective level as your group mate.&lt;BR&gt;- The Mentor and Apprentice will receive experience, loot, and quest credit as if the Mentor were the same level as the Apprentice. Mentors, be sure to revisit any of those quests or locations that you may have missed along the way!&lt;BR&gt;- The Apprentice will receive an experience bonus while under the guidance of a Mentor. Up to five other players can act as a Mentor for a single player at the same time (each increasing the experience bonus).&lt;BR&gt;- Mentors receive experience and advance toward their actual level while mentoring; the rate at which they receive XP depends on the level of their Apprentice. Mentoring someone below level 20 will earn very little XP for the Mentor, while taking an Apprentice that is level 25 or higher will earn a greater percentage of experience for the Mentor.&lt;BR&gt;- The effectiveness of your gear will scale down in level. You don't need to go out and get different gear to Mentor friends of different levels.&lt;BR&gt;- While you are Mentoring, you can use any of your abilities that you would normally have available at that level.&amp;nbsp; &lt;BR&gt;- The Mentor's skill values equal those of a character with 80% XP toward their next level.&lt;BR&gt;- You can select "Stop Mentoring" if you wish to cease acting as a Mentor to your ally.&lt;BR&gt;- If the Mentor or Apprentice leaves the group or exits the game, the Mentor will return to his or her original level. &lt;BR&gt;- When one player starts Mentoring another, all maintained spells will be dropped from the Mentor. &lt;BR&gt;- A player who is being Mentored is not allowed to Mentor someone else.&lt;BR&gt;- You cannot turn off Mentoring while you are dead. If the group (or the Apprentice) disbands while you are dead, you stop Mentoring but remain dead until you release from your corpse or are revived.&lt;BR&gt;- Mentors will only gain combat XP when they are within reward range (50 meters) of their Apprentice.&lt;BR&gt;- Mentors will only gain XP if their Apprentice also gains experience.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Solo and Small Group Loot Improvements ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- All solo and small group encounters in the following zones now have the chance to drop improved treasure: Antonica, the Commonlands, Nektulos Forest, Thundering Steppes, the Orcish Wastes, the Enchanted Lands, Rivervale, the Feerrott, Everfrost, and Lavastorm.&lt;BR&gt;- It will be easier to collect sets of armor and accessories from certain types of creatures. A solo creature that drops a given armor type is likely to drop additional armor pieces of the same type. A creature that drops accessories is likely to drop more accessories.&lt;BR&gt;- More loot! You will now see more items of various levels drop than ever before.&lt;BR&gt;- There is now greater variety in the volume and type of loot that normal solo creatures and advanced solo/small group encounters will drop.&lt;BR&gt;- Encounter drops are now separated by the high and low levels for each zone. For example, level 12 solo encounters in Antonica will drop level 10-14 appropriate gear, spells, and recipes. A level 16 solo encounter in Antonica will drop level 15-19 items.&lt;BR&gt;- Progressive solo population has been added to the Enchanted Lands, the Orcish Wastes, and Thundering Steppes.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Increased Solo and Small Group XP ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Solo and small group experience has been increased again to further enhance the solo/small group game. Players over level 30 will especially notice an increase in solo and small group XP rewards.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** New Zones ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- New Level 50 Raid Zone: The Deserted Mine can be entered from the Orcish Wastes. Protect the Coercer you find within, or who knows what might happen!&lt;BR&gt;- New Solo Instance: Valley of the Rogue Magi can be found in the Commonlands near Matthias Siegemaker. Encounter elementals, gargoyles, skeletons, zombies, and more foul creatures within.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Looking for Work (/lfw) ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Artisans can now let other players know they are willing to take crafting requests with the /lfw command.&lt;BR&gt;- Using /lfw works much like the /lfg (looking for group) tag. Players can perform a "/who lfw" command and find artisans willing to take crafting requests.&lt;BR&gt;- Players can also search for a specific profession, such as "/who carpenter" for a list of Carpenters who are online or "/who lfw alchemist" to get a listing of Alchemists currently flagged as looking for work.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** The Bloodline Chronicles ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- The Hand of Marr and Brethren of Night have moved their camps deeper into Nektulos Forest as they continue their research into the strange affliction plaguing the people of Freeport and Qeynos.&lt;BR&gt;- The grinnin that remain in the forest have moved further downstream.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Gameplay ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- We have reduced the percentage of XP debt shared by group members.&lt;BR&gt;- Improving your Swimming skill now increases the speed at which you swim.&lt;BR&gt;- Encounter behavior has been changed such that if an encounter breaks and would have reset (and respawned the same encounter), it will now check if it was overpowered or overmatched and, if not, it will instead unbreak and become a viable target for a short period of time.&amp;nbsp; If the encounter is defeated successfully during that time, players will receive all of the original encounter XP bonus and some portion of the loot.&lt;BR&gt;- The time required to camp out has been reduced from 30 seconds to 20 seconds.&lt;BR&gt;- If a player was kicked from a guild while offline, their spendable guild status points will no longer be lost once they rejoin a new guild.&lt;BR&gt;- Encounters should no longer break if your pet lands the final blow on a wild dog in The Sprawl.&lt;BR&gt;- All group members in the same zone when a guild is created should automatically receive an invitation to join it.&lt;BR&gt;- A pop-up message will now let players know that they must use their boat tickets before camping or leaving the zone.&lt;BR&gt;- Flying mounts should no longer have a random orientation when they first start flying.&lt;BR&gt;- Fixed an issue that was sometimes preventing an encounter from ever resetting after being broken.&lt;BR&gt;- Characters who have more than 100% XP in their current level but have not gained a level due to a hallmark restriction (such as their class quest) will no longer be prevented from entering zones tied to those quests.&lt;BR&gt;- Experience earned through questing is no longer affected by Mentoring, Vitality, or any other XP modifier (except for paying back XP debt).&lt;BR&gt;- If an aggressive opponent would con red to the lowest-level member of the group but instead cons gray to the group because of its average level, the NPC will remain aggro and attack all the members of that group. A normally aggressive creature that will not aggro should no longer have a red border around its name. In short: grey mobs that have a red border will attack your group; grey mobs without a red border will not.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Housing ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Items marked No Trade can be placed in a house by trustees or the owner.&lt;BR&gt;- All No Trade items placed in a house remember who placed them and can only be picked up by that character. &lt;BR&gt;- The house owner and any Trustees can move any No Trade items placed in the house.&lt;BR&gt;- The house owner can destroy No Trade items not owned by them.&lt;BR&gt;- No Trade items already placed in houses before the update are treated as follows:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - If items with identical names are found in the house, the first four items of the same type are set to No Owner.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - No Owner house items cannot be picked up until they are claimed. The "pickup" menu item is replaced with a "claim ownership" menu item for these items.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - After the first four identical items are set to No Owner, all subsequent items of the same type are automatically owned by the house owner.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - If the Owner of the house wishes to claim all No Owner items, that character can use the command /house_own_all to do so.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - If the Owner of the house uses the "Collect Contents" button, they will NOT pick up No Owner items, they must explicitly claim those items using the right click menu or /house_own_all.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Example: A house contains three "Know your Gnolls" books and twelve Simple Forges.&amp;nbsp; All three "Know your Gnolls" books become No Owner and can be claimed by any trustee or the house owner. Four of the Simple Forges become No Owner and can be claimed by any trustee or the house owner. Eight of the Simple Forges are automatically owned by the house owner and can only be picked up by that character.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Zones and Population ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Skeletons on the Isle of Refuge should now be solo encounters, except for those in the graveyard itself.&lt;BR&gt;- Two relics have been found in Lavastorm that allow easier access to the entrance of Solusek's Eye. To use the relics, you must first discover them.&lt;BR&gt;- You will now appear directly outside the door when exiting Solusek's Eye, and a safe area has been added to allows groups to gather.&lt;BR&gt;- Sartar, Raster, and Cythan have gained a new ability that might take you aback.&lt;BR&gt;- The merchants on or near the docks of Qeynos Harbor now sell fish meat rather than edible food.&lt;BR&gt;- Fire Toad will be seen less frequently on the beach in Lavastorm.&lt;BR&gt;- Harbinger will not be encountered as often in the Obelisk of Vul.&lt;BR&gt;- The number of fishing spots in many outdoor zones has been reduced, making way for other harvestable resources.&lt;BR&gt;- The success and failure boat timers for the following zones have been set to 25 minutes: the Orcish Wastes, the Enchanted Lands, Everfrost, the Fanged Sea, and Lavastorm.&lt;BR&gt;- The Windstalker Rumbler should no longer break the encounter when attacked.&lt;BR&gt;- The restrictions placed on zoning into Blood Skull Valley have been lessened; players can now enter with 1-24 people instead of 12.&lt;BR&gt;- Modifications have been made to The Malevolent Knight in the Freeport Graveyard.&lt;BR&gt;- Some modifications have been made to the Drayek event in Icebound.&lt;BR&gt;- More elder hawks have been spotted near their nesting grounds in Thundering Steppes.&lt;BR&gt;- Lower-level deer should no longer roam in the higher-level areas of Thundering Steppes.&lt;BR&gt;- All solo encounters within A Pirate's Hidden Stash, The Rumbler Caves, and An Open Grave should now be of the correct difficulty.&lt;BR&gt;- Rognon the Angler should no longer spawn twice in the same instance.&lt;BR&gt;- Zoning out of the Crypt of Vox will now allow you to arrive in a safer location.&lt;BR&gt;- Evacuating the dungeon instances in the Thundering Steppes and the Enchanted Lands should now take you to the dock area of those zones.&lt;BR&gt;- Wildlife in front of the gnoll towers in the Thundering Steppes will no longer break the encounter when attacked.&lt;BR&gt;- Advanced solo creatures in the Thundering Steppes will now be aggressive toward travelers.&lt;BR&gt;- Gurk Strongarm will be found within the mill in the Orcish Wastes more often.&lt;BR&gt;- A typo in the name of some lizardman encounters in the Feerrott has been fixed.&lt;BR&gt;- The mariner's bell in Nektulos Forest that allows players access to the Enchanted Lands should now have the correct name.&lt;BR&gt;- The reentry timer into the Cove of Decay has been fixed. Players should now be able to reenter the zone after two hours.&lt;BR&gt;- Reentry timers have been added to Miragul's Menagerie, Icespire Summit, and Drayek's Chamber.&lt;BR&gt;- The reentry timer into the Trembling Lagoon has been fixed. Players should now be able to reenter the zone after four hours.&lt;BR&gt;- The reentry timer has been fixed for Zarvonn's Tower.&lt;BR&gt;- Players attempting to access Heroic or Solo zones from Thundering Steppes, the Orcish Wastes, or the Enchanted Lands should now be able to make the choice much easier.&lt;BR&gt;- The mouse-over text into instanced zones in Thundering Steppes, the Orcish Wastes, and the Enchanted Lands has been modified.&lt;BR&gt;- Some inconsistently leveled NPCs in the Rumbler Caves have been set to an appropriate level.&lt;BR&gt;- The reentry timer on the Vault of Flames has been modified.&lt;BR&gt;- Ruins of Varsoon: Chamber of Immortality now has a reentry timer.&lt;BR&gt;- The "overgrown bed of greenslade" should now be spelled correctly in the Feerrott.&lt;BR&gt;- Douve Thule Sattar and Dread Satter in the Feerrott will now appear with less frequency.&lt;BR&gt;- Guardian mist grinnins may now be found within Nektulos Forest.&lt;BR&gt;- Group encounters in Lavastorm and Solusek's Eye will now drop treasure more frequently.&lt;BR&gt;- Patrolling mobs should now be less likely to attack players in the Heart of Fear event.&lt;BR&gt;- Players will be given a message when trying to enter an optional zone that they haven't downloaded.&lt;BR&gt;- The following zones no longer have reuse timers if you fail the events inside:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Guild level 5 Qeynos raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Guild level 5 Freeport raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: The Condemned Catacomb&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Vale of the Shattering&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Firemyst Gully&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Foul Wind&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Freeport 15 Guild Raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Qeynos 15 Guild Raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Vanudozalon's Lair&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Arch Lich Uludan&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Antonica: Darathar's Lair&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - All Qeynos class quest instances&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Edgewater Drains: Murkwater Nook&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Vermin's Snye: Sepulcher of Jahnda&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Crypt of Betrayal: Deathly Scarab Hive&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: Bloodskull Valley&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: Guild level 20 Qeynos raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: Guild level 20 Freeport raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: The Training Grounds&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: The Valley of Zarvonn&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: Guild level 10 Qeynos raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: Guild level 10 Freeport raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: Guild level 30 Qeynos raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: Echoes of Time&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Commonlands: Gobblerock's Hideout&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Everfrost: Icespire Summit&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Feerrott: The Trembling Lagoon&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Feerrott: Dythra's Lair&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Feerrott: The Gathering of Fear&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Feerrott: Meeting of Minds&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Lavastorm: The Sanctum of Fire&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Lavastorm: Maiden's Gulch&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Lavastorm: Maiden's Gulch, Draconic&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Nektulos Forest: Cauldron Hollow&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Obelisk of Vul: The Vestibule&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Runnyeye: Chamber of Rulgax&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Runnyeye: Overlord's Throne Room&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Solusek's Eye: Bastion of Flames&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Solusek's Eye: Nagafen's Lair&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Solusek's Eye: The Infernal Forge of Ages&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - South Qeynos: Scout subclass instances&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Temple of Cazic-Thule: Screaming Mace subzone&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Temple of Cazic-Thule: Sanctum of Fear&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - The Temple of Cazic-Thule: Niscanith's Lair&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Everfrost: Menagerie&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Everfrost: Tobrin's Eyepatch subzone&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Everfrost: Ar'ticae's Lair&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Fallen Gate: Vault of the Fallen&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Fallen Gate: Trendaloz's Lair&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Thieves' Way: Den of the Darkblade Assassins&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Serpent Sewers: The Serpent's Lair&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Orcish Wastes: Deathfist Citadel&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Orcish Wastes: Deathfist Citadel, Draconic&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Permafrost: King Drayek's Chamber&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Permafrost: King Drayek's Chamber, Draconic&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Permafrost: Crypt of Vox&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Stormhold: Tomb of Valor&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Thundering Steppes: Cove of Decay&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Thundering Steppes: Treaty for Treasure&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Thundering Steppes: Freeport 25 guild raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Thundering Steppes: Qeynos 25 guild raid&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Thundering Steppes: Mjolni's Lair&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Thundering Steppes: Rognog the Angler&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Ruins of Varsoon: Chamber of Immortality&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Quests ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Quest coin and experience rewards have been increased from this day onward. The experience increase will be especially noticeable in non-repeatable quests that are of a lower level than your character. You may want to complete any quests that you may have missed during your journeys in Norrath.&lt;BR&gt;- Books providing details on the Norrathian calendar can now be found in each city's library.&lt;BR&gt;- All items that initiate a quest have been changed to No Trade.&lt;BR&gt;- Fixed an issue that would sometimes prevent players from starting the Feerrott access quest.&lt;BR&gt;- Logan Belchbottom's "Lost Friend in Fallen Gate" can now be completed by those who outleveled the quest after receiving it.&lt;BR&gt;- An item used in "Far Seas Supplier - Elven Attack" can now be obtained in order to complete the quest.&lt;BR&gt;- The "Nektulos Creature Cataloging" quest will now require players to seek out "a dusk dart" instead of "a voracious bleeder".&lt;BR&gt;- The quest "A Foul Wind" can now be found under the "Access" category.&lt;BR&gt;- The quest "The Idol of Fear" can now be found under the "Access" category.&lt;BR&gt;- "The Treaty For Treasure" quest can now be found under the "Access" category.&lt;BR&gt;- Players should now be able to complete "Fresh Samples", even if they've already outleveled the quest.&lt;BR&gt;- Tome quests in the Obelisk of Vul and Serpent's Sewer should now have a quest category added to them.&lt;BR&gt;- A new version of "Children's Rhymes" has been added. Please note, the original version in a player's quest journal will remain unaltered.&lt;BR&gt;- Permafrost tome quests will now be listed in the appropriate section of the quest journal.&lt;BR&gt;- Taskmaster Deldrin's dialogue has been clarified.&lt;BR&gt;- The "Karnath the Forgotten" quest in Thundering Steppes should now be easier to complete.&lt;BR&gt;- Added the correct quest category to item and tome quests in Serpent's Sewer if they previously lacked them.&lt;BR&gt;- Added the correct quest category to item and tome quests in the Obelisk of Vul.&lt;BR&gt;- The target for the "Wanted Gnoll Bandit!" quest has been changed to a darkpaw raider.&lt;BR&gt;- "The Fate of Fleshripper" should now update properly.&lt;BR&gt;- The "Gut Ripper" quest will now need to be completed in order.&lt;BR&gt;- The "Double-Plated Breastplate" quest will now need to be completed in order.&lt;BR&gt;- The "Black Horn Ring" quest will now require players to harvest a Crimson Clay Pebble instead of mud stones.&lt;BR&gt;- Players should now be able to complete the "A Mission for Midia" quest.&lt;BR&gt;- Dialog issues with the "Of Spars and Sails and..." quest have been corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- Rubbish the Scarecrow should once again be talking in the Secrets of Runnyeye quest.&lt;BR&gt;- Rama&amp;#8217;nai, Captain Ogof, and Captain Gaer will appear more frequently to assist those on the Greater Lightstone Quest.&lt;BR&gt;- Lady Vox should no longer despawn in her crypt during the Draconic quests.&lt;BR&gt;- The Herald of Nektropos can now be spoken to every 30 seconds instead of every 10 minutes.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** City Sabotage ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Some Sabotage quest objects in South Qeynos, West Freeport, South Freeport, North Freeport, and East Freeport have been relocated.&lt;BR&gt;- An inaccurate quest detail with "Towers of Stone" has been corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- "A wandering cow" has been renamed "an infected cow".&lt;BR&gt;- Players should now be able to interact with buckets in Qeynos.&lt;BR&gt;- Quests will now be completed properly when returning to Gol M'Tun.&lt;BR&gt;- Several sabotage quest items have been renamed in order to stay consistent with the requirements of the quest.&lt;BR&gt;- "Sabotage: The Furious Cows" quest is now listed in the Sabotage category.&lt;BR&gt;- "Sabotage: Halt the Expansion" quest should now be working correctly.&lt;BR&gt;- "Sabotage: Sealed Lips" quest should now be working correctly.&lt;BR&gt;- Interactive objects involved in the Sabotage quest series can now only be interacted with once.&lt;BR&gt;- NPCs that are a part of the Sabotage Quest system should no longer offer quests to players without showing the offer window.&lt;BR&gt;- The appearance of sabotage-related tents in Antonica has been changed to that of an open tent.&lt;BR&gt;- Bait buckets for the sabotage quests in Antonica will now appear less frequently, allowing other targets to appear more often.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Items ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Prismatic weapons now have improved damage/delay and more effective procs.&lt;BR&gt;- Merchants no longer sell items related to Erollisi Day.&lt;BR&gt;- Heritage items are now No Trade. NPC merchants have a keen desire to get their hands on these rare items.&lt;BR&gt;- The Inscribed Wooden Staff no longer has a typo in its name.&lt;BR&gt;- Delacar's Axe of Savagery now uses the correct two-handed weapon animation.&lt;BR&gt;- Bruise Forger Cestus now references the Fists damage type rather than Slash.&lt;BR&gt;- Some turtle-related items (turtle meat, etc) now have proper icons.&lt;BR&gt;- Some tooltips that mentioned "talbard" have been corrected to "tabard".&lt;BR&gt;- Repair costs on heritage items have been reduced.&lt;BR&gt;- Tutorial quest reward items are now flagged as No Value.&lt;BR&gt;- The repair costs on heritage quest rewards have been adjusted.&lt;BR&gt;- Sigil-Painted Linen Sleeves can now be equipped.&lt;BR&gt;- Thulzite Gems now cost 5 gold. Additionally, lizardmen in the Temple of Cazic-Thule should drop them more frequently.&lt;BR&gt;- The quality of the food and drink that players start with on the Isle of Refuge has improved.&lt;BR&gt;- The Serrated Bone Dirk now has repair costs in line with other heritage quest items.&lt;BR&gt;- Forearms of Forbidden Rites should now have the correct icon.&lt;BR&gt;- The procs and regenerative effects on many rare and raid-quality items should now function correctly. This includes Golden Efreeti Boots, Prismatic weapons, Kiteshield of the King, Royal Greatflail, Vicious Sai, and more.&lt;BR&gt;- The food and drink sold by merchants on the Isle of Refuge should now match those sold in the cities.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;#8211; The proc effect on the Screaming Mace will now grant additional power to go along with the increased power pool.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Spells and Combat Arts ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Assassin changes:&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Slip Away should now function correctly and its description has been clarified.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Assassin's Mark should now function correctly.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Torment is now called Assassin: Torment to prevent confusion with the Inquisitor and Coercer versions of this art.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Bard changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Denon's Deafening Strike will now share a reuse timer with Quick Strike.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Berserker changes:&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Press will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Rupture will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Tides of War will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Bloodlust is now called Berserker: Bloodlust to prevent confusion with the Fury version of the art.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Coup de Grace's description has been modified.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Brigand changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Lurk and Craven Walk will now place a reactive feign death effect on the Brigand. The reactive effect will take place the next time the Brigand is damaged.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Maddening Shot will now reduce the target's power.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Low Blow and Dirty Blow have had their growth levels adjusted.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Plead for Mercy now has an Apprentice IV quality spell effect.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Waylay should now have an appropriate description reflecting that it has a chance to stun the enemy.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Cuss Apprentice IV should now have the appropriate spell effect.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Bum Rush now has the chance to interrupt your opponent.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Bruiser changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Roughhouse Apprentice IV will now decrease deflection appropriately.&lt;BR&gt;- Cleric changes:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Redoubt should now display a grammatically correct message when cast.&lt;BR&gt;- Coercer changes:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Demoralizing Gaze should now function correctly.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Bewilder's prose text should no longer have any grammar errors.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Torment is now called Coercer: Torment to prevent confusion with the Inquisitor and Assassin versions of this spell.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Mind's Eye, Dreadful Thoughts, and Consuming Thoughts have had their power reduction reduced to be more in line with that of Illusionists.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Psychic Wail's effects now match its description.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Conjurer changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Vexation can now be upgraded.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Flameshield will now do Heat damage instead of Divine damage.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Geotic Brand's buff effects will no longer fluctuate after zoning.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Provocation and Vexation now tick at the proper interval.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Fiery Doom will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Flaming Agony will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Spiked Rain will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Aqueous Hunters now has a more water-based visual effect.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Aery Stalker now has a more air-based visual effect.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Rockslide's examine information no longer redundantly indicates that it "Casts Rockslide."&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Tellurian Recruit and Pandrus' Tellurian Hero now share timers.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Defiler changes:&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Degeneration, Atrophy, Contamination, Suppuration, Loathsome Seal, Tierbold's Pestilent Miasma, and Mizzmog's Sallow Degradation now correctly debuff stamina.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Baleful Countenance's description has been changed to reflect that it has a fear proc.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Dirge changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Wail of Woe now deals mental damage.&lt;BR&gt;- Druid changes:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Elemental Amending should now give the appropriate resistances.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Vigor now displays the appropriate text message when cast.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Fury changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Call of the Hunt now provides an out-of-combat run speed increase.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Feral Pulse will now transform the target into a ghost lion instead of a wolf. It should also correctly affect all nearby members of your group.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Toxic Quills should now function as intended.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Feral Tenacity now has an appropriate visual effect.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Seizing Brambles should now function correctly.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Bloodlust is now called Fury: Bloodlust to prevent confusion with the Berserker version of this spell.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Dooming Swarm will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Deadly Swarm will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Guardian changes:&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Ruin and Ferocious Charge will now do slashing damage over time appropriately.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Anchor Apprentice IV now has an attack speed decrease.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Illusionist changes:&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Construct of Order, Construct of Light, and Basten's Construct of Light will no longer remove maintained effects.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Dismay will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Speechless will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Unsar's Endearing Splendor's prose has been modified to reflect its intended functionality.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Devitalizing Stare has had its power regeneration reduced slightly.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Inquisitor changes&lt;/FONT&gt;:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Scolding Alleviation will now affect the entire group.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Dogmatic Healing will now provide a minor attack speed increase.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Oppression and Torment now correctly debuff stamina.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Oppression now appears in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Fanatical Reverence's description now indicates that it increases damage per second rather than attack speed.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Reproach is now called Inquisitor: Reproach to prevent confusion with the Swashbuckler and Templar versions of this spell.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Torment is now called Inquisitor: Torment to prevent confusion with the Assassin and Coercer versions of this spell.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Several spells had grammar issues that were corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Monk changes:&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Everburning Flame had its duration increased to 15 minutes.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Mystic changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Fallacy had a spelling error in its prose that has been corrected.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Delusion, Fallacy, Chimerik, Cry of the Ancients, Howl of the Ancients, and Kelian's Curse of Spirits now correctly debuff stamina.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Necromancer changes:&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Revivication can now be used to resurrect your allies.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Zarvonn's Vitae Gorge was changed so it deals damage over time and heals over time as well. The spell should also show up in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Terror no longer stuns the caster while the fear spell is in effect. This should remove the "Interrupted!" message that was being displayed.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Pestilential Blast and Skinrot will now debuff your opponent correctly.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Boon of the Lifeless and Words of the Wicked now tick at the proper interval.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Grisly Mark, Horrific Mark, and Nevagon's Pestilential Mark now correctly debuff stamina.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Accursed Cloud will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Breath of the Unearthed will now appear in the maintained spells window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Opal's Aggravating Seal now shares a reuse timer with Agitation.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Cloak of the Venril: The lifetap damage shield will now work properly.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Grisly Brace: The spell description has been modified.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Rending Frenzy had a grammar issue that was corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Paladin changes&lt;/FONT&gt;:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Divine Vengeance now grants strength.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Predator changes&lt;/FONT&gt;:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Hann's Quick Stab will now share a reuse timer with Quick Strike.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Elaa's Relentless Ambush will now share a reuse timer with Ambush.&lt;BR&gt;-&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt; Priest changes&lt;/FONT&gt;:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Courage had its prose file updated to reflect the chance to proc Blessed Weapon.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Ranger changes:&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Steady Aim had its duration increased to 15 minutes.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Natural Selection will now deal AoE damage.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Longshank will now stealth the Ranger on a successful hit.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Huntsman's Trap should now snare an attacker if it successfully damages the Ranger.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Survival of the Fittest now correctly debuffs stamina.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Miracle Shot and Miracle Arrow will now grow to the appropriate levels.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Rogue changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Hager's Befuddling Strike will now share a reuse timer with Quick Strike.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Snoop will now display flavor text within the chat window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Smuggler's Talent will now display flavor text within the chat window.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Scout changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Escape no longer displays its rank, as it is not upgradeable.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Quick Strike will now share a reuse timer with Hann's Quick Stab, Denon's Deafening Strike, and Hager's Befuddling Strike.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Ambush will now share a reuse timer with Elaa's Relentless Ambush.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Shadowknight changes&lt;/FONT&gt;:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Tainted Caress and Cursed Caress should again allow for the creation of Tainted Essences.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Grim Harbinger should now function correctly and will provide a message in the chat window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Infernal Pact should now proc correctly.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Tainted Sacrament no longer overwrites maintained spells.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Grim Harbinger should now function correctly and will provide a message in the chat window.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Shaman changes&lt;/FONT&gt;:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Eliania's Salve of the Spiritist had a text error in its chat message. This has been fixed.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Sorel's Withering Limbs now correctly debuffs stamina.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Summoner changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Agitation now ticks at the proper interval.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Buffs applied to a pet will no longer remain after the pet owner leaves the group.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Essence Shift and Bloody Ritual will no longer cause your pet to run toward you.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Swashbuckler changes&lt;/FONT&gt;:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Disheartening Guile should now work correctly. It now has a 6 second duration and decreases your opponent's crush, slash, and pierce mitigation.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Cat's Paw now has a 20 second duration and should work as described.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Flash of Steel now interrupts and reduces the agility of your target at a reduced hate level.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Brazen Thrust should now work correctly. The knockback effect has also been changed to an interrupt.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Dexterous Slashing's description has been modified to reflect the functionality of this combat art.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Swarthy Distraction's reactive hate proc will no longer cost power when it triggers.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Ambuscade's knockback effect has been changed to an interrupt.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Razor Edge now has a stun effect.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Frigid Blast now drains your opponent's power. Its description also indicates that the ability requires a bow rather than any ranged weapon.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Bootleg's description has been changed to reflect that it gives an enhanced movement speed. Its duration has also been changed to 15 minutes.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Dazzling Shroud should now work correctly.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Feigned Bravado's description has been clarified and its duration has been increased to 15 minutes.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Bladeweaver will now correctly lower hate production. Its description now indicates that the art gives Stamina rather than Strength.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Bladeweaver and Dexterous Slashing agility buffs now stack with each other.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Lie in Wait should now function correctly. When stealth is broken, the Swashbuckler's strength should increase and the attacker should be mesmerized.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Reproach is now called Swashbuckler: Reproach to prevent confusion with the Inquisitor and Templar versions of this art&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Watery Shot's description now indicates that the ability requires a bow rather than any ranged weapon.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Hamstring's description now indicates that you must be behind or flanking the target to perform this ability.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Templar changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Reproach is now called Templar: Reproach to prevent confusion with the Swashbuckler and Inquisitor versions of this spell.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Troubador changes&lt;/FONT&gt;:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Lore's Magniloquent Roust now works as described.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Exquisite Shrill now correctly debuffs stamina.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Warden changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Sylvan Embrace will now affect all group members within 10 meters of the caster.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Benison of the Wild is now an upgrade to Blessing of the Wild as intended.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Stacking issues between Blessing of the Wild, Benison of the Wild, Protection of the Seasons, and Blessing of Oak have been corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Warlock changes:&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Bellengere's Sapping Salvo has received the same upgrades as Dark Distortion.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Heneva's Viral Blast now has the same icon as Noxious Bolt.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Devastation had its reuse timer adjusted to 45 seconds.&lt;BR&gt;- &lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;Wizard changes:&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - El'Arad's Custodial Warding can now be canceled via the spell window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Concurrence can now be canceled via the spell window.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Fiery Pulse has a new description and icon to reflect that it is a heat-based spell.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Erudite: Summon Wisp will now be on its own reuse timer and will not prevent you from summoning a normal pet.&lt;BR&gt;- Barbarian: Cold Retribution now appears in the maintained and spell effects windows.&lt;BR&gt;- Half Elf: Tend Wound had a minor grammar error that was fixed.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Heroic Opportunities ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Shower of Daggers should now have the correct proc effect. Its description has also been corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- Soldier's Instict's prose has been corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- The following Heroic Opportunity buffs can now be canceled via the spell effects window:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Crucible of Life&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Inspiring Piety&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Scholar's Insight&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Resonating Cascade&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Divine Nobility&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Tradeskills ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- The price at which crafted items sell back to NPC merchants now includes a value for harvested components. The harvested items themselves, however, still have no value to merchants.&lt;BR&gt;- Lower-level refined and interim products have been removed from tradeskill merchants. Bread, pasta, and a packet of spices will still be sold because these items are used through every level range.&lt;BR&gt;- Fuels used in tradeskill production will now display which tier they intended for in their examine text.&lt;BR&gt;- Examining a recipe should now show exactly what type of fuel is required for that recipe.&lt;BR&gt;- Recipes for shurikens have been added to Artisan Essentials Volume 8, Outfitter Essentials Volume 18, Weaponsmith Essentials Volume 21, Weaponsmith Essentials Volume 31, and Weaponsmith Essentials Volume 41.&lt;BR&gt;- Increased the number of charges on poisons and potions that were previously missed.&lt;BR&gt;- The events that occur during production of ebon plates have been changed to heavy armoring instead of weaponry.&lt;BR&gt;- The examine text on poisons will now display the maximum number of times that the poison can trigger before it fades from your weapons.&lt;BR&gt;- Doubled the effectiveness of Reduce Heat.&lt;BR&gt;- Modified high grade honey to allow for pristine item production.&lt;BR&gt;- Changed the descriptions of Stain, Laminate, Enamel and Glaze to indicate that durability is reduced rather than power.&lt;BR&gt;- Wash recipes have been added to Apothecary recipe books.&lt;BR&gt;- Thread recipes have been removed from Apothecary recipe books.&lt;BR&gt;- Several totem recipe descriptions have been corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- Apothecary, Weaving, Timbercraft, and Geomancy reaction arts are now granted at the appropriate levels.&lt;BR&gt;- The Vigor of Trust spell recipe has been added to the appropriate Scholar volumes.&lt;BR&gt;- Several Provisioner recipes have had their levels adjusted to match the level of the&amp;nbsp; book they came from.&lt;BR&gt;- Certain crafted containers that did not previously show up on merchant sell lists will now do so.&lt;BR&gt;- Feyiron Plate and Feyiron Ring recipes were contained in both Armorer Essentials Volume 29 and Volume 30. The duplicate recipes have been removed from Volume 30.&lt;BR&gt;- Pristine and Crude Alder Bookcases now have the correct appearance.&lt;BR&gt;- Tin Hunting Arrows will now produce in a higher quantity per combine than before.&lt;BR&gt;- Merchants should now sell the following fuels: Walnut Kindling, Mulberry Kindling, Cherry Kindling, Hickory Kindling, Mesquite Kindling.&lt;BR&gt;- Refine recipes contained within Apothecary recipe books now use the Thaumaturgy Technique and Apothecary Knowledge.&lt;BR&gt;- The level and difficulty of the Blackened Iron Arrow Head recipe has been corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- Worked shallots should no longer be edible.&lt;BR&gt;- The durability of the worked quality Strengthened Leather Strap has been increased to the appropriate level.&lt;BR&gt;- Blinding Strike Apprentice IV is now named Eye Rake Apprentice IV since it scribes that spell.&lt;BR&gt;- The extra copies of the Iron Bar recipe have been removed from Geomancy Essentials Volume 10.&lt;BR&gt;- The extra copies of the Iron Plate recipe have been removed from Geomancy Essentials Volume 10.&lt;BR&gt;- The extra copy of the Burlap Thread recipe has been removed from Weaving Essentials Volume 10.&lt;BR&gt;- The extra copy of the Burlap Yarn recipe has been removed from Weaving Essentials Volume 10.&lt;BR&gt;- Added recipes for the creation of Arcane Concerto and Noxious Concerto.&lt;BR&gt;- Many recipe names were fixed to better match the name of the product being created.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Commands, Controls, and User Interface ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- The Community window will now allow you to sort your friends by whether they are online or offline. There is now a checkbox that allows you to toggle only showing friends who are currently online.&lt;BR&gt;- There is now a message in the chat window letting you know when an NPC spell has been interrupted.&lt;BR&gt;- Chat window tabs will now number themselves more logically. A tab can never be given a blank title.&lt;BR&gt;- Combat start and stop messages will now go to the proper chat filter.&lt;BR&gt;- Chat updates for skill increases should now match the on-screen message.&lt;BR&gt;- Examining an item involved in a quest should now correctly close the dialog box after being put away.&lt;BR&gt;- Attempting to swap an empty bag with a full bag should no longer appear to destroy the empty bag.&lt;BR&gt;- The location for the graveyard icon on the Commonlands map was updated to be more accurate&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Art ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Made further improvements to riders that were floating above horses.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** Audio ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Tradeskill device cues should now be easier to hear.&lt;BR&gt;- You can again change the speaker type from within the game.&lt;BR&gt;- Fixed certain sound anomalies that would sometimes occur as you enter a new zone.&lt;BR&gt;- Added "/playsound " which plays 2d sounds locally.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - This is to support user sound modifications. It lets users trigger any sounds locally for testing/script feedback.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - Users can modify sounds by placing properly named .wav files into /ui/sounds or /ui//sounds&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp; - The UIBuilder documentation has an initial list of these .wav files.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** UIBuilder ***&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;BR&gt;- There is a new version of the UIBuilder.zip file. The updated UIBuilder includes support for several new features. Please read the documentation file for further details.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;*** UI Files Modified ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_community.xml&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- The EverQuest II Team&lt;/P&gt;</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=21</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=21&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=21</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2005 15:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sorry for the recent downtime</title>
      <description>IT WAS THE ANTI SERVER GOBLINS!&amp;nbsp; Yes, the Anti web server goblins recently launched an attack on the Gnome Resistance HQ.&amp;nbsp; It was a horrific battle but&amp;nbsp;WE WERE VICTORIOUS!!!!!! &amp;lt;editors note:&amp;nbsp; Boss is off his medication, Please Excuse him&amp;gt;</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=20</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=20&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=20</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2005 17:06:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bug Fixes: Feb 18th</title>
      <description>&lt;SPAN class=headline&gt;Update Notes: February 18, 2005&lt;I&gt; 2/18/2005 6:00 AM&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt; &lt;BR&gt;
&lt;P&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training ***&lt;/FONT&gt; &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- We are now allowing characters ONE CHANCE to reselect their Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training options. &lt;BR&gt;- If you have previously chosen Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training, you can reset your selections and make new choices by typing the "/respec" command. This will remove all previous choices from your Knowledge Book and will place a blinking "+" sign in the lower right corner of your screen. &lt;BR&gt;- Clicking the "+" sign will open the selection window and allow you to pick new Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training. &lt;BR&gt;- You may receive your selections in a different order this time. Class-dependent choices (like Tactics) will be presented after the others. Characters who gain these abilities as they level up normally will get them in the normal order. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;** IMPORTANT! ** &lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- While you can issue the "/respec" command at any time, once you will not be able to receive quest rewards until you make all pending choices available to you. &lt;BR&gt;- You do not need to use the /respec command immediately. It can be used at a later date. &lt;BR&gt;- Please be aware that you can only use the /respec command ONCE. Make your choices carefully. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Gameplay *** &lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- The Power pools for Bards and Crusaders should once again be affected by Agility and Strength, respectively. &lt;BR&gt;- Using the /respec command will now remove the visible effects of any Traits, Traditions, Training, and Tactics choices you had previously made. &lt;BR&gt;- You will now receive an on-screen message if you have equipped an item that needs to be attuned. &lt;BR&gt;- The rarity of harvestable items will now vary based on level range. Rare components in level 30 and under zones should be slightly more common. &lt;BR&gt;- Trapping now provides meat 25% of the time and pelts 75% of the time. Previously those percentages were reversed. &lt;BR&gt;- King Drayek now has abilities and treasure on par with other epic encounters of his royal stature. &lt;BR&gt;- The Sullon Mines and the Tallon Hording Halls are once again available. &lt;BR&gt;- There should now only be one sabotage target available in a zone at any given time. Would-be saboteurs need to keep their eyes open. &lt;BR&gt;- Insight and Scintillating Aura once again apply their affects every 6 seconds instead of every 30. &lt;BR&gt;- Swapping an empty bag with a full one in your inventory should no longer seem to destroy the empty bag. &lt;BR&gt;- The keyboard layout will now default to whichever language you have set in your operating system. &lt;BR&gt;- Equipment that is flagged as No Trade should no longer need to be attuned. &lt;/P&gt;
&lt;P&gt;- The EverQuest II Team&lt;/P&gt;</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=18</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=18&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=18</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2005 12:44:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gnomes might not be food, but pizza sure is!</title>
      <description>&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;A href="http://everquest2.station.sony.com/pizza/"&gt;http://everquest2.station.sony.com/pizza/&lt;/A&gt;&amp;nbsp;
&lt;HR id=null&gt;
&lt;/DIV&gt;
&lt;DIV&gt;Let's hear it for contributing to the obesity epidemic!!!! WOOT All ya gotta do is type /pizza in game and you can be further removed from a normal life!!!! Why unplug when you can have hot tasty food delivered right to your door and you dont event have to log out!!!&lt;/DIV&gt;
&lt;DIV&gt;
&lt;HR id=null&gt;
&lt;/DIV&gt;
&lt;DIV&gt;Seriously, this is kinda cool and kinda scarey at the same time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/DIV&gt;</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=17</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=17&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=17</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2005 16:13:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stratics House of Commons chat</title>
      <description>&lt;DIV&gt;Stratics is having another one of their patented House O' Commons chats tonight with the Devs of EQ2 where they will be discussing things such as why Gnomes really are the master race and how to get ratonga blood out of your clothes.&amp;nbsp;Oh and they may discuss like, game issues and stuff. &lt;/DIV&gt;
&lt;DIV&gt;
&lt;HR id=null&gt;
&lt;/DIV&gt;
&lt;DIV&gt;Stratics is pleased to announce a House of Commons with the developers of EverQuest2, today, Thursday, February 17th. It will be at 5pm PDT / 8pm EDT in the #StraticsHoC channel on Stratics IRC.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;A href="http://eq2.stratics.com/" target=_blank&gt;&lt;B&gt;EQ2 Stratics&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/A&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;BR&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=16</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=16&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=16</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2005 12:06:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Super secret patch day!</title>
      <description>&lt;SPAN class=headline&gt;Update Notes: February 17, 2005&lt;I&gt; 2/17/2005 6:00 AM&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt; &lt;BR&gt;
&lt;P&gt;&lt;FONT size=5&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Headlines ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- See your enemies in a whole new way with our new /con system!&lt;BR&gt;- Short-duration group buffs now last 10 minutes! Single-target buffs last 15 minutes!&lt;BR&gt;- No more fizzles on spells that are blue or lower to you, and less fizzles on other spells!&lt;BR&gt;- Shorter timers and less restrictions on instanced zones!&lt;BR&gt;- Give your beloved house pets a name!&lt;BR&gt;- All tradeskill classes can now refine their own materials and components!&lt;BR&gt;- Wizards and Warlocks go nuke happy!&lt;BR&gt;- Tanks now tank better with increased mitigation!&lt;BR&gt;- Strike back at your rival city through new sabotage quests!&lt;BR&gt;- More encounters added for soloers and small groups, including solo instanced dungeons!&lt;BR&gt;- You can now store empty bags inside other bags!&lt;BR&gt;- Improved examine information for spells, arts, potions, and more!&lt;BR&gt;- Four new level 50 epic raid zones have been added!&lt;BR&gt;- Now easier to search for potions, poisons, activated items, and food!&lt;BR&gt;- Even more residents of Norrath gain their voices with our optional voiceover download!&lt;BR&gt;- Choose different Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training options!&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** IMPORTANT NOTE ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Most equipment must now be attuned before it provides any benefit. This is likely to affect items currently being worn by your character.&lt;BR&gt;- Wearing gear that is not attuned will display a warning message in your Inventory window.&lt;BR&gt;- If you wish to attune everything your character is wearing, you can type the "/attune_equip all" command. This will only affect items currently being worn.&lt;BR&gt;- Until you attune your gear, IT WILL NOT PROVIDE ANY PROTECTION WHICH MEANS YOU MAY DIE HORRIBLY. Please remember to attune your gear!&lt;BR&gt;- Items that have been attuned cannot be sold or traded to other players, but they can be sold to NPC merchants.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- We are now allowing characters to reselect their Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training options.&lt;BR&gt;- If you have previously chosen Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training, you can reset your selections and make new choices by typing the "/respec" command. This will remove all previous choices from your Knowledge Book and will place a blinking "+" sign in the lower right corner of your screen.&lt;BR&gt;- Clicking the "+" sign will open the selection window and allow you to pick new Traits, Traditions, Tactics, and Training.&lt;BR&gt;- You may receive your selections in a different order this time. Class-dependent choices (like Tactics) will be presented after the others. Characters who gain these abilities as they level up normally will get them in the normal order.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;** IMPORTANT! **&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- While you can issue the "/respec" command at any time, you will not be able to receive quest rewards until you make all pending choices available to you.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Consider System ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- A new NPC consider system has been added that provides players with information on the creatures they encounter.&lt;BR&gt;- When appropriate, your target's level appears next to its name.&lt;BR&gt;- The target window varies based on the target's level of challenge. A weak opponent will have a plain target window with swords under the target's name, while the target window of an epic opponent will be much more ornate.&lt;BR&gt;- While the new system still shows which opponents are linked in an encounter, the consider message is based on the challenge presented by each individual target. Players who prefer to evaluate their opponents' strengths for themselves may enjoy this option&amp;nbsp; &lt;BR&gt;- You can switch between the old system and the new one by selecting the User Interface tab on the Options window. Under the Name and Chat Bubble heading, you can toggle the NPC Evaluation drop-down between Simple (new system) and Detailed (old system).&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** City Sabotage ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Wreak havoc behind enemy lines! Sabotage missions are now available from agents in Antonica and the Commonlands.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Solo/Duo Instanced Zones ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Solo versions of the instanced dungeons in Orcish Wastes, Enchanted Lands, and Thundering Steppes have been added. You can choose whether you wish enter the solo or heroic versions of these dungeons. We recommend the solo versions for one or two players, and the heroic version for groups of three or more.&lt;BR&gt;- Tallon Hording Halls&lt;BR&gt;- Sullon Mines&lt;BR&gt;- The Dark Den&lt;BR&gt;- The Caves of Wonder&lt;BR&gt;- Cavern of Tangled Weeds&lt;BR&gt;- The Rumbler Caves&lt;BR&gt;- A Pirates Hidden Stash&lt;BR&gt;- An Open Grave&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** New Level 50 Raids ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Four new 24-person level 50 raid zones are now available for play.&lt;BR&gt;- Shattered Stillness, entered from Antonica, is where you must defeat Arch Lich Udalan.&lt;BR&gt;- Echoes of Time, accessed in Commonlands, is the home of the mighty King Zalak. &lt;BR&gt;- Cove of Decay: Epic Angler, located in the Thundering Steppes, is where you can find Rognog the Angler, the renowned giant fisherman.&lt;BR&gt;- Meeting of the Minds, found in the Feerrott, is the lair of the mysterious Overlord Oxulius.&lt;BR&gt;- The reuse timer on these raids is 18 hours on success, 6 hours on a failure.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Gameplay ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;BR&gt;- The Swornlove siblings wish to thank you for helping them keep the spirit of Erollisi Day alive. Now that the festival is complete, they will no longer be seeking your assistance.&lt;BR&gt;- You no longer need to defeat an entire encounter to get credit for completing most quests.&lt;BR&gt;- Your speed while on a mount is no longer limited by the maximum speed of the mount. If you receive a movement buff that is faster than the default speed of your mount, you will now move at the faster speed for the duration of the speed increase. This includes spells such as Spirit of the Wolf and abilities such as Sprint.&lt;BR&gt;- There are now stable hand merchants in West Freeport and South Qeynos that will purchase mounts at their full value, less any merchant markup you paid when buying them. &lt;BR&gt;- House pets can now be named while you are in your house by right-clicking on your pet in the inventory window and selecting Name Pet.&lt;BR&gt;- Creatures that used to appear alive after being killed should now look properly dead.&lt;BR&gt;- Added an on-screen message after purchasing a ticket to travel by sea that lets players know they must use the ticket before camping or leaving the zone.&lt;BR&gt;- There is now a ding, accompanied by congratulatory text, when your guild levels up.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Mechanics ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- The damage bonus given by extremely high amounts of strength has been reduced. For example, having a strength of 400 previously gave a 200% damage bonus; after this change, the damage bonus is 155%. There is no change to the damage bonus at a STR of 100, and only a slight reduction at 200 STR.&lt;BR&gt;- Heavy armor now mitigates 11% more damage. Light armor now mitigates 35% more damage. &lt;BR&gt;- Having stamina greater than 200 will now increase the character's maximum health pool.&lt;BR&gt;- Maximum power will increase when the stats used to determine it (strength, agility, intelligence, or wisdom) go above 200.&lt;BR&gt;- Melee combat arts no longer decrease in effectiveness when equipping a weapon that is blue, green, or grey to the user.&lt;BR&gt;- If an epic opponent can only be hit by a certain quality of weapon, that weapon's level must be within 75% or 5 levels of the target's level.&lt;BR&gt;- A bug that was giving some characters extra points in certain skills has been corrected. For example, Artisans will no longer receive 5 extra points in the skills they stop advancing when they choose a class or subclass, and Brawlers no longer gain extra Deflection at lower levels.&lt;BR&gt;- Players will no longer receive a "mini-ding" at reaching 100% of a level if they are unable to gain a level due to a milestone requirement (such as the citizenship quest, class quest, etc.).&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Spells ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Spell casters will no longer fizzle on any spell that is blue, green, or grey to them, as long as their casting skills are maximized.&lt;BR&gt;- The fizzle rate on orange, yellow, and white-con spells has been reduced.&lt;BR&gt;- Targeted persistent hostile spells (such as DoTs) should no longer drop if the caster summons a pet.&lt;BR&gt;- Spectral Guard and Malefic Shroud will now last up to 10 hits before expiring instead of fading after a single hit.&lt;BR&gt;- Flaming Agony and Fiery Doom should now show in the maintained window once they have been cast.&lt;BR&gt;- Vexation upgrades are now available in from the appropriate merchants, recipe books, and loot drops.&lt;BR&gt;- The stat bonuses given by Geotic Brand will no longer change when a player zones.&lt;BR&gt;- Flameshield now does heat damage instead of divine.&lt;BR&gt;- Summoned pets should no longer "dance" their way into unintended aggro.&lt;BR&gt;- Dumbfire pets will no longer remove maintained spell effects from an encounter. This includes the following spells:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Conjuror: Aqueous Hunters&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Shadowknight: Tainted Sacrament, Cursed Sacrament&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Necromancer: Jaul's Rotting Packhounds, Swarm of Rats, Plague of Rats&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Wizard: Protoflame&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Warlock: Netheros&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Defiler: Purulence, Eerie Avenger&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Illusionist: Construct of Order, Construct of Logic, Basten's Construct of Light&lt;BR&gt;- Wizard changes:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Breath of the Tyrant and Immolation no longer share the same reuse timer.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Ball of Flames and Ball of Fire no longer share the same reuse timer.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Piercing Icicles and Icy Coil no longer share the same reuse timer.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Ball of Flame now has a cast time of 2 seconds and a recast time of 6 seconds.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Burning Intimidation now does 4 times its previous amount of damage.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Immolation now deals 2 additional ticks of heat damage at 120% of the initial instant damage. The cast time has been increased to 3 seconds and the recast time is now 21 seconds.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Ice Comet's damage has been increased 275%, and its reuse time is now 45 seconds.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Freeze and Daenor's Lingering Frost now do 3 times their previous amount of damage.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Icy Coil's initial instant damage has been increased 350%.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Piercing Icicles now deals 200% additional instant piercing damage.&lt;BR&gt;- Warlock changes:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Negative Absolution no longer shares a reuse timer with Null Absolution or Nil Absolution, and the maximum number of targets has been limited to 5.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Null Absolution no longer shares a reuse timer with Negative Absolution or Nil Absolution, and the maximum number of targets has been limited to 5. The spell now deals additional poison damage over time.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Nil Absolution no longer shares a reuse timer with Negative Absolution or Null Absolution, and the maximum number of targets has been limited to 5. The spell now deals additional poison damage over time and lowers strength by 5.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Dark Distortion no longer shares a reuse timer with Nil Distortion, and its damage has been increased to 150%.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Nil Distortion no longer shares a reuse timer with Dark Distortion. Its damage has been increased to 240% and it has a reuse timer of 18 seconds.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Flashfreeze now has a casting time of 1 second, and its damage has been tripled.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Noxious Bolt now has a reuse time of 6.5 seconds, and its damage has been tripled.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Dark Emanations no longer shares a reuse timer with Torment of Shadows.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Torment of Shadows no longer shares a reuse timer with Dark Emanations. Its instant damage has been tripled, and its damage over time has doubled.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Dark Nebula now does 3 times its previous damage. It is an upgrade to Grievous Blast, sharing a reuse timer with Grievous Blast and Putrid Cloud.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Devastation will now affect up to 5 targets in a radius of 10 meters with a recast time of 45 seconds. Its instant damage and DoT effect has been reduced by 50%.&lt;BR&gt;- Short duration group buffs now last 10 minutes, and single target buffs now last 15 minutes. This affects the following spells:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Assassin: Bleeder's Talent, Merciless Villainy&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Bard: Bria's Stirring Ballad, Performer's Talent&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Berserker: Bloodlust, Battle Chant, Screaming Fury, Tides of War, Destructive Rage, Greater Fury, Uthros' Superior Tactics&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Brigand: Burgle, Rough Skin, Stealthy Burglary, Aegis&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Bruiser: Intimidating Orders, Rousing Cry, Velan's Nervy Order&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Coercer: Recklessness, Refresh, Annoying Demeanor, Empathic Link, Mind's Eye, Konious' Glowing Breeze, Glyssa's Emboldening Glyph&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Conjurer: Provocation, Fire Seed, Volatile Refuge, Vehement Stone, Flameshield, Blazing Presence, Varski's Encouraging Ward&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Crusader: Offering of Armament, Theron's Heartening Call&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Defiler: Dread Invective, Lucar's Grasping Tendrils&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Dirge: Death's Scent, Lithe Disbelief, Tuyen's Chant of the Arcane&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Druid: Nettleshield&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Enchanter: Breeze&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Fighter: Call to Arms&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Fury: Bristlepelt, Savagery, Fae Fire, Porcupine, Brishan's Quillshield, Hammerwind's Zealous Frenzy&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Guardian: Form of Ferocity, Guardian's Call, Call of Command, Desperate Flurry, Do or Die, Call to Battle, Return to Battle, Briteblade's Command, Braksan's Desperate Rally&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Illusionist: Fleeting Thoughts, Alacrity, Scintillating Aura, Intensity, Kor-Sha's Adroit Seal, Fozzin's Propitious Visions&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Inquisitor: Act of Belief&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Monk: Wisdom of Zephyl, Everburning Flame, Quiet Purity&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Mystic: Avatar&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Necromancer: Boon of the Lifeless, Rending Frenzy, Opal's Aggravating Seal, Darkbriar's Corpseskin&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Paladin: Blessing of the Penitent, Divine Inspiration, Blessing of the Devout, Prayer of Devotion, Call to Glory, Caswon's Penitent Benediction, Theron's Call of Hope&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Predator: Hunter's Instinct&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Ranger: Steady Aim, Forester's Insight, Veil of the Forest, Tolan's Talent&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Rogue: Smuggle, Street Smarts&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Shadowknight: Unholy Order, Insatiable Hunger, Genux's Dark Embrace&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Sorcerer: Burning Radiance, Accord&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Summoner: Agitation&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Swashbuckler: Swarthy Distraction, Freeboot, Flight of Fancy, Feigned Bravado, Bootleg, Bladeweaver&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Templar: Vigilant Benediction, Glory of Combat, Resolve&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Troubador: Elise's Ditty, Daelis' Dance of Blades, Cassindra's Chant of Clarity&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Warden: Barbcoat, Primeval Instinct, Numbing Spores, Duststorm, Vesteri's Gorseshield, Salmekia's Pact of the Pride&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Warlock: Venomous Runes, Abhorrent Gift, Toxic Grasp, Nihilism, Palon's Burning Blood&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Warrior: Battle Tactics, Uthros' Defiant Cry&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Wizard: Flametongue, Concurrence, Frostbound Gift, Frostshield, Casthopur's Frostburn, El'Arad's Custodial Warding&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Items ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Empty bags can now be stored inside other bags. You can't put any items into a bag that is located within another.&lt;BR&gt;- Items that have been attuned or that are marked as no trade can now be sold to NPC merchants.&lt;BR&gt;- Attuned items should now stay attuned when you zone.&lt;BR&gt;- The run-speed benefits of mounts and certain items have been reduced:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Starter Mounts (2.5pp) - 24%, formerly 32%&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Standard Mounts (5pp) - 32%, formerly 40%&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Best Non Status Mount (8.2pp) - 40%, formerly 48%&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Flying Carpets/Undead Mounts (50pp and status) - 48%, formerly 56%&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Crusader Mounts - 10%, formerly 32%&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Totem buff - 24% with a 30 minute duration, formerly 40%&lt;BR&gt;- Cold Link Greaves should now have the correct item icon.&lt;BR&gt;- Necklace of Doom can now be equipped in the correct slot.&lt;BR&gt;- The Rallosian Tunic is now light armor.&lt;BR&gt;- The pants for the Monk and Bruiser level 20 quest armors should no longer use the tattered legging appearance.&lt;BR&gt;- The Bramblewood round shield now looks like a round shield.&lt;BR&gt;- Inspecting Petrified Eyes will now provide text explaining bone consumption.&lt;BR&gt;- Vials of swordfish blood should no longer display a bug icon.&lt;BR&gt;- The Rod of Everlasting Flame should now have the correct appearance.&lt;BR&gt;- Bruise Forger Cestus now does the same type of damage as other cestus weapons.&lt;BR&gt;- Starter weapons on the Isle of Refuge will not need to be attuned before using them.&lt;BR&gt;- All kukri swords now look like kukri instead of falchions or scimitars.&lt;BR&gt;&amp;#8211; Holiday foods will now provide the same regeneration as other store-bought foods. This includes Aromatic Red Wine, Box of Jumjum Chocolates, Schmenko's Warm Spiced Cider, Festive Fruitcake, Nyla's Holiday Eggnog, and Jumjum Snap Cookies.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Zones and Population ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;BR&gt;- Timers on most instanced zones have been reduced. Level and group size requirements have been removed, except for guild raids purchased with status points and certain quest-specific zones. The new timers are as follows:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Level 10-19 zones - 1 hour fail, 8 hour reuse&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Level 20-29 zones - 2 hour fail, 12 hour reuse&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Level 30-39 zones - 2 hour fail, 18 hour reuse&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Level 40-49 zones - 4 hour fail, 18 hour reuse&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Level 50+ zones - 6 hour fail, 18 hour reuse&lt;BR&gt;- The quality of drops from level 50 epic raid encounters has been increased.&lt;BR&gt;- The vertical doors in Solusek's Eye and the Obelisk of Lost Souls should work better.&lt;BR&gt;- Keys that allow you to progress deeper into the Wailing Caves will now be found on their respective owners' corpses rather than inside treasure chests.&lt;BR&gt;- Venekor's breath attack has been adjusted so that subsequent ticks of its damage-over-time spell do the same amount of damage as the initial hit.&lt;BR&gt;- The Vision of Vox's breath weapon does less damage, but can now affect all members of a raid party. Her loot quality has been improved.&lt;BR&gt;- The loot dropped by encounters in the Draconic quests has been improved.&lt;BR&gt;- Foulgill the Rotten's loot has been adjusted to better match the challenge of the encounter.&lt;BR&gt;- Raids cannot zone into the instanced dungeons in Enchanted Lands and Thundering Steppes.&lt;BR&gt;- Entrances to the instanced dungeons in Orcish Wastes, Enchanted Lands, and Thundering Steppes will now appear more frequently.&lt;BR&gt;- Advanced solo/small group encounters have been added to the Orcish Wastes, the Feerrott, and Rivervale.&lt;BR&gt;- That greedy little rat Stiletto fired his scouts and is carrying out his orders alone now to maximize his profits.&lt;BR&gt;- Bouncer Prud can now be found more frequently.&lt;BR&gt;- Opponents that require two or more groups are now more likely to drop useful crafting components.&lt;BR&gt;- NPCs in the Open Grave Heroic zone should now be between 25 and 27, except for the boss who is a higher level.&lt;BR&gt;- Adjusted some of the abilities of the Drakota Niscanth.&lt;BR&gt;- Under Rumbler should now be spawning correctly in the Rumbler Caves.&lt;BR&gt;- Level 40+ epic encounters do slightly more spell damage and heal for slightly more.&lt;BR&gt;- Boss lifetap abilities now do more damage.&lt;BR&gt;- Fixed some cases where boss mobs would drop twice their intended amount of personal treasure.&amp;nbsp; &lt;BR&gt;- The damage done by Darathar's breath weapon has been reduced.&lt;BR&gt;- Stench in the Serpent Sewer should now drop items appropriate for his level of difficulty.&lt;BR&gt;- Level 50 spell scrolls will now only drop from epic encounters.&lt;BR&gt;- NPCs that had been using charm spells will temporarily use other abilities until an issue with charm effects can be corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- NPCs that are Wizards or Warlocks will also benefit from the changes made to player class spells. Approach with caution.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Quests ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Sir Tatters will now give the Small Matter of Bristles quest to those adventurers who declined or were unable to accept the quest before.&lt;BR&gt;- Nillipuss will now only reward adventures upon completion of his quest. &lt;BR&gt;- Varski, Part III can now be completed and the appropriate rewards will be given.&lt;BR&gt;- Drodo will now let you complete Drodo's Goodies if you completed Curse of the Bloody Shank beforehand.&lt;BR&gt;- Completion of The Lost Legend of Lavastorm heritage quest will now award status points.&lt;BR&gt;- Targok will now give you another chance at accepting the third part of his quest if you initially declined the invitation.&lt;BR&gt;- The items Bendik Jonkers seeks can now be found in the Edgewater Drains.&lt;BR&gt;- Language quest items will now drop as corpse loot to allow those who have outleveled the creatures to complete the associated language quests.&lt;BR&gt;- Additional dialog responses have been added into the Bitter Brew quest.&lt;BR&gt;- Players will now receive a title reward for completing the "Deception" quest.&lt;BR&gt;- Fixed some issues with the Hostile Forge instance and lowered its reuse timer.&lt;BR&gt;- Corrected an issue with the access quest to the Vestibule.&lt;BR&gt;- Emissary Midia in North Freeport should now allow you to complete her quest.&lt;BR&gt;- You should now be able to find the bones of the Knights of the Swords of Flame.&lt;BR&gt;- Gawar the Bad should now be appearing correctly in Antonica and Thundering Steppes.&lt;BR&gt;- The "Deepening Barrier" quest should now be working correctly.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Tradeskills ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;BR&gt;- Four new crafting abilities have been discovered: apothecary, weaving, timbercraft, and geomancy. These skills allow all artisans to refine the materials and components needed to make final products. New recipe books can be found on merchants or scattered throughout Norrath which teach you how to use these skills. Artisans automatically gain 5 points per level in these skills.&lt;BR&gt;- New events and reaction arts have been created for apothecary, weaving, timbercraft, and geomancy. Reaction arts for these skills are based on thaumaturgy, binding, woodcraft, and geocraft. These skills increase through use. The higher your skill level, the better your chances of creating higher-quality items.&lt;BR&gt;- Using the new crafting abilities to create components not normally made by your profession requires additional fuel, since you aren't a master of the skills from which these new recipes originate.&lt;BR&gt;- All tradeskill recipes now require a new type of fuel at each 10-level range. Fuel cost increases with level. &lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 0 - 4c &lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 10 - 14c&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 20 - 58c&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 30 - 2s 30c&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 40 - 9s 22c&lt;BR&gt;- Culinary recipes use different types of fuel that are less expensive:&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 0 - 1c (Walnut Kindling)&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 10 - 4c (Mulberry Kindling)&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 20 - 14c (Cherry Kindling)&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 30 - 55c (Hickory Kindling)&lt;BR&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; - Base level 40 - 2s 21c (Mesquite Kindling)&lt;BR&gt;- A bug causing certain artisan-related skills to be 5 points too high has been corrected.&lt;BR&gt;- The Advanced Scholar 15 book has been added to the appropriate loot drops.&lt;BR&gt;- You can now consume food and drink properly when performing tradeskills.&lt;BR&gt;- Tradeskill society tasks will now reward a 60% profit margin based on the fuel costs necessary to create the items.&lt;BR&gt;- Guild tradeskill tasks that award status will also provide a 20% monetary profit based on the fuel costs necessary to create the items.&lt;BR&gt;- Crafted food and drink now restores 25% more health and power per tick. Store purchased food and drink has had its restorative benefits reduced by 66%. Summoned food and drink is now half as effective. &lt;BR&gt;- NPC vendors should offer to buy crafted goods at 80% to 120% of production costs. Please note that their offer is based on how many steps are required to make the item you're selling. Finished goods will sell for a small profit, whereas selling back a refined item will result in a slight loss.&lt;BR&gt;- The number of charges on totems has been increased from 1 to 5.&lt;BR&gt;- The number of arrows and thrown weapons produced has been increased from 5, 10, 15, or 20 (based on quality level) to 6, 13, 19, or 25.&lt;BR&gt;- The number of charges on potions and poisons has been increased from 1, 2, 3, or 4 (based on quality level) to 4, 5, 6, or 7.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Controls, Commands, and UI ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Examining a spell or art now gives you more detailed information on the exact effects of the ability.&lt;BR&gt;- Heal amounts are now sent to the chat window, as in "You heal &amp;lt;target&amp;gt; for X hit points." A healing subcategory has been added to the chat options.&lt;BR&gt;- A Combat General chat option has been added to filter start/stop fighting messages.&lt;BR&gt;- Dragging a recipe icon into the chat window should no longer cause a crash.&lt;BR&gt;- Checking and unchecking categories in Chat Options now work more logically.&lt;BR&gt;- Merchant UI: New categories have been added for Potions, Poisons, Lore, and Attuneable items.&lt;BR&gt;- Merchant UI: Searching for Activateable items works properly.&lt;BR&gt;- Merchant UI: Searching for food by con color works properly.&lt;BR&gt;- Merchant UI: The names of unusable items now appear in red.&lt;BR&gt;- The scroll speed of the recipe examine window has been increased.&lt;BR&gt;- The chat tab frame now fades along with the main chat window frame.&lt;BR&gt;- Various issues with chat scrolling have been addressed.&lt;BR&gt;- A keymap has been added for the Implied Target window. You will find the option to bind a key to this window in the Controls tab of the Options menu under Window Keys.&lt;BR&gt;- Chat tabs no longer share the same buffer. You can now view up to 1000 lines of text in each chat tab.&lt;BR&gt;- Chat tab titles can now be up to 20 characters long.&lt;BR&gt;- Shift + Page Up and Shift + Page Down now let you scroll through responses on the primary chat window (defined with "Always Chat Here").&lt;BR&gt;- Your guild will no longer show up at the bottom of the social structure list.&lt;BR&gt;- Quest update messages now tell you the current/needed target numbers. The wording on many quest update messages has been clarified, and colors have been changed for emphasis.&lt;BR&gt;- The tooltip on ranged weapons should now report the correct damage information for when the user masters the weapon.&lt;BR&gt;- Item con colors in the broker, merchant, trade, and examine windows should better indicate whether someone can use an item.&lt;BR&gt;- Changed the default targeting options so that an arrow indicates the current target and there are no frames around the names of encounter members. As always, you can set the options to your liking.&lt;BR&gt;- The /who command will now allow you to search on a partial guild name. Typing "/who bumb" would list people in a guild called "Bumblebees" as well as those in a guild called "Bumblers."&lt;BR&gt;- There is now a confirmation dialog when destroying coins.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Art ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- Riders should no longer float above their horses. Additional fixes for riding animations will follow in our next update.&lt;BR&gt;- Fixed the tail on fancy horse LODs.&lt;BR&gt;- Improved&amp;nbsp;the horses' idle animations. &lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** Audio ***&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- You can no longer change the speaker type from within the game.&lt;BR&gt;- Many city folk who were quiet before have found their voices.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;FONT color=#ff0000&gt;*** UI Files Updated ***&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_examine.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_FrameStyles.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_gamedata.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_ime.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_generictexttemplate_chatfont.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_experience.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_target.xml&lt;BR&gt;e2qui_mainhud_impliedtarget.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_mainchat.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_persona.xml&lt;BR&gt;eq2ui_proxyactor.xml&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;- The EverQuest II Team&lt;/P&gt;</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=15</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=15&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=15</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2005 12:01:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ask SOE #31 (EQ2Vault)</title>
      <description>In this Episode of Ask SOE #31, John Smedly discovers that Nora is pregnant with his child, meanwhile, franco is on the run from columbian drug lords.  ..... &lt;shuffles papers around...&gt; Oh crap my bad, thats whats happening in my favorite soap opera, as the Gnome turns, Really Ask SOE#31 is just about all the nerfs that are coming up .... &lt;A href="http://eq2vault.ign.com/View.php?view=asksoe.Detail&amp;amp;category_select_id=37"&gt;eq2vault&amp;nbsp;&lt;/A&gt; &lt;CLICK MORE NOW! YOUR GNOMISH OVERLORDS COMMAND IT&gt;</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=14</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=14&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=14</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2005 13:12:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oh and by the way</title>
      <description>I've been informed by the Gnomish High Council that more people need to register, or register on the forums.  If this isn't done I've been informed that all people over the height of a halfling are to be executed..... Errr, Wait a sec, Im an ogre that make me... &lt;mumbles under breath&gt; carry the 2, -5 ummmm &lt;/end Mumbling&gt;  At least 1 foot higher than a halfling!!!! DAMN YOUSE PEOPLE GET TO THE REGISTERING OR WE ARE ALL GONNA DIEEE!</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=13</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=13&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=13</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2005 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lack of updates</title>
      <description>Im sorry for the lack of updates recently, my Gnomish Oppressors have kept their slave Ogre busy doing... err stuff, yea and thats why I havent posted.  However, the big little gnome in charge tells me dat more poster types are a'comin, so I can get back to sleeping errr.... I mean umm doing stuff, or whatever</description>
      <link>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=12</link>
      <author>Host Account</author>
      <comments>http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=12&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://www.gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=12</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2005 12:55:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>