<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://mikeshea.net/rss.css" type="text/css"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

  <channel>
    <title>LoralCiriclight.com</title>
    <link>http://loralciriclight.com/</link>
    <description>Tales and adventures of Loral Ciriclight in the online role playing game, Everquest.</description>
    <dc:language>en-us</dc:language>
    <dc:creator>mike@mikeshea.net</dc:creator>
    <dc:rights>Copyright 2004</dc:rights>
    <dc:date>2004-06-24T04:03:14+00:00</dc:date>
    <admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.movabletype.org/?v=2.661" />
    <admin:errorReportsTo rdf:resource="mailto:mike@mikeshea.net"/>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>

    <item>
      <title>Recruitment</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001136.html</link>
      <description> Note: This short story appeared in the July 2004 Everquest newsletter. Tiim watched the shoppers of the Freeport market...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1136@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>Note: This short story appeared in the July 2004 Everquest newsletter.</p>

    <p>Tiim watched the shoppers of the Freeport market as he always did on Saturday mornings. The exotic scents of a hundred different spices filled his nostrils. Dozens of the market's shoppers milled about the stalls, some from the soft and fat noble class, others rough and lean adventurers.</p>

    <p>Tiim watched the purses of these shoppers carefully. A coin or two from time to time might fall through careless fingers and Tiim must grab them if he wished to eat. If he became desperate enough he would have to cut the purse strings himself. To be caught in such an act meant losing his hands. A boy like Tiim needed his hands if he didn't want to starve.</p>

    <p>Tiim's eyes shifted to the pair of armored guards who scanned the people strolling by. Those near the guards kept their heads down and eyes forward. The tall guards, armored in steel breastplates, greaves, and bucket helms, kept their eyes out for people like Tiim.</p>

    <p>Most people have an ability to sense when they are being watched. When they feel eyes on them, even from behind, a person will turn and look without even knowing what they are looking for. A boy in Tiim's line of work, the work of thievery, knew this sense well. Tiim never looked directly at the guards or any other person.</p>

    <p>Tiim had further honed this sense. He didn't only know when he was being watched but when others were being watched as well. Someone else was watching the guards. Someone close. Tiim slowly turned and saw a figure studying the guards.</p>

    <p>The man was tall. A gray cloak and hood covered his face. Tiim saw the man's scruffy chin in the light of the morning sun. Two pinpoints of light reflected off of the man's eyes from within the shadow of the man's hood. Tiim made out the dull gleam of a mail shirt under the stranger's cloak. The man wore tall soft leather brown boots heavily seamed and coated in the dust of the road.</p>

    <p>The man turned his head towards Tiim and the young thief's heart jumped. He had been carefully taking note of the stranger from the corner of his eye but the stranger had felt his gaze anyway. Tiim yawned, his natural protective response in moments of high stress. He looked down and dragged the toe of his tattered cloth sandal in the dirt. The ruse of relaxation seemed to work. The hooded stranger looked away and back to the guards.</p>

    <p>A scuffle at one of the merchant tents took the guards' attention and the cloaked man moved quickly. The stranger headed to an alley, attempting to escape from the marketplace. He might have made it if two other guards hadn't come out of the very alley the stranger hoped to escape to. It was pure bad luck.</p>

    <p>One of the guards recognized the cloaked man and shouted. The other reached out to grab the stranger by the front of his cloak. There was a flash of movement and instantly the guard was on the ground holding his deformed broken wrist to his chest.</p>

    <p>The other guard began to draw his sword but the stranger drew his own shining silver shortsword and cut out to the side with speed far beyond the clumsy guard. Tiim saw a ribbon of blood in the air and the second guard crumpled to the ground.</p>

    <p>Tiim always trusted his instincts even if they made no logical sense. His instincts had kept him alive for thirteen years and today they would change his life forever. Tiim felt this instinct like a needle stuck into his spine and began to move.</p>

    <p>The two other guards raced towards the stranger just as the second of the two guards from the alley fell. They shoved and punched their way through the crowd and hit the cloaked man hard. The stranger ducked into a ball and hit the first rushing soldier at the knee. Tiim heard the snap of the guard's dislocated knee and saw him somersault onto his back howling in pain. The second guard clipped the cloaked man in the jaw with an iron-gauntleted fist. That is when Tiim arrived.</p>

    <p>Tiim's rusty dagger served him well over his years on the street. It was a part of him and it was no surprise that he found it in his hand even though he had no memory of drawing it. Without slowing down, Tiim's hand slashed out. A leather pouch fell from the cloaked man's belt and into Tiim's waiting hand. Tiim disappeared into the crowd. He had just a moment to see the stranger drop to both knees and hamstring the fourth guard with his gleaming shortsword.</p>

    <p>Tiim ran for an hour using every secret passage and hidden alley he knew. He darted into sub-basements and alcoves. He ran under the docks past the unseeing gazes of Freeport's street dregs. Finally after running down his favorite darkened alley, Tiim stopped.</p>

    <p>There the cloaked man waited for him.</p>

    <p>The man had thrown back his hood and Tiim saw his red hair pulled back over his pointed ears. The stranger, a half elf if Tiim had to guess, had his hands comfortably on his hips. The shortsword, hilted in shining gold and jewels, sat on his left hip.</p>

    <p>"I've never seen hands as fast as yours." The man's voice was even and smooth. A thousand lies came to Tiim's lips but Tiim saw in the half-elf's blazing green eyes that no lie would take. He knew of only one way to survive this confrontation. He held out the leather pouch.</p>

    <p>"I never saw you coming and I see everything," said the half-elf plucking the pouch from Tiim's hand. "I have need of someone like you."</p>

    <p>The man smiled so warmly that Tiim's guard immediately fell. In his whole life no one had ever smiled to Tiim with such kindness and warmth. If he had not been an orphan he might have recognized the smile as one given to a child from a pleased parent.</p>

    <p>"How would you like to join the Antonican Bards?"</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-06-24T04:03:14+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Book of Gunthak</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001135.html</link>
      <description>SOE released a large patch this week, one with many changes from the community feedback they received from the guild...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1135@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>SOE released a large patch this week, one with many changes from the community feedback they received from the guild summit.  Read the <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/updates/recent_updates.jsp?id=62500">full patch message</a> and then continue for today's editorial.</p>

<p>More collision bug fixes should reduce the bugs we've seen even more.  Since the last update I personally haven't seen any of the big collision issues introduced with the Direct X 9 update.</p>

<p>The Plane of Knowledge now has a stone to the boat in Gunthak down in the evil section of the zone.  Lower level players now have much easier access to the zones from Legacy of Ykesha.  Changes allowing players to group and hunt more quickly are always welcome.</p>

<p>Quite a few changes were made to Gates of Discord.  Most of these changes affect zones beyond Kodtaz, a land few people can see.  The beasts that previously dropped class-specific spells now drop tokens.  Turning in the token returns a class appropriate spell.  In my hunts in the sewers, Tipt, and Vxed, I've seen spells drop only three times and each time it was for a class not present.  This is a welcome change.</p>

<p>A scripting change to Plane of Time shuts down unused instances of Time.  This helps guilds who became stuck because of a previous guild.  While Time instancing is still a large issue for high-end guilds, it doesn't appear it will be fixed before Omens of War is released at the end of August.</p>

<p>An NPC in the Plane of Knowledge will now teleport you to the Plane of Hate for a price.  This change has some wizards in uproar; previously the only way to the Plane of Hate was with a wizard's teleport.  The cost is higher for the NPC version and Plane of Hate isn't exactly the most popular zone so I don't see the change as a large one.</p>

<p>A new /guidehelp system lets players ask for assistance with in-game events such as weddings, GM quests, and server events.  I hope to see more GM events in the future.  GM events breathe life into an otherwise static game.  There is a lot of opportunity to enrich Norrath's lore through GM events like the Fironia Vie event in Kunark did years ago.  Most GM events became smaller in scope and did not affect the story line.  If GMs were handed a script or timeline of events to follow, the story of Norrath could grow over time through these dynamic events.</p>

<p>The raid management window received some changes including the ability to add notes to individual players, a Message of the Day feature, and the much needed ability to drop raid members who have left the zone.  Horror stories of raids having to disband and rebuild because of an AFK raid member are over.</p>

<p>The "/stopcast" command has many people scratching their heads.  The main reason people wanted it was to stop casting on horseback but the command specifically does not work on horseback.  SOE never meant horses to allow mana regeneration while moving.  Horses were designed to be a status symbol.  The meditation while riding became the most popular reason to buy a horse.  SOE has no intentions of "fixing" this "bug" but they will not improve it by allowing riders to cancel spells like they can do on their feet.  This has been a long-standing policy with horses and is unlikely to change.</p>

<p>A new PvP test server includes a variety of changes for player versus player combat.  New point-based armor rewards, new spell balancing, and rumors of an in-game hit-list complete with a reward system threaten to make PvP a fun place to play.  The violent and aggravated PvP server citizens receive little in the way of an update so this is a nice change for them.  As long as they don't bleed into my soft blue server and eat newbies, I'm happy.</p>

<p>New Lost Dungeon armor is under discussion though the developers continue to discuss the exact power of this armor.  Hopefully it's equivalent in scope to Elemental and Time items considering the requirement for such equipment in Gates of Discord.</p>

<p>Keep an eye out for some form of augment swapping in the next update.</p>

<p>While the changes in this week's patch mean little to most players, the updates in the future promise some exciting changes for characters of all levels and all paths.  Keep reading!<br />
</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-06-18T14:59:06+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Return to the Sewers</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001134.html</link>
      <description>SOE will begin to release changes based on last week&apos;s guild summit next week. Only two changes are noted: a...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1134@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>SOE will begin to release changes based on last week's guild summit next week. Only two changes are noted: a Plane of Knowledge stone for Gunthak and a way to clear empty instances of Time, but I wouldn't be surprised to see more soon.</p>

<p>The Gunthak portal helps level 30 to 50 players a lot. It wasn't exactly hard to run through Paineel, Warrens, and Stonebrunt, but its nice to skip them and head right to Gunthak. It saves a lot of time.</p>

<p>The Time change interests Time-capable guilds who ask repeatedly for an instanced Plane of Time. SOE had this at the top of their "future items" list. I heard whispers of a two month process to rebuild Plane of Time into an instanced zone. I would rather see revamps of Fear and Sky than see Time instanced for a select few. Like Sleepers Tomb, North TOV, and Vex Thal, Time will be put aside when the raiding guilds reach deep into Gates of Discord and start to battle in Omens of War. Quick changes to Time are fine but spending two months on it sounds extreme.</p>

<p>SOE is looking at new LDON gear to help smaller groups and guilds gear up for Gates of Discord. This could help open up more options for single-group hunters as well as raiders who need one or two items they can't seem to get in raids. Gates has a lot of single-group instanced trials including the four sewers, Vxed, Tipt, single group hunting in KodTaz, and the three infamous Ikkinz trials. All of these are available to single groups if you're able to get to them and survive. Vxed, Tipt and above are tuned for Plane of Time and "Time+" level players.</p>

<p>The subject of new LDON gear brings up a few unanswered questions. How much will high-end LDON items cost? How powerful will they be? Will there be other requirements to reach them? Some developers feel that simply awarding it for adventure points is too easy, that some sort of greater challenge must exist to acquire these items. I don't agree. While raid leaders and long-time raiders face great challenges, people slip into mature raiding guilds and acquire massive amounts of armor without seeing that challenge. 30 to 60 hours of LDON hunting is long enough to acquire high-end Elemental or Time tier 1 or 2 loot.</p>

<p>Augment swapping is on the way. Augment swapping solvents will most likely require a trade skill to create. There will be a cost associated with augment swapping, but the cost is not yet determined.</p>

<p>SOE also discussed refunding adventure points on LDON items. People may spend 1500 points on a LDON breastplate and then bank it when a new one comes along. SOE hasn't worked out the details yet but a 50% refund has been discussed. Considering my bank is full of my purple Hate armor, my Skyshrine quest armor, and about a dozen outdated bits of treasure, I think a 50% refund is generous. No drop armor is outdated all the time.</p>

<p>I forgot to mention last week that SOE plans to release a level 40 to 55 LDON raid to Stormhammer and then the rest of the servers soon. LDON raids were initially designed for Plane of Time raiders with little else to do. Unfortunately, no raids were developed for lower level or lower power adventurers. The set duration, difficulty, and player numbers of LDON instanced raids allow for extremely tailored raid encounters for all levels. I hope we see more LDON raids for levels 55s to 65s with gear below elemental.</p>

<p>I had a chance to hunt in the Sewers of Barindu recently and enjoyed the changes I saw. The mobs hit for 66% of the damage they used to. Moderately equipped tanks can tank normal mobs and as a Cleric I had to work for a living again without being overwhelmed. The experience was good but could use a boost when compared to the Planes with their graveyards and easy access. Named mobs were still quite hard and a gating mob ended up wiping us out, but the experience was good and the loot was not bad.</p>

<p>My CR was a disaster. I died once in Qinimi on my way back to Barindu, my body got stuck under the earth, and it ended up decomposing before I could get a GM to summon it. I still want more CR options than having to spend two hours after a loss to recover. Death should be painful but there should be options.</p>

<p>Painful CR or not, I will go back to the sewers.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
11 June 2004</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-06-11T19:42:51+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Guild Summit Report</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001133.html</link>
      <description>It&apos;s been quite a weekend. SOE loves their game. Almost the entire staff of designers, artists, programmers, customer service representatives,...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1133@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>It's been quite a weekend. </p>

<p>SOE loves their game.  Almost the entire staff of designers, artists, programmers, customer service representatives, and management are former players who joined SOE because they love the game.  Every attendee of the guild summit I spoke with never felt that SOE fed them a line.  Only twice did <span title="Brenlo is the best guy ever">Brenlo</span> hold his tongue in response to my questions; one when asked about SOE's plan with IGE and later when asked about focus effects above 65, a subject not yet decided.  Every developer spoke clearly and in detail with every question I asked.</p>

<p>"Gush on, valiant Fanboi!" you shout, but let me reveal the darker side.  Though Smedley said that the bulk of active EQ players were below level 50 I only know of one or two attendees of the sixty that play characters below level 65 and both hardly play anymore.  I learned on the first night that SOE developers have a private forum with raiding guild leaders to discuss raid encounter tuning.  I can't help but wonder why no such forum for single-group players exists.</p>

<p>After nearly ten hours of focus groups and future discussions Brenlo handed out <a href="http://www.thesteelwarrior.org/forum/showthread.php?t=7457">a list of twenty issues</a> SOE would review and implement very soon.  Of these twenty, twelve of them were raid specific and most of the rest were general fixes.  Only one focused on casual content: a solo instanced encounter of some sort.</p>

<p>Many single group issues came up, however, and SOE reacted positively.  I left at least half a dozen copies of <a href="http://mobhunter.com/article.jsp?articleid=-1950615164">Loral's Evil Agenda</a> in the hands of SOE employees including Robert Pfister, Executive Producer of Everquest (who had already read it but politely accepted it before wrapping the remains of his hot dog in it and casually tossing it over his shoulder).</p>

<p><span title="Smed Loves the pirate!">John Smedley</span> stated first that Gates of Discord's release was SOE's worst mistake in five years.  He personally apologized.  I spent my day job listening to managers who speak often and say little.  Smedley was the opposite.  His introduction gave the statistic that most active EQ players are below 50 and revealed that EQ and EQ2 development teams receive royalties for their games individually.  This dispells the theory that SOE is secretly trying to wean us off of EQ and onto EQ2.  The EQ team wants to keep us playing as long as possible.  Rod Humble augmented this address stating that while voices often state that Velious is SOE's best expansion (I still think LDON is), Ykesha is the best selling expansion.  Many attendees attribute this to shared bank space, but I'm not so sure.</p>

<p>Smedley revealed the failed plan to bring out level 65 to 70 during the fifth year anniversary two months ago and Brenlo confirmed that SOE designed Gates of Discord with level 70 in mind.  This explains a lot of the expansion's difficulty.  I spoke with just about anyone who would listen about the overly long duration of sewer, Vxed, and Tipt trials and the designers agreed that four hours for an often failed event was too long.  Whether it's fixed before we see level 70 or not is hard to say.  SOE designed Gates to be very hard.</p>

<p>Later I asked Smedley to confirm the rumor that we would have new PC models before the end of 2004 and he confirmed it.  SOE is outsourcing the project to another company, an act that vexes SOE artists.  It's their baby and they want to do the models but there simply isn't the time, a statement we heard often.  The developers who spoke at the initial meeting stated that they want and expect Everquest to stand up graphically to other current massive online games including EQ2.  The graphic update we battled through recently helps us get there.</p>

<p>The shifting number of allowed players in raid encounters between Planes of Power, Lost Dungeons, and Gates of Discord frustrates a lot of guilds and leads to many players quitting.  Everquest's designers stated that 54 is the new official number for future Everquest raids.</p>

<p>Though focused on raid content, all love of the single-group gamer is not lost.  Brenlo confirmed that new high-end elemental level equipment will update the LDON adventure merchants.  Single-group hunters will be able to gear up for Gates of Discord content without Time or Elemental access.  Omens of War includes only one flagged zone though certain encounters may be locked.  This resembles Kunark, Velious, and Luclin expansions where most of the content was open to all players.  Omens of War includes zones for all players tuned to help characters level up to 70.</p>

<p>SOE based the high cost of AAs on the experience found in the Plane of Fire, a zone many single-group hunters cannot yet reach.  While Omens zones will offer experience zones to help non-flagged hunters, SOE should up the experience in Tipt, Vxed, and the sewers closer to Fire than they are now.  The difficulty in reaching these zones and the difficulty in the encounters warrants the experience boost.</p>

<p>While SOE designed Epic 2.0s to be the best class items available to the most powerful raiders, Epic 1.5s will be available to high level players and require only one or two groups to complete.</p>

<p>It was an amazing weekend filled with the obnoxious rings of cell phones, one so loud that its owner cried out to his deity in shock and horror.  The icy glare of the guild leader from the dark and frightening Rallos Zek server gazed over us bluebies like we had green target circles under our feet.  Twice I became stuck between Gilfalas of <a href="http://p202.ezboard.com/fpaladinsofnorrathgeneral.showMessage?topicID=19890.topic">Paladin's of Norrath</a> and Raaj of <a href="http://www.thesteelwarrior.org/forum/showthread.php?t=7457">The Steel Warriors</a> who crashed together in debate over Defensive.</p>

<p>Ryan Robinson, the Sheriff of Norrath and customer support supervisor told the story of a trade scam buried under over thirty transfers from different accounts that took two weeks to track down, but they did.  This fellow needs his own Stephen Bocco police drama.  40% of the 47,000 petitions the CS department receives monthly are lost items and 70% of these are scams of some sort.  A lot of CS's day is chasing ghosts.</p>

<p>Here's a brief summary of the things I found most interesting:</p>

<p>- We will have new PC models by the end of the year.<br />
- New high-end high-cost items will be available on LDON adventure merchants.<br />
- Gates was designed for level 70, thats why its so hard.<br />
- Rallos Zek is a chaotic server of horror and villainy.<br />
- Gilfalas just wants "a little something!"<br />
- Omens of War has only one locked zone, the rest of it is open to all players.<br />
- While Epic 2.0s are for the uberist of the ubers, Epic 1.5s are available to the rest of us.<br />
- Some sort of instanced solo adventure is in the works.<br />
- The Omens of War task system, a small 30 minute quest system, will be available to levels 20 and above.<br />
- There will be a quest for Gates of Discord spells, though details aren't available.<br />
- Chat channels cross over between Everquest and Everquest 2.<br />
- The development team wishes they never called it Everquest 2.<br />
- Soon augments can be removed and replaced on other items.<br />
- Smedley loves pirates.<br />
- The graphic engine update we went through will help EQ stay graphically competitive with other MMOGs.</p>

<p>There are dozens of other reports of the summit including posts on <a href="http://www.thesteelwarrior.org/forum/showthread.php?t=7457">Steel Warriors</a>, <a href="http://p202.ezboard.com/fpaladinsofnorrathgeneral.showMessage?topicID=19890.topic">Paladins of Norrath</a>, <a href="http://www.thesafehouse.org/viewtopic.php?p=145875">The Safehouse</a>, <a href="http://forums.gucomics.com/viewtopic.php?t=2220">GU Comics</a>, <a href="http://www.therunes.net/forums/viewtopic.php?t=4178">The Rune</a>, <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=5406">Caster's Realm</a>, <a href="http://thedruidsgrove.org/forums/showthread.php?t=8094">The Druid's Grove</a> and a lot of places I haven't found yet.  Druid's Grove even <a href="http://thedruidsgrove.org/forums/showthread.php?t=8098">has pictures</a> including some unfortunate ones of <a href="http://www.thedruidsgrove.org/images/summitspring2004/bus1.jpg">your fearless writer, Loral</a> (I'm the one in the black shirt on the right).</p>

<p>I received a lot of positive feedback from at least six other attendees I spoke with on the way back home and feedback from the postings above agree.  SOE is working hard to improve Everquest and fix previous mistakes.  Though not all of my agenda points were met; mainly what I wanted to hear was "Lost Dungeons 2 in December"; I am very happy with the direction things are going.  I look forward to the next few months.</p>

<p>Our world is strong.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
7 June 2004</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-06-08T04:32:54+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001127.html</link>
      <description>Next week SOE is hosting a visit for guild leaders and community representatives to talk about the state of the...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1127@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Next week SOE is hosting a visit for guild leaders and community representatives to talk about the state of the Everquest and get feedback.  This article outlines the evil agenda I plan to bring to San Diego and hand to the Everquest developers.  </p>

<p>I cannot speak for the entire community. I read the message boards every day.  I play hours every night.  I talk to low level players, high level players, raiders, casual hunters, trade-skillers, and everyone in between and I have no doubt that I am missing the majority of opinions.  We have no idea what all 400,000 players think.  Few players post to message forums. Few players send feedback. Few players even bother to read websites like this one.  It's impossible to know what they think needs to be fixed. I can, however, give my view on the state of Everquest and the features I believe will help the game. </p>

<p>Lets begin Loral's Evil Agenda:</p>

<ul>
<li>Focus on single-group content.</li>
<li>Offer easier corpse recovery in old world and GoD zones.</li>
<li>Offer quest, adventure-point, or vendor alternatives for level 65 and GoD spells.</li>
<li>Offer progressive content in 30 minutes or less.</li>
<li>Add higher-end equipment to LDON adventure merchants.</li>
<li>Add more Lost Dungeon content including zones, adventure types, and rewards.</li>
<li>Make the Sewers, Vxed, and Tipt easier to get to, easier to recover from, easier to battle in, and offer more significant rewards.</li>
</ul>

<p>Focus on single-group content.  The six-person group was once the single unit that all content was balanced against.  Planes of Power and Gates of Discord put raiding and raid-equipped players above moderately equipped single groups.  Increase content for single groups.  Increase high-end equipment opportunities for single group hunters.  Use adventure merchants, expeditions, and instanced zones to bring more content and progression opportunities to single group hunters.  Make the six person group the focus of Everquest again.</p>

<p>Offer easier corpse recovery for old world and Gates of Discord zones.  Planes of Power and Lost Dungeons of Norrath offer excellent escapes for nasty corpse recoveries.  Befallen, Blackburrow, Kaesora, Dalnirs Crypt, and all other old-world dungeons offer no such option.  The Plane of Fear has a higher risk than any raiding zone in Planes of Power.  Don't punish Befallen hunters with horrible corpse recoveries while Plane of Fire hunters recover in 20 minutes.</p>

<p>Offer quest, adventure-point, or vendor alternatives for level 65 and GoD spells.  For single group hunters, level 65 spells are rare and gates of discord spells are almost non-existent.  Offer quests or adventure point systems for high level spells.  Give casual hunters a clear path to these spells.   Place level 65 and GoD spells on LDON adventure merchants or add a similar system to GoD.</p>

<p>Offer progressive content in 30 minutes or less.  Many players have limited play time.  There is little progress anyone can make in thirty minutes.  Many people solo and work on trade skills when they have limited time.  Improve solo content; improve trade skill content; add adventure-point based task systems.</p>

<p>Add higher-end equipment to LDON adventure merchants.  Lost Dungeons offers a fair and consistent method for acquiring equipment.  Players are able to progress towards powerful gear in small steps.  This equipment lacks power when compared to Elemental, Time, and GoD equipment.  Add high-cost equipment with two slot 3s, higher power melee weapons, and augments with the higher-end focus effects such as Marr's Gift, Preservation of Xegony, Mana Regeneration +3 and +4, and Faerune.</p>

<p>Add more Lost Dungeon content including zones, adventure types, and rewards.  Many players love Lost Dungeons and want more adventure types, zones, and lower power raid content.  Add new adventure types and rebalance the rescue and assassination quests.  Increase the cash and experience rewards.  Use the expedition feature of Gates of Discord in Lost Dungeons so people can come and leave in the early parts of an adventure.</p>

<p>Make the Sewers, Vxed, and Tipt easier to get to, easier to recover from, easier to battle in, and offer more significant rewards.  These zones are very hard for their current rewards and many powerful groups fail in the last few minutes of a four hour hunt.  Tune these zones for high level characters without raid-level equipment.</p>

<p>Minor Quips and Suggestions:</p>

<p>Fix sitting animations for male elves.  Why do I still look like a statue when I sit?</p>

<p>Revamp Sky and Fear.  Fear is the only zone left where people cannot get a safe summon at the zone in.  It is the hardest of the Planes with the worst loot.  The time for three-day sky raids is over.  Let Call of the Hero work in Sky.</p>

<p>Debug quests.  A lot of people fail on quests when they hand in stacks.  The rat whisker quest still eats stacks of rat wiskers without returning them.  Buggy quests frustrate players of all levels.  Add better quality control to quest and trade skill content.</p>

<p>Support dual-monitor systems.  I'd love to put my buff and extra chat windows on another monitor while using my main monitor for the world view, target, and group windows.  Duel monitor support adds a lot of capability for high-end systems.</p>

<p>Offer partial refunds on adventure-merchant augments.  A 50% refund wouldn't unbalance the game and would give people some points back for future gear.</p>

<p>No more rats, bats, and spiders.  I've fought these throughout my 65 levels and 260 AA points.  Its time I fought nothing smaller than a armadillo.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
31 May 2004<br />
Loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-05-31T21:11:35+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 49: The Rescue</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001129.html</link>
      <description>There is no horror worse than to stare with mortal eyes into the depths of hell. The mortal mind cannot...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1129@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>There is no horror worse than to stare with mortal eyes into the depths of hell.  The mortal mind cannot grasp beyond the horizons of pure evil.  We have born and died in a world of balance; a world of black and white and gray.  The people we meet are not pure definitions of good or evil.  Anger and revenge filled every paladin's heart at one time or another.  Love touched the dark heart of a necromancer, though small that touch may have been.  Our people walk a rope of good and evil.  It is why the gods watch us.  It is how we grow.</p>

<p>But around our world, in the cracks and seams of our lives, there is a darker world.  There are many dark worlds.  There is Disease; there is Nightmare; there is War; there is Fire.  There is Torment.</p>

<p>Torment's webwork of steel and stone stretch through a sky of blood over waters thick and black.  Torment cries and laughs in the heart of despair.  To look upon it is to feel the crushed spirit of hopelessness.  To see the twisted beasts walking the labyrinth of its web-like sprawl is to see true horror.  Few mortals see the devastation of Torment.  Few ever escape its clutches.  There are a few, however, who have felt the steel-barbed whip of Torment. Lost souls fall through the seams of life and into eternal pain and despair. Twisted beasts of coarse fur, yellow tusks, maws of white poisonous fangs and cloven hooves roar and rip into the mortals trapped in this prison world.</p>

<p>Time has no meaning in the demi-plane of Torment.  Sometimes it gushes in a black river.  Other times it is a single red drop of blood falling for centuries.  A denizen of Torment cannot say how long it has been since mortals entered the red world freely.  It is not frequent.  So it was a surprise to see six mortals step through the white crackling rift that tore a wound through space and time.  As much as it surprised the demons of Torment, the fury of their attack surprised them even more.</p>

<p>The crack of lightning shows the twisted walkways as the rift tears open time and space.  On the backdrop of black and red the six mortals show blue and gold and silver.  They show no fear of the world they entered.  They hold weapons themselves forged in the planes.  They are Planewalkers, adventurers familiar with the outer worlds and they came with purpose.</p>

<p>For centuries, Gtzzg walked the impossibly suspended walkways of Torment.  He crushed bones in his huge hands and ripped into the soft skin of thousands.  His yellow eyes gleamed and his thick hair stood up on his massive shoulders.  He was the first to attack these intruders.  He wanted them before the other demons; the sightless screaming telepathic ravens, the tentacled constructs, or the wolves; got to them.</p>

<p>Gtzzg roared his psychic roar and held his massive claws out as he rushed in.  None in the party moved.  He reached the group of mortals but never landed a blow. A mace, gleaming white with internal power and forged to battle just such a beast, smashed into the demon's skull.  Plates of bone and gushing black blood splashed onto the ancient stone walkway.  The mace crushed half of the demon's mind.  He couldn't see out of one eye.  His mouth opened in protest to this impossible situation when the mace came in again.  The demon knew no more.</p>

<p>The adventurers hit Torment like a white hot scythe.  They hewed and cleaved through dozens of the Plane's demons.  The six mortals sprinted through fountains of spraying black blood, severed limbs, and the tainted smoldering ruins of their foes.  Arrows streaked silver across the dark red sky, tearing demonic ravens out of the air one after another.  The mortals ran with purpose, navigating the twisted walkways as the demons of the Plane did.</p>

<p>They ran into a smaller of the plane's cell blocks, a huge block of black stone carved with images of torture and pain.  Two guards, massive wolf-headed beasts with horns protruding from their backs and shoulders, held their ground.  They saw the rush of the adventurers and prepared their telepathic attacks.</p>

<p>A dozen arrows tore into the face and chest of one, blinding him.  A bolt of lightning crashed into the other, sending it into convulsions.  The cruel demon-slaying mace smashed into the jaw of the electrocuted wolf-demon sending its teeth back into its head.  A slice of flashing silver, the thin edge of a heavily enchanted blade, cut through the neck of the other blinded demon and deep into the wall behind it.  The head spun through the air, over the edge of the walkway, and tumbled into the black water hundreds of feet below.</p>

<p>The swing of an enchanted hammer smashed the steel door into pieces.  White light poured into a room that only knew darkness.  A figure, tiny and broken, cowered away from the light.  The thin figure was naked and pale.</p>

<p>Loral stepped into the cell.  His golden armor shined with an internal fire.  His white hair hung in his face matted with sweat.  Black blood covered his silver hammer in his right hand and sizzled off of the burning shield attached to his left.  He went to the figure in the corner, dropping his hammer and placing his hand on the figure's shoulder.</p>

<p>"I'm here, father."  Loral's voice cracked and a tear cut a clean path down his grimy face.  He gently embraced the figure who did not return it.</p>

<p>"It's time to go home."</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-05-29T20:50:18+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caves of the Kobold Slavers</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001126.html</link>
      <description>It&apos;s been a while since we&apos;ve had an update but this one has a couple of neat things in it....</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1126@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
It's been a while since we've had an update but this one has a couple of neat things in it.  Today's patch included a new tutorial, possible fixes to the Plane of Knowledge crashes, some UI updates, and a couple of more tidbits.

Last week I started up a level 1 Berserker on the test server to try out the new tutorial and I was very impressed.  It's a mixture of local and server-based quests and a new generic low-level zone.  It walks new players through Everquest's complex interface as well as it can.  It makes great use of the "Find PC" yellow magic trail to lead a new character from NPC to NPC.  As a veteran player, I cannot give a truly objective analysis but it appears it will do a good job of teaching new players the basics of our game.  The rewards for walking through the tutorial include enough experience to reach level 3 and a powerful charm.

Proper marketing and improvements to simplify Everquest's interface bring new players online.  The more players in Everquest, the better the content and service we'll see.

Which leads us to Sony's new pricing plan.  For $120, a customer receives a one year subscription to Everquest and all seven current expansions.  This is an excellent deal but few new players are willing to make a $120 commitment on a game they haven't played yet.  This pricing plan works very well for players with multiple accounts.  There will soon be a package called "Everquest: Platinum" (how's that for false IGE style advertisement?) containing all expansions up through Gates of Discord for $30.  A $10 version called Everquest: Chronicals (Everquest: Copper?) is said to contain the old world, Kunark, Luclin, and Ykesha.  The strange set of expansions is due to their inclusion of new races.  My Neriak spies tell me future low-priced expansions will include mid-level and high-level content to go along with this beginner's set.

The biggest problem we've seen recently are the Plane of Knowledge crashes.  The developers posted many updates to the problems but crashing in the most popular zone in EQ builds a lot of frustration within Sony's paying customers.  We can hope this patch helps the problem; if not, Sony can expect quite a few more posts on the tech forums.

Sony released little news on Omens of War but some changes to the Test server already <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=druidbalance&amp;message.id=608">sent spell casters into spasms</a>.  The spells don't even have names yet but people are already wearing their "My Spells Only Do 54.918DPS: Everquest is Dead!" T-shirts.  I'll assess Omens of War when I've actually played it, thank you very much.  IGN posted an <a href="http://pc.ign.com/articles/518/518286p1.html">article about Omens of War</a> with only a few bits of information we didn't know.  I found one line particularly disturbing: "There will be around 20 new zones with this expansion, most of them geared toward GoD-capable players."  From what I've experienced and what I've heard, a "GoD-capable player" is ... no one.  Say it ain't so, Brenlo.

Which brings us to the revamp of Gates of Discord.  I see little change for all of the excitement Sony made over the new revamp.  I still died from see-invis mobs in Barindu after failing at the fourth hour on a Vxed hunt.  I still don't get experience like I do in restricted zones of Fire and Earth.  I've seen no Gates spell drop.  I'm reminded of the fifty "Planes of Power spell drops have increased" patch messages when I've still only seen one non-raid rune drop in all of my days in the Planes.  The changes to KodTaz and above may be nice; apparently it's easier to get into Qvic; but what about the other 93% of casual high-level players (lies, damndable lies, statistics)?  I don't expect another Gates revamp. I'd rather see improvements to Lost Dungeons of Norrath and I look forward to Omens of War; but this big change didn't seem very big to me.

At least young Bolmer, the level 1 Berserker, can take out my frustrations on the skull of a Kobold slaver in the dastardly tunnels of Whatever.

Loral Ciriclight
26 May 2004
loral@loralciriclight.com
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-05-27T05:10:57+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whispers of War</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001111.html</link>
      <description>Content has many forms. New levels, gear, encounters, abilities, and zones excite us. It&apos;s the one thing that separates Norrath...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1111@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Content has many forms.  New levels, gear, encounters, abilities, and zones excite us.  It's the one thing that separates Norrath from AOL Instant Messenger.  It is the context of our existence in Norrath.  New features, zone revamps, even small UI patches are a form of new content to explore.  Last week revealed quite a lot of upcoming content.  Please spear me before I say the word content again.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/omensofwar/">Omens of War</a> whisper past us in the bars and inns of Norrath's cities.  It appears the Wayfarer Brotherhood has bitten off a little more than it can chew.  The wars of Mata Muram begin in two months.</p>

<p>SOE revealed few details about Omens of War but what they have revealed created quite a stir.  New epics, new levels, a task system, a guild tribute system, new titles, and new graphics are all listed on the Omens of War website.  There were a couple of other bits of discovered information including <a href="http://forums.thesafehouse.org/viewtopic.php?t=4552">zone names</a> that sound a lot like Lost Dungeon zone names (West Battlegrounds A, B, C, D) and notice that epic 2.0s are <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=TNZ&amp;message.id=76140#M76140">separate quests</a> from original epics.  One won't have to turn in or even acquire the original epics before acquiring the new epics.  Even the Everquest board moderators don't seem to know much about this new expansion.</p>

<p>I hope to see a short-duration task system available to all levels.  Why should the level 20s be the only ones to deliver propaganda between the Wayfarer camps?  I'm already collecting zombie skin and vampire teeth for them, a demeaning job for a high priest of Tunare if I do say so myself, so why not make me the Norrathian equivalent of FedEx?  Maybe I can get some special shorts!</p>

<p>Nothing is yet known about the zones, the encounters, or the rewards.  I dream of another adventure point system.  I loved the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/message.jsp?articleid=-563313134&amp;msgid=-2095349685#message">Wayfarer cookie idea</a> posted by Pverex on last week's article.  I dream of zones that scale for levels 20 to 70.  I dream of Lost Dungeon style adventures with expedition style control.  I dream of a smooth experience curve above 65 so I can still hunt with my level 50 friends.  </p>

<p>The release date of Omens of War appears to be the end of July.  <a href="http://mobhunter.com/message.jsp?articleid=-563313134&amp;msgid=-496660957#message">Rod Humble stated</a> on my well received previous Mobhunter article that the beta for Omens will be wider than Gates of Discord was. I look forward to the release of new details.</p>

<p>The next big bit of news is the <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=62046">revamp of Gates of Discord</a>.  A lot of folks aren't happy with Gates for a variety of reasons.  The expansion appeared tailor made for Elemental / Time guilds but strange, difficult, and buggy encounters and a lack of good loot disappointed a lot of them.  Everyone who faced it felt that the beasts of Taelosia hit a bit too hard.  I still cannot walk ten feet through a town without someone reminding me of the 1200 point-hitting gnat that turned me into holy dungeon pizza.  Lower level players found little reason to purchase Gates.  Only one zone is huntable below 50, tributes became too expensive for their usefulness, and new tradeskills were often incomplete.</p>

<p>Details of the revamp are still hazy and only when we try Gates after the revamp will we know how good the changes were.  The proposed changes include zone retuning, experience modification, easing travel, lowering output damage, increasing spell drops (again), increasing cash drops, and a reduction in required flags for Ikkinz (wherever that is).  These sound good but even <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=62073">Brenlo's second explanation</a> left out a little detail.  Exactly what were the intended level ranges of the five open zones?  What will the tuning of these zones entail?  We'll know Wednesday, I assume.</p>

<p>In the mean time, begin preparing for war.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-05-10T18:46:18+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The End May Be Nigh Someday!</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001112.html</link>
      <description>Sony began accepting applications for beta-testing Everquest 2. It&apos;s no surprise to hear that thousands of people submitted applications. Would-be...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1112@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Sony began accepting applications for beta-testing Everquest 2.  It's no surprise to hear that thousands of people submitted applications.  Would-be beta-testers hammered the application servers resulting in some typical page request errors, duplicate applications, and a host of other problems.  In order to sign up for the beta, one must apply from the computer one plans to play on.  This prevents people from applying on most work machines.</p>

<p><a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/tracker?role=Dev">Moorgard and Faarwolf</a> have been keeping people well informed on the process and procedures of beta signups.</p>

<p>Sony released a small patch today.  The changes included one's ability to change his or her surname, hitpoint regeneration improvements, and /rewind.</p>

<p>The ability to change one's surname comes as a small surprise.  GMs will cease to be flooded with requests to change surnames.  It is now easier to annul the many failed in-game marriages we often hear about.  It's a small change but I see no disadvantage.</p>

<p>Hitpoint regeneration now improves the longer you sit.  This regeneration allows players a chance to solo and recover a bit easier.  Wizards, Druids, and a few other classes have an easier time soloing than rogues, warriors, and other melee classes.  This regeneration gives other classes at least a chance at soloing successfully.  The problem shows up when we consider grouping.</p>

<p>Grouping builds relationships.  Grouping teaches people new skills.  Grouping helps people learn more about the game than they would find out on their own.  Grouping helps people find guilds. Grouping builds social skills, both in-game and in real life.  To throw that away for soloing is to remove the whole reason to play Everquest.</p>

<p>Everquest offers many advantages for grouping.  Grouping is necessary for Lost Dungeons of Norrath.  Grouping offers a large experience bonus over soloing.  Most of the game's content below level 65 is tuned for single group hunts.  The single group is the most common unit of gameplay in Everquest.</p>

<p>These hitpoint regeneration changes are good, however.  This change helps individuals and groups without healers alike.  I don't expect it to harm the game at all.</p>

<p>Our Neriak spies returned with reports that Sony is <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=62046">retuning Gates of Discord</a>.  Tuning changes include experience boosts, tuning of Natimbi, Qinimi, Barindu, Riwwi, and Ferubi, NPC max damage mitigation so clerics can tank (relax, I'm kidding, I meant knights), increased spell drops, easier zone travel, NPC innates (I have no idea what this is), and the inclusion of some non-agro animal mobs. All of these changes look excellent and I applaud Sony's attention to these problems.</p>

<p>Afterlife, one of the top guilds across all servers, quit on Wednesday.  Their post was the first negative posting I can recall seeing on their website.  They felt strongly enough to break two metaphors in one sentence.  I had always enjoyed Afterlife's objective and clean updates and its a shame to not only see them leave but to see them leave with such a poisoned tongue.  At least they didn't post a count-down.</p>

<p>I'd be surprised if every member of Afterlife cancels their subscriptions and stops paying.  I imagine the guild may disband; I imagine many of them will go to another game; I'd even expect some to return.  It would surprise me if every member felt as strongly as the post stated.</p>

<p>Obviously if that many people have been having no fun since The Rathe (an encounter they defeated a year ago), I have to question why it would take so long for them to quit.  It sounds like we all need a reading of the divine article <a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001076.html">Why I Play Everquest</a> by one of the most highly respected writers of Everquest news, lore, and editorials.  Remember the golden rule:</p>

<p>Have Fun Every Day You Play.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-05-05T18:46:45+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Found: More Lost Dungeons</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001113.html</link>
      <description>Sony released a new patch today with a few interesting new features. Sony released new adventure zones on Stormhammer and...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1113@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Sony released <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/updates/recent_updates.jsp?id=61961">a new patch</a> today with a few interesting new features.</p>

<p>Sony released new adventure zones on Stormhammer and on the regular servers.  The zones sound interesting except for their restrictive level limitation.  The rest of Lost Dungeons included zones scaled for levels 20 to 65 so I don't understand why these zones were not scaled the same way.  The zones are not restricted by time limits or adventure goals but also do not offer adventure point rewards.  Besides being instanced, they don't sound very different from normal zones.  I only wish the level limits were less severe.</p>

<p>This patch included the first release of "Hot Spots".  Certain zones offer experience rewards for a limited time in order to get adventurers of various levels to travel around a bit more.  Like the Fabled mobs for the anniversary, this offers a reward for those who take the time and energy to explore these hot zones.  Like the new adventure zones, none of these apply to level 65 players, but the 65 level folks did just get Gates of Discord.</p>

<p>All players now have access to the Plane of Knowledge.  The Plane helped all of Everquest become a lot more accessible to new players and this is a good improvement.  I am surprised Sony doesn't bundle Kunark and Velious into the core game and give these two aged expansions to everyone.  Sony could then release expansions with these two previous expansions in mind.  I'd love to see a Lost Dungeon expansion released in Kunark and Velious.</p>

<p>Oh yes, we received one nerf today.  The named mobs in the GoD sewer and mountain trials no longer spawn on creation, they spawn later in the hunt.  This prevented named farming by respawning the dungeon over and over.  I can see why they did it but a nerf is a nerf.</p>

<p>The Fabled mobs and their gleaming new treasure no longer spawn.  The new beasts and their gleaming treasure breathed some life back into old zones and hopefully the new hot spots will do the same.  Under-population of old-world zones worries a lot of people.  Many new players never hunt in places like Runnyeye, Paw, the Gorge of King Xorbb and Dalnirs.  Of course, I blame this on a lack of reliable corpse recovery, but I blame my lower back pain on the lack of reliable corpse recovery.  The real reason of under-population is a higher risk for a lower reward than populated zones.  Fabled mobs fixed this for a short period of time and only in very select camps at very select zones.</p>

<p>Sony begins accepting beta test applications for Everquest 2 in May.  The beta itself begins in June.  With those dates, it seems likely that Everquest 2 will be released on schedule at the end of the year.  It wouldn't surprise me if we see an announcement for a new expansion around the same time.  No one knows how Everquest 2 will affect Everquest.  SOE will want to show their continued support for Everquest, support I expect to see continue as long as it is profitable to do so.  Some see Everquest 2 as the doom of Everquest.  Many said the same thing about Dark Age of Camelot, Final Fantasy XI, Star Wars Galaxies, and others.  While the release of Everquest 2 has more impact than those will, I do not see much changing for at least another year.  As long as Everquest is a fun and fresh world to live in, we will want to live there.</p>

<p>It would not surprise me to hear about a new expansion soon.  With the unknown fears of Everquest 2 making many nervous, Sony will want to quell any thoughts that Everquest 1 is doomed.  I'm hoping for a "Lost Dungeons of Norrath Part II" with dungeons in Najena, The Gorge of King Xorbb, Old Paineel, and a giant's lair in Raithe Mountains.</p>

<p>The debate on tank status in Gates of Discord rages on.  Some don't seem to understand that this only affects about four discovered zones.  Only on certain Gates of Discord expeditions does warrior tanking appear to be required.  These trials are required for progression but so was the Plane of Justice and many people were stuck there for weeks.  </p>

<p>Paladins and Shadowknights tank hard adventures in Lost Dungeons and hunting groups in the elemental planes all of the time.  The problem isn't that paladins and shadowknights aren't good tanks, it is a problem with the difficulty of a specific and small set of content.</p>

<p>Loral's rant of the week: Where in Hate are my 65 GoD spells?  I love the Lost Dungeon loot system and while I'd love to see something like that in Gates and every future expansion, I'd especially like to see it for spells.  A wayfarer merchant offering up spells to those who have completed X number of Sewer and Mountain trials would give more people a chance at those spells without reducing the difficulty in acquiring them.</p>

<p>The Adventure Merchant system reduced the randomness of loot distribution without making it too easy to get them.  It is the same as the dragon kill point systems that most uberguilds use today.  It shouldn't replace dropping loot, but it could easily augment it.</p>

<p>So ends the rant and so ends this week's update.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Mobhunter Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-04-28T18:47:08+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>


  </channel>
</rss>

