<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Update!</title>
    <description>Updates</description>
    <link>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;BlogID=7</link>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2006 11:15:53 GMT</pubDate>
    <docs>http://backend.userland.com/rss</docs>
    <generator>RSS.NET: http://www.rssdotnet.com/</generator>
    <item>
      <title>Dragons go "Nite-Nite"</title>
      <description>Well we're wrappin up '05 in a good manner. On a whim decided to go try and maj'dul dragons and tore them a new one. sorry dragons, no lube or warning.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ding guild lvl 40, well deserved, thanks everyone who took that little (or in some cases, alot) bit of extra time and got that status for us.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=/portals/6/dragons.jpg&gt;</description>
      <link>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=32</link>
      <author>Odiopopulis Aeternus</author>
      <comments>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=32&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=32</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2006 11:13:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T6 Stuffs 4TW</title>
      <description>Who's Your Daddy Now&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=/portals/6/yoyoloot.jpg&gt;</description>
      <link>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=31</link>
      <author>Odiopopulis Aeternus</author>
      <comments>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=31&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=31</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2005 22:29:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RAID!!</title>
      <description>&lt;IMG SRC=\Portals\6\hahha.bmp&gt; &lt;/IMG SRC&gt;

Rafael askin fid bout our supah sekrut nightly raids
Hrm...

</description>
      <link>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=29</link>
      <author>Odiopopulis Aeternus</author>
      <comments>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=29&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=29</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2005 14:48:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recruit</title>
      <description>Tell us how u really feel, Jonluke

&lt;img src="http://gnorrath.com/Portals/6/recruit.jpg"&gt;</description>
      <link>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=28</link>
      <author>Odiopopulis Aeternus</author>
      <comments>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=28&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=28</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2005 12:05:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carpet</title>
      <description>We been doin lots of stuffs round here lately, Ding guild 31, RAWR. Lots of discoveries and lots of xp! WTG all the tradeskillers showin what we got in that dept. Gratz kosuke on first guildy to 60, its ok, u can take a nap now. Lots of other individuals not mentioned, Gratz to u too.

&lt;img SRC=Portals\6\carpets.jpg&gt;&lt;/Img SRC&gt;
</description>
      <link>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=27</link>
      <author>Odiopopulis Aeternus</author>
      <comments>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=27&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=27</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2005 21:06:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Update</title>
      <description>Update Notes : 10/5/2005 7:00 AM &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Headlines *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Try your luck at the Gigglegibber Goblin Gamblin' Game! &lt;br&gt;- No more run-speed reduction with stealth and invisibility! &lt;br&gt;- Tell at a glance if you don't have enough power to use a spell or art! &lt;br&gt;- Imbued item recipes now available for level 50+ crafters! &lt;br&gt;- Many user interface windows have a new look! &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** The Gigglegibber Goblin Gamblin' Game *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Fun-seeking tricksters calling themselves the Gigglegibber Goblins have been spotted recently selling tickets for a gamblin' game. &lt;br&gt;- Six numbers are chosen ranging from 1 to 36. If your 6 numbers match the winning numbers, you get the jackpot! &lt;br&gt;- The jackpot grows larger as more people play. &lt;br&gt;- Tickets for the game cost 1 silver each. &lt;br&gt;- Match 2 numbers and you win 2 silver. &lt;br&gt;- Match 3 numbers and you win 5 silver. &lt;br&gt;- Match 4 numbers and you win 25 silver. &lt;br&gt;- Match 5 numbers and you win 2.5 gold. &lt;br&gt;- Match all 6 numbers and you win the jackpot! &lt;br&gt;- Note: The Gamblin' Game is unavailable on Station Exchange-enabled servers. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Stealth and Invisibility *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- The run speed debuff associated with stealth and invisibility spells has been removed. &lt;br&gt;- The concentration cost of stealth and invisibility spells has been removed. &lt;br&gt;- The duration of group stealth and invisibility spells has increased to 10 minutes. &lt;br&gt;- Run speed buffs (including horses) will suspend while stealthed or invisible. &lt;br&gt;- Run speed debuffs will still apply their movement penalty while stealthed or invisible. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Window Decoration *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Many game windows now have a sharper look. These include Character Creation, the Knowledge Book, Inventory, Trade, Bank, and many more. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Desert of Flames *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Gameplay &lt;br&gt;- Sumixum now sells Arena Champions trophies to those who earn them. &lt;br&gt;- Gnomes in plate armor should now have an easier time climbing. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Quests &lt;br&gt;- Guerrilla Lorkil should no longer spawn if you have already completed his quest. &lt;br&gt;- Trials of Ash, Disciples Edicts, and Proving Grounds should now all have valid targets. &lt;br&gt;- A Slippery Situation now requires that you find an actual torch rather than killing Phenos the Explorer at this stage of the quest. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Zones and Population &lt;br&gt;- Raid forces entering the Gates of Anket Aken should now zone into their own instances. &lt;br&gt;- Cazel should now drop treasure at a rate more appropriate for the number of players needed and reuse timer of the zone. &lt;br&gt;- Keeper of Silence now has an appropriate chance to drop either the gold or silver scale. &lt;br&gt;- The merchants in the Peacock Club Tavern no longer sell crafted items. &lt;br&gt;- Killing any named in the Poets Palace single-group version will begin a reuse timer. &lt;br&gt;- Bosses in the Maj'Dul Court faction instances should drop their fabled items at a more appropriate rate. &lt;br&gt;- Genies now have varied colors in their ethereal particles. &lt;br&gt;- Tornados now look a little more menacing. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Voice Emotes &lt;br&gt;- The following emotes should now trigger a voice while in combat (assuming a voice has been selected on the Persona window): /assistme, /battlecry, /flee, /followme, /growl, /healme, /helpme, /helping, /heroic, /incoming, /lookhere, /lookout, /mine, /no, /oop, /stay, /taunt, /threaten, /train, /underattack. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** The Bloodline Chronicles *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- The D'Morte Burial Chambers and Delving into the Darkness are now more solo friendly. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Gameplay *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Characters should no longer remain unconscious for long periods of time. You can no longer bleed to death, and will regain 20% of your max unconscious health every 6 seconds. &lt;br&gt;- You can no longer board a flying mount (griffin or flying carpet) while casting a spell. &lt;br&gt;- Duel losses no longer contribute to your total death count. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Quests *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- The needlessly confusing "Are you an artisan or an adventurer?" question has been removed from the Qeynos/Freeport introductory quests. Thanks to the community summit attendees for pointing this out! &lt;br&gt;- Sage Indis Surion and Sage Navarius Orvalis now sell the newer versions of the catalog and mastery tomes to players who have already completed these quests. &lt;br&gt;- You will now be rewarded for the completion of "Kallon's Vengeance" and "Caravan Lost." &lt;br&gt;- Journal information and minor changes were made to the Stormhold quests "Bolt-Streaked Cuirass," "Haunted Helm," "Rumble," "Virtue Belt" and "Vigilance." &lt;br&gt;- A new version of the Drafling Tower quest "Deadly Stinger" is available. &lt;br&gt;- "Trinkets of the Dead" in Nektropos Castle now requires Thexian diplomats instead of Sheila's Handmaiden. &lt;br&gt;- After slaying Scout Captain Underwood for Jaeta in Nektulos Forest, he will no longer attack you. &lt;br&gt;- Enemies in the Lair of the Necromancer will now be a little less deadly for solo players. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Zones and Population *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Killing grey con creatures will now affect your faction standing. &lt;br&gt;- Darathar and his minions have been adjusted in difficulty to account for the combat changes. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Guilds *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Characters that were not flagged as patrons before Live Update #13 will now trigger guild broadcasts when completing writs or status quests. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Housing *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- The price of the Antonican Defender house pet has been adjusted and the No Trade flag was removed. &lt;br&gt;- The Antonican Defender and Halasian Mauler are now larger in size. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Items *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- An item will now grey out when your character is 15 levels above the item's equip level (rather than 75% of your level or 10 levels). &lt;br&gt;- Wearing armor below your level will no longer be as punishing for low-level characters. &lt;br&gt;- The Wand of Ice will now cast properly. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Spells and Combat Arts *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- The names of spells and combat arts in your Knowledge Book or hotkey bars no longer have a con color. They are white if you can use them or red if you can't (such as when mentoring). They will grey out 15 levels after they are gained. &lt;br&gt;- Spell and Combat Art icons will now tint bright blue when you do not have sufficient power to cast them. The color can be changed in Options &gt; User Interface &gt; Game Colors &gt; Low Power Indicator. &lt;br&gt;- Single target and group see invis abilities no longer consume power over time. Group versions should now affect group members appropriately. &lt;br&gt;- Heroic Opportunity starter spells and arts should no longer grey out. &lt;br&gt;- If you have a spell effect active that cancels when you take damage, the spell will only cancel if an attacker inflicts the damage (e.g. falling damage will no longer cancel that spell). &lt;br&gt;- Scrolls for abilities that cannot be upgraded should no longer exist in the world. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Berserker changes: &lt;br&gt;- The Berserk visual effect of the Furious Rage line has a slightly different appearance. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Fury changes: &lt;br&gt;- The proc portion of Savage Feast will no longer be dispelled as a hostile effect. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ranger changes: &lt;br&gt;- Indium arrows summoned via Arrow Rip will now function at the proper level. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Warden changes: &lt;br&gt;- Essence of the Great Bear now shares the same resistances as the rest of the spell line. &lt;br&gt;- Protecting Grove should once again be healing group members. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Tradeskills *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Imbue recipes now exist for level 50+ Armorers, Tailors, Weaponsmiths, Jewelers, and Woodworkers. &lt;br&gt;- Warring Conviction, Purifying Flames, Wintry Cold, Bolt of Storms, Arctic Flames, and Fuliginous Tendrils are now found in the level 51 recipe books. &lt;br&gt;- Noxious Bolt is now a level 29 recipe instead of 30. &lt;br&gt;- Discretionary Flow is now a level 27 recipe instead of 30. &lt;br&gt;- Nullification is now a level 24 recipe instead of 30. &lt;br&gt;- Miasma is now a level 25 recipe instead of level 28. &lt;br&gt;- Dark Emanations is now a level 31 recipe instead of 33. &lt;br&gt;- The Summoner's Mark line of spells for Summoners, Conjurers, and Necromancers are now included in the correct recipe scrolls for level 28/42/56 Sages. &lt;br&gt;- Fear should now be included in the level 24 sage recipe scrolls. &lt;br&gt;- Aqueous Stalkers should now be included in the level 24 Sage recipe scrolls. &lt;br&gt;- Poisonous Veil should now be included in the level 20 Sage recipe scrolls. &lt;br&gt;- All Apprentice II, III, IV and Adept III spell scroll icons are now visually consistent for each archetype. &lt;br&gt;- Broadcloth Yarn and Broadcloth Thread have been removed from Tailor Essentials Volume 30, since they already exist in Volume 29. &lt;br&gt;- Roasted Rolled Oats and Rolled Oat Malt have been removed from Provisioner Essentials Volume 30, since they already exist in Volume 29. &lt;br&gt;- Rock Blast is now in Volume 15 of the Advanced and Essentials Scholar recipe books. &lt;br&gt;- Summoner's Mark is now Volume 15 of Advanced and Essentials Scholar recipe books. &lt;br&gt;- Consumable pasta has been removed from tradeskill merchants. &lt;br&gt;- The Spellbinder's Sconce should no longer show appear as a pink box. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Art *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Barbarian and froglok males should appear shirtless when no chest armor is equipped. &lt;br&gt;- Zombie Illusion forms will no longer display your equipped items. &lt;br&gt;- Fiery hand trails that appear while casting spells will now work on non-humanoids. &lt;br&gt;- Ice particles should now be visible in all environments. &lt;br&gt;- Kerra females should no longer sink into their horse's saddle when running. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** Commands, Controls, and User Interface *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- Group options (such as yelling for help) should once again default to the settings of the group leader. &lt;br&gt;- The default setting for which group members can yell for help is now set to "all" for new characters. &lt;br&gt;- Player and officer notes can now be set properly in the Guild window. &lt;br&gt;- /clear_hotkey_bank &lt;hotbar #&gt; will now clear the specified hotbar. &lt;br&gt;- Crash issues related to the Group, Guild, and Chat windows have been fixed. &lt;br&gt;- Long guild rank names will now wrap to a second line on the Ranks tab of the Guild window. &lt;br&gt;- The lock and delete buttons in the Events tab should now function correctly. &lt;br&gt;- The "remove" button in the Guild window should once again work correctly. &lt;br&gt;- The "change rank name" button will no longer open a large number of rename windows. &lt;br&gt;- Typing /namingpolicy will now open the Help window to an article that explains the in-game naming policy. This policy applies to everything players can name, including characters, guilds, and pets. &lt;br&gt;- The help window now has a current list of the most commonly reported problems and their resolutions. &lt;br&gt;- Certain graphics card drivers should no longer display video corruption on the bottom and right portions of the screen when anti-aliasing is turned on. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;*** UI Files Updated *** &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;eq2ui_commonelements.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_dropdown_template2.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_event_template.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_event_template_compact.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_eventfilter_template.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_gamedata.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_hud.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_hud_choice.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_hud_disconnected.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_hud_zoning.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_inventory_bank.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_inventory_exchange.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_inventory_guildbank.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_inventory_inventory.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_inventory_loot.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_inventory_merchant.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_inventory_trade.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_listrank_template.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_loginscene.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_death.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_help.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_options.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_bugreport.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_claim.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_feedback.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_groupoptions.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_guild.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_help.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_knowledge.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_knowledgesort.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_mainhud_lotto.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_newcharscene.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_permission_template.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_book.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_bugreport.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_claim.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_feedback.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_groupoptions.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_instructions.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_loadskin.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_scriptexecutor.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_setprice.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_setpricestatus.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_usagealarm.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_popup_zoneteleporter.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_textstyles.xml &lt;br&gt;eq2ui_windowelements.xml &lt;br&gt;images\commonelements.dds&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;-The EverQuest II Team&lt;br&gt;</description>
      <link>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=26</link>
      <author>Odiopopulis Aeternus</author>
      <comments>http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=26&amp;#Comments</comments>
      <guid isPermaLink="True">http://gnorrath.com/Default.aspx?tabid=72&amp;mid=481&amp;ctl=ViewEntry&amp;EntryID=26</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2005 19:56:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>