<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Everquest news, editorials, and commentary.</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<copyright>Copyright 2004</copyright>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2004 11:14:46 -0500</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2004 14:12:57 -0500</pubDate>
<generator>http://www.movabletype.org/?v=3.01D</generator>
<docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs> 

<item>
<title>Everquest 2 Review</title>
<description>Today Mobhunter offers a double-sized article: a full review of the first two weeks of Everquest 2.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000041.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000041.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2004 11:14:46 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>November News Roundup</title>
<description>This week we take a look at some community news including the release of EQ2, some code changes, Caster&apos;s Realms&apos;s new administrator, and a few other odds and ends from around the net.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000040.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000040.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2004 09:44:53 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>October 2004 Fan Faire Report</title>
<description>We return from New Orleans full of strange visions and fine tales to tell.  Pull up a chair and listen to the stories of the future of Norrath.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000039.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000039.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2004 07:21:27 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral&apos;s Evil Halloween Agenda</title>
<description>Next week Loral travels to the strange lands of New Orleans.  He travels with a satchel full of this Evil Agenda in the hopes of helping to manipulate Everquest to his own evil lands of darkness and horror.  Read on...if you dare!</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000038.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000038.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2004 06:59:15 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Warts Under the Emperor&apos;s Clothes</title>
<description>It is a month after the release of Omens of War and the world of Norrath changed forever.  While this expansion has many strengths, it also has a few weaknesses.  This week we peek underneath the beautiful and ornate exterior to examine a few of the expansion&apos;s weaknesses.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000037.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000037.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2004 11:32:45 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Myths of Class Balancing</title>
<description>This week we get away from some of the controversy surrounding our beloved game and go into the green pastures of a topic we can all enjoy and agree upon.  I kid, of course.  Lets roll up our sleeves and dig into the myths of class balance.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000036.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000036.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2004 23:09:52 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Interview with Scott Adams</title>
<description>This week it is my pleasure to interview Scott Adams.  Scott and Pasty Loral dicuss Scott&apos;s mark on the computer game world, Scott&apos;s Everquest career, and Scott&apos;s EQ Wishlist.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000035.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000035.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2004 00:27:26 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Early October News</title>
<description>This week we relax from the onslaught of Lorals editorials for a more traditional look at the news.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000034.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000034.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2004 00:17:32 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>After Omens</title>
<description>Today we take a look at the chaotic news of the last couple of weeks and we take a harder look at the Omens of War expeditions.  If you look closely, you will see Loral flip flop again.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000033.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000033.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2004 18:13:39 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Omens of War Review</title>
<description>In this week&apos;s article we review the first week of Omens of War.  We take a look at zones, levels, aas, gear, graphics, and the extra features Omens of War has to offer.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000032.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000032.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2004 23:38:56 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Meaningless Words of Everquest</title>
<description>This week we discuss five meaningless and overused terms in the Everquest community.  These five terms muddy the clear waters of communication and hide our true intent from the eyes of SOE.  Remove them from your communications, replace them with detail, and we can finally express our true desires.
</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000031.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000031.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2004 07:49:57 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Focus and the Flip Flop</title>
<description>Today we discuss the great foci change of &apos;04 with a bit of discussion on the politics of language thrown in for a bit more flavor.  An essay from 1946 probably doesn&apos;t count as a pop culture reference, but I&apos;m working on it.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000030.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000030.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2004 14:12:29 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Visions and Omens</title>
<description>Our first exploration of Omens of War begins this week.  We look at some of the new zones, new alternate advance abilities, and the task system.  Promising times lay ahead.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000029.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000029.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2004 14:08:48 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Five Steps to One Million Subscribers</title>
<description>This week we look at what steps SOE might take to double Everquest subscribers.  Improved retail versions, new PC graphics, another LDON expansion, a simpler interface, and improved stability can all lead SOE to a million Everquest subscribers and a better game for all of us.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000028.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000028.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2004 12:46:21 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Calm Before the Storm</title>
<description>Today we deliver another gathering of news from across the lands and across the ethereal worlds of the net.  We look at some new changes to test, some discussions of new LDON raids, and the continuing class issue updates.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/000026.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/000026.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2004 13:46:06 -0500</pubDate>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>