<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/" />
<modified>2004-08-17T17:59:14Z</modified>
<tagline>Everquest news, editorials, and commentary.</tagline>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2</id>
<generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="3.01D">Movable Type</generator>
<copyright>Copyright (c) 2004, Loral</copyright>
<entry>
<title>Five Steps to One Million Subscribers</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000028.html" />
<modified>2004-08-17T17:59:14Z</modified>
<issued>2004-08-17T17:46:21Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.28</id>
<created>2004-08-17T17:46:21Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we look at what steps SOE might take to double Everquest subscribers.  Improved retail versions, new PC graphics, another LDON expansion, a simpler interface, and improved stability can all lead SOE to a million Everquest subscribers and a better game for all of us.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>I want to see one million people playing Evequest.  I want to see Sony Online Entertainment double the subscribers they currently have.  I do not have a master's degree in business or marketing but that never stopped me from having an opinion before and it won't stop me now.  This article outlines five steps to improve Everquest's success.</p>

<p>Loral's Marketeer Five Step Evil PowerPoint Slide for the success of Everquest:</p>

<p>- Continue to release fresh retail versions of Everqust.  Make it clear to the consumer which one they should buy and cheap enough to compete with newer MMOGs.</p>

<p>- Update the PC models and graphics to compete with newer MMOGs and make EQ look like a brand new game.</p>

<p>- Release another Lost Dungeons of Norrath style expansion with scaling content for levels 20 to 70.</p>

<p>- Simplify the interface; perform usability studies; simplify the skill and discipline system.</p>

<p>- Improve Everquest stability; make patches modem friendly; offer updated versions of EQ on DVD as DVD drives proliferate.</p>

<p>Step 1: Market Everquest as a new game every expansion and offer a free version.  The release of the Everquest Platinum edition greatly improved SOE's chances for increasing subscribers.  For $30, a new player gets the basic game, all seven current expansions, and a month to try it out.</p>

<p>Release the basic game with a one month trial for free to let people try the game out.  Pass this single-disc version around like AOL.  Have people making coasters out of it and throwing it at that guy hovering over by the fax machine.  While the current free download helps, the sheer size of the game makes it almost inaccessible to new players.  Offering free CDs in gaming stores, magazines, and bulk mail will bring in a lot of new players.</p>

<p>Continually update this $30 version with everything but the most recent expansion.    Pull older versions off the shelves.  Make it clear which versions players need to buy.</p>

<p>Step 2:  Update player character graphics.  There are no graphics more important than PC graphics.  When people shop for a new MMOG, player graphics are the first thing they see.  Everquest has excellent world and beastie graphics, but the current player graphics need work.</p>

<p>SOE plans to release new player graphics by the end of the year.  It is important that they stick to this deadline.  EQ2, Worlds of Warcraft, and Final Fantasy X offer brand new and fresh player graphics.  New PC graphics is SOE's first chance to impress new players, it is the first graphics a new player sees. New player graphics are the most important change this year.</p>

<p>Player graphics require three things to succeed.  They must scale well on existing systems and offer good performance during raids.  They must be customizable enough to create unique characters identifiable from far away.  They must be good enough to let us escape into the lives of our characters.  </p>

<p>Step 3:  Release another Lost Dungeon-like expansion.  Lost Dungeons of Norrath offers the most highly scalable content in any of the previous expansions.  LDON offers usable and rewarding content from level 20 to level 65.  Mobs are always blue.  Treasure and rewards scale well.  Groups are easy to find and the camps are well connected.  The dungeons allow for easy corpse recovery but still offer a good challenge.  Players can finish an event in between 45 and 90 minutes.</p>

<p>A new Lost Dungeons expansion should use the Gates of Discord expedition system so players can leave if they have to.  Like LDON, it should allow players to work towards powerful items in small steps.  The storylines should put the players in the role of the hero and not the errand boy.  The storyline should progress as the players hunt.  Threats should seem real.  Adventure types should reward the players equally for equal difficulty and there should be a wider variety of them than the current ones.</p>

<p>Step 4: Simplify the interface.  Everquest's interface is very difficult for new players.  The basic controls alone require a lot of work but stack on communications and character improvement interfaces and you have one of the most complex game interfaces ever seen.</p>

<p>Reduce the number of windows a player must go through to set up disciplines.  Start all skills at 1 so they will raise on their own instead of requiring a player to run back and check with a guild master every couple of levels to see if there is a skill they missed.  Tell the player when a new discipline is available and let them scribe it like a spell.  Streamline the hotbox macro creation process so it is easy to build complex macros mixing skills, disciplines, spells, and other commands.</p>

<p>Perform usability tests with new players to see where interface elements break down and where they can be improved.  Basic usability tests are cheap to perform and can easily improve profits on even simple systems.</p>

<p>Simplify the interface and more players will stick with the game.</p>

<p>Step 5: Improve stability and lower network requirements.  When I first played Everquest Online Adventures on the Playstation 2, I was impressed by two things.  One, they download patches into three megs of space and it never gets any bigger.  Two, they focus almost entirely on game enhancements instead of stability improvements.</p>

<p>Make Everquest as stable as a console game.  Improve hardware testing and application testing so that players can reasonably expect the game to work every time they log in.  Many players still face a variety of technical issues and these issues are far more damaging to the game than almost any content problem.  The chaos of PC architectures makes testing very difficult.  Stability should be a number one concern for SOE developers.</p>

<p>The large patches that Everquest players face require a high-speed connection.  While the game itself plays well over dial up, downloading two hundred megs of updates cut off a lot of players from playing.  As DVD drives become more common on newer machines, offer Everquest with all expansions on a single DVD but lock the content the user didn't pay for.  Update this DVD with the most recent large patches so even existing players can go get the updates from a game magazine or from their local game shop.  Keep patches small and consider dial up players when they are released.  No patch should take longer than 30 minutes to download.  Even thirty minutes will cut out a lot of players.</p>

<p>I don't claim that these five steps are the keys to the success and future of Everquest, but from the five years I've played this game, the above steps seem to be the ones most hindering to new players.  New players are the key to success for Everquest in the years to come.  While a lot of players would rather SOE focus on the top 1%, that 1% is going to go away eventually and only by bringing in new and fresh players can Everquest continue to grow into the future.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
15 August 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Calm Before the Storm</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000026.html" />
<modified>2004-08-09T19:06:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-08-09T18:46:06Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.26</id>
<created>2004-08-09T18:46:06Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today we deliver another gathering of news from across the lands and across the ethereal worlds of the net.  We look at some new changes to test, some discussions of new LDON raids, and the continuing class issue updates.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>We seem to sit within the valley between one expansion and the next.  We had some great new patches since the release of Gates of Discord, and we hear of some nice future updates.  Even with Omens of War on the horizon we sit here in the gap of a slow news week all the same.</p>

<p>One of the most interesting threads floating around within the Everquest community is <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=testing&amp;message.id=2568">Hobart's Test Server Update</a>.  If you ever want to see what new changes we should expect in the next patch, thats the place to go look.</p>

<p>The most recent updates to the test server include a lot of features for the raid tool.  Raid leaders will soon be able to lock and unlock a raid, remove group leader flags from raiders, remove players from any group within the raid, and buttons to put group members into other groups.  These changes are wonderful organizational changes and may be the best changes to the raid tool since its release back in Planes of Power.  Even for smaller two or three group raids, it is wonderful to be able to switch which player is in which group without going through the shuffle.</p>

<p>Now, of course, this will lead to whole fields of raiders going AFK while raids organize and may lead raid leaders to ask for the next logical update: "Give me a Warcraft 3 interface so I can just control the whole raid myself".  I kid, of course.  These changes help raiders quite a bit and feedback from summit raid leaders has been very good.</p>

<p>Along with new raid organization functions comes new consent functions.  Many raiders and even a few groupers want more powerful consenting features for corpse dragging.  More than a few players see death as a nice opportunity for a much needed AFK break frustrating draggers to no end when they must send "CONSENT PLZZ" about fifty times before getting a response.  Soon players can consent guilds, consent groups, and consent raids for dragging.  Again, these improvements help solve a lot of problems mainly for raiding guilds.</p>

<p>Expect new hunting hot spots with the next patch, says Brenlo of the Hairy Feet.  Hot spots, zones with increased zone experience modifiers, help push players to explore some areas to which they might not always travel by rewarding them with much improved experience gain.  The current hot spots existed for some time now and a change is due.  We don't know which zones will turn into hot spots yet, but many await the change.  Hot spots are a great feature for mid-level players.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Stormhammer&amp;message.id=783">thread on the Stormhammer server forums</a> sheds a harsh light on the 12 person LDON raid recently released on Stormhammer and moving soon to the live servers.  While I heard it was tuned for level 55s to 65s, a few players who actually tried it say it is tuned for Elemental, Time, and GoD equipped players.  These equipment restrictions put this raid in the same category as all of the LDON raids.  They are too hard, restricted to only Elemental+ equipped players, and offer too little a reward to make it attractive to those able to accomplish it.</p>

<p>The LDON raid system and the Gates of Discord Expedition system offer a lot of potential for mid-levelers and non-raiders to experience some of the fun and excitement of raiding.  These expeditions can offer raid-level content at any set level with restrictions on who can enter and how often without blocking it behind a rare flag-mob.  This new two-group raid looked like a great way to get 55s to non-raid-equipped 65s into some Lost Dungeon raids but it appears it is just another raid for the top-tier raiders.  With all of the unused raid content of LDON, I don't know why SOE tuned this event for the same players who already ignore LDON raids.</p>

<p>We have seen little new information on Omens of War.  Everyone has questions about how it will support their play-style.  No one knows what levels 66 to 70 will do to older expansions like Lost Dungeons and Gates.  SOE released no official word on existing level 65 focus effects but rumors speak of a nice flexible solution.  The task system interests a lot of people but I still feel too much weight falls onto it.  It may be doomed just by the sheer amount of attention it will get.  I hope it lives up to the expectations but only time will tell.</p>

<p>With the lack of other major news, people spread to their sixteen camps and began the class wars once again.  SOE plans to provide class definition documents that they have worked on for some time now.  These definitions help define what each classes role is in a group and in a raid.  I don't know if they will cover soloing but I do believe they cover a class from levels 1 to 65 (probably to 70).</p>

<p>Every class should bring a combination of abilities to a group at all levels that sets it apart from other classes.  No one class should be better in all ways than another.  Every class should have options and use for soloing, grouping, and raiding.  Every class should have a unique identity and background.</p>

<p>Feedback on the new Mobhunter design has been good and very useful.  Our plan is to switch over to the new version next Saturday.  Please give <a href="http://mobhunter.com/new/">the new Mobhunter design</a> a look and try out the comment system.</p>

<p>I have a small update on one of my secondary requests on Loral's Evil Agenda.  It appears with Nvidia-based video cards, one can span Everquest across two windows.  I had little luck with an Nvidia Geforce 5500; the EQ window never got bigger than about 2400 pixels wide; but the new Geforce 6800 GT runs EQ in a window 3200 x 1150 pixels wide for a total of 3.6 million pixels.  There are a couple of problems, however.  One cannot run in full screen mode or they crash to desktop and the window can't be a full 3200 x 1200 or it slows down to one frame a second.  If you don't mind seeing your start bar all the time, it can be a wild way to play.  </p>

<p>Why would someone want to play across two monitors?  If one runs a "/viewport 1601 0 1600 1150" they get a normal EQ view on the right monitor and a black background on the other.  Chats, maps, inventories, spell gems, buffs, and any other windows you don't have to see right away can be thrown over to the other monitor.</p>

<p>Its a bit of a gimmick but it is a neat way to play.  Here is a picture of <a href="http://mobhunter.com/new/images/eq_dual_monitor.jpg">Everquest running across two monitors</a>.</p>

<p>Look forward to an editorial on Everquest's current state of corpse recovery in the next two weeks and until then, play on.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
7 August 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The New Mobhunter</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000025.html" />
<modified>2004-08-01T01:58:35Z</modified>
<issued>2004-08-01T01:45:33Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.25</id>
<created>2004-08-01T01:45:33Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we release a new version of Mobhunter for our faithful readers to poke with sharp pointy sticks.  Come take a look!
</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Over the past few weeks the tinkering gnomes at Mobhunter installed and tested a new version of the site you so dearly love.  Give the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/new/">New Mobhunter Design</a> a look and try out the new comment system.  There were quite a few reasons for a change and the new version offers a few advantages over the previous version including the following:</p>

<p>- Both the homepage and each article should load faster.</p>

<p>- Both the homepage and each article has a simpler design suitable for printing and reading on smaller screens.</p>

<p>- Comments are now flat instead of threaded.  Read all new comments at once instead of clicking through the threads.</p>

<p>- The links on the homepage are now updated and easier to maintain.</p>

<p>- The site continues to have the same clean look you appreciate.</p>

<p>- Mobhunter now has both a <a href="http://mobhunter.com/new/index.xml">Really Simple Syndication 2.0</a> and <a href="http://mobhunter.com/new/atom.xml">ATOM</a> newsfeed for headline syndication.  For more information about news syndication, read <a href="http://news.yahoo.com/rss/">Yahoo's RSS page</a>.</p>

<p>- For you HTML Tech-heads, the site now supports XHTML 1.1, CSS 2.0, and W3C Accessibility guidelines for the disabled.</p>

<p>- The new version includes dynamic space-age knowledge scripts to add 24% more wacky pop-culture references.  You'll be wearing your pants backwards and singing "Jump, Jump" before you can spell "Chia-pet".</p>

<p>The comment system will take a little bit of getting used to and we may make changes for the articles that get over fifty comments.  Please give it a good test.  Assuming we get the kinks smoothed out, we will release the new version in a couple of weeks.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
31 June 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Swapping, Selling, and Soloing</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000024.html" />
<modified>2004-07-25T02:20:12Z</modified>
<issued>2004-07-25T02:17:26Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.24</id>
<created>2004-07-25T02:17:26Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week we take a look at the most recent patch, some updates to the test server, and some interesting discussions happening around the community. Oh yes, we also overthrow the aristocracy of the uberguild and give power to the people...oh wait, thats next week.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Last week's update gave us quite a few improvements.  Both the LDON adventure-point trade-in and the safe augment removal system went in and both work quite well.  At the last moment SOE changed the refund value to 70% from 50%.  The 20% increase combats the problem of adventurers skipping mid-level gear and saving up for only high-end gear.  The 300 and 750 point armor sets are much more desirable now that one can return them when one decides to upgrade.  With the save augment removal one can move augments from older to newer sets of this armor.</p>

<p>The changes to Lost Dungeons go a long ways towards helping single-group hunters equip themselves for the harder content in Gates of Discord.  While we will not receive new LDON equipment until after Omens of War, these changes bring new life to LDON.</p>

<p>The new tribute change improves the value of Gates of Discord for players under level 55.  The  ability to start and stop tributes gives players a bit more control over these chaotic and expensive effects.  The tribute system is much improved over the original.</p>

<p>The ability for zoning pets made a lot of pet classes happy.  Now the equipment and buffs one gives a pet last a lot longer.  Now if only pet classes could name their pets.  Identity is everything.</p>

<p>A new LDON raid on Stormhammer focused on two groups of level 55 to 65.  Early reports from my Stormhammer spy network state that the raid is quite a bit harder than level 55 equating it more towards Elemental / Time level.  LDON raids offer much unused potential.  SOE could easily build Vox / Naggy type raid encounters for all levels and equipment power using the expeditions of Gates.  They could focus on two, three, four, five, or six groups.  They could bring raiding to everyone, not just the most powerful guilds, but instead they focus most raid content on Elemental / Time level guilds.</p>

<p>Currently LDON raids offer too little reward for their difficulty.  Raiding guilds skip them because of low rewards and everyone else skips them because of their high difficulty. The easiest way to fix this problem is to lower the difficulty and lower the reset time of these events.  They offer too much potential to let them rot.</p>

<p>The Veeshan's Peak revamp made it to live servers with the last update.  A new quest parallel to the old one both lead to a new raid event in Skyfire mountains.  Another hideous shade of the Dar challenges elemental level players and rewards them with access to the revamped elemental-level raiding and hunting zone.  I would complain about another hunting zone blocked by raid-level encounters but there is a lot of unlocked single-group content at the elemental level in Gates now including Riwwi, Tipt, Vxed, and the sewer trials.</p>

<p>Though listed on the top ten items SOE would focus on after the guild summit, it appears we will not see solo instanced adventures at least until after Omens of War.  Again, I would complain except that raid-focused requests such as the instancing of Time also face the same timeline.  There is a simple explanation for the delay; it takes too much time for the amount of work solo instanced adventures require.</p>

<p>Some asked for SOE to reduce the number of required players from three to two or one but this doesn't solve one of the biggest problems with soloing, not everyone can solo and some solo far better than others.  For some, soloing is more profitable than grouping.  That is simply broken.  Grouping should always offer a higher gain than soloing for all classes.  Soloing should be desired only when time restricts a player too much to group.</p>

<p>Only two solutions solve this problem.  Increase the ability for a class to solo where needed or focus content around each class so each class solos effectively.  Both of these changes require extensive work both in development and in balancing.  New solo abilities could unbalance a class in grouping and raiding creating another round of “my class is worse than your class” woes.  New content requires a lot of development work for little gain.  Building an entire zone, even if it's small, for a single class only reaches a fraction of its possible population.</p>

<p>The delay of instanced solo content puts a lot of weight on the shoulders of the new Omens of War task system.  It may be too much weight to bear if Sony doesn't find other solutions.</p>

<p>The real problem comes down to limited content for people with limited time.  People with only 30 minutes to play need something useful to do.  If they're a wizard, they can go solo but if they're a warrior, life isn't as easy.  Tradeskills and quests help but not enough.  Adding new mini-games might help.  Additional quests like the low level newbie quests but for middle and high level hunters might help as well.  Everquest requires short duration content, in whatever form it decides to take.</p>

<p>Hobart's testing thread shows us the updates we'll see in future days.  This includes new multi-slot augments for slot 7 and 8 augments; consenting options for groups, raids, and guilds; and a new system-friendly Everquest that lets you cap your framerate.  My machine's whole purpose in life is to run Everquest so I see little reason to focus it but I suppose some people want to watch others rip their cars in half on Ebaums World while raiding Uqua.</p>

<p>In the last sixty days we've seen many excellent improvements for all players.  While a lot of cynics, myself included, have accused SOE of focusing on raid-level content, they showed their level of support to all players regardless of level or play style.  Gates shifted from an expansion for only a select few to offering up some excellent zones and encounters.  Simple changes like the Gunthak stone, tribute activation, LDON point returns, and the excellent tutorial helps old and new players of every class and level.  A bright future lays ahead.</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Advantages of Point-based Loot</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000022.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-07-13T17:58:53Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.22</id>
<created>2004-07-13T17:58:53Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week&apos;s Mobhunter discusses the advantages of a point-based loot system. While Everquest primarily uses random drops to reward players with equipment, Lost Dungeons of Norrath showed us a new, fair, and powerful loot system. It is my hope that we see systems like this used more in the future.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>This week's Mobhunter discusses the advantages of a point-based loot system.  While Everquest primarily uses random drops to reward players with equipment, Lost Dungeons of Norrath showed us a new, fair, and powerful loot system.  It is my hope that we see systems like this used more in the future.</p>

<p>Along with instanced dungeons and content scaled for all levels, the Lost Dungeons expansion brought us the adventure merchants.  This new method for acquiring treasure rewarded each member of a group with points they could spend on new items.  This article discusses the advantages and disadvantages of the adventure point system.</p>

<p>The adventure point system lets developers tune equipment directly against the effort required to acquire it.  A Breastplate of the Sands always takes 1492 adventure points.  At a minimum this takes 15 hard adventures at level 65 or 15 hours at a minimum to complete.  Most likely it takes 30 hours; 30 normal adventures at level 65.  Random loot, in comparison, may drop the top item the first time or the 500th time.  Even the developers do not know how often it will drop.  Developers control the odds of a dropped item but they do not directly control the drop rates.</p>

<p>Adventure point systems reward all participants in an event evenly.  Adventure point systems also offer clear progression towards equipment goals. Each adventurer wins and each adventurer knows how much closer they are to the item they desire after each adventure. </p>

<p>For years many high-end raiding guilds used a point-system for raid loot distribution called the Dragon Kill Point system.  This system, maintained by the leadership of the guild, awarded loot to the members of the guild who deserved it most based on attendance.  This works well for most guilds but works poorly for less organized groups.  Such systems face corruption or destruction when the leaders either move on or turn sour.  </p>

<p>While the DKP system works well for many high-end guilds, a game-based point system works for everyone.  Any player from any guild can earn points by attending encounters or adventures that award points.  They may hunt with a different group every day but every day they earn points.  For unguilded or lower-end guilds, such systems help players grow steadily towards their goals.  Point-based systems help facilitate pick up groups between players who do not know each other but may one day grow into great friends.  It rewards players without regard to their guild tag and does not require the sacrifice of a group for the progress of an individual.</p>

<p>There are some problems with an adventure point system.  The wide range of armor available on the same point systems in LDON rewards everyone with progress at the most powerful gear.  Because any player of level 20 can go to the Lost Dungeons, they begin earning points towards the high-end armor right away.  The only thing in the way of top-end gear is time.  Regardless of how easy LDON missions become, the points each player earns always lets that player buy new gear.</p>

<p>Dedicated adventure loot for specific content solves this problem.  The sewers in Gates of Discord have a set difficulty � Level 65 pre-elemental level.  The developers know how difficult the sewers are and tuned it for a specific group.  They also know that Elemental armor would benefit this group.  They do not want players gaining elemental loot every time they enter the dungeon so instead they make them rare drops.  The problem with rare drops is that even the developers don't know if this treasure drops the first time or the fiftieth.  The players are not progressing towards this gear, they hope for a good loot table roll and a good roll against the other players.  It can turn players against one another instead of supporting them all equally.</p>

<p>Instead, consider a sewer trial that rewards each player with one sewer point for each completion of a sewer expedition.  Our friend, Mordin Rasp, offers us Elemental-level loot for ten points each.  Do ten sewers, get a nice item.  For the Tipt / Vxed trials, offer a different set of loot on a different point system.  Loot is carefully controlled and is directly based on the difficulty of the encounter and the time one needs to spend in it.  The loot system cannot be corrupted by other players and everyone in the trial earns something for their effort.</p>

<p>Point-based loot should not replace random drops.  Developers design random loot to be a surprise to players, not something to be farmed over and over.  A mixture of point-based loot and random loot helps ensure players can gear up for new content but doesn't remove the excitement of getting a surprise item off of a hideous beast.</p>

<p>Point-based loot works well for progressive loot like the basic armor.  Chest, wrist, leg, feet, head, hands and arm equipment could come from point-based systems while rings, earrings, masks, and necklaces, may still come from lucky random drops.  Players work steadily towards progressive armor while still receiving random equipment for secondary slots.</p>

<p>The point based system of Lost Dungeons of Norrath was one of the great improvements of Everquest.  SOE has no plans to further capitalize on this system.  While it is not the solution to loot in Everquest, it offers many advantages in many situations over random drops and dice roll rewards.  It rewards groups of strangers as well as guilds.  It helps all players earn gear required for further progression.  Much in the same way a Player vs Environment system fosters cooperation, point-based loot systems rewards successful groups, not lucky individuals.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
10 June 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Summit Changes Round 2</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000021.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-07-06T17:43:06Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.21</id>
<created>2004-07-06T17:43:06Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">An upcoming patch this week includes many new changes and improvements for the live servers. This week&apos;s article discusses changes to the tribute system, safe augment removal, LDON adventure point refunds, two new LDON raiding zones, the Veeshan&apos;s Peak revamp, and a few other changes.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>A patch due out next week offers a lot of good changes for players of all levels including safe augment removals, Lost Dungeon adventure point refunds for unused gear, changes to the tribute system, changes to the user interface, some new zones and zone revamps, and changes to pets.</p>

<p>For a price between 1 and 4000 platinum players can purchase solvents that remove augments from items without destroying them.  There are eighteen such solvents with prices that increase depending on the power of the augment.  Low-end augments cost one or two platinum; the 1500 point LDON augments cost 1000 platinum, and raid-level Gates of Discord augments cost around 4000 platinum.</p>

<p>Adventure merchants on test now buy back LDON purchased equipment at 50% of its original cost including the augments mentioned above.</p>

<p>While the changes above don't add more powerful items to the adventure merchants, it helps players replace and purchase more of the existing higher-end items.  The ability to trade in unused equipment allows players to purchase more of the current high-end armor and augments.</p>

<p>New Lost Dungeon raiding zones make their way to Stormhammer and the Live servers next week.  A 40 to 55 Lost Dungeon raid moves from Stormhammer to the regular servers while Stormhammer receives a 55 to 65 raid for sub-elemental equipped raiders.  These additions may help improve the use and perception of Lost Dungeon raids which did not meet the expectations of either lower-power or higher-power raiding groups.</p>

<p>The test server also includes an excellent change to the tribute system.  Players will soon activate tributes when needed with an �activate� button.  Players are immediately charged the point cost for whatever tributes they selected from their tribute master in their home town.  Activated tributes last ten minutes and can be reactivated when needed.  This change drastically improves the tribute system.</p>

<p>Pets for all pet classes will soon zone along with their master.  Like the current beastlord warders and the Wizard's Mr. Flappy Flap, pets for all pet classes will now travel across zones and last during short link-deaths.  This is a huge improvement for pet classes..</p>

<p>Some new changes to the interface include visible buff timers and a numeric mana pool display.  Players have asked to see an exact mana count for years and they will finally have it.  The buff duration timer, though available for 15 leadership points, helps people manage their buffs a lot easier.  Expect to see all new user interfaces with both of these features.</p>

<p>SOE will release a rebuild of Veeshan's Peaks, the first locked raiding zone in Everquest, next week.  Those with a key to the old Veeshan's Peaks have to perform one last piece of the quest to gain access to the new VP while those without the old key must go through a new quest to gain access.  The zone is tuned for Elemental-level raids.</p>

<p>I had more of an opportunity to hunt in the Gates of Discord over the past few weeks and I continue to find improvements since the recent Gates revamp.</p>

<p>A few nights ago I took a group between 60 and 65 into the explorers version of the Sewers.  Players can spawn two different versions of the sewer expeditions; one that does not lead to a flag for Kodtaz and one that does.  The non-flagging version seems a lot easier for a mid 60s group.  Though we saw no rare beasts and received no treasure beyond some platinum, the beasts did not hit nearly as hard as they once did.  We earned over 1% experience per kill, around the same experience as Valor, and did so in an instanced zone.</p>

<p>The last patch included changes to the spell drops in Gates.  Instead of dropping a class specific spell, a rune dropped that could be traded in by any spell casting class for their own class specific spell.  What wasn't mentioned is that the drop rates for these runes was decreased.  Some players report killing over one dozen named mobs and not receiving a single spell.  I know dozens of level 65s who spend a lot of time in Gates and still have not a single spell.  While SOE considers spells to be loot; not everyone should have them all; spells are one of the selling points of a new expansion and when we cannot even get one of them we don't feel like we're getting our money's worth.</p>

<p>Every expansion should have at least one or two spells for sale on top of higher-end spell drops.  Only ancient spells should be so exclusive.</p>

<p>I've had a lot of interesting comments and heated discussions with developers and players regarding equipment progression for single-group hunters.  With the refunds and safe augment removal changes to Lost Dungeons and the items available in Riwwi, Ferubi, Barindu, the sewers, Vxed, and Tipt, it may be possible for a single group to progress into Kodtaz and the Ikkinz trials without requiring elemental and time gear.  A few higher-end items in LDON would not unbalance the game and would help single-group hunters with limited time see more of what Gates has to offer.</p>

<p>Since the guild summit we've seen a lot of improvements to Everquest and next week's patch is no different.  Most of these changes help players of all levels and most classes.  Small improvements like the selective activation of the tribute system, the new user interface labels, the LDON safe augment removal and and point refunds, improve the game significantly.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 July 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Progression in Everquest</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000020.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-06-29T09:32:02Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.20</id>
<created>2004-06-29T09:32:02Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">In this week&apos;s editorial we look at how progression works in Everquest. We discuss what progression is, where it runs free, where it gets blocked up, where it is strong, and where it needs to improve.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p> The short-winded summary:</p>

<p>These days, players have smooth equipment, experience, and zone progression from level 1 to 65 / 100ish AAs. At this point, equipment becomes the only way to progress and the only way to reach new zones. High-level raiders burn through content faster than anyone else, this is why expansions like Gates of Discord and Planes of Power exist. Characters from levels 1 to 64 require new features similar to the new tutorial, the PoK stones, the tribute system, the bazaar, and the LFG tool. Characters at level 65 need new levels, aas, and equipment and need to be able to reach these without raiding. Players at all levels need something meaningful to do in 30 minutes.</p>

<p>The longer pontification:</p>

<p>In an interview on the success of Everquest, one of the original designers attributed this success to three things: dependency between classes, social interaction, and progression. Progression keeps us hunting, raiding, trading, and traveling. Without it, Everquest would be AOL Instant Messenger with graphics. With it, Norrath breathes and her people prosper.</p>

<p>Players progress in Everquest in three main areas: experience, loot, and zones. Everyone from levels 1 to 65 seek out these three almost infinite goals as they travel through Norrath. When one line of progression begins to slow down, we focus on the other two. If two lines slow, we go for the third. If the third slows, we become tired and weak and spend our days writing angry messages to Brenlo.</p>

<p>Levels are the most basic form of progression; offering the largest changes in power but also the largest difficulty in development time. SOE offset the difficulty in implementing level increases with Alternate Advance points. AAs are easier to design and implement, use the same experience method as levels, and don't threaten to unbalance the game. Equipment upgrades are the second most common way to progress in Everquest.</p>

<p>Most don't think about zones as a form of progression, but it is the only one that visibly changes as character levels increase. While gear and levels generally increase arbitrary numbers, zones look and act far differently from one another. One of the reasons we want to get to level 30 is to see Dawnshroud Peaks. One of the reaons we want to get to 45 is to see The Gray. 46 lets us enter the hideous planes of Disease, Nightmare, and (*shiver*) Fear. Each of these zones offers new hideous rats, bats, and spiders for us to destroy. Many of us dreamed of that firey doorway into Fear and dreamed of the day we could face Cazic's hellish minions. Today, many of us can reach that world (Tunare knows why we would want to), and now we dream of the furthest reaches of the Elemental Planes, the Plane of Time, or the lost temples of Taelosia.</p>

<p>Progression changed much over the last five years. New tools like the Knowledge portals, the bazaar, the tutorial, quest armor, and instanced dungeons change how players progress today from how we did so many years ago.</p>

<p>Characters progress in level, equipment, and zones steadily and continuously throughout most of the game. While the shift from soloing to grouping around level 30 becomes more difficult; sometimes it's all we can do to find a group; there is no lack of new items in the bazaar to purchase, new zones to hunt in, or new levels to gain.</p>

<p>From level 20 on, there are instanced dungeons in the Lost Dungeons of Norrath and even a new instanced expedition in Natimbi that allows most characters below 50 solo without interruption by other players. The instanced dungeons offer unlimited experience zones from level 20 to level 65; over-camped hunting zones are history. If you can get three people together, you can at least try a Lost Dungeon even if you aren't successful in the adventure.</p>

<p>Equipment progression is also smooth from level 1 to perhaps level 64. Nice items with restrictive level recommendations can be purchased for low prices, higher end items cost more but upgrades are usually for sale at reasonable prices. Players lower than 65 may want to camp a rare item or two, but they may better spend their time acquiring levels and save that equipment camping time for later. Occasionally one might get a nice dropped item and another may pay for something with adventure points in LDON, but the best value for the time spent comes from the bazaar below 60.</p>

<p>Characters of all levels now have the opportunity for constant experience progression at every level. Every level has zones full of dark-blue beasts that offer between 1% and 2% experience every battle. Alternate Advanced skills help off-set those who raced to 65 and it isn't until each class crosses over perhaps 100 to 150 AA points (each the equivalent of leveling from 50 to 51) that the diminishing returns of the skills outweigh the desire to acquire them. Who really wants to spend four hours so you don't eat food so quickly. Achieving level 65 with 150 AA points takes quite a long time. However, many have spent that time and much more. How do they generally progress? Equipment.</p>

<p>Most level 65s with moderate to high AAs begin to focus on equipment. It is their equipment and the equipment of their guild that gets them into the deeper reaches of the Planes of Power which lead to ... more equipment, which leads to Gates and ... more equipment. The cycle continues. New items are replaced with newer items with 10 more hitpoints. Raiders bank priceless no-drop gear many times over for that new shiny item.</p>

<p>It is at this time when the game changes. While high-end equipment in the Lost Dungeons adventure points exists, as do high-priced items in the bazaar, most powerful equipment for level 65s comes from raiding. In order to progress into new zones, you must have the right equipment. The only way to get that equipment is to raid.</p>

<p>Times were far worse than they are now. In the early days of Planes of Power, the excessive use of flags practically required raiding in order to get any of the three forms of progression. If you wanted new gear, new zones, or experience for new levels and AAs, raiding was your best option. Many friend-guilds split apart to feed the massive raiding guilds. For these guilds, raiding wasn't a fun side-adventure like it was in the days of Nagafen, raiding is their business and they do it every day.</p>

<p>The opening of many lower-tier planes and the new zones in Gates of Discord helped solve narrow direction. The sewers, Tipt, and Vxed offer experience rewards close to the deeper Planes. Zones like Ferubi and the first sets of the Breakdown in Communication quest give two or three groups a shot at some nice gear.</p>

<p>However, the gap still exists. The easiest way to acquire new equipment and new zones, two of the three forms of progression, is to join a raiding guild. Most people hit the wall of usefulness in AA progression at this point, whatever their guild. Equipment is the primary progression method and equipment leads to new zones.</p>

<p>It is this gap I ask SOE to fill. The Lost Dungeon adventure point system lets players work in small increments towards powerful gear. It lets SOE control the flow of equipment by controlling prices. LDON gear is no-drop so it doesn't effect the economy. Many times I recommended that SOE increase LDON gear to off-set the requirements for progression through raiding.</p>

<p>However even this should be a small focus for SOE. SOE needs to make the game more enjoyable at all levels. New features for all players keep them playing. Features like the tribute system (that admittedly needs work), the knowledge portals, soul binders, extra bank slots, armor dyes, and the bazaar help all players.</p>

<p>Low and mid-level players need new features as well although probably not through level, equipment, or zone content but with features that help them find groups or spend shorter amounts of time playing with profitable results.</p>

<p>Not every new feature helps every player, Everquest needs new raiding content, new levels above 65, new equipment beyond Time, especially when we see how far and fast powerful players travel through existing content. For these players, the faster they can get through the game the better, although it leads them faster and faster to the black gaping hole of space known as "the endgame". If they see it, they see the emptiness of their own progression. They see that none of it is real. They travel through that black void and end up in strange worlds of night elves or perhaps even a super-hero fighting armies of TV-helmeted villains. It is the will of the gods and the job of SOE to make sure we never see that black void.</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Book of Gunthak</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000019.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-06-18T19:59:06Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.19</id>
<created>2004-06-18T19:59:06Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today&apos;s article covers this week&apos;s patch including the new Gunthak stone, changes to Time, updates for the PvP servers, strange new slash commands, and a few other updates.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>SOE released a large patch this week, one with many changes from the community feedback they received from the guild summit.  Read the <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/updates/recent_updates.jsp?id=62500">full patch message</a> and then continue for today's editorial.</p>

<p>More collision bug fixes should reduce the bugs we've seen even more.  Since the last update I personally haven't seen any of the big collision issues introduced with the Direct X 9 update.</p>

<p>The Plane of Knowledge now has a stone to the boat in Gunthak down in the evil section of the zone.  Lower level players now have much easier access to the zones from Legacy of Ykesha.  Changes allowing players to group and hunt more quickly are always welcome.</p>

<p>Quite a few changes were made to Gates of Discord.  Most of these changes affect zones beyond Kodtaz, a land few people can see.  The beasts that previously dropped class-specific spells now drop tokens.  Turning in the token returns a class appropriate spell.  In my hunts in the sewers, Tipt, and Vxed, I've seen spells drop only three times and each time it was for a class not present.  This is a welcome change.</p>

<p>A scripting change to Plane of Time shuts down unused instances of Time.  This helps guilds who became stuck because of a previous guild.  While Time instancing is still a large issue for high-end guilds, it doesn't appear it will be fixed before Omens of War is released at the end of August.</p>

<p>An NPC in the Plane of Knowledge will now teleport you to the Plane of Hate for a price.  This change has some wizards in uproar; previously the only way to the Plane of Hate was with a wizard's teleport.  The cost is higher for the NPC version and Plane of Hate isn't exactly the most popular zone so I don't see the change as a large one.</p>

<p>A new /guidehelp system lets players ask for assistance with in-game events such as weddings, GM quests, and server events.  I hope to see more GM events in the future.  GM events breathe life into an otherwise static game.  There is a lot of opportunity to enrich Norrath's lore through GM events like the Fironia Vie event in Kunark did years ago.  Most GM events became smaller in scope and did not affect the story line.  If GMs were handed a script or timeline of events to follow, the story of Norrath could grow over time through these dynamic events.</p>

<p>The raid management window received some changes including the ability to add notes to individual players, a Message of the Day feature, and the much needed ability to drop raid members who have left the zone.  Horror stories of raids having to disband and rebuild because of an AFK raid member are over.</p>

<p>The "/stopcast" command has many people scratching their heads.  The main reason people wanted it was to stop casting on horseback but the command specifically does not work on horseback.  SOE never meant horses to allow mana regeneration while moving.  Horses were designed to be a status symbol.  The meditation while riding became the most popular reason to buy a horse.  SOE has no intentions of "fixing" this "bug" but they will not improve it by allowing riders to cancel spells like they can do on their feet.  This has been a long-standing policy with horses and is unlikely to change.</p>

<p>A new PvP test server includes a variety of changes for player versus player combat.  New point-based armor rewards, new spell balancing, and rumors of an in-game hit-list complete with a reward system threaten to make PvP a fun place to play.  The violent and aggravated PvP server citizens receive little in the way of an update so this is a nice change for them.  As long as they don't bleed into my soft blue server and eat newbies, I'm happy.</p>

<p>New Lost Dungeon armor is under discussion though the developers continue to discuss the exact power of this armor.  Hopefully it's equivalent in scope to Elemental and Time items considering the requirement for such equipment in Gates of Discord.</p>

<p>Keep an eye out for some form of augment swapping in the next update.</p>

<p>While the changes in this week's patch mean little to most players, the updates in the future promise some exciting changes for characters of all levels and all paths.  Keep reading!</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Return to the Sewers</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000018.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-06-12T00:42:51Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.18</id>
<created>2004-06-12T00:42:51Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This week&apos;s news roundup discusses the new Gunthak portal, Time changes, high-cost LDON gear, a new raid instance, augment swapping, LDON item refunds, and Loral&apos;s latest sewer disaster. We at Mobhunter get killed by gnats so you don&apos;t have to!</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>SOE will begin to release changes based on last week's guild summit next week. Only two changes are noted: a Plane of Knowledge stone for Gunthak and a way to clear empty instances of Time, but I wouldn't be surprised to see more soon.</p>

<p>The Gunthak portal helps level 30 to 50 players a lot. It wasn't exactly hard to run through Paineel, Warrens, and Stonebrunt, but its nice to skip them and head right to Gunthak. It saves a lot of time.</p>

<p>The Time change interests Time-capable guilds who ask repeatedly for an instanced Plane of Time. SOE had this at the top of their "future items" list. I heard whispers of a two month process to rebuild Plane of Time into an instanced zone. I would rather see revamps of Fear and Sky than see Time instanced for a select few. Like Sleepers Tomb, North TOV, and Vex Thal, Time will be put aside when the raiding guilds reach deep into Gates of Discord and start to battle in Omens of War. Quick changes to Time are fine but spending two months on it sounds extreme.</p>

<p>SOE is looking at new LDON gear to help smaller groups and guilds gear up for Gates of Discord. This could help open up more options for single-group hunters as well as raiders who need one or two items they can't seem to get in raids. Gates has a lot of single-group instanced trials including the four sewers, Vxed, Tipt, single group hunting in KodTaz, and the three infamous Ikkinz trials. All of these are available to single groups if you're able to get to them and survive. Vxed, Tipt and above are tuned for Plane of Time and "Time+" level players.</p>

<p>The subject of new LDON gear brings up a few unanswered questions. How much will high-end LDON items cost? How powerful will they be? Will there be other requirements to reach them? Some developers feel that simply awarding it for adventure points is too easy, that some sort of greater challenge must exist to acquire these items. I don't agree. While raid leaders and long-time raiders face great challenges, people slip into mature raiding guilds and acquire massive amounts of armor without seeing that challenge. 30 to 60 hours of LDON hunting is long enough to acquire high-end Elemental or Time tier 1 or 2 loot.</p>

<p>Augment swapping is on the way. Augment swapping solvents will most likely require a trade skill to create. There will be a cost associated with augment swapping, but the cost is not yet determined.</p>

<p>SOE also discussed refunding adventure points on LDON items. People may spend 1500 points on a LDON breastplate and then bank it when a new one comes along. SOE hasn't worked out the details yet but a 50% refund has been discussed. Considering my bank is full of my purple Hate armor, my Skyshrine quest armor, and about a dozen outdated bits of treasure, I think a 50% refund is generous. No drop armor is outdated all the time.</p>

<p>I forgot to mention last week that SOE plans to release a level 40 to 55 LDON raid to Stormhammer and then the rest of the servers soon. LDON raids were initially designed for Plane of Time raiders with little else to do. Unfortunately, no raids were developed for lower level or lower power adventurers. The set duration, difficulty, and player numbers of LDON instanced raids allow for extremely tailored raid encounters for all levels. I hope we see more LDON raids for levels 55s to 65s with gear below elemental.</p>

<p>I had a chance to hunt in the Sewers of Barindu recently and enjoyed the changes I saw. The mobs hit for 66% of the damage they used to. Moderately equipped tanks can tank normal mobs and as a Cleric I had to work for a living again without being overwhelmed. The experience was good but could use a boost when compared to the Planes with their graveyards and easy access. Named mobs were still quite hard and a gating mob ended up wiping us out, but the experience was good and the loot was not bad.</p>

<p>My CR was a disaster. I died once in Qinimi on my way back to Barindu, my body got stuck under the earth, and it ended up decomposing before I could get a GM to summon it. I still want more CR options than having to spend two hours after a loss to recover. Death should be painful but there should be options.</p>

<p>Painful CR or not, I will go back to the sewers.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
11 June 2004</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The Guild Summit Report</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000017.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-06-08T09:32:54Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.17</id>
<created>2004-06-08T09:32:54Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">This weekend&apos;s guild summit revealed a lot of history and a lot of the future of Everquest. Read Loral&apos;s report on the state of the game.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>It's been quite a weekend. </p>

<p>SOE loves their game.  Almost the entire staff of designers, artists, programmers, customer service representatives, and management are former players who joined SOE because they love the game.  Every attendee of the guild summit I spoke with never felt that SOE fed them a line.  Only twice did <span title="Brenlo is the best guy ever">Brenlo</span> hold his tongue in response to my questions; one when asked about SOE's plan with IGE and later when asked about focus effects above 65, a subject not yet decided.  Every developer spoke clearly and in detail with every question I asked.</p>

<p>"Gush on, valiant Fanboi!" you shout, but let me reveal the darker side.  Though Smedley said that the bulk of active EQ players were below level 50 I only know of one or two attendees of the sixty that play characters below level 65 and both hardly play anymore.  I learned on the first night that SOE developers have a private forum with raiding guild leaders to discuss raid encounter tuning.  I can't help but wonder why no such forum for single-group players exists.</p>

<p>After nearly ten hours of focus groups and future discussions Brenlo handed out <a href="http://www.thesteelwarrior.org/forum/showthread.php?t=7457">a list of twenty issues</a> SOE would review and implement very soon.  Of these twenty, twelve of them were raid specific and most of the rest were general fixes.  Only one focused on casual content: a solo instanced encounter of some sort.</p>

<p>Many single group issues came up, however, and SOE reacted positively.  I left at least half a dozen copies of <a href="http://mobhunter.com/article.jsp?articleid=-1950615164">Loral's Evil Agenda</a> in the hands of SOE employees including Robert Pfister, Executive Producer of Everquest (who had already read it but politely accepted it before wrapping the remains of his hot dog in it and casually tossing it over his shoulder).</p>

<p><span title="Smed Loves the pirate!">John Smedley</span> stated first that Gates of Discord's release was SOE's worst mistake in five years.  He personally apologized.  I spent my day job listening to managers who speak often and say little.  Smedley was the opposite.  His introduction gave the statistic that most active EQ players are below 50 and revealed that EQ and EQ2 development teams receive royalties for their games individually.  This dispells the theory that SOE is secretly trying to wean us off of EQ and onto EQ2.  The EQ team wants to keep us playing as long as possible.  Rod Humble augmented this address stating that while voices often state that Velious is SOE's best expansion (I still think LDON is), Ykesha is the best selling expansion.  Many attendees attribute this to shared bank space, but I'm not so sure.</p>

<p>Smedley revealed the failed plan to bring out level 65 to 70 during the fifth year anniversary two months ago and Brenlo confirmed that SOE designed Gates of Discord with level 70 in mind.  This explains a lot of the expansion's difficulty.  I spoke with just about anyone who would listen about the overly long duration of sewer, Vxed, and Tipt trials and the designers agreed that four hours for an often failed event was too long.  Whether it's fixed before we see level 70 or not is hard to say.  SOE designed Gates to be very hard.</p>

<p>Later I asked Smedley to confirm the rumor that we would have new PC models before the end of 2004 and he confirmed it.  SOE is outsourcing the project to another company, an act that vexes SOE artists.  It's their baby and they want to do the models but there simply isn't the time, a statement we heard often.  The developers who spoke at the initial meeting stated that they want and expect Everquest to stand up graphically to other current massive online games including EQ2.  The graphic update we battled through recently helps us get there.</p>

<p>The shifting number of allowed players in raid encounters between Planes of Power, Lost Dungeons, and Gates of Discord frustrates a lot of guilds and leads to many players quitting.  Everquest's designers stated that 54 is the new official number for future Everquest raids.</p>

<p>Though focused on raid content, all love of the single-group gamer is not lost.  Brenlo confirmed that new high-end elemental level equipment will update the LDON adventure merchants.  Single-group hunters will be able to gear up for Gates of Discord content without Time or Elemental access.  Omens of War includes only one flagged zone though certain encounters may be locked.  This resembles Kunark, Velious, and Luclin expansions where most of the content was open to all players.  Omens of War includes zones for all players tuned to help characters level up to 70.</p>

<p>SOE based the high cost of AAs on the experience found in the Plane of Fire, a zone many single-group hunters cannot yet reach.  While Omens zones will offer experience zones to help non-flagged hunters, SOE should up the experience in Tipt, Vxed, and the sewers closer to Fire than they are now.  The difficulty in reaching these zones and the difficulty in the encounters warrants the experience boost.</p>

<p>While SOE designed Epic 2.0s to be the best class items available to the most powerful raiders, Epic 1.5s will be available to high level players and require only one or two groups to complete.</p>

<p>It was an amazing weekend filled with the obnoxious rings of cell phones, one so loud that its owner cried out to his deity in shock and horror.  The icy glare of the guild leader from the dark and frightening Rallos Zek server gazed over us bluebies like we had green target circles under our feet.  Twice I became stuck between Gilfalas of <a href="http://p202.ezboard.com/fpaladinsofnorrathgeneral.showMessage?topicID=19890.topic">Paladin's of Norrath</a> and Raaj of <a href="http://www.thesteelwarrior.org/forum/showthread.php?t=7457">The Steel Warriors</a> who crashed together in debate over Defensive.</p>

<p>Ryan Robinson, the Sheriff of Norrath and customer support supervisor told the story of a trade scam buried under over thirty transfers from different accounts that took two weeks to track down, but they did.  This fellow needs his own Stephen Bocco police drama.  40% of the 47,000 petitions the CS department receives monthly are lost items and 70% of these are scams of some sort.  A lot of CS's day is chasing ghosts.</p>

<p>Here's a brief summary of the things I found most interesting:</p>

<p>- We will have new PC models by the end of the year.<br />
- New high-end high-cost items will be available on LDON adventure merchants.<br />
- Gates was designed for level 70, thats why its so hard.<br />
- Rallos Zek is a chaotic server of horror and villainy.<br />
- Gilfalas just wants "a little something!"<br />
- Omens of War has only one locked zone, the rest of it is open to all players.<br />
- While Epic 2.0s are for the uberist of the ubers, Epic 1.5s are available to the rest of us.<br />
- Some sort of instanced solo adventure is in the works.<br />
- The Omens of War task system, a small 30 minute quest system, will be available to levels 20 and above.<br />
- There will be a quest for Gates of Discord spells, though details aren't available.<br />
- Chat channels cross over between Everquest and Everquest 2.<br />
- The development team wishes they never called it Everquest 2.<br />
- Soon augments can be removed and replaced on other items.<br />
- Smedley loves pirates.<br />
- The graphic engine update we went through will help EQ stay graphically competitive with other MMOGs.</p>

<p>There are dozens of other reports of the summit including posts on <a href="http://www.thesteelwarrior.org/forum/showthread.php?t=7457">Steel Warriors</a>, <a href="http://p202.ezboard.com/fpaladinsofnorrathgeneral.showMessage?topicID=19890.topic">Paladins of Norrath</a>, <a href="http://www.thesafehouse.org/viewtopic.php?p=145875">The Safehouse</a>, <a href="http://forums.gucomics.com/viewtopic.php?t=2220">GU Comics</a>, <a href="http://www.therunes.net/forums/viewtopic.php?t=4178">The Rune</a>, <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=5406">Caster's Realm</a>, <a href="http://thedruidsgrove.org/forums/showthread.php?t=8094">The Druid's Grove</a> and a lot of places I haven't found yet.  Druid's Grove even <a href="http://thedruidsgrove.org/forums/showthread.php?t=8098">has pictures</a> including some unfortunate ones of <a href="http://www.thedruidsgrove.org/images/summitspring2004/bus1.jpg">your fearless writer, Loral</a> (I'm the one in the black shirt on the right).</p>

<p>I received a lot of positive feedback from at least six other attendees I spoke with on the way back home and feedback from the postings above agree.  SOE is working hard to improve Everquest and fix previous mistakes.  Though not all of my agenda points were met; mainly what I wanted to hear was "Lost Dungeons 2 in December"; I am very happy with the direction things are going.  I look forward to the next few months.</p>

<p>Our world is strong.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
7 June 2004</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000016.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-06-01T02:11:35Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.16</id>
<created>2004-06-01T02:11:35Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Next week SOE is hosting a visit for guild leaders and community representatives to talk about the state of the Everquest and get feedback. This article outlines the evil agenda I plan to bring to San Diego and hand to the Everquest developers.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Next week SOE is hosting a visit for guild leaders and community representatives to talk about the state of the Everquest and get feedback.  This article outlines the evil agenda I plan to bring to San Diego and hand to the Everquest developers.  </p>

<p>I cannot speak for the entire community. I read the message boards every day.  I play hours every night.  I talk to low level players, high level players, raiders, casual hunters, trade-skillers, and everyone in between and I have no doubt that I am missing the majority of opinions.  We have no idea what all 400,000 players think.  Few players post to message forums. Few players send feedback. Few players even bother to read websites like this one.  It's impossible to know what they think needs to be fixed. I can, however, give my view on the state of Everquest and the features I believe will help the game. </p>

<p>Lets begin Loral's Evil Agenda:</p>

<ul>
<li>Focus on single-group content.</li>
<li>Offer easier corpse recovery in old world and GoD zones.</li>
<li>Offer quest, adventure-point, or vendor alternatives for level 65 and GoD spells.</li>
<li>Offer progressive content in 30 minutes or less.</li>
<li>Add higher-end equipment to LDON adventure merchants.</li>
<li>Add more Lost Dungeon content including zones, adventure types, and rewards.</li>
<li>Make the Sewers, Vxed, and Tipt easier to get to, easier to recover from, easier to battle in, and offer more significant rewards.</li>
</ul>

<p>Focus on single-group content.  The six-person group was once the single unit that all content was balanced against.  Planes of Power and Gates of Discord put raiding and raid-equipped players above moderately equipped single groups.  Increase content for single groups.  Increase high-end equipment opportunities for single group hunters.  Use adventure merchants, expeditions, and instanced zones to bring more content and progression opportunities to single group hunters.  Make the six person group the focus of Everquest again.</p>

<p>Offer easier corpse recovery for old world and Gates of Discord zones.  Planes of Power and Lost Dungeons of Norrath offer excellent escapes for nasty corpse recoveries.  Befallen, Blackburrow, Kaesora, Dalnirs Crypt, and all other old-world dungeons offer no such option.  The Plane of Fear has a higher risk than any raiding zone in Planes of Power.  Don't punish Befallen hunters with horrible corpse recoveries while Plane of Fire hunters recover in 20 minutes.</p>

<p>Offer quest, adventure-point, or vendor alternatives for level 65 and GoD spells.  For single group hunters, level 65 spells are rare and gates of discord spells are almost non-existent.  Offer quests or adventure point systems for high level spells.  Give casual hunters a clear path to these spells.   Place level 65 and GoD spells on LDON adventure merchants or add a similar system to GoD.</p>

<p>Offer progressive content in 30 minutes or less.  Many players have limited play time.  There is little progress anyone can make in thirty minutes.  Many people solo and work on trade skills when they have limited time.  Improve solo content; improve trade skill content; add adventure-point based task systems.</p>

<p>Add higher-end equipment to LDON adventure merchants.  Lost Dungeons offers a fair and consistent method for acquiring equipment.  Players are able to progress towards powerful gear in small steps.  This equipment lacks power when compared to Elemental, Time, and GoD equipment.  Add high-cost equipment with two slot 3s, higher power melee weapons, and augments with the higher-end focus effects such as Marr's Gift, Preservation of Xegony, Mana Regeneration +3 and +4, and Faerune.</p>

<p>Add more Lost Dungeon content including zones, adventure types, and rewards.  Many players love Lost Dungeons and want more adventure types, zones, and lower power raid content.  Add new adventure types and rebalance the rescue and assassination quests.  Increase the cash and experience rewards.  Use the expedition feature of Gates of Discord in Lost Dungeons so people can come and leave in the early parts of an adventure.</p>

<p>Make the Sewers, Vxed, and Tipt easier to get to, easier to recover from, easier to battle in, and offer more significant rewards.  These zones are very hard for their current rewards and many powerful groups fail in the last few minutes of a four hour hunt.  Tune these zones for high level characters without raid-level equipment.</p>

<p>Minor Quips and Suggestions:</p>

<p>Fix sitting animations for male elves.  Why do I still look like a statue when I sit?</p>

<p>Revamp Sky and Fear.  Fear is the only zone left where people cannot get a safe summon at the zone in.  It is the hardest of the Planes with the worst loot.  The time for three-day sky raids is over.  Let Call of the Hero work in Sky.</p>

<p>Debug quests.  A lot of people fail on quests when they hand in stacks.  The rat whisker quest still eats stacks of rat wiskers without returning them.  Buggy quests frustrate players of all levels.  Add better quality control to quest and trade skill content.</p>

<p>Support dual-monitor systems.  I'd love to put my buff and extra chat windows on another monitor while using my main monitor for the world view, target, and group windows.  Duel monitor support adds a lot of capability for high-end systems.</p>

<p>Offer partial refunds on adventure-merchant augments.  A 50% refund wouldn't unbalance the game and would give people some points back for future gear.</p>

<p>No more rats, bats, and spiders.  I've fought these throughout my 65 levels and 260 AA points.  Its time I fought nothing smaller than a armadillo.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
31 May 2004<br />
Loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Caves of the Kobold Slavers</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000015.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:02:55Z</modified>
<issued>2004-05-27T10:10:57Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.15</id>
<created>2004-05-27T10:10:57Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">A new patch today brought us a new tutorial, some fixes to the Plane of Knowledge crashes, and some other stuff. We also look at the Gates revamp and Sony&apos;s new pricing plans.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>It's been a while since we've had an update but this one has a couple of neat things in it.  Today's patch included a new tutorial, possible fixes to the Plane of Knowledge crashes, some UI updates, and a couple of more tidbits.</p>

<p>Last week I started up a level 1 Berserker on the test server to try out the new tutorial and I was very impressed.  It's a mixture of local and server-based quests and a new generic low-level zone.  It walks new players through Everquest's complex interface as well as it can.  It makes great use of the "Find PC" yellow magic trail to lead a new character from NPC to NPC.  As a veteran player, I cannot give a truly objective analysis but it appears it will do a good job of teaching new players the basics of our game.  The rewards for walking through the tutorial include enough experience to reach level 3 and a powerful charm.</p>

<p>Proper marketing and improvements to simplify Everquest's interface bring new players online.  The more players in Everquest, the better the content and service we'll see.</p>

<p>Which leads us to Sony's new pricing plan.  For $120, a customer receives a one year subscription to Everquest and all seven current expansions.  This is an excellent deal but few new players are willing to make a $120 commitment on a game they haven't played yet.  This pricing plan works very well for players with multiple accounts.  There will soon be a package called "Everquest: Platinum" (how's that for false IGE style advertisement?) containing all expansions up through Gates of Discord for $30.  A $10 version called Everquest: Chronicals (Everquest: Copper?) is said to contain the old world, Kunark, Luclin, and Ykesha.  The strange set of expansions is due to their inclusion of new races.  My Neriak spies tell me future low-priced expansions will include mid-level and high-level content to go along with this beginner's set.</p>

<p>The biggest problem we've seen recently are the Plane of Knowledge crashes.  The developers posted many updates to the problems but crashing in the most popular zone in EQ builds a lot of frustration within Sony's paying customers.  We can hope this patch helps the problem; if not, Sony can expect quite a few more posts on the tech forums.</p>

<p>Sony released little news on Omens of War but some changes to the Test server already <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=druidbalance&amp;message.id=608">sent spell casters into spasms</a>.  The spells don't even have names yet but people are already wearing their "My Spells Only Do 54.918DPS: Everquest is Dead!" T-shirts.  I'll assess Omens of War when I've actually played it, thank you very much.  IGN posted an <a href="http://pc.ign.com/articles/518/518286p1.html">article about Omens of War</a> with only a few bits of information we didn't know.  I found one line particularly disturbing: "There will be around 20 new zones with this expansion, most of them geared toward GoD-capable players."  From what I've experienced and what I've heard, a "GoD-capable player" is ... no one.  Say it ain't so, Brenlo.</p>

<p>Which brings us to the revamp of Gates of Discord.  I see little change for all of the excitement Sony made over the new revamp.  I still died from see-invis mobs in Barindu after failing at the fourth hour on a Vxed hunt.  I still don't get experience like I do in restricted zones of Fire and Earth.  I've seen no Gates spell drop.  I'm reminded of the fifty "Planes of Power spell drops have increased" patch messages when I've still only seen one non-raid rune drop in all of my days in the Planes.  The changes to KodTaz and above may be nice; apparently it's easier to get into Qvic; but what about the other 93% of casual high-level players (lies, damndable lies, statistics)?  I don't expect another Gates revamp. I'd rather see improvements to Lost Dungeons of Norrath and I look forward to Omens of War; but this big change didn't seem very big to me.</p>

<p>At least young Bolmer, the level 1 Berserker, can take out my frustrations on the skull of a Kobold slaver in the dastardly tunnels of Whatever.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
26 May 2004<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Something New</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000023.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-05-16T12:54:08Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.23</id>
<created>2004-05-16T12:54:08Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">As our faithful readers already know, change is slow to come here at Mobhunter. The look, the functionality, and the Planes of Power ad have all been constants you&apos;ve been able to count on for years. But it&apos;s time that we add something new.

Read on to discover our latest addition... </summary>
<author>
<name>Csenicier</name>


</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Things are busy for me here at the Mobhunter compound. Not only is it my job to make Loral's coffee, but I also keep his cup fresh while he's typing on our strict deadlines. Add to that my time spent on the phone begging SoE to hire me as Moorgard's coffee guy and it becomes clear that there's little time left for things like site design and maintenance.</p>

<p>I have taken some time from my sycophantic toadying to add a little something new to the Mobhunter franchise. I think it's pretty self explanatory. Give it a try.</p>

<p>Keep in mind that this, like everything here at Mobhunter, is a work in progress. I have other cool features that aren't implemented yet. And clearly, not every EQ server is yet supported. If people like this tool, I'll make it better.</p>

<p>Post here to let me know what you think. </p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Whispers of War</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000014.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-05-10T23:46:18Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.14</id>
<created>2004-05-10T23:46:18Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">We received a lot of big news last week. Today we discuss the Omens of War and the Gates of Discord retune. Enjoy!</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Content has many forms.  New levels, gear, encounters, abilities, and zones excite us.  It's the one thing that separates Norrath from AOL Instant Messenger.  It is the context of our existence in Norrath.  New features, zone revamps, even small UI patches are a form of new content to explore.  Last week revealed quite a lot of upcoming content.  Please spear me before I say the word content again.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/omensofwar/">Omens of War</a> whisper past us in the bars and inns of Norrath's cities.  It appears the Wayfarer Brotherhood has bitten off a little more than it can chew.  The wars of Mata Muram begin in two months.</p>

<p>SOE revealed few details about Omens of War but what they have revealed created quite a stir.  New epics, new levels, a task system, a guild tribute system, new titles, and new graphics are all listed on the Omens of War website.  There were a couple of other bits of discovered information including <a href="http://forums.thesafehouse.org/viewtopic.php?t=4552">zone names</a> that sound a lot like Lost Dungeon zone names (West Battlegrounds A, B, C, D) and notice that epic 2.0s are <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=TNZ&amp;message.id=76140#M76140">separate quests</a> from original epics.  One won't have to turn in or even acquire the original epics before acquiring the new epics.  Even the Everquest board moderators don't seem to know much about this new expansion.</p>

<p>I hope to see a short-duration task system available to all levels.  Why should the level 20s be the only ones to deliver propaganda between the Wayfarer camps?  I'm already collecting zombie skin and vampire teeth for them, a demeaning job for a high priest of Tunare if I do say so myself, so why not make me the Norrathian equivalent of FedEx?  Maybe I can get some special shorts!</p>

<p>Nothing is yet known about the zones, the encounters, or the rewards.  I dream of another adventure point system.  I loved the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/message.jsp?articleid=-563313134&amp;msgid=-2095349685#message">Wayfarer cookie idea</a> posted by Pverex on last week's article.  I dream of zones that scale for levels 20 to 70.  I dream of Lost Dungeon style adventures with expedition style control.  I dream of a smooth experience curve above 65 so I can still hunt with my level 50 friends.  </p>

<p>The release date of Omens of War appears to be the end of July.  <a href="http://mobhunter.com/message.jsp?articleid=-563313134&amp;msgid=-496660957#message">Rod Humble stated</a> on my well received previous Mobhunter article that the beta for Omens will be wider than Gates of Discord was. I look forward to the release of new details.</p>

<p>The next big bit of news is the <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=62046">revamp of Gates of Discord</a>.  A lot of folks aren't happy with Gates for a variety of reasons.  The expansion appeared tailor made for Elemental / Time guilds but strange, difficult, and buggy encounters and a lack of good loot disappointed a lot of them.  Everyone who faced it felt that the beasts of Taelosia hit a bit too hard.  I still cannot walk ten feet through a town without someone reminding me of the 1200 point-hitting gnat that turned me into holy dungeon pizza.  Lower level players found little reason to purchase Gates.  Only one zone is huntable below 50, tributes became too expensive for their usefulness, and new tradeskills were often incomplete.</p>

<p>Details of the revamp are still hazy and only when we try Gates after the revamp will we know how good the changes were.  The proposed changes include zone retuning, experience modification, easing travel, lowering output damage, increasing spell drops (again), increasing cash drops, and a reduction in required flags for Ikkinz (wherever that is).  These sound good but even <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=62073">Brenlo's second explanation</a> left out a little detail.  Exactly what were the intended level ranges of the five open zones?  What will the tuning of these zones entail?  We'll know Wednesday, I assume.</p>

<p>In the mean time, begin preparing for war.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>The End May Be Nigh Someday!</title>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/000013.html" />
<modified>2004-07-23T13:01:26Z</modified>
<issued>2004-05-05T23:46:45Z</issued>
<id>tag:mobhunter.com,2004://2.13</id>
<created>2004-05-05T23:46:45Z</created>
<summary type="text/plain">Today we discuss Everquest 2&apos;s beta registration, this week&apos;s patch and its results, the death of Afterlife, and a special report on Gates of Discord retuning.</summary>
<author>
<name>Loral</name>
<url>http://loralciriclight.com/</url>
<email>loral@loralciriclight.com</email>
</author>

<content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
<![CDATA[<p>Sony began accepting applications for beta-testing Everquest 2.  It's no surprise to hear that thousands of people submitted applications.  Would-be beta-testers hammered the application servers resulting in some typical page request errors, duplicate applications, and a host of other problems.  In order to sign up for the beta, one must apply from the computer one plans to play on.  This prevents people from applying on most work machines.</p>

<p><a href="http://eqiiforums.station.sony.com/eq2/tracker?role=Dev">Moorgard and Faarwolf</a> have been keeping people well informed on the process and procedures of beta signups.</p>

<p>Sony released a small patch today.  The changes included one's ability to change his or her surname, hitpoint regeneration improvements, and /rewind.</p>

<p>The ability to change one's surname comes as a small surprise.  GMs will cease to be flooded with requests to change surnames.  It is now easier to annul the many failed in-game marriages we often hear about.  It's a small change but I see no disadvantage.</p>

<p>Hitpoint regeneration now improves the longer you sit.  This regeneration allows players a chance to solo and recover a bit easier.  Wizards, Druids, and a few other classes have an easier time soloing than rogues, warriors, and other melee classes.  This regeneration gives other classes at least a chance at soloing successfully.  The problem shows up when we consider grouping.</p>

<p>Grouping builds relationships.  Grouping teaches people new skills.  Grouping helps people learn more about the game than they would find out on their own.  Grouping helps people find guilds. Grouping builds social skills, both in-game and in real life.  To throw that away for soloing is to remove the whole reason to play Everquest.</p>

<p>Everquest offers many advantages for grouping.  Grouping is necessary for Lost Dungeons of Norrath.  Grouping offers a large experience bonus over soloing.  Most of the game's content below level 65 is tuned for single group hunts.  The single group is the most common unit of gameplay in Everquest.</p>

<p>These hitpoint regeneration changes are good, however.  This change helps individuals and groups without healers alike.  I don't expect it to harm the game at all.</p>

<p>Our Neriak spies returned with reports that Sony is <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/community/dev_view.jsp?id=62046">retuning Gates of Discord</a>.  Tuning changes include experience boosts, tuning of Natimbi, Qinimi, Barindu, Riwwi, and Ferubi, NPC max damage mitigation so clerics can tank (relax, I'm kidding, I meant knights), increased spell drops, easier zone travel, NPC innates (I have no idea what this is), and the inclusion of some non-agro animal mobs. All of these changes look excellent and I applaud Sony's attention to these problems.</p>

<p>Afterlife, one of the top guilds across all servers, quit on Wednesday.  Their post was the first negative posting I can recall seeing on their website.  They felt strongly enough to break two metaphors in one sentence.  I had always enjoyed Afterlife's objective and clean updates and its a shame to not only see them leave but to see them leave with such a poisoned tongue.  At least they didn't post a count-down.</p>

<p>I'd be surprised if every member of Afterlife cancels their subscriptions and stops paying.  I imagine the guild may disband; I imagine many of them will go to another game; I'd even expect some to return.  It would surprise me if every member felt as strongly as the post stated.</p>

<p>Obviously if that many people have been having no fun since The Rathe (an encounter they defeated a year ago), I have to question why it would take so long for them to quit.  It sounds like we all need a reading of the divine article <a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001076.html">Why I Play Everquest</a> by one of the most highly respected writers of Everquest news, lore, and editorials.  Remember the golden rule:</p>

<p>Have Fun Every Day You Play.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>

</content>
</entry>

</feed>