<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Mobhunter</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/" />
  <modified>2005-11-21T21:22:02Z</modified>
  <tagline></tagline>
  <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7</id>
  <generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="3.01D">Movable Type</generator>
  <copyright>Copyright (c) 2005, Loral</copyright>
  <entry>
    <title>The Great Depths Reitemization</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001435.html" />
    <modified>2005-11-21T21:22:02Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-11-21T09:12:43-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1435</id>
    <created>2005-11-21T14:12:43Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week SOE updated over one thousand items in the Depths of Darkhollow expansion.  Today we discuss these changes and what they mean for Everquest overall.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last week SOE released a patch that upgraded over 1000 items in the Depths of Darkhollow expansion.  These upgrades were limited to single-group non-monster missions and drops in static zones off of random or named beasts.  This is the largest upgrade in equipment that any expansion has ever received and SOE made the intent clear:</p>

<p>"After DoD launched, we saw a lot of feedback from players that non-raid loot rewards weren't't appropriate for the difficulty of the content. Carefully evaluating the cases players brought up led us to audit the model that has been used for itemization for several expansions now."</p>

<p>"The old itemization model was based around the top end single group gear being roughly 50% of the stats of top end raid level gear. This worked fine when it was first implemented, but as stats have increased, so too has the gap between raiders and non-raiders. Since content is tuned with player power in mind, this has caused a growing gap in the difficulty of expansion zones, in turn leading to the problems players have been reporting."</p>

<p>"After a lot of evaluation on the potential impact, we decided to change the itemization model to bring single group gear closer to the level of raid attainable gear. Beyond providing more tangible upgrades in the expansion, this change should also have a number of positive effects on the game as a whole and is something we will continue to use when making items in the future."</p>

<p>You can read the full report over at <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9920">Caster's Realm</a> or <a href="http://crucible.samanna.net/viewtopic.php?t=1200">Samanna.net</a>.</p>

<p>Equipment receive an average of about 125% to 150% upgrade in statistical power, mostly in hitpoints and mana.  Few focus, combat, or regeneration effects were modified except in cases where the rewards dropped in the wrong paths.  For example, some Hive-level missions dropped Corathus-level loot.</p>

<p>The boards lit up with responses, both positive and negative as usual.  One post, <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=141471">DoD Upgrades Went Too Far</a> discusses the issue of single-group loot eclipsing raid loot in Planes of Power.  </p>

<p>To me, this clearly shows just how out of proportion the loot has been over the past four years.  Few complained very long when better Kunark single-group loot dropped than that received off of old-world dragon raids.  Few complained when Velious single group loot outperformed Kunark loot.  Only Planes of Power offered such powerful loot and at such extreme quantities; thirty six 150 to 200 hp and mana drops in a single Plane of Time raid; that players had little choice but to raid in Planes of Power even four years after the expansion's release.</p>

<p>This new loot opens up a lot of opportunity.  For one, single group players now have a clear and long line of progression in level, alternative advancement, content, and equipment without ever having to raid.  Play time is now the only factor in the advancement of single-group hunters.</p>

<p>This also offers up alternative equipment progression areas for guilds or raiding groups.  Instead of farming the same raids over and over to gear up enough people for the next step, guilds can augment their raid rewards with single group items in high end DoD hunts.  This new jump in power should be able to take guilds beyond Plane of Time and into the deeper Gates, Omens, Dragons, and Depths raids.  As individual power grows, the opportunity for pick-up raids increases as well.</p>

<p>This jump in power also opens up more content in old worlds for non-raiders such as the MPG trials and the Ikkinz expeditions.</p>

<p>Not every item received a proper upgrade.  With fifty missions, five static zones, and over one thousand items, a few slipped through without upgrades.  For example, two of the four rewards on the the Jarzarrad the Prophet missions were upgraded to 210 mana items but the other two, the rewards for the harder two missions in the set, stayed at their original 150.  I expect we will see these reported inconsistencies addressed in the next patch.</p>

<p>Some items seemed to improve a bit too much.  A humorous post by my friend, the Kyv, states that <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=141619">the Gear Gap between Raiders and Casuals has gone too far in the other direction</a>.  He cites two new augments dropping in Illsalin and Dreadspire with well over 100 hitpoints and mana.  These two single-group acquirable rewards, though currently available to single-group raid-equipped players, offer better statistics than the rewards from raid encounters in the same zone.  While closing the equipment gap between raiders and non-raiders is an admirable goal, the intent wasn't to trivialize raids within the same expansion.  I expect we will see these augments change soon.</p>

<p>As the equipment on single-group missions improved, so did the population of these areas.  Instead of most players focusing on easy monster missions to polish off a few AAs before a raid, players now hunt in difficult missions for excellent experience and nice usable loot.</p>

<p>This latest patch also tuned the difficulty of the missions in Depths of Darkhollow to offer a smoother curve of progression.  The intent is for single group hunters to have a smooth line of progression from easier missions through the harder ones.  With around fifty single group missions, the progression path and the loot will help steer players through a long range of missions and story arcs instead of focusing them on only one area like the Faerie monster mission.</p>

<p>Monster missions also received some updates.  SOE lowered the experience of easier monster missions such as Queen Noknok's Tomb and released two new monster missions, one in Paw and one in Solusek A.  Monster missions are in danger of the creator problem in Dragons of Norrath.  The Creator mission offered the best reward for the fastest mission.  Instead of trying out every mission available in Dragons, players focused on the one that offered the best reward for the smallest effort.  Even those wishing to try other missions often had to choose between hunting the Creator or not hunting at all.</p>

<p>Rashere, the lead designer, <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=TNZ&message.id=214201#M214201">wrote a note</a> on SOE's intent to offer scaling rewards based on popularity.  As certain missions grow in popularity, their experience reward lowers and those on the least popular missions increases.  This keeps players traveling across many missions instead of focusing on the same one.</p>

<p>This patch helped fix the largest problem in Depths of Darkhollow: low powered rewards.  It also did much to improve the game overall.  The power rift caused by large amounts of high powered equipment in Planes of Power has gone away.  Single group hunters now have a clear progression to excellent items and the content their new power will make available.  It also helps players gear up for higher-end raiding guilds and lessens the requirements of raiding guilds to gear up new members.  This is a great change for Everquest.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
19 November 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Interview with Maddoc on Live Events</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001434.html" />
    <modified>2005-11-17T00:21:37Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-11-11T09:46:53-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1434</id>
    <created>2005-11-11T14:46:53Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral interviews Jason Mash, Maddoc, a senior designer for Everquest on the topic of Everquest&apos;s Live Events.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>This week I had the opportunity to sit down (well, email) Jason Mash, senior designer for Everquest and the brain behind some of the more recent Live events including the War of Antonica event we saw recently.  Let's dig right in.</p>

<p>Loral: What is your general philosophy, doctrine, and purpose behind live events?  Why do you do them?  With what questions do you begin?</p>

<p>Maddoc: One of my most fond memories of EverQuest, especially in the early days, were the random events that would occur throughout the world in various zones. For instance, in Qeynos Hills, a skeleton army would spawn occasionally and GM's (who played some much larger, meaner skeletons) would participate in the event. I remember a feeling sense of wonder and awe that I was participating in this event, helping to rid the world of these terrible undead minions.</p>

<p>The overall purpose behind the design of live events is basically to invoke the same sense of awe and wonder. Typically, we want to create an event that the players can interact with, influence in some cases, enjoy participating in, and ultimately have a lot of fond memories of. We also want to expand on existing lore, sometimes in very subtle ways, which adds a layer of community coherence by giving them something to collectively try and figure out and discuss. For those who are interested in the lore, that's always an aspect that they enjoy, and I like to help foster that as much as possible.</p>

<p>Loral: What goes into the design of a live event?  How long does it take?</p>

<p>Maddoc: A live event goes through a number of phases, the first (and probably most important) of which is the planning stage. We figure out what our goals are for the particular event, what lore we want to present to the players, how we want them to interact with the event, how we want them to influence the event, and ultimately the sequence of events that the players will encounter as the event progresses.</p>

<p>A live event doesn't have a standard amount of time that it takes to build since it's very tightly and directly tied to the scale of the event. I (along with Prathun, Absor, and Keridon) had roughly 6 weeks to design and implement the Retake of Grobb live event. That particular event was very large scale, spanning an unprecedented 90% of the old-world EverQuest zones, which was able to be done due to the amount of time we had to work on it.</p>

<p>Loral: What sorts of things did you learn when doing the War of Antonica events leading to the retake of Grobb?</p>

<p>Maddoc: The Retake of Grobb event was a learning experience for everyone involved, giving us an opportunity to do something that had never been done in EverQuest before, while at the same time giving the player's something global to participate in and affect to a certain extent.</p>

<p>There were only a couple things that I would like to change about the event progress, the most notable of which being the presentation of some of the more subtle lore points. Some of them were a little too obscure or dependant on players being in the right place at the right time, so I'd make them a little more obvious.</p>

<p>Loral: How do live events fit into the release of a new expansion?  Tell us a little about the design and story of the Depths of Darkhollow release event.</p>

<p>Maddoc: In conjunction with the ongoing storyline in EQLive, we incorporated the events that would lead Norrathians into Darkhollow. The storyline had been planned months in advance when we first conceived of the expansion.</p>

<p>The turning point began when Lanys T'Vyl, child of the Prince of Hate, entered Neriak, the dark elf city, and demanded the help of Queen Cristanos Thex in the way of a sacrifice for the greater good of dark elves. Lanys had a plan, specifically magic knowledge, which could elevate their evil race above all in Norrath. Cristanos obliged and offered up her very own husband, King Naythox Thex, as the sacrifice for Lanys' designs.</p>

<p>By deceiving and drugging Naythox, Cristanos made her husband ready for the ritual Lanys had planned and there was a procession from the dark elf city into the nearby Nektulos Forest. There was a decision to conduct the ritual outside the city should anything go terribly wrong.</p>

<p>For many days, Cristanos' necromancers of her Dead guild chanted in a circle around Naythox Thex as they worked the magic of the curse Lanys mapped out for them. There were many interruptions as the army of the light and good in the world, Norrath's Keepers, attempted to thwart the queen's and Lens's efforts. Skirmishes took place across the forest until, one night, Lanys, the leader of the Dark Reign army, and Firiona Vie, leader of Norrath's Keepers, met on the battlefield.</p>

<p>As the battle reached a fever pitch, the curse upon Naythox was almost complete and was seemingly fed by the chaos around it. While all in the forest focused on the clashing blades of war, Cristanos saw her opportunity to withdraw her husband to act in her own scheme and teleported them both back to Neriak, the dark elf city, with the aid of her wizardly handmaiden.</p>

<p>The removal of Naythox also removed the focus of the curse and the discordant energy in the air created an explosion that few have seen before. And when the dust cleared, the armies of both sides, including their leaders and commanders, had disappeared and a passage to a dark underground world appeared the path to Darkhollow.</p>

<p>And while Norrathians discovered Darkhollow, no one yet knows where Lanys, Firiona, or their allies have gone.</p>

<p>Loral: Where do you see live events going into the future?  Do you see monster missions playing any part?</p>

<p>Maddoc: I foresee monster missions becoming more and more integral to live events in the future. On that front specifically, we've currently got a Halloween event that's in progress that makes use of the monster mission system, and it seems to be going over really well with the players. It's very likely that they'll continue to make an appearance.</p>

<p>Loral: What are some of the main complaints you hear in regards to live events and how do you address them?</p>

<p>Maddoc: The most common complaint I've heard recently is that there's sometimes not enough notice that an event is going to happen, which I think we'll work into the next event, perhaps giving a day or two warning before big events or battles.</p>

<p>Loral: What was your favorite event or piece of an event?</p>

<p>Maddoc: I'm very partial to the armies in the Retake of Grobb event (mostly because I spent a lot of time developing it for the RTG events), specifically the technology that manipulated their movement across Norrath. I'd like to develop that technology further, adding in a lot more flavor to them, such as training sessions, night-time activity, and other events of the same nature. There's so much potential for this new technology that I believe we could put to use in many other places in EverQuest besides live events.</p>

<p>How awesome would it be to see small patrols of guards gather together, fall into formation, and begin a training session in their home city? After which, they could go on a march throughout the lands, patrolling for and exterminating any immediate threats to their culture? Maybe they are occasionally given orders to escort an Emissary of the Court to another, distant city. It's all part of an interactive and dynamic world that I'd love to expand on and add into EverQuest at any chance.</p>

<p>Loral: How much did you love those most excellent Reports of the Wilds?</p>

<p>Maddoc: Reports of the Wilds? What are these mysterious relics of which you speak? All friendly jokes aside, they were very well written and I enjoyed them thoroughly. :)</p>

<p>Notes:  With luck, we will have more such interviews with other members of the Everquest Live staff.  I thank Jason for spending the time to answer these questions and hope to talk to him again soon.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
14 November 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Patch of Hallow&apos;s Eve 2005</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001433.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-31T04:25:24Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-29T13:22:07-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1433</id>
    <created>2005-10-29T18:22:07Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week we take a discuss the first major patch since the release of Depths, the Hanvar changes in Anguish, the Depths loot situation, the Walk of Game contest, the EQ Halloween festivities, an the most recent developer&apos;s chat.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>SOE released the first major patch since the release of Depths on Thursday.  The new user interface was one of the most noticeable changes.  This new UI was released with the Escape to Norrath Everquest demo, and finally made it to our servers this week.  Reactions to new user interfaces are pretty easy to predict.  Some folks hated it, some folks loved it.  While most of the changes were cosmetic, the new horizontal and vertical hotboxes shook some people up.  I found it a lot easier to run all four hotbox sets at once with this new layout.  I keep two above my array of chat boxes on the bottom of the screen and two along the left and right sides of the screen.</p>

<p>The new spell gems are a bit of a change.  Anyone who has used Thomas King's UIs in the past will recognize the style but they aren't quite as intuitive as the older spell gems.  SOE moved the older UI to a new "default_old" folder so traditionalists can stay with the older UI, but I imagine we'll see less support for the old UI as new features are added.  Overall, however, the new user interface gives EQ a nice fresh look, an important move for a six year old game.</p>

<p>The new audio trigger feature introduces a lot of potential.  One can set up the audio triggers to alert them when they receive tells, when buffs have worn off, when invis drops, when someone mentions their name, or even add some nice sound effects to critical blasts and critical heals.  The tool is flexible enough to use in very specific situations like the emotes in Anguish or complete heal rotation triggers.  Powerusers will most likely find the best uses for this tool, but it offers a lot of possibilities.</p>

<p>Everquest now uses the default system mouse during play.  The biggest improvement seems to be mouse cursor speed regardless of the framerate of your game.  Players can also mouse out of the EQ window in windowed mode without having to release the mouse.  This addition wasn't without bugs, however.  It appears some discrepancy between Microsoft's use of the mouse and EQ's caused the mouse to stick in the upper left corner.  Dev Rapez <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=211#M211">posted a fix</a> that requires an upgrade from Microsoft.</p>

<p>Stormhammer received a new Arena.  I heard whispers of this new Arena at the last Fan Faire and I expect we will see it on live servers in a month or so.  Stormhammer is a server in dire straights at the moment.  At nearly 1/10th the population of the other servers, players on Stormhammer find it harder and harder to progress through the content of newer expansions.  While most servers had the Nest opened up within a month or two after the release of Dragons of Norrath, Stormhammer only had it opened up recently.  Sony needs to make a decision about Stormhammer and the most likely solution is to disband the server, send the players to any other server they'd like to go, and lower their monthly rate back to the normal fee.</p>

<p>The patch message mentioned power improvements to spirit shrouds.  We have yet to see how much more powerful these shrouds will be.  My "Shroud the Creator" contest is still going on.  Send me a screenshot of six spirit shrouded characters defeating the Creator and win a new copy of God of War for the Playstation 2.  The screenshot must show six shrouded players, a /who to show the levels and races, and the dead creator all in one shot.</p>

<p>This patch also included this year's Halloween events.  Keep an eye out in Kithicor woods for some strange activities including a trick-or-treat scavenger hunt, an undead attack in East Commonlands, a high level quest in Hate, and what appears to be a monster mission of divine proportions.  There is also an excellent <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=TNZ&message.id=210505">spoiler thread</a> on the EQLive forums for weaker souls.</p>

<p>We didn't see any improvements to Depths of Darkhollow's loot in this patch, but we can expect it for the next one.  A few developers commented on the loot balancing process and while the exact statistics of these new improvements aren't yet known, we can expect some nice upgrades.</p>

<p>The patch did include a new quest NPC in Undershore who rewards players for finishing Depths of Darkhollow mission sets.  The rewards for these quests appear to be items with a clickable +50 resist buff, one for each of the five resists and a final one for all five at once.  From the quest's text, it appears to open up some event as well but details are not yet known.</p>

<p>The developers joined EQ Stratics on Thursday night for another developer's chat.  Aside from pompous egotistical pasty jerks hogging all of the questions, the chat went well.  We learned that SOE is as excited about the success of Monster Missions as many players.  Zorillius mentioned the release of one or more new monster missions before the end of the year.</p>

<p>Prathun, the force behind the creation of the Demi-Plane of Blood, the top raid zone in the game said that he felt progress through raid content in Depths is about where he expected or "slightly behind par".</p>

<p>The raiders of Anguish learned that during the last patch, the raid mob Hanvar grew in strength.  This nerf appeared to fix an outstanding bug from the previous designer that fell through the cracks.  While many raiders are upset about the nerf, the most common complaint seems to be about the time it took to fix it.  Raiders have already defeated the encounter and it is unlikely to severely block those seeking the epic 2.0 spheres that Hanvar drops.  </p>

<p>While the Hanvar nerf may seem like a very big deal to those currently working on epic 2.0s, it is unlikely to stay a big deal for long.  Player power continues to go up so any upgrade to difficulty will simply keep Hanvar from turning into the next Qvic M'Shas. In a couple of months, people won't know the difference.  How many people still complain about the Vulak nerf?  From all accounts, Hanvar was bugged and finally got fixed.</p>

<p>Everquest is <a href="http://www.walkofgame.com/">up for a star at the Walk of Games</a> at the Sony Meteron in San Francisco.  These stars celebrate the most influential games of our time.  While Everquest no doubt often faces criticism, I can think of no other game I have played for this long and one that has had the most impact on my life.  I can't think of a more influential game on that list.</p>

<p>Time to go trick or treating!</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
29 October 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Two Contests and the Lost Files of Moorgard</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001431.html" />
    <modified>2005-11-14T02:59:33Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-17T08:10:55-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1431</id>
    <created>2005-10-17T13:10:55Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we officially announce two Mobhunter contests and the great finding of the Lost Files of Moorgard.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last week, in order to test a theory and add a bit of fun, I announced the official Mobhunter Spirit Shroud contest.  Here are the details:</p>

<p>Mobhunter's Spirit Shroud Contest!</p>

<p>Take yourself and five friends, switch to level 70 spirit shrouds of any type, and go defeat the Creator Dragons of Norrath mission.  Send me a single screenshot of you and your five friends in spirit shroud form, an inventory window to show me your level, a /who in your chatbox to show me the level, class, and race of your group's shrouds, and the body of the dead creator.  This should all be in a single screenshot.  Email the screenshot to loral@loralciriclight.com in jpg format.</p>

<p>If you are the first to send me this screenshot, you will win a brand new copy of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B0002XL3BA/">God of War</a> for the Playstation 2, this year's best action / adventure game.</p>

<p>Now on to the second contest:</p>

<p>Mobhunter's Red Cross iPod Shuffle Giveaway!</p>

<p>Support for those affected by Hurricane Katrina is still greatly needed.  Visit the <a href="http://www.redcross.org/">Red Cross homepage</a> and donate $20 or more to the Katrina relief effort.  Forward me a copy of your Red Cross donation receipt and your name will go into a raffle for a 1gb iPod Shuffle player.  The shuffle is slightly used but in fine working order. On November 15th 2005, I will have someone draw a name out of a hat filled with all of the $20 or more Red Cross receipts to find a winner for the 1GB iPod Shuffle player.  You may only submit one donation per name and address.</p>

<p>So donate today.  Help those who need our aid and perhaps win a fine mp3 player at the same time.</p>

<p>Now for our last bit of news, the Lost Scrolls of Moorgard!</p>

<p>In the late hours of the evening, when the blackness of of night was absolute, I found myself hunched over my writing table scrawling out this article on sheets of parchment with a large  quill.  A whisper brought my head up from my words, slipping through the ancient halls of Castle Mobhunter.  I picked up my candelabra dripping hot red wax onto the oak table, gathered my monk's robes about me, and with trepidation, followed the strange whisper.</p>

<p>The whisper led deep into the lower vaults of the castle, revealing halls and rooms I had never before seen, halls lost to the current residents of the castle.  The whisper traveled further until it led to a huge oak door banded with steel and marked with a great M.  I pushed on the door and felt an ancient latch break free.  The door swung open.</p>

<p>A room filled with dust and cobwebs held nine large pots.  I lifted the heavy lid off of one of these pots and felt old stale air escape for the first time in centuries.  Inside were sheaves of lambskin bound and tied in thick covers of leather.  I untied it, feeling the twine turn to dust under my fingers, and read the first page.  Suddenly understanding dawned on me.  I had found the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/moorgard/">Lost Scrolls of Moorgard</a>!</p>

<p>From September 25th, 2000 until August 16th 2003, Moorgard wrote over four hundred articles for Mobhunter.  These articles entertained and informed thousands over the years.  They helped steer Everquest into a new age.  Now these articles, once thought lost forever, have been found.</p>

<p>These articles document the history of Everquest from the times of Kunark to the times of the Planes of Power.  Follow Everquest back through its history from the eyes of Everquest's best editorial writer.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
17 October 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sinkholes in the Depths</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001425.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-18T23:59:56Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-08T11:52:50-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1425</id>
    <created>2005-10-08T16:52:50Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Depths of Darkhollow opened up some of the most exciting and innovative features we have seen in any massive online game.  No expansion is perfect, however.  This article looks at three of the largest problems in Depths of Darkhollow: disappointing rewards, unbalanced missions, and low powered high level spirit shrouds.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Depths of Darkhollow included some of the most innovative features in any of the ten previous Everquest expansions.  The creativity of this expansion shows us how far this game has come and how far it can go in the future.  With monster missions and spirit shrouds, Depths offers the most content to the widest range of players since Lost Dungeons of Norrath.</p>

<p>Yet no expansion is perfect.  This article outlines the three biggest problems in Depths of Darkhollow and offers recommendations to help fix these problems.  Let us begin.</p>

<p>Problem 1: Disappointing Rewards</p>

<p>The mission system in Depths of Darkhollow moves away from the point system found in LDON and Dragons of Norrath to a new mix of both dropped rewards and rewards earned for the completion of a mission.  Unfortunately, the loot on many of the non-monster missions is well below the power of equipment required to defeat the mission.  Those who need the loot cannot defeat the mission and those who can defeat the mission often have equipment far better than the reward.  Here's an example:</p>

<p>The third mission from Kelliad in Stoneroot falls, "Building a Disguise", sends you off to kill 10 Witherans, 25 drachnids, 10 more drachnids, and a final boss.  While the base mobs themselves are not very difficult to defeat, the boss hits for over 3,000, harder than most of the gods in Planes of Power.</p>

<p>What was our reward for defeating this magnificent foe?  </p>

<p>Rippled Cape<br />
AC: +11 Str: +12 Dex: +6 Wis: +12 Int: +12 Agi: +6 Fire Resist: +20 Cold Resist: +20 Magic Resist: +20 HP: +120 Mana: +130</p>

<p>This mission was harder than any other fight I have ever faced in Everquest.  The reward, however, was less powerful than the rewards found six expansions and three years ago.  Here is a cloak I picked up as rot loot in Plane of Time over two years ago:</p>

<p>Cloak of Ferocity<br />
AC: +25 Str: +18 Sta: +20 Wis: +18 Int: +18 Agi: +20 Fire Resist: +15 Disease Resist: +15 Cold Resist: +15 Magic Resist: +15 Poison Resist: +15 HP: +145 Mana: +145<br />
Vengeance III<br />
Fury of Druzzil</p>

<p>From Dragons of Norrath I can purchase this cloak doing any of the missions in the expansion.  This takes a lot less work than the battle against the Chamber Guardian:</p>

<p>Cloak of the Red Dawn Augmented with a Glittering Demantoid Stone<br />
AC: +16 Dex: +11 Sta: +11 Cha: +10 Wis: +9 Int: +9 Fire Resist: +13 Disease Resist: +12 Magic Resist: +13 HP: +115 Mana: +135 End: +135<br />
Strikethrough: +2%</p>

<p>This is only one example of many.  In-game chats and forum postings all complain about lackluster loot rewarded for exciting and difficult missions.</p>

<p>How can SOE fix this?  Improve the loot drops from the non-monster missions in Depths of Darkhollow.  It is time that single-group players meeting an appropriate challenge can have access to the type of loot found six expansions back in Planes of Power.  Single group hunters require this gear to progress through the Illsalin missions and to hunt in places like The Nest, the MPG trials, and Riftseekers in older expansions.  Replace 120 hitpoint and mana drops with 150 hitpoint and mana drops and add focus and combat effects.</p>

<p>Problem 2: Unbalanced Difficulties on Missions</p>

<p>While many of the new missions in Depths of Darkhollow offer exciting and appropriate challenges for those who seek them, some of the missions found in Depths are far harder than many groups are able to defeat.  Let's go back to our previous example, the Chamber Guardian of the "Building the Disguise" mission.</p>

<p>The Chamber Guardian is a powerful drachnid with an AE knockback snare that steadily grows in power as his hitpoints go down.  In the final 10% of the fight he can hit for more than 3000 in a single hit.  Our Time-geared fighter died in one round.  We defeated him our second time through, after an hour of clearing back to him, only when I used Staunch Recovery, the veteran reward ability that fully regenerates mana.  It took me over 13,000 mana to keep our tank alive during this fight.</p>

<p>What content was this tuned around?  What non-raider could ever be expected to burn 13,000 mana?  What would have happened if I had a DON-equipped paladin instead of a Time-geared warrior? </p>

<p>This is a mission in the middle of the expansion.  It isn't a final mission and the end reward for this and the four other missions in the series is a level 68 spell.  No level 68 player can withstand the Chamber Guardian's power.</p>

<p>Again this is only one example.  In the "Preemptive Strike" mission on "Normal" difficulty the party faces post Riftseeker level trash mobs and ten shades that hit above 2000.  Had I not done this mission with a Qvic-geared tank, I don't think I would have completed it.</p>

<p>Monster missions face some of the same problems in both directions.  Some monster missions, like the original Griffin mission, ended up being too easy to finish.  Others, like the "Defending the Grove" monster mission seem impossible.  No doubt there should be a range of difficulties but the difficulty seems to shift from trivial to impossible very quickly.</p>

<p>This problem can be fixed with better and more accurate testing.  Single group "normal" difficulty missions, and those missions with no difficulty should be tuned around players with single-group acquired equipment.  "Hard" missions and some of the more powerful missions in Dreadspire should be tuned around those with Time+ raid gear.</p>

<p>Problem 3: Spirit Shroud Power, Progression, and Experience Gain</p>

<p>Shrouds above level 60 have a very difficult time coming anywhere even near the power of a regular level 60 or above player.  With the high difficulty of content in newer expansions, shrouds cannot meet the needs of any high level player.</p>

<p>I had hoped that shrouds could be used to switch from one archetype to another in case the group could not find that one last required class type.  However, in nearly all cases, one is better off playing one's main character even if one isn't of a desired class type.  For example, as a level 70 cleric I am much more suited to tanking than a level 70 shrouded warrior.</p>

<p>This problem shows off the much larger problem of the power spread across the highest level.  This has been a problem for some time but as our power grows overall, the gap becomes wider.  As long as that gap remains as wide or wider than it is now, things like spirit shrouds will never meet the needs of anyone at high levels.</p>

<p>Shroud progress is also very slow.  After an entire LDON as a level 50 rogue shroud, I earned less than 10% towards the next unlocked shroud.  Add this to the very low experience I earned for my main and Monster Missions end up looking like a much better way to hunt with my friends.</p>

<p>These problems can be fixed in a few ways.  First, increase the amount of experience earned while in a shroud.  Second, speed up shroud progression.  Three, increase shroud power at level 70 and begin to take a longer look at how to narrow the power gap at level 70.</p>

<p>Last week I announced my Mobhunter Spirit Shroud Contest.  Send me a screenshot showing that six level 70 players using only spirit shrouds defeated the Creator mission on Dragons of Norrath and you win a free unopened copy of "God of War" for Playstation 2.  The screenshot must show six spirit shrouded players, a "/who" statement or inventory screen to show levels, and a dead Creator corpse.  Send this screenshot to loral@loralciriclight.com.</p>

<p>The problems above do not fully describe every problem in Depths of Darkhollow but from a content focus, they are the three biggest.  These problems are solvable.  Better mission testing, balancing the difficulty of "normal" missions, increasing mission rewards, and increasing rewards while using spirit shrouds would go a long way to help improve this expansion.  The shroud power problem is much more difficult to solve since it is only a manifestation of the larger power gap problem at the high levels.</p>

<p>All of these issues came up at the last EQ community summit and I have faith that we will see them addressed in the near future.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
8 October 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Summit Report, September 2005</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001424.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-13T15:09:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-03T16:39:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1424</id>
    <created>2005-10-03T21:39:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Loral returns from the west with tales of the September 2005 Everquest Summit.  Read on for details on the summit discussions, some editorial fluff, and exclusive juicy details on a new and most excellent feature soon to be released.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Still groggy from a late-night level 50 Lost Dungeon hunt and a later-night scramble to pack up my books, notebooks, and fancy fountain pens, I woke up Thursday morning and began my trek west to the steel towers of SOE and all the worlds held within.</p>

<p>I had the advantage at this summit of knowing or at least recognizing most of the other EQ community representatives from previous summits and fan faires and rode the bus to the hotel with Samanna of the Spirit Realm.</p>

<p>Thursday night we met with Rashere, Brenlo, Kytherea, and Ashlanne for dinner.  Most of our discussions revolved around Gemdiver's pre-Summit State of the Game article where he accidentally dubbed the term "Age of Rashere".  We had a lot of fun with that.  We discussed monster missions, mission progression in Depths, Everquest's past, and the future.</p>

<p>We learned at the dinner that the Depths of Darkhollow expansion was the number two best selling PC game during the week of its release behind the latest Sims expansion.  The dev team was very excited and proud of this news.</p>

<p>Friday was mainly a day of recreation.  We visited San Diego's excellent yet hilly zoo.  Friday evening we met with the SOE developers for dinner and challenges of Dance Dance Revolution and Street Fighter 2 (I still owe Prathun a rematch after our 1 to 1 ending scores but at least I pwn3d Zajeer).  My ideas of tying Dance Dance Revolution to the Overlord Mata Muram encounter continues to fall on deaf ears (Overlord Mata Muram says "You! Cleric 01246, DANCE!").</p>

<p>Saturday morning after breakfast we headed to SOE for our day of official discussions.  It was here I began to blanket the lands with my twenty two printed copies of "Loral's Evil Agenda".  Knowing some would no doubt be destroyed in horrible ways, I made sure to bring many extra copies.  Little did I know that lord Brenlo would go so far as to literally eat one on the bus ride to SOE.</p>

<p>Our first meeting brought up the topic of EQ's marketing.  With the recent release of Escape to Norrath, SOE began a new way to market EQ.  There were a lot of suggestions and feedback on the release and availability of Depths of Darkhollow.  Whatever people thought about the clockwork boar, a lot of people in the room bought the box just for that rather than download it.</p>

<p>While Escape to Norrath offers an excellent window into EQ, the 300 meg download can be heavy.  Some of us suggested that SOE offer this on CDs like AOL does, no doubt a costly proposal, or as a bundle with PC-Gamer.</p>

<p>Our second session was titled "Everquest, level 1 to Uber" and focused on player progression from the lowest levels of the game to the highest.  I mentioned improving the 20 to 50 game on my Evil Agenda and suggested that SOE consider more progressive missions and quests for these levels to show mid-level players the benefits we see in expansions like Dragons and Depths.  Armor and class weapon quests do a lot to drive players to fun content but currently most players buy weapons in the bazaar.</p>

<p>I also brought up reevaluating the costs of LDON items, especially below level 65.  Zajeer explained his intention to look at these points and make sure that players are no longer leveling faster than they can buy items in LDON.</p>

<p>Rashere began a discussion about SOE's interest in reducing downtime, especially with combat endurance.  Right now EQ doesn't have an in-combat and out-of-combat state system to ensure that players are no longer locked in combat.  Such a system would let players regenerate hitpoints, mana, and endurance faster than when they are in combat.  Use of a monster's agro list can help but it isn't the ideal solution.</p>

<p>We discussed one topic in which I have been interested for some time, the identification of player power at level 70.  Frodlin, the warrior corrispondant and an excellent debate partner of mine, joked about an Everquest 2 style "Level 70 double up arrow", an idea I liked a lot.  With alternate abilities and gear now far more powerful than ever before, an in-game identifier of player power would help SOE properly tune encounters.</p>

<p>Gemdiver had my third favorite quote of the weekend when he asked "Since there are two other wizards here, I will stay away from wizard problems, but what is the state of class re-envisioning things like druid stances and rogue vs. wizard dps."  Even when he's trying he can't let go of wizard issues.  The answer was that about 70% of the outlined re-envisioning took place so far with good results and other things, like the druid stances, take a bit more time to program in.</p>

<p>Our third meeting discussed Depths of Darkhollow.  Craig Knapp mentioned Gemdiver's recent "State of the Game" paraphrasing "Depths of Darkhollow could be the greatest EQ expansion if the loot didn't suck."  Gemdiver's actual quote wasn't quite this strong: "If Zajeer and SOE upgrade the DoDH mission drops to a Qvic level of gear, they will have pulled off the greatest expansion this great game has ever seen."</p>

<p>Depths loot quickly became a hot topic.  Zajeer, the item designer, explained that loot was based on drops from previous zones of comparable difficulty including Noble's Causeway, Muramite Proving Grounds, and Riftseekers.  Loot on Monster Missions was much harder to gauge since monster mission difficulty is independent from character power.</p>

<p>Zajeer and the other designers have seen the complaints about the loot quality in Depths.  Zajeer himself plans to spend the next couple of weeks looking at the difficulty of missions and the loot dropping within to make sure the risk vs. the reward is appropriate.</p>

<p>I suggested a few things on this topic including a set of class or archetype armor built for level 70 single-group hunters or perhaps more evolving items so that while the first item drop may not be excellent, it could grow into something quite nice.  On the topic of class armors, Zajeer was apprehensive saying that he received a lot of negative feedback on previous class armor sets (I believe he was talking about high-end raiding armor feedback, not group armor).  On the topic of evolving items, he gave me my second favorite quote of the trip: "That's not too bad of an idea."</p>

<p>I look forward to Zajeer's rebalance of Depths loot over the next couple of weeks.</p>

<p>The topics of progression for shrouds and evolving items both came up.  Rytan stated that shroud progression was slower than he had intended.  Evolving item progression is about where Zajeer intended it but it is important to note that evolving items only progress when mobs are killed solo or in a group.  Quests, task experience, mission rewarded experience, and raids do not give experience to evolving items.</p>

<p>The last official discussion of the day was an open discussion.  Craig Knapp began the discussion by asking about Everquest's current death system.  Currently EQ handles death much different than competing MMOs and while many of the designers feel that death continues to erode into a meaningless disadvantage in EQ, the topic is still hotly debated internally.</p>

<p>There are many ways death can be handled.  Everyone agreed that death still requires some penalty but it is likewise clear that those facing the stiffest death penalties are those in the middle of the game, not at the end.  High-end hunters have the easiest time finding resurrections, regaining experience, and recovering equipment.  Those in the middle often do not have anyone who can help them and if they find a cleric able to res at their level, they recover significantly less experience than those with 96% resurrections available.</p>

<p>Cheating and Macroquest came up during this discussion as well.  Grumbuk, the assistant lead programmer on Everquest, has worked hard to defeat many of the cheats and exploits found in EQ.  He described his philosophy on cheating, saying that EQ has no desire to lose business based on false detection of a non-cheating player and that the strongest countermeasures for cheats and exploits are when the cheater knows what SOE does but still cannot defeat it.  It is clear that the EQ programmers pay a lot of attention to cheats and exploits and are developing both systems and techniques for dealing with this problem.</p>

<p>A lot of the information gleaned from this summit came from the spaces in-between the official events.  Here are some interesting bits:</p>

<p>This weekend was the first time I had heard discussion about the Demi-Plane of Blood, the final raid zone in Depths of Darkhollow. Prathun told me a little of the types of challenges faced in this new raid zone and they sound like an excellent departure from standard statistical-based raids and more like some of the things we saw in MPG trials and with Mata Muram himself.</p>

<p>I heard about a few monster missions I haven't yet experienced or heard of including a recreation of the release of the Green Mist in Overthere.</p>

<p>The EQ mouse pointer will soon be based on the windows mouse.  This means you can simply mouse out of an EQ window instead of the strange "SHIFT ALT R" mouse release.  This may also speed up mouse precision quite a bit in game since the mouse and the framerate of the display will be independent.</p>

<p>Now we come to the most interesting bit of information I heard at the Summit.  SOE will release a new audio queue system added to test soon and to live soon after.  This audio system lets players assign audio clips to chat window events.  For example, if I receive a tell, I can get a little chime.  However, this system is far more flexible than simple tell chimes.  Players can base audio samples to any string of text displayed in any chat window.  For example, if one receives a tell from his or her guild leader, he or she will hear a different chime.  If a particular item comes up in the auction channel that one has been waiting for he or she can hear a cash register.  If a cleric's turn comes up in the CH rotation, the cleric can hear a bell ring.</p>

<p>The sound system will be completely skinnable with new sounds and allows you to assign these sounds to any string of text that comes up in any of your chat boxes.  Add a big boom to critical blasts or hear a warning bell when a Conviction fades.</p>

<p>The ten million dollar "Loral's Evil Agenda - Submit To It" campaign worked quite well.  I saw copies of the evil agenda floating all over the place.  At one surrealistic moment, someone folded one into a paper airplane, threw it across a resteraunt, and nearly put out the eye of an unsuspecting Moorgard, the first and most excellent Mobhunter writer, a couple of tables away.  What a strange chain of events that would have been.</p>

<p>For each Evil Agenda burned in the hotel fire pits, I saw another read by developers during some infrequent downtime.</p>

<p>This was a difficult time for a Summit.  The Everquest developers currently spend their time fixing issues that come up in Depths of Darkhollow.  The expansion is too new to say for sure what SOE needs to fix, although we certainly had suggestions.  It is too early to say whether monster missions will remain popular although I suspect they will as long as SOE releases new ones.  It is far too early for SOE to say anything about any future expansion.</p>

<p>However, this summit stood as a perfect point for developers and summit attendees to step back and look at the whole game.  Discussions on the death penalty, mid-level content, LDON point costs, and reducing downtime are all important to the health of this game.  The benefit, however, comes not when we talk but when we begin to see SOE implement changes based on this feedback.  Sometimes these changes take a while, but we have seen some of the best changes to Everquest within the last year and I see no sign of that slowing down.</p>

<p>I have met the SOE developers a few times in the past at fan faires and community summits.  It never ceases to amaze me how hard they work and how enthusiastic they are about their game.  These are not 9 to 5 employees.  They work all the time.  They put in ten to twelve hour days every day of the week.  They know their product very well.  Some of them are no doubt stubborn but they believe in what they do.  They rarely cave under the pressure of biased criticism and if you want to convince them, you have to bring both data and show them how a change helps the entire game. These developers love their game.</p>

<p>It was especially a pleasure to meet the other community reps again and I will leave you with a variety of other summit reports and pictures:</p>

<p><a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=11491">EQ Vault: Report 1</a><br />
<a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=11494">EQ Vault: Report 2</a><br />
<a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=11495">EQ Vault: Report 3</a><br />
<a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=11511">EQ Vault: Final report</a><br />
<a href="http://www.eqclerics.org/forums/showthread.php?t=20678">Boanerges's Report</a><br />
<a href="http://crucible.samanna.net/viewtopic.php?t=908">Samanna's Report</a><br />
<a href="http://applets.crgaming.com/images/DDR2-vi.jpg">Pic</a>. (left to right) Gemdiver of Caster's Realm, me, and Rashere the lead designer watching Merloc and Glorianna play Dance Dance</a>.<br />
<a href="http://www.eqinterface.com/Summit05/">Nolrog's Tons o' Pics</a>.<br />
<a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/1068040/">Nolrog's Pics in a Flickr Set</a></p>

<p>I will link more reports as I receive them.  Please send a comment if you find one I haven't linked yet.</p>

<p>I thank SOE for the opportunity and the excellent event.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 October 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda, September 2005</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001420.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-13T15:09:02Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-09-24T09:24:14-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1420</id>
    <created>2005-09-24T14:24:14Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">With the recent release of Depths of Darkhollow and a new Everquest community summit coming up this week, now is the perfect time for Loral to once again outline his evil plans.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>With the announcement of SOE's latest Everquest Community Summit it was time once again to sit back and ponder the best possible future direction for Everquest.  Previous evil agenda covered everything from encounter variety to mentor systems and many of these items are now addressed.  With the latest expansion released only two weeks ago, it becomes difficult to say for sure where the future should head.</p>

<p>We begin this Evil Agenda start with four larger areas for improvement and then include a list of a few smaller areas or areas already discussed previously (often at great length).  Let us begin.</p>

<h2>1. Further Improve Monster Missions.</h2>

<p>Monster missions added a whole new gamestyle to this six year old game and it has become a favored style of play for many since its release.  Add 18 and 24 person monster raids to give any group of 18 to 24 players a chance to try out the raid style so popular with many higher level players.  Offer missions for groups with three players.  Continue to use monster missions as a way to experience lore by tying them to old moments in Norrath history.</p>

<h2>2.  Continue to Tie Future Expansions to Old World Lore.</h2>

<p>Many nostalgic players talk about the great days of Kunark and Velious.  By making these two older expansions part of the core base of the game, SOE can then base instanced dungeons, monster missions, and even entire expansions off of these older lands.  Many players now off in other lands may return if they see "Everquest: Ruins of Kunark II" on the shelf.</p>

<h2>3.  Improve the Dynamics of Combat.</h2>

<p>New AAs like Gift of Mana show a new style of combat where random elements can change player behavior during combat.  This leads to new and unique battles instead of typical "Step 1: complete heal, step 2: see step 1".  Consider the heroic opportunities from EQ2.  Work on encounters that increase difficulty without simply upping the creature's damage.</p>

<h2>4.  Improve the 20 to 50 Game.</h2>

<p>These past six months we have seen a new tutorial, new 10 to 20 missions, and two rebuilt newbie zones.  New 20 to 50 missions and tasks will help players grow from these new additions to the later content found in Omens of War, Dragons of Norrath, and Depths of Darkhollow.  New mid-level missions, more quests, new armor quests, or even an "epic-lite" quest would greatly improve the 20 to 50 game.</p>

<p>With those four major Evil Agenda points behind us, lets look at a few additional changes that would continue to improve the game:</p>

<ul>

<p>    <li>Continue to tune spirit shrouds to ensure usefulness above level 55.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Find solutions to the limitations of the global model file.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Rebuild Plane of Knowledge to reduce lag, add features, and improve cultural bonding (like "Halastown").</li></p>

<p>    <li>Add an sound effect as an option when receiving a tell.</li></p>

<p><li>Find a way to make new player models a possibility.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Add a separate con color for mobs within five levels of the player.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Improve the point-rewards for LDON gear from 20 to 65 to make LDON viable for gear progression again.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Make "/" work for cross server and cross game tells instead of ";" and "[".</li></p>

<p>    <li>Further consolidate and simplify the user interface. Combine like windows.</li><br />
</ul></p>

<p>I look forward to the future of Everquest.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
24 September 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Onward into the Depths</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001419.html" />
    <modified>2005-09-27T20:19:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-09-20T13:07:59-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1419</id>
    <created>2005-09-20T18:07:59Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we look at some of the initial issues of Depths of Darkhollow and begin to prepare for a new EQ community summit.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last Tuesday we found ourselves falling into the Depths of Darkhollow and seeing Everquest in an entirely new light.  The message forums exploded with new information and strange new lingo.  A lot of excited posts talked about the new monster missions and began decoding some of the longer quests.</p>

<p>Within all of this, SOE announced a new Community Summit focused on EQ in the Past, Present, and Future.  I think that means "we want to talk about big issues and not get bogged down with class problems right now".</p>

<p>So here is the plan for the next couple of weeks.  I planned to give Depths about two or three weeks before writing up a "Potholes of Depths of Darkhollow" article outlining some of the problems faced in this expansion but the new EQ Community Summit popped up and I have to write an Evil Agenda for that.</p>

<p>So this weekend I will publish a "Loral's Evil Agenda, September 2005" article.  A week after that I will write up the results of the summit article and a week later I will write up the Potholes of Depths article.</p>

<p>The response to the new expansion has been generally positive.  People seem to really like the monster missions and after the dozen of them I've done, I am still really excited about it as a new style of play.  Future monster missions and some added features will no doubt make its way into this month's evil agenda.</p>

<p>One thing I found interesting about the monster missions is that the rewards received are pretty good at level 70, somewhere around Wall of Slaughter and Muramite Provingground level.  These monster missions may be a good way for underequipped level 70 players to gear up to at least a 120 hp / mana baseline.</p>

<p>Depths departs from the mission center hub that we saw in Dragons of Norrath and that makes mission progression a bit more difficult to understand, discover, and conquer.</p>

<p>Each of the five main hunting zones; Corathus, Undershore, Stoneroot, Hive, and Illsalin; are of a set difficulty.  The missions off of these zones are slightly harder than the difficutly of the hub zone.  So Corathus missions should be easier than Ilislan missions.</p>

<p>The Mission NPCs, however, can be anywhere.  So Hive missions are acquired in Corathus, while Illsalin missions are acquired in Undershore.  Even more difficult is the ease with which players find Illsalin missions compared to the elusive Corathus Creep missions.  One hopes that SOE can make the easier missions as easy to find as the harder missions.</p>

<p>My friends Gemdiver and Nanyea of Caster's Realm released an excellent <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9584">Depths of Darkhollow Mission System</a> that captures much of the known Depths missions and plans to include even more as they get more information.</p>

<p>Difficulty compared to the rewards received is a large topic right now. Personally I found the Illsalin missions to be very difficult even on "normal" and from what I heard, the loot rewards were low considering the power required to defeat it.  This seems to be a common problem even for the "hard" missions.  A lot of other players with whom I often debate on equipment gap issues agree that these missions should be dropping loot more on par with MPG trials and Qvic armor instead of low elemental quality.  Hopefully we will see greater equipment rewards and lowered difficulties for "normal" missions.</p>

<p>Shroud progression came up as a problem as well.  Players report having to kill up to two thousand NPCs to acquire the next shroud.  Progression this slow is far more frustrating than it is rewarding so hopefully we will see this improved as well.</p>

<p>Other players have the opposite problem with some of the monster missions.  Monster missions such as "Shadowmane Invasion", an excellent battle between two rival werewolf tribes, offer a far greater reward than most traditional hunting zones. In some cases players earned 2.5 AAs for about 20 minutes of work.  Already I was beginning to get flashbacks to the dark days of constant Creator missions when I heard "this mission offers twice the reward, why would we do anything else?".  No doubt a nerf is already in progress.  I didn't buy this game to play one mission over and over. Each mission should offer an equal reward compared to the risk and effort.</p>

<p>Monster missions revealed another problem as well.  Since players of any level can group together for a monster mission, the loot scales itself based on the level of your main character.  However, one cannot learn what the actual power of that gear will be until one already loots it and leaves the mission.  A quick change added the highest power of the rewarded item to that artifact's description so at least level 70 people know what they will receive, but it is still unclear to lower level players what they might win.</p>

<p>An ugly bug poked out its head with missions in general.  Players who either zoned or went linkdead during the success of a mission found themselves unrewarded for the mission and locked out with a 56 day lockout timer.  This problem seems common and the developers have already acknowledged it and are working on a solution.   Hopefully this gets fixed soon.</p>

<p>I offer the following list of recommendations to SOE for initial improvement to Depths of Darkhollow:</p>

<p>- Lower the difficulty of the "normal" missions so pre-RS level 70 hunters can accomplish them.</p>

<p>- Fix the 56 day lockout bug.</p>

<p>- Continually monitor and ensure that mission rewards meet an appropriate balance.  We don't want another creator.</p>

<p>- Offer appropriate rewards for the difficulty on normal missions. Gear rewards should be better than the gear required to defeat a mission.</p>

<p>- Make it easier to find Corathus Creep missions.  Easier missions should be easier to find.</p>

<p>- Lower the requirements for shroud progression.</p>

<p>This weekend I will write up my fifth Evil Agenda to outline possible large-scale improvements to Everquest.  This time, however, I am at a bit of a loss to come up with critical improvements to the game that haven't been answered in the past.</p>

<p>So this is your chance.  If you have a large issue that you think needs to be handed to the developers, either send me a note or post your idea here.  I will not take every request and you must convince me that this request is a game-wide issue not already addressed.  Class issues are, of course, not going to be addressed here; seek your class representative to champion your cause.</p>

<p>Good hunting.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
20 September 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Depths of Darkhollow: In-depth Preview</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001416.html" />
    <modified>2005-09-27T20:18:45Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-09-09T20:04:22-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1416</id>
    <created>2005-09-10T01:04:22Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">With the release of Depths of Darkhollow early next week and a release of the beta non-disclosure agreement, Loral now brings you an in-depth preview of Depths of Darkhollow.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Nearly a year has passed since the release of Worlds of Warcraft and Everquest 2.  With such fierce competition, many worried that Everquest was finally on the downward spiral.  We worried that these new games would have features and functions impossible in a game like Everquest and that the EQ development team would be hard pressed to add anything unique or interesting to Everquest that hadn't been done before.</p>

<p>We should not have worried.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow is Sony Online Entertainment's tenth Everquest expansion in six years.  It is, by far, the most bold and innovative expansion ever released.  While other games struggle to keep up with features like LDON adventures and the Mission System, Depths of Darkhollow adds unique, useful, and fun features never seen in any other massive online game.</p>

<p>Since the difficult release and lackluster response of Gates of Discord, SOE has improved Everquest with every expansion.  Every expansion improved upon the strengths of the previous and Depths of Darkhollow appears no different.</p>

<p>One would assume that a tenth expansion in any game would have difficulty improving upon the original game and nine previous expansions, but Depths of Darkhollow shows once again how far this six year old game can go.</p>

<p>Let's dig in.  We start with the basic content found in most expansions and end this preview by looking at the more radical features: spirit shrouds, monster missions, and evolving items.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow includes six new large static zones including The Undershore, Stoneroot Falls, The Ruins of Illsalin, Corathus Creep, The Hive, Dreadspire Keep.  The release of Depths of Darkhollow also included a rebuilt Nektulos forest for all EQ players including those not purchasing the expansion.  These zones scale from level 45 to level 70 with three zones tuned for level 68 to 70 hunters.  Dreadspire Keep should give a good challenge to those bored of Riftseekers.</p>

<p>These static zones include a wide range of design from huge statues and torch-lit tent cities to huge suspended stone bridges crisscrossing huge chasms.  The EQ artists found an excellent balance between the hyperrealism of Everquest 2 and the epic, but cartoony feel of World of Warcraft.  The design and architecture of Depths includes a lot of detail without sacrificing the feeling of epic fantasy.</p>

<p>Dreadspire Keep, the end-zone of Depths of Darkhollow, is not locked by a raid like the end-zones in most previous expansions but instead by a single group event.  Dreadspire is an entirely different style of zone, one of such strangeness that it must be seen and heard to be believed.  You will travel through the depths of shadowy hell only to find yourself walking into the set for Masterpiece Theater with a pale-skinned butler handing you a warm glass of brandy.</p>

<p>Since Lost Dungeons of Norrath, every Everquest expansion has included instanced single group hunting areas.  Dragons of Norrath included the Mission system and Depths further capitalizes on Missions by adding over forty single group missions from level 55 to 70.  Depths of Darkhollow changes the path towards mission progression from the ways of Dragons.</p>

<p>Depths mission progression consists of a set of missions in each of the static zones.  You are rewarded for each mission accomplished and again when you complete a set of missions in each of the zones.  There will be random rewards for those who do a mission more than once, but unlike Dragons, you will be rewarded for completing a variety of different missions rather than completing the same mission over and over.</p>

<p>Here is an example. You and your ragged band of adventurers meets an important figure in the Depths of Darkhollow who sends you on a mission.  You go on the mission, fight a big horrible creature and its minions.  When the boss is defeated, your group is rewarded with a dropped item you may divvy up as you choose.  If this is the first time you or any of the others have done this particular mission, you will receive a one-time reward that may be a piece of gear or some other tasty treasure.  Future battles against this mission will still drop a piece of gear off of the boss, but future one-time rewards must be received from different dungeons you have not yet defeated.</p>

<p>One important note and change that may frustrate some players.  Mission entrances are sometimes very deep in hostile zones.  Getting TO a mission can become as difficult as the mission itself.  These missions are tuned to include the time it takes to arrive as well as the time it takes to complete so they shouldn't become much longer to complete than missions in previous expansions.  It can be frustrating, however, to accept a mission and not actually begin it until after an hour of traveling.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow also includes some single group events (I heard them referred to as single group raids, a term that made my head spin but my heart soar) that are triggered by a group but take place in open zones.  These are a mixture of instanced missions and regular overland killing but the idea is unique.  This fits well with my previous request for more interesting single group content than static hunting and boring boss monsters.</p>

<p>Many Anguish-level raiders found the high-end raids in Dragons of Norrath to be too easy and not rewarding enough to hold their interest.  Once Overlord Mata Muram was defeated in the Citadel of Anguish more than a few times, these raiders had little to do.  Depths attempts to pacify and perhaps humble these high-end raiders.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow includes two dozen events and raids ranging from 24 person elemental level events to 54 person Anguish and post-Anguish level raids. Anguish raiders can expect over a dozen 54 person high-end raids.  This will hopefully give high-end raiders more than enough challenge and also offer further parallel progression paths for lower-end raiders to reach more powerful challenges and greater rewards.</p>

<p>While not a level-cap increasing expansion, Depths offers a bit of character progression.  Depths includes about a dozen new AAs for each character class for a total of perhaps 200 points of further AA progression.  Depths includes one new discipline for melee and even a new discipline for hybrids, something they have requested for some time.</p>

<p>Spell casters will see two or three new spells for each caster class in the level 65 to 70 range.  New forms of spell research will allow players to research previously dropped spells from older expansions including the elusive 69 and 70 runes from Omens of War.  The exact details of this research is still unknown but acquiring these spells should be less frustrating than in the past.  [Update 9/12/2005: I found out today that these researched spells will only be up to level 65, not up to 70, however my understanding is that there will be greater access to Omens 69 and 70 spells within Depths of Darkhollow.]</p>

<p>Now we will look at some of the unique features of this expansion.</p>

<p>One of the greatest challenges and frustrations of a massive online game comes when two friends both play the same game but one quickly outstrips the other due to longer play times.  Soon these two friends, who used to hunt together often, cannot hunt together at all due to such a wide level range.  A <a href="http://www.penny-arcade.com/view.php?date=2004-12-31&res=l">Penny Arcade parody of Worlds of Warcraft</a> covers it well.</p>

<p>Other games have found ways to solve this problem.  City of Heroes included the sidekick system that raised the level of one player to meet the other.  Everquest 2 included the Mentor system that let one player lower his or her level to that of a friend.  Everquest added a big twist on this mentor system with Spirit Shrouds.</p>

<p>Spirit shrouds allow players to polymorph into a monster of their level or below in increments of 5.  These monsters are broken up into archetypes called "templates".  Each template includes a set of skills that meet a typical character archetype such as melee, spellcaster, healer, utility, or tank.  There are eight sets of spirit shrouds with over twenty different monster models and over thirty different shrouds total.</p>

<p>My good friend Nanyea wrote a <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9515">detailed look at spirit shrouds</a> and I recently wrote an <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9550">instructional guide to spirit shrouds</a>.  I also wrote a previous article called <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9103">What Will Play as a Monster Mean for EQ</a> feature.</p>

<p>The primary purpose for spirit shrouds is to allow higher level players an opportunity to effectively hunt with lower level friends.  It meets this job very well. Shrouds also let players try out templates vastly different from their own. If you spent most of your time playing a pasty cleric, you can now try out playing as a melee, spellcaster, or tank.</p>

<p>At higher levels, shrouded monsters become less powerful than characters of the same level.  Much of this is based on the large equipment and Alternate Advancement power increases at higher levels.  Shrouds should allow players to switch to a needed archetype if a group is missing one core member, but they will not be able to hunt in the most powerful areas.  A group of three primary characters and three shrouded characters should to be able to hunt in places like Wall of Slaughter and the lower Dragon missions.</p>

<p>However, if a group cannot find one core class for a hunt, they might consider monster missions instead.</p>

<p>When I first heard about Depths of Darkhollow I was most excited about spirit shrouds.  After my first Nagafen monster mission, I changed my mind.</p>

<p>Monster Missions are the best feature of Depths of Darkhollow.  Monster missions let any group of four to six players of any level and any class face a challenge as monsters in an instanced scenario.  Monster missions open the door to entire new possibilities for challenging encounters.  They are self-contained events under perfectly controlled environments and power levels.  They are easily balanced and not affected by any outside influence.  They are the most fun I've had in EQ in a long time.</p>

<p>There are twenty such monster missions in Depths of Darkhollow.  About half of these are in the depths itself while ten go back to old world zones to let players face some old world challenges.  Imagine invading Freeport as a band of pirates.  Imagine fighting off the undead hoards as froglok paladins in lower guk.  Imagine breathing waves of fire upon sniveling raiders who invade in an attempt to steal your Cloak of Flames.  The possibilities are endless.  My only hope is that we continue to see new monster missions added in the future.</p>

<p>Depths offers a new form of equipment known as "evolving items".  These items grow in power the more you use them.  They may start off as weaker pieces of equipment but the more you use them, the stronger they get.  There are several dozen such items in Depths of Darkhollow.  Intelligent items are a rare subset of these.  These items will actually communicate to the player through emotes and possibly tells.  Though these items will be quite rare and unique, they will be available to single group hunters as well as high-end raiders.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow is the first expansion to offer a box prize so useful that I will suffer the traffic of Washington DC to buy my copy retail rather than download it from SOE directly.  Those who purchase the retail version of Depths of Darkhollow will receive an in-game clockwork boar mount.  This mount is comparable to the 10k plat horse and drogmar mounts but with a unique model and look.  Rewards like these offer an incentive to retail outlets to carry this expansion and it is these boxes on the shelf that bring new players to Everquest.  Unfortunately, poor retail systems between the US and other countries make it nearly impossible for non-US players to receive such a reward.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow shows how far Everquest can evolve.  While many questioned how long a game like EQ can survive, we only have to look at the ingenuity in expansions such as this one to see how far Everquest can continue to go.  Depths of Darkhollow offers all of the strongest features of a good solid expansion along with two of the most radical concepts I have seen in any roleplaying game.  Considering the hours and hours of content this expansion contains, it is easily worth the $30 price tag.  While time will tell for sure, Depths has all of the signs to be the best Everquest expansion ever released.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
9 September 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Shrouds, Monster Missions, AAs, EQ2, and WoW</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001412.html" />
    <modified>2005-09-20T18:27:43Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-09-03T10:16:46-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1412</id>
    <created>2005-09-03T15:16:46Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today, as we glance to the horizon for the coming of Depths of Darkhollow, we discuss a recent developer&apos;s chat, some EQ community articles, some EQ2 news, and some WoW news.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>We stand on the crest of the release of Depths of Darkhollow, Everquest's tenth expansion.  My network of spies reports that the Non Disclosure Agreement by which many of us are bound to hold the secrets of this new underground world will lift soon.  In the meantime, let's talk about some of the news in the past couple of weeks.</p>

<p>The latest <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=180&no_redir=true">Everquest Developer's Chat</a> mainly talked about the spirit shroud system although lord Rashere revealed bits and teasers about the new Depths AAs:</p>

<p>"I'm putting together a good variety of AAs including some that introduce new concepts to EQ. If you're in the beta, you should be able to check them out soon."</p>

<p>Indeed, they were on beta a day later and the new concept is quite exciting.  I will talk about it more in a few days.</p>

<p>Rytan also talked a little bit about spirit shroud progression, a subject I think is very important:</p>

<p>"The progression for spirit shrouds is completely separate from the experience you gain to increase your character's level. So you won't have to allocate any of your normal experience to advance your shrouds. It's completely a bonus on your normal experience."</p>

<p>Progression is the drive that keeps us playing Everquest.  I am glad to see an independent progression path for spirit shrouds and I hope SOE continues to expand upon this as they do with tradeskills and AAs.  Earning experience as a spirit shroud is nice, but being able to unlock new shrouds through their use will keep us using them.</p>

<p>Rashere also mentioned that 1/3 of the missions in Depths of Darkhollow will be monster missions.  From the 60 missions mentioned on the Depths of Darkhollow homepage, that makes about 20 different monster missions.</p>

<p>Earlier this week I was more excited about spirit shrouds than anything else, but recent tests of the monster missions changed my mind.  Monster missions open up an entire new way to play Everquest, not simply in shifting you to a new entity but in the tailored scenario around you.  Expect me to spend some time talking about monster missions in a few days.</p>

<p>In other Everquest news, Caster's Realm had a few interesting articles this past week.  My friend, the Kyv, wrote a <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9520">Guide to the Muramites</a> and my other friend Nanyea of Township Rebellion and a regular writer for Caster's Realm wrote <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9515">All About Spirit Shrouds</a>.  I had the opportunity to write an editorial on Caster's Realm this past week entitled <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9504">Who Deserves New Content</a>.  There are also some sneak screenshots of the new <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9528">Clockwork Boar mount</a> available to those who purchase Depths of Darkhollow in retail stores.</p>

<p>It appears the next SOE Fan Faire will not be until April 6 according to a recent posting from our favorite halfling, Brenlo.</p>

<p>It is always useful and interesting to take a look at some of the other massive online games in recent news.  Here's a bit of news on the EQ2 and World of Warcraft fronts.</p>

<p>Everquest 2 made a couple of big changes on their test server recently: the removal of group experience debt and unlocking encounters while in combat.  The first change, the removal of group experience debt, is one I looked forward to for a long time.  I mentioned it in my smaller <a href="http://eq2.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=8957">Evil Everquest 2 Agenda</a> from the last fan faire.  The big thing I'd like to see in EQ2 next would be some sort of mission or adventure system similar to EQ1.  Not just group instanced dungeons, but actual focused group missions with a nice pickup-friendly reward system.</p>

<p>SOE will release Everquest 2's newest expansion, <a href="http://everquest2.station.sony.com/expansions/desertofflames/">Desert of Flames</a>, on 12 September.  This is one day before the release of Depths of Darkhollow, putting a sixty dollar hole in the pocketbook of anyone playing both games.  Fortunately or unfortunately my level 26 swashbuckler isn't quite hefty enough to brave the new deserts so I might give this one a pass for the time being.</p>

<p>Not to toss fuel onto a smouldering fire but it appears that <a href="http://www.bit-tech.net/news/2005/08/25/Sony_Station_Exchange/">Sony Station Exchange</a> is quite profitable, pulling in $180,000 in transactions in 30 days.  While I don't worry about future games built around a model such as this; we all pay for content one way or another; I don't like the idea of retrofitting this into existing games.  Fortunately, I don't see that happening to Everquest or the non-exchange EQ2 servers.  It doesn't appear World of Warcraft will add any similar system either.</p>

<p>It is hard to ignore the force with which World of Warcraft has hit the market.  Blizzard recently announced that they have hit four million paying subscribers, nearly eight times what Everquest ever reached.  One has to admire their ability to bring so many new players into the massive online world and apparently, despite a lack of level cap increases and expansions, keep them playing.</p>

<p>World of Warcraft is a very solid game.  I have never played a massive online game with a better newbie game.  It is easy to get into and easy to play.  No doubt the ability to solo just about anywhere helps considerably, although I think this is a danger to the core of massive online gaming.</p>

<p>A recent <a href="http://www.gamergod.com/article_display.cfm?article_id=287">interview with WoW developer, Shawn Carnes</a>, had a lot of interesting insights.  Here is one surprising quote that got a lot of people stirred up:</p>

<p>"An expansion is planned, not in 2005, possibly in late 2006 barring unforeseen chaos. Work is already going on for the expansion, and it's going good [sic]."</p>

<p>I don't doubt that they can hold their player-base until late 2006 but it still sounds like quite a ways off considering how many players have capped their characters and are already struggling for something to do besides raid for gear.</p>

<p>Still, no one can ignore Warcraft's success.  They have an extremely solid game with a great UI, great graphics, and great gameplay.  If they came out with more regular expansions, level cap increases, and added a mission or adventure system, they would dominate the market for a long time.</p>

<p>On a last note, Everquest 2 recently added in a /donate command to help players donate to the Red Cross to help in the wake of hurricane Katrina.  Here was the press release:</p>

<blockquote>Please help us get the word out to the SOE community at large about our hurricane relief efforts.

<p>Hurricane Katrina has left an incredible wake of destruction across the Mid-Atlantic States. Sony Online Entertainment would like to ask you to take a moment to make a donation to the American Red Cross in order to help alleviate some of the suffering.</p>

<p>In EverQuest II we have added the /donate command, type in /donate to be taken to the American Red Crosss Hurricane 2005 relief page. For those members of SOE Communities in other games, you can contribute using this link, American Red Cross. The American Red Cross will process your donation and make sure that it is put to maximum use to help those whose lives have been affected by the hurricane.</p>

<p>Additionally, for our 13,000+ players actually in the affected areas, we will be suspending billing until such time as they are able to play again. In addition, any items or structures in any of our games, which decay over time, will be preserved until the users next login.</p>

<p>Thank you in advance for your support and generosity.</p>

<p>The SOE Family</blockquote></p>

<p>If you have the means, please <a href="https://secure2.convio.net/arc/site/Donation?ACTION=SHOW_DONATION_OPTIONS&CAMPAIGN_ID=1161&JServSessionIdr010=z84f82fvu1.app25b">donate to the Red Cross</a>.</p>

<p>That's it for now.  Keep your eye on Mobhunter over the next few days for a post-NDA-release writeup of Depths of Darkhollow!</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 September 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>News After the Fall of Gukta</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001411.html" />
    <modified>2005-09-20T18:27:43Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-08-15T08:02:12-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1411</id>
    <created>2005-08-15T13:02:12Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we have a short update on the latest happenings in our constantly changing world of Norrath including the fall of Gukta, more on the Boar, and some interesting articles and rumors on the internets.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The war of Antonica seems to have ended and our green Froglok friends find themselves in a new tent-city in south Rathe Mountains.  This was a bit of a surprise conclusion to the war.  No one expected that SOE would change the troll city from back whence it came.  I personally expected part of Freeport to be blocked off for Ykesha and his new men.  No doubt these changes upset the Froggie allies as much as the Troll allies were angered to lose their city in the first place.</p>

<p>The Frog city has it's charm.  It reminds me of Kelethin only lower to the ground (thank Tunare).  One other interesting change, it appears that Frogloks can now start as necromancers, shadowknights, and rogues.  That adds a bit more flavor to the race and will hopefully help fill out the low level game with some newer twinks.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/dod/">Depths of Darkhollow homepage</a> has been built up with a pretty flash introduction, the Depths movie, a bunch of screenshots, and pre-order information.  Depths pre-orders have brought up some interesting debates.  For the first time in a while, the free gift for buying the retail makes it worth running through traffic to buy the box instead of clicking the "download now" button.  The Clockwork Boar, a unique mount with the same power as a 10,000 plat horse or Drogmar mount, comes included with the boxed retail version of Depths.  Those who either buy depths in the store or download it will receive a gargoyle monster shroud.</p>

<p>Many have asked why SOE would offer such a great incentive for a store-bought purchase when they are no doubt making a bigger profit on the download.  The answer is: boxes on shelves sell EQ.  We are horrified at how well advertisement works, but it works.  If SOE can keep EQ on the shelves with new expansions, SOE gains more customers.  Expansions keep Everquest alive and boxed sales help bring in new players.</p>

<p>For those of us who are happy either way, it won't be fun battling Tuesday night traffic to get to Best Buy and find out it hasn't hit the shelves yet.  All of my friends will be running around me as wolves nipping at my boots and hooting while I stand there as my old boring self.</p>

<p>Of course, it will be worth it for that one time when I am stuck with a broken down smoking clockwork boar, telling my friend "I think it slipped a rod".</p>

<p>My friend Gemdiver over at Caster's Realm released some <a href="http://everquest.station.sony.com/dod/">exclusive Depths of Darkhollow screenshots</a> including a couple I took (that first double-wolf shot is one of mine).  More and more people find the opportunity to join the Depths of Darkhollow beta.  Keep a keen eye on the forums for chances to join in if testing is your cup of tea (*ignores the jeers of "but we're all betatesters in EQ you pompous egotistical loudmouth cleric!"*).</p>

<p>Our friend Zorillius recently announced that the Test server community would evolve.  There are a few advantages to the test server such as double experience and full veteran rewards.  SOE is going to add shorter reset times on all AAs, easier flagging requirements, and different boss timers.  The most controversial change, however, comes from an ability for those on Test to invite players on the live servers to copy their main character over to test.</p>

<p>Test has always been an interesting community.  They suffer through a lot so that we can have a more stable game (*once again ignores the cynical jeers*) and they don't mind telling you about it.  They live through client bugs that keep them off game for days, encounters that are far from tuned, and all sorts of strange oddities.  They do, however, get to see some of the latest changes sometimes months before we do.</p>

<p>Test is a community, however, and they act much like any of the other servers.  To see hoards of copied players rushing in threatens the community they built.  It will be interesting to see how this plays out, but I expect that SOE needs more players of all levels to help test EQ and this will solve that need.</p>

<p>Thanks to longtime Mobhunter supporter, Redcloud, we have a couple of interesting MMO articles to read.  <a href="http://www.pointlesswasteoftime.com/games/wowworld.html">A World of Warcraft World</a> takes an interesting and amusing look at how MMOGs will shape our world.  I have a theory that 50 million players in the US will be playing some sort of massive online game, whether it be fantasy or football (or both), by 2012.  Massive Online Games have changed our world and changed our lives.  We like to say "it's just a game" but I have never played a game for five years straight that got me to write 3000 words a week in articles for three different sites.  It's just A game but it's also not just a game at the same time.</p>

<p>Next Generation posted a reprint of <a href="http://www.next-gen.biz/index.php?option=com_content&task=view&id=723&Itemid=2">The Laws of Online World Design</a> by yukalale playing SOE big-head thinker, Raph Koster.  These are some of my favorite couch-potato game designer rules that we should all keep in our head when we critique and ponder this favorite game world of ours.</p>

<p>It appears the <a href="http://www.macworld.co.uk/news/index.cfm?NewsID=12317&Page=1&pagePos=14">Macintosh version of Everquest</a> has risen from the dark depths.  SOE is now offering a free download for the Macintosh version of Everquest including the base game, Kunark, Velious, Luclin, and Planes of Power.  SOE has had trouble maintaining and supporting the Mac version of EQ in the past.  A while ago we discovered that SOE only had one developer for the mac version and that developer had left.  It will be interesting to see if this catches on, but they have a lot of work to do to catch up to the PC version.</p>

<p>Last week I wrote an update of an old article of mine, now titled <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9347">Why I Play Everquest 2005</a>.  Every six months to a year I like to step back and really ask myself why I play this game.  I think it is a valuable method to ensure that I continue to have fun and don't ever feel like I'm wasting my time.  It's a bit pompous and perhaps even too high-brow for me to follow all the time, but hopefully its an entertaining read.</p>

<p>Thus ends this week's news roundup.  Keep watching the forums for the latest happenings.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
15 August 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Riddles in the Depths</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001410.html" />
    <modified>2005-09-20T18:27:43Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-08-01T00:23:28-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1410</id>
    <created>2005-08-01T05:23:28Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">In this week&apos;s news roundup we look at the progression of the War of Antonica and dig into some of the clues given at the most recent EQ Stratics Developer Chat.  Learn the secrets of the Clockwork Boar!</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The war of Antonica rages on. While the elves stay close to home after the orcish attacks three weeks ago, Barbarian mercenaries and the Frogloks of Gukta battle against Ykesha's armies in the southern rathe mountains. Armies of barbarians marched from Halas to rathe Mountains where they battled Ykesha's forces from the south. Many adventurers were chewed to pieces in the upper and lower jaws of this huge battle. Some, however, found a trinket or two within the piles of corpses.</p>

<p>The quality of these items and the dubious methods by which they were acquired made people angry. Some worried that items of such a high quality reduced the value of the items rewarded in higher-end raid content. The random rewards and the short duration of this event, however, won't build any threat against consistent raiding with known loot.</p>

<p>Warlord Ykesha himself faced adventurers on the battlefield. When it became clear that he was not meant to be destroyed by mortal hands, these adventurers found other ways. They brought armies of Frogloks against him for hours until the sustained damage became even too great for the warlord. These adventurers sadly discovered that Ykesha's shield was little more useful than a cloth cap; less useful, in fact. Still, the look of such a shield is no doubt a prize in itself.</p>

<p>Now we see the trolls looking south to Gukta and <a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/images/forum_images/community/Absor.JPG">prophets of doom</a> already call the city lost. Let us all pray for our little green friends.</p>

<p>I wrote two more Reports of the Wilds for a total of six including:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50016">Report 1: Descent of the Trolls, Ithiasor the Black</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50017">Report 2: Warlord Bortar</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50020">Report 3: Xon Quexill's Plot, The Creature of Innothule</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50021">Report 4: The War of Greater Faydark</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50022">Report 5: Warlord Ykesha</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://eqlive.station.sony.com/news_section/newsview.jsp?story=50023">Report 6: The War of Antonica</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Last Thursday EQ Stratics hosted another excellent <a href="http://eq.stratics.com/DoD/dodhoc.php">Developer's Chat</a>. More often that we'd like, dev chats don't give us a lot of news that us nosy website writers can't dig up on our own. The dev team likes to stay tight lipped on future efforts until they are sure they will occur. When announced, these new efforts usually show up on the EQLive forums rather than in a developer chat.</p>

<p>However, in this week's chat we received a lot of juicy detail on Depths of Darkhollow. Lets take a look.</p>

<p>Many Anguish-level raiders complained that Dragons of Norrath offered few raids at their power. It appears that Depths will include a significant number of raids aimed at players who have already finished Anguish. </p>

<p>I feel it is important to understand that not all raiders are of nearly the same power. Often raiders refer to themselves, other raiders, and raid targets as though they were all right around their same power. I have heard Qvic+ raiders state that true raiding doesn't begin until Qvic. I've heard Time raiders say that raiding means Time and above. Much like there are players of all levels, there are also raiders of all levels. Four Anguish level guilds may seem like a lot for a server, but there are hundreds of guilds on every server and dozens below Anguish who also want newer content.</p>

<p>However, when a guild defeats Anguish, there is nothing else out there to challenge them. Everyone below this power still has something ahead of them to defeat. That is probably the best reason why it is important that Depths include targets post Anguish to keep Anguish raiders happy.</p>

<p>This chat gave us a few more details about the "Play as a Monster" feature or as I like to call it - the Monster Mash. As we have heard, this feature is actually split into two parts: Spirit Shrouds, and Monster Missions. The Monster Missions will allow a group to switch into the bodies of monsters in order to complete a mission. Some of these missions will be flashbacks into the history of Everquest. </p>

<p>We learned from this chat that the monster missions will not have restrictions on the levels of the players who want to join them. This means that a group with a level 20, 34, 36, 54, 60, and 70 characters can all group together and go on a mission. Loot will be distributed based on your level. This is a huge improvement in the social features of this game. Now players can group with their friends regardless of class or level for these missions.</p>

<p>During Sprit Shrouding, a player can switch to a monster with a pre-defined class template of their level or below. During their time in a spirit shroud, players will earn items and experience as normal which will switch back to their main character. Spirit shrouding adds a whole new variable to the existing game. I can't wait to do the new Crushbone missions with a level 18 werewolf.</p>

<p>There will be normal missions in Depths of Darkhollow as well. The rewards for these missions will not be a point-based loot system. With Dragons, players focused on the missions that offered the best point rewards for the least effort, such as Creator or Gimblax. Depths missions will offer rewards to those seeking a variety of progressive missions instead of the those completing the same mission over and over. It isn't yet clear exactly how this will work or whether it will compete well against a point-based loot system for pickup groups.</p>

<p>New "Intelligent Items" will have many different abilities and will earn experience as characters do. Intelligent items can be acquired through regular hunting, raiding, or tradeskilling. They will have many personalities including cowardly, heroic, persuasive, or mocking.</p>

<p>If you purchase the retail version of Depths of Darkhollow you will receive a free Clockwork Boar mount. This may be the best retail purchase in-game reward yet. Over the years I have continually missed out on the retail rewards because retailers cannot keep up with my desire to play the expansion the minute it goes live. It looks like this year I may have to wait a day if I want that crazy clockwork boar!</p>

<p>It was a great dev chat and I look forward to the next one. In the meantime, let us look to our froggy friends to the south and wish them well.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
1 August 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Rising of the Trolls</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001409.html" />
    <modified>2005-09-20T18:27:43Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-16T10:52:45-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1409</id>
    <created>2005-07-16T15:52:45Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week we offer up a news roundup of the latest happenings in Norrath including the most recent patch, a couple of news articles of note, and the most recent War of Norrath.  Enjoy!</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>War rages across Norrath once again.  With the memories of the battles of Firiona Vie not so far behind us, we once again find a game-wide event unfolding over the month of July.</p>

<p>Adventurers found themselves sent to battle dragons in Kunark or cutting down a new troll warlord named Warlord Bortar.  A new two-group events has players defending strange high elves performing a ritual in Innothule.  Dark elves march on the Eastern Commonlands.  Neriak spies lurk in the shadows.</p>

<p>Then war found Greater Faydark.  For three nights the elven armies and orcish hordes gathered in the woods.  War Suppliers asked for armor and weapons.  No one knows for sure how the turn-ins effected the war but some believe they increased the forces on one side or the other.  Four or five sets of thirty or so elves faced an equal amount of orcish forces.</p>

<p>The serverwide.war channel fluttered like CNN.  Reports came in of orcish attacks.  Victors revealed powerful weapons dropped by slain Elvish commanders.  On Quellious, a force of over one hundred adventures faced off against an untargetable orcish general named Warlord Mish.  Unfortunately the battle did not find us yet and wouldn't until a day later when the orcs finally marched on the elves.</p>

<p>The war wasn't without problems.  Elven generals initially dropped far better loot than the orcish generals. Many opportunistic players switched sides and killed the generals who carried the shiniest items.  Elven enchanters often charmed or tashed orcs, causing players to quickly become the targets of vengeful elves when they accidently attacked the wrong orc.  Many of these problems were fixed but not until well into the war.  On Quellious, however, the elves were eventually successful in their defense against the orcs.</p>

<p>This battle was just the beginning, however.  The plots continue throughout the month and a new troll warlord far more powerful than Warlord Bortar begins to build his army in Lavastorm, Nektulos, and the Foreign Quarter.  Keep an eye out.</p>

<p>Over the past two weeks and probably continuing throughout July, I have written some in-character reports of these battles including the following:</p>

<p><a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001382.html">Report 1: Descent of the Trolls, Ithiasor the Black</a></p>

<p><a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001383.html">Report 2: Warlord Bortar</a></p>

<p><a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001384.html">Report 3: Xon Quexill's Plot, The Creature of Innothule</a></p>

<p><a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001385.html">Report 4: The War of Greater Faydark</a></p>

<p>Any such reports are almost always written after the event, however.  The best way to participate in the war is to watch the EQLive forums for new topics on the war and to join the serverwide.war channel by typing "/join serverwide.war".  That channel helps people share information about the war as it happens.</p>

<p>This past week SOE also released a <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=165#M165">minor patch</a>.  This patch mainly fixed a few outstanding bugs with the previous patch and added a few smaller features.</p>

<p>One feature of the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/000067.html">patch that changed Everquest</a> that I did not talk about is the new option to autoconsent your group, guild, and raid to drag your corpse.  Like the game-wide invites, this is a smaller feature that has a huge impact.  Many many times entire raids have been destroyed because players can't drag corpses of their friends until that friend zones and consents.  This new feature makes groups and raids far more mobile even when faced with the death of a comrade.  Just grab the bleeding corpse by the belt, heave it over one shoulder, and head for the hills!</p>

<p>Of course, like the NewPlayers channel, General channel, and game-wide<br />
invites, these tools are only useful if people choose to use them.  Many players apparently don't read the patch messages very carefully.  One has to go to the Options menu (alt O) and select the autoconcent group, guild, and raid buttons.</p>

<p>There were a couple of interesting articles that had popped up last week including an IEEE Spectrum article called "Engineering Everquest" and another on "Virtual Sweatshops" in the Guardian.</p>

<p>The IEEE Spectrum article, <a href="http://www.spectrum.ieee.org/WEBONLY/publicfeature/jul05/0705eq.html">Engineering Everquest</a>, spent far more time talking about the game of Everquest than it did talking about the technology.  Considering the heavy competition in the Massive Online Gaming field, companies like SOE probably want to hold their system architectures close rather than give away all of their best secrets in a technical journal.  The article talks about the "Death Star" (I bet every gaming company has a server vault called the Death Star), a server farm containing over 500 servers in a 1500 server army spread across three buildings.  The article also talks a little bit about a recent software architecture change called "Just-in-time computing" that dynamically shifts system resources to the areas that need it the most.  It isn't clear from the article but I believe this is how instances work.</p>

<p>The Guardian article <a href="http://observer.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,6903,1436411,00.html">Virtual Sweatshops</a> talks about the third-world shops that hire people to play EQ, EQ2, and World of Warcraft to earn in-game resources sold out-of-game.  They take a detailed look at a fellow in Romania who works for ten hours a day in a backroom of a run down apartment where eleven employees keep accounts running for 24 hours straight.</p>

<p>The article does a good job of shattering its own title.  Compared to the child labor sweatshops where ten year olds work in heavy labor unsafe jobs for barely enough money to eat, these "virtual sweatshops" don't even compare.  Even the author admits that some people working at these outfits come in and play on their time off.  I doubt any ten year old kid went in on his time off to make more Nike shoes.</p>

<p>The article doesn't spend much time to show that this business is illegitimate and I suppose that is a small point when you talk about the larger topic of out-of-game sales of virtual property.  However, from within Everquest, such businesses harm the economy of the game.  It devalues virtual property when it is tied to an out-of-game economy.  If taken to the extreme, it would one day be so cheap to buy platinum that<br />
most anyone would choose to save time and just pay for it.</p>

<p>Whenever I read an article like this one I am reminded of an excellent short story by <a href="http://craphound.com/bio.php">Cory Doctorow</a> called <a href="http://www.mikeshea.net/articles/001292.html">Anda's Game</a> about a young girl who becomes a hitman in-game against competing virtual sweatshops.  It's a great read.</p>

<p>Thus ends this week's news roundup.  Keep an eye on the shadows and watch out for the rising of ancient powers.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
17 July 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Patch that Changed Everquest</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001408.html" />
    <modified>2005-09-20T18:27:43Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-04T10:35:44-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1408</id>
    <created>2005-07-04T15:35:44Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week SOE released a patch that forever changed the face of Everquest.  While some of the features may seem subtle to some and even annoying to others, when one digs into what these changes mean, one sees a much more usable game and a tighter community.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>People tend to spend a great deal of time paying attention to very small things.  Last week's article on the Equipment Gap received 130 comments in six days.  We spend much time concerning ourselves with class balance, Time instancing, equipment statistic issues, and uber versus casual debates.</p>

<p>None of that is important.</p>

<p>What is most important in Everquest is meeting people and having fun.  The damage per second on wizard blasts makes little difference.  Adding another 50 hitpoints to a level 70 breastplate makes little difference.</p>

<p><a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=96330&view=by_date_ascending&page=1">This week's patch</a> added three major changes that helps bring in new players and ties the social community of Everquest closer together.  These include the new tutorial, the new level 10 to 20 quests, cross-zone group invites, and the autojoined chat channels.</p>

<p>Players now have a wide variety of tools to help find other players for groups.  Now you can use the LFG tool to find players looking for groups and ask in the General chat if anyone is interested.  If they are, you can immediately invite them into your group regardless of what they are. Group members can coordinate much easier when everyone is in a group instead of a barrage of tells.  The cross-zone invite is a great convenience as well as a tool for helping build social bonds between group members faster.</p>

<p>The new chat channels also create entire new social circles.  No doubt, due to the age of the game and the typical resistance to change, many people will immediately leave the public channels and stay with the channels they know best.  Many will stay, however, and hopefully some of the cynics will return to them.  These channels act as an excellent communication pathway.  The General chat cuts across all players, whether level 25 or level 70, whether a once-a-week player or a hard core raider.</p>

<p>Smart players will use this channel to find groups or build pickup raids.  Supportive players will use it to help people learn more about the game and teach them about their classes.</p>

<p>If you are a player who wants to help teach new players how to play Everquest, add "NewPlayers" to your autojoin list ("/autojoin NewPlayers").  This lets you join that channel regardless of your level.  New players are automatically added to this channel so you can easily find new players to help.  Using other players as a resource is the only way most players can cut through much of the complexity in this game.  Use of the General and NewPlayers channels help solve this very well.</p>

<p>If you're one of the cynics who found the channels invasive and distracting, consider at least joining the General channel and saying hello.</p>

<p>Over the past couple of days I have taken my new warrior through the newly released Everquest Tutorial, Mines of Gloomingdeep.  This tutorial will soon become the core of the "Escape to Norrath" free demo, but it is available to all new players now.</p>

<p>The new tutorial is a lot of fun.  While the popup windows on the initial lessons can be a bit distracting, especially for older players who learned six years ago how to "hail" someone, the rest of the tutorial is a blast.  The lessons are now done as quests in the quest journal, helping EQ compete with the quest journals of EQ2 and World of Warcraft.  </p>

<p>There are about fifteen quests including three group quests.  Along the way you can collect a new set of armor specific to the tutorial with statistics similar to the original newbie quest armor.  There are three boss encounters; the spider queen, the Kobold Overlord, and the demon in the pits.  I particularly enjoyed the pit demon mission.  The Kobolds in their digging dug too deep and released a great horror.  Only you and your heroic friends can stop it.</p>

<p>The new tutorial helps give direction to new players.  Both times I hunted there I saw over forty other players hunting as well.  Groups formed quickly and met challenges.  There was some twinking but powerleveling isn't really possible.  </p>

<p>The tutorial looks great.  The Mines of Gloomingdeep uses a unique zone, newer graphic models from Dragons of Norrath and even a new unique kobold model.  The graphics are very good with light reflections and excellent detail.  In my battle with the pit demon I marveled at how good EQ can look after six years.</p>

<p>If you haven't tried out the new tutorial, spend a few minutes rolling up a level 1 and go through it.  It is a lot of fun.</p>

<p>This patch also included a bunch of new level 10 to 20 quests from the Plane of Knowledge.  When a new player leaves Gloomingdeep they are now sent to the Plane of Knowledge, the central hub of Everquest, and given a set of new exploratory quests to help them get around.  While it detracts from the cultural bonding that we once knew starting out in our home cities, the low population of those cities made it harder for players to meet one another.  It is a difficult change but one for the better.</p>

<p>There were many other changes in this patch but my hand grows weary.  I will leave you with today's Mobhunter Exclusive:</p>

<p>Mobhunter Exclusive: Blood Boils Among the Trolls</p>

<p>As a reporter in the world of Norrath it is important for me to keep my fingers on all of the strands of information that cross our waters and travel over our mountains.  It is sometimes important for me to deal with unsavory and questionable people in order to learn everything I must know.  One of these unsavory characters, a young troll spy, sent me a scribbled note through the Antonican Bards and it is the contents of this troll spy's note I will report to you here.</p>

<p>It appears the trolls within Neriak begin to plot.  They speak of violence.  They speak of war.  They speak of a warlord named Bortar who will deliver them from Neriak and send them back against the Frogloks of Gukta.  These notes come at great cost; it took eight scholars and five engineers to teach the troll how to write with a quill.  Here are some of their whispers:</p>

<p># Luruk Dridor says 'Me hear talk  Trolls angry about being stuck here long time  Me wonder what happen next'<br />
# Grigdor says 'Me hear dat Daboo do most talking, dat Daboo almost kill Elf cause Elf try to tell him what to do'<br />
# Luruk Dridor says 'Me hear dat too  Me tink dat Daboo be lucky he stay calm  He kill Elf den we all end up in fight'<br />
# Grigdor says 'Me hear Draboo [sic] say stupid tings at bar too  Tings dat Elfs can hear and not like'<br />
# Luruk Dridor says 'What tings?'<br />
# Grigdor says 'Daboo say dat Elfs not let Bortar lead Trolls to kill Frogs  He blame Elfs for not giving Trolls enough room in stupid city'<br />
# Luruk Dridor says 'Me tink dat someting Daboo say  Sound like Daboo  Daboo not too smart'<br />
# Daboo Dogak says 'SHUT UP!  Me right here you know!'<br />
 <br />
# Gardunk says 'You hear Ranjor?  He loosing mind'<br />
# Kaglari says 'He just tired of Elf city and still mad about losing home'<br />
# Gardunk says 'He not only one  If Bortar not come back soon, Clan Grobb fight Dark Elves  Me not sure Clan Grobb win'<br />
# Kaglari says 'Grobb win if work together  Lots of Trolls here not want fight here, want fight for Grobb, kill dem frogs'<br />
# Gardunk says 'True dat  Kaglari have much control over Clan Grobb hearts  Kalgari talk to clan, calm down Ranjor'<br />
# Kaglari says 'Ranjor not listen anymore, me try  Me tink Hukulk more likely fight  He talk quiet, but his heart angry  Angriest in clan'<br />
# Gardunk says 'Me angry too  Me want fight  But me want home back, not take Elf home  Ugly place, Elf home'<br />
# Kaglari says 'Might not be able to stop fight, might only choose where clan fight  Me try to keep all quiet until Bortar come back'<br />
# Gardunk says 'Me hope you can'<br />
 <br />
# Zignal Luk says 'Me had enuf  Dis not Troll home!  Troll not belong in stupid Elf home!'<br />
# Wista says 'Me no mind  Make good money here'<br />
# Ootok says 'You not want home back?  You not want kill frogs!  You stupid as Ogre!'<br />
# Wista says 'Me want kill stupid frogs, but me like glowy things in elf city'<br />
# Zignal Luk says 'No matter what Wista like  We no wait more  Bortar lazy slob, no act  We take action soon, no matter what Bortar say anymore'<br />
# Ootok says 'Zignal right  Trolls wait too long for revenge'<br />
# Wista says 'Zignal maybe right, but Zignal talk too much  Elf no like talk of revenge, make too many trolls angry'<br />
# Zignal Luk says 'Me duty to remember Troll past, make Troll culture  If me shut up, nobody remember'<br />
# Wista says 'Zignal shut up before inkies hear'<br />
# Zignal Luk says 'Me be quiet, but me not be quiet long'<br />
 <br />
# Ranjor says 'Me tink it not a good idea'<br />
# Hukulk says 'Me tink you not real Troll  Me tink you coward'<br />
# Ranjor says 'I tink me gonna kill you now!'<br />
# Glubtak says 'Dey at it again  Stupid Trolls, fight each other not enemy'<br />
# Ranjor says 'You shut stupid mouth!  You not know nothing!'<br />
# Hukulk says 'She right  Me kill you not help Grobb Clan, so me not fight'<br />
# Ranjor says 'You coward!'<br />
# Hukulk says 'No, me smart  You not control self, you fool'<br />
# Glubtak says 'You both shut up  You know Bortar tell Trolls not fight Trolls  Me Bortar's friend, me not want to tell him you fight'<br />
# Ranjor says 'Me tired of talk!  All time talk!  Me want do something!'<br />
# Hukulk says 'You get chance soon enuf, Ranjor'<br />
 <br />
# Slunga says 'Hey, Capee, you kill anyone today?'<br />
# Capee says 'No  Me no find anyone to kill  But me hurt some Elf real good'<br />
# Slunga says 'Ha!  Dat good!  Me tired of dem Elfs  Wish me had time to smash some'<br />
# Capee says 'You no have customers, ever  You got time'<br />
# Slunga says 'Stupid Capee  Even if no customers, not allowed to leave  Boss make me stay'<br />
# Capee says 'Well, me hear dat some Trolls tinking of taking Elf city for selves  Me like dat plan'<br />
# Slunga says 'Dat sound good to Slunga'<br />
# Svunsa says 'You two shut up  Me not pay you to make trouble or talk stupid'</p>

<p>Changes are on the horizon.  Keep watch.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
4 July 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Equipment Gap</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001407.html" />
    <modified>2005-09-20T18:27:43Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-25T12:24:18-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1407</id>
    <created>2005-06-25T17:24:18Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Things have gotten a bit too cozy on Mobhunter recently.  Today we take a look at that most popular of topics, high-end equipment balance.  Let the fun begin.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>"Remember how Kunark came out and suddenly players and items were just so much more powerful than in the original game? Remember when Velious came out and it seemed at first that items were only increasing in effectiveness by a small margin? Well, throw the curve out the window, students, because there is not just a gap between good items and awesome items, there's a freaking canyon."</p>

<p>- Moorgard, 29 June 2001, Mobhunter</p>

<p>Over the past few weeks we have talked about the fan faire, the new expansion, and some of the new directions SOE has taken Everquest.  This week I thought we would take a step back and talk about a topic in Everquest that has been around since the days of Kunark: Equipment balance.</p>

<p>No doubt this article will ruffle a few feathers.  My intent, however, is not to focus on one particular style of play but instead to look at the details of this topic that often get lost.  If all you see is "Loral wants better gear for the casual gamer again" then you're probably not reading hard enough.</p>

<p>There comes a point at the highest levels of the game when equipment can double the power between two equally leveled players.  This generally only happens at the highest levels, right now between levels 65 and 70.</p>

<p>Consider these two pieces of equipment:</p>

<p>Faithbringer's Breastplate of Conviction:  AC: +125 Str: +30 Dex: +25 Sta: +30 Cha: +25 Agi: +25 Fire Resist: +30 Cold Resist: +30 Magic Resist: +30 Poison Resist: +35 HP: +315 Mana: +355, Mana Regeneration: +5,  Regeneration: +10, Avoidance: +10, Shielding: +5%, Spell Shield: +6%, Effect: Blessed Healing Aura: Increase Healing by 50%, Focus Effect: Keldovan's Light: Decrease Spell Mana Cost by 25%, Required Level: 70</p>

<p>Plate Vest of the First Order: AC: +72 Dex: +12 Sta: +12 Wis: +12 Int: +12 Agi: +12 Fire Resist: +13 Disease Resist: +13 Cold Resist: +13 Poison Resist: +13 HP: +125 Mana: +120 End: +120, Required Level: 70</p>

<p>I want you to pay particular attention to the last part of these two lines: "Required Level: 70".  These items are designed for the same level character.  Yet the power of the first item is well over twice the power of the second especially when one considers the focus effects, regen, mana regen, avoidance, and shielding.</p>

<p>No doubt the difficulty in acquiring these items is vastly different.  One can be purchased from the Dragons of Norrath vendor after completing somewhere between 7 and 12 missions.  The other requires drops from the Arch Magus or Overlord Mata Muram in Anguish.</p>

<p>Obviously, these items don't compare in either power or in the difficulty to receive it.  However, there are some areas where these items must be compared.</p>

<p>Encounters are based on levels, not equipment.  At level 70, the same creatures are dark blue to you regardless of your equipment.  The same mobs give the same experience regardless of your gear.  Yet, based on the power of your equipment, an encounter could be either impossible or trivial depending on what type of equipment you use.</p>

<p>At level 70, level no longer accurately describes how powerful you are.  Yet systems in the game continue to use level as a way to determine encounter difficulty.  Lost Dungeon adventures and Dragons of Norrath missions scale their content based on level, not equipment.  The Omens of War Task system and the quests given to you in Dragons of Norrath are based on level, not gear.  Some of these are trivial to well-equipped players and impossible for the rest.</p>

<p>Even those with the best equipment expect growth yet they cannot get it from single-group hunts.  Not everyone raids all the time.  There comes a time when even high-end raiders want to get together in a group of six and fight an appropriate challenge.  At the highest end, even the most powerful single-group areas offer little reward for high-end raiders.  High-end raiders cannot increase their equipment power in single-group events.  This leads them towards a "raid or nothing" attitude.  Why bother hunting anywhere if there is no reward for doing so?</p>

<p>One single-group hunting zone or mission cannot challenge both single-group equipped players and high-end raid equipped players.  No challenge will be acceptable to both groups.  I hear it often.  Riftseekers is too easy for raid-equipped players and too hard for single-group equipped players.  The only players who seem to find the perfect challenge in this high-end zone are those who happen to be equipped with Time or Elemental gear of roughly 150 hps and mana each.</p>

<p>The power gap will come back as a hot topic when Depths of Darkhollow brings us monster templates based on level.  If these templates are built around single-group equipment, raiders will find them extremely low powered for the level.  If they are built around raid-level equipment, they will be more powerful than many players' main characters.  The only answer is to base them on single-group equipment and accept that raiders will find them extremely low powered.</p>

<p>How can SOE begin to close the equipment gap?  There are few, if any, easy answers.  It isn't just a matter of offering better equipment for single-group encounters.  Doing so devalues the reward of higher-end raid encounters.  </p>

<p>It is not unreasonable to expect that the absolute best single-group equipment available should meet 75% of the absolute best raid-level equipment.  If a cleric breastplate from Overlord Mata Muram includes a 50% healing focus and 355 mana, a breastplate from the hardest single-group encounter might offer 250 mana and a 35% healing focus.</p>

<p>Even with gear 75% of high-end raid gear there isn't anything to say that difficult single-group zones will still be impossible for non-raiders.  In places like Riftseekers that extra 25% power makes the difference between success and failure.</p>

<p>A more difficult solution would be to add some sort of "legendary" status to items.  Items with this status could have different statistics when used during a raid than they do when used during single-group events.  This lets equipment balance out during single-group events but meet the proper requirements during raid events.</p>

<p>Another solution, also radical, would be to add in a Dungeons and Dragons style "power level".  Equipment and levels could combine into a single power rating that determines the difficulty of an encounter.  However, after playing 3rd edition D&D for a year now, the power level in D&D isn't very accurate and doesn't help much when matched to challenges.  There is nothing to say that a power level in EQ would be any more accurate, but perhaps it would help.</p>

<p>Every new expansion increases the power for both raiders and non-raiders.  With the recent addition of slot 9 augments to Dragons of Norrath gear, single-group players now have customizable armor comparable to Elemental and Time level armor.  More of Norrath becomes accessible to more players with every increase in power.</p>

<p>However, it is clear that Everquest becomes very gear dependent at the highest levels of the game.  It has been this way for the last four or five years and I see few ways to fix this problem without radically changing the game.  As it has been since the days of the Ring War, the topic of equipment power will always continue to be a hot one.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
26 June 2005<br />
Loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>

</feed>