<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>Who remembers, &quot;A fire beetle says, &apos;hit by non-melee damage for 15 pts!&apos;&quot; ??

T</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Who remembers, &quot;A fire beetle says, &apos;hit by non-melee damage for 15 pts!&apos;&quot; ??

That goes waaay further back than kicking snakes... 
And it was &quot;live&quot; for more than a year, long enough for people to ask that it be left in because, &quot;polite talking beetles and snakes are a part of EQ&quot;. :)

IMHO, I think the progression server is a misnomer. It does not &quot;progress&quot; the game, it is a complete regression</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>11:30 pm PST on the Combine...

55 People in Ak&apos;Anon.  /ooc was alive with people offer other p</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>11:30 pm PST on the Combine...

55 People in Ak&apos;Anon.  /ooc was alive with people offer other people help, and not one condesending remark about *newbs*.

/sarcasm on

Oh yeah, this was a horrible idea, every one just hates it....

/sarcasm off

For the 1% or 2% of the game base that concider themselves l33t ubber raiders, who want that next expansion to have 4000 points worth of AA&apos;s and who can&apos;t comprehend why &quot;casual&quot;</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I am glad to see the progression servers start off so successfully. I personally don&apos;t desire t</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I am glad to see the progression servers start off so successfully. I personally don&apos;t desire the SLOW crawl through early Antonica without the other expansions, but i am happy so many others do. I wonder if the obvious desire to play the servers is due to playing EQ old school or being on a server where everybody starts off fresh at Level 1 without server transfers. It would have been interesting if they opened a totally normal server at th</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I really do hope that the progression server(s) concept works out well.

But only as I would love to</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I really do hope that the progression server(s) concept works out well.

But only as I would love to see them then try out a variation on that theme by having all races &amp; classes in from the start, there are plenty of cities in the Old World to accomodate them, &amp; I think it would be very interesting to see what the class/race balance would be on such a server.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Well glad to see that the progression servers are going as I thought they would. Already numerous pe</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Well glad to see that the progression servers are going as I thought they would. Already numerous people in the upper 20&apos;s and the server has been on line 2 days.
Guess level 50 should be by next weekend and the first expansion online within 2 weeks. This is sure going to be a &quot;long lasting&quot; experience.
The new Freeport is a royal pain in the arse. Whoever thought that they needed to &quot;revamp&quot; the zone and move things all </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The progression servers are doing as I thought they would too and I&apos;ve never seen so many peopl</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The progression servers are doing as I thought they would too and I&apos;ve never seen so many people happy playing EQ again.  It&apos;s like a weight has been lifted off people&apos;s backs and they can have *fun* again.

Yes, the top 2% of people are leveling fast. So what. I&apos;m level 8 wearing leather pants, a cloth cap and wielding a rusty sword and playing with 100&apos;s of others like me. Personally, I don&apos;t want to be level 50 wh</description>
</item>
<item>
<title><![CDATA[I played in various hot zones in the past and I never saw any noticeble experience gains. T</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description><![CDATA[I played in various hot zones in the past and I never saw any noticeble experience gains. To me they were nothing more than advertisements to other zones you might of ignored (your level up ding included a pop up window suggesting these zones).

This new method is a little better. You'll get 2-4 decent items for your level each place. On their first go at it all the named were 1 hour spawns and drops were tradeable so people were farming</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>There&apos;s also talk of doing level 65 hotzones in the future.  And apparently, if done the way th</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>There&apos;s also talk of doing level 65 hotzones in the future.  And apparently, if done the way the developer wants, all of these hotzones will be changing 2 to 4 times a year based on a theme (this time was Kunark).  Also, changes made as far as new drops and call for help and such will remain in the zone even after it loses its hotzone status (unless the dev has changed his mind since last I read his postings on the subject)

At least on my s</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Please tell me the change isn&apos;t as dramatic as it sounds. As a former enchanter I&apos;m trying</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Please tell me the change isn&apos;t as dramatic as it sounds. As a former enchanter I&apos;m trying to envision doing CC in LGuk or Old Seb with the froggies hitting (and resisting) like PoP mobs. It&apos;s not a pretty picture. 

I&apos;ve always felt like the increase in mob DPS in PoP was a huge mistake. Tactics became very rigid when no one but the tank could survive being hit for more than a few seconds at most. Ironically a change meant to</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I can definitely say that resists can&apos;t be that bad. While playing my twink necro and agro kiti</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I can definitely say that resists can&apos;t be that bad. While playing my twink necro and agro kiting, I have been able kite red mobs 4-5 levels higher the my necro and have very few reisists.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I&apos;ll have to disagree with you Crumpkin.  Just posted some results on EQ Vet forum of Engorging</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I&apos;ll have to disagree with you Crumpkin.  Just posted some results on EQ Vet forum of Engorging Roots (level 56 druid spell) durations since the patch.  Root used to last the full 3 minutes on all mobs in Skyfire when cast by my 68 druid.  Now it frequently wears off in less than a minute.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Noticed the mobs in Dreadlands had been given a 1/3more HP recently. This change is really sucky for</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Noticed the mobs in Dreadlands had been given a 1/3more HP recently. This change is really sucky for casters, who now need to burn more mana to drop a mob. My mage was suddenly getting owned by mobs which he could beat with like 20% to spare. This is really a very crappy change.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>You wouldn&apos;t notice it on all mobs.  First, it&apos;s zones prior to PoP, although there&apos;s</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>You wouldn&apos;t notice it on all mobs.  First, it&apos;s zones prior to PoP, although there&apos;s some people saying that they&apos;re having issues in other zones that shouldn&apos;t have been affected.  Second, it&apos;s supposed to only be mobs 50 and below who are not boss type mobs.  Third, the changes may not affect all mobs, and in some cases supposedly may lower HP or make the mobs easier,  But, generally, it&apos;s supposed to have ra</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Considering how much more powerful players, their spells, and their equipment have become since the </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Considering how much more powerful players, their spells, and their equipment have become since the game was released, any changes to make NPC&apos;s more challenging in the lower levels in old world zones were long overdue.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Considering how much less rewarding the older zones are, many people came to them not by choice but </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Considering how much less rewarding the older zones are, many people came to them not by choice but by necessity. You and your friends make up a less than ideal group? Go to an older zone. Want to solo but you&apos;re not one of the real soloing classes? Go to an older zone. Now that&apos;s gone.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>