<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://mikeshea.net/rss.css" type="text/css"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

  <channel>
    <title>LoralCiriclight.com</title>
    <link>http://loralciriclight.com/</link>
    <description>Tales and adventures of Loral Ciriclight in the online role playing game, Everquest.</description>
    <dc:language>en-us</dc:language>
    <dc:creator>mike@mikeshea.net</dc:creator>
    <dc:rights>Copyright 2004</dc:rights>
    <dc:date>2004-01-23T22:22:04+00:00</dc:date>
    <admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.movabletype.org/?v=2.661" />
    <admin:errorReportsTo rdf:resource="mailto:mike@mikeshea.net"/>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>

    <item>
      <title>Why I Play Everquest</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001076.html</link>
      <description>Not everyone considers their time in Everquest well spent. Frustration, jealousy, and greed show up on almost every class message...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1076@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Not everyone considers their time in Everquest well spent. Frustration, jealousy, and greed show up on almost every class message board. Class envy, content issues, and guild competition are debated with little statistical proof or credible evidence. Why are people so upset?</p>

<p>I quit playing Everquest at level 20 when I realized that as I grew, I would always still get killed by a variation of a rat, a bat, or a spider. Then two months later it dawned on me. The reason Everquest is different than other games is the 3000 other people playing it. They are the strength of the game. Items or levels or rat-like monsters do not matter, people do.</p>

<p>Around this time I came up with Loral's Rules for Everquest. Understanding them and following them let me enjoy the strength of the game and focus on what really matters.</p>

<h2>Rule 1: Enjoy Every Day You Play.</h2>

<p>If you aren't enjoying the game every day you play, change how you play. If every time you log on you feel an uncomfortable desire to experience grind or get depressed when you realize you have a raid, you are playing for the wrong reasons. I've seen many people quit because they do not like the "end game", an idiotic term for a massive online game, because they realize at level 65 what I realized at level 20. Equipment and lvl progression alone won't make the game enjoyable.</p>

<p>Find what you enjoy doing and do it. If you enjoy group hunting with friends most, go hunt. If you enjoy fishing at the lake in West Commonlands, go fish. If you're bored then go explore. Find a new cave and root out the evil that lives there, green mob or not. If you aren't enjoying the game now then levels and equipment won't help.</p>

<h2>Rule 2: The Grass Is Not Greener.</h2>

<p>Envy and greed are the two most destructive emotions in Everquest. They lead to the only real destruction that can happen in this game, the destruction of friendships. The game isn't much different at 65 than it is at level 20. A Blade of War at level 65 isn't better than the tarnished shortsword at level 2. Enjoy the level you are without sprinting to get to the next.</p>

<p>We all feel the instinct grow. We all want to progress. We all want higher levels, more AA points, and better equipment. Don't be a slave to these feelings. The shine of your blade never seems as bright as the shine of the other guy's. Your class never seems as powerful as those around you. These illusions are false.</p>

<h2>Rule 3: Gear, Experience, Levels, and AAs, aren't real. Friendships are.</h2>

<p>The only thing you take away from your time in Everquest are experiences and friendships. Your friends list is your most powerful item. The connection to four thousand other people is what sets Everquest aside from Final Fantasy.</p>

<p>There is no return on your Everquest investment other than friendships and fond memories. If you hate raiding or hate camping an item then don't do it. The item you receive will not last. In a few years it will be gone forever. That new shiny shield may seem like a great discovery but the friends who helped you get it are the real treasure. Never hurt a friendship over loot. Don't abuse your friendships for personal gain. You are destroying something real for something fake. You aren't gaining an item, you are losing something far more valuable. Treat everyone with respect and most will treat you the same.</p>

<h2>Rule 4: Items, Levels, Characters, and worlds will fall apart in ten years. What will you walk away with?</h2>

<p>In ten years how will you look back at your time playing Everquest? Do you consider it "wasted" because you don't have any of your fancy gear or even a record of your vast array of alternate abilities? What will your level or items mean to you then?</p>

<p>Only the fun times you had with your friends will matter when Everquest is no more. Keep contact with them and you may join them in another new game or get together for hamburgers and talk about the time you battled Trakanon. Those experiences and those friendships are the only thing that will last longer than the game.</p>

<h2>Rule 5: Roleplayers Have More Fun and Roleplaying is Contagious.</h2>

<p>Roleplaying is the breath of life in a game like Everquest. It is the seasoning to an otherwise bland meal. Without roleplaying, its just a bunch of statistics and polygons.</p>

<p>How does your character act? What is her background? Take examples from a movie or book, whether fantasy or not. Perhaps your fighter is the Lucca Brazzi of Everquest, lumbering and dangerous but without the best social etiquette. Perhaps your wizard is Elizabeth's Sir Walsingham, smart and strategic and always scheming. Perhaps your rogue is like Lara Croft, sexy and self confident as she dives into the ancient crypts with little concern. Give them a personality of their own. Give them faults. Make them real. Use emotes that speak for your character's emotions in any situation.</p>

<p>The more you roleplay, the more people roleplay around you. If you're into your character, they get into theirs. The more you roleplay the more you will enjoy the game.</p>

<p>Nothing puzzles me more than the constant negativity I read in Everquest editorials and message board postings. We pay for this game. If you hate the game then quit playing. Everquest is not an investment, its a game. All you can ever possibly hope to get out of it is entertainment, friendships, and experiences of great battles to remember. If you aren't having fun, then change the way you play until you are having fun. It is your money and your time, don't waste any of it doing anything you don't want to do.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-01-23T22:22:04+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 45: The Fireborn</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001071.html</link>
      <description>For three thousand years Fxandrakulzis the Fireborn ruled his lair in the caverns of Garulon within the Plane of Fire....</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1071@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>For three thousand years Fxandrakulzis the Fireborn ruled his lair in the caverns of Garulon within the Plane of Fire.  It was not a large lair, perhaps two thousand minions, but it afforded him the opportunity to delve into his passion, necromancy.  Five hundred years previous the Fireborn acquired a book outlining the dark art.  Following its instructions he tore apart dozens of his demonic minions and mortal slaves only to raise them as twisted undead beasts.  But the Fireborn was not satisfied.  He constantly sought out new necromatic magic to add to his dark powers.  Soon his wishes were answered.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="./images/mir_fireborn_in_fire.jpg"><img src="./images/mir_fireborn_in_fire_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Fireborn" /></a>
    </div>

<p>At the height of his power, the lich Miragul opened up rifts to both the Plane of Torment and the Plane of Fire.  He knew of the Fireborn and had heard of his vast knowledge of necromancy.  It took a great deal of the lich's power, but soon through a burning summoning circle deep in his icy labratory, Miragul pulled the Fireborn into the world of Norrath.</p>

<p>The Fireborn found that the lich Miragul was the only mortal he had ever liked, even perhaps admired if a greater demon can admire any mortal.  Together they built creations of true villainy and great horror, the Demonbone Skeletons.  These twisted remains of mortal bodies and demonic spirits had a thirst for blood beyond any creature of Norrath and an unnatural strength to match.</p>
    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="./images/mir_fireborn.jpg"><img src="./images/mir_fireborn_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Fireborn in Miragul's Lair" /></a>
    </div>

<p>One day Miragul left the Fireborn's laboratory and never returned.  It mattered little to the red leathery-winged demon.  He drew fourth minions of his own world, huge muscled beasts like himself and continued his work.  Soon the icy caverns of Miragul's lair were filled with the Fireborn's demon-blooded undead.  Even planar beasts of Torment served his will, some huge rough-furred hulks and others hideous malformations of flesh, muscle, and fanged tentacles.  Soon after, the caverns of Miragul's lair had been uncovered.</p>

<p>It was then that the Fireborn met the priest.</p>

<p>He had just finished the construction of a huge and powerful demonbone skeleton, one built from the bones of a cloven hoofed Tormentor and a mammoth.  It was filled with a dark spirit that made even the Fireborn shivver.  He found the entrance of the adventuring party to be quite timely.</p>
    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="./images/mir_fireborn_table.jpg"><img src="./images/mir_fireborn_table.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Labs of Miragul" /></a>
    </div>
<p>The Fireborn sent a telepathic command to his new beast and both he and a fellow red-winged demon watched the monstrosity rush out into the icy caverns.  A crash of thunder filled the hall.  A blast of heat rushed into the normally chilled halls.  For the Fireborn and his companion it was a taste of the fiery pits of home.  The clash of battle could be heard in the hall for perhaps a minute and then the party entered the Fireborn's lair.</p>

<p>The Fireborn took no chances.  He sent the other demon forward and sent a wave of lava over the party.  Each member of the six used some form of protection from molten rock.  Three hid behind shields, two behind cloaks, and one simply let it roll off of the protective shell of his armor.</p>

<p>The party was very well equipped.  He soon saw that their skills matched their equipment when his minion was cut down under a flurry of blades and spells.</p>
    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="./images/mir_fireborn_battle.jpg"><img src="./images/mir_fireborn_battle_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Battle" /></a>
    </div>
<p>The Fireborn had not lived for four thousand years by acting rashly.  He knew when he was out-matched.  He was already chanting his darkspeech, preparing to return to his own world when the first arrow pierced his side.  His spell fizzled when a stunning blast from the outstretched hand of a dwarven bladeswinger knocked him back.  The sword wielders of the party where on him in an instant, tearing into his thick red skin and through his leathery wings.  He ripped at them with claws lined with fire, inflicting hideous gaping wounds but blue waves of light sealed them and the party continued their attack.</p>

<p>Then a voice filled his head, a telepathic voice in the darkspeech of the demon princes.  It was a voice he knew well.</p>

<p>"Hello, dear friend," Xuzl spoke.</p>

<p>"Master! Protect me from these hideous mortals!" the Fireborn pleaded in his own telepathic reply.</p>

<p>"You cannot win, especially not against one holding me," the voice spoke calmly.</p>

<p>The Fireborn saw it.  A circular shield blazing with fire held by the golden-armored priest.  A thousand questions entered his mind but all of them were silenced when a beam of searing red energy burned a perfect hole through the center of his head like a third eye.  The last thing he saw was the shield blazing with fire, the fire of his master.  He awoke on his island of rock in the center of a thousand mile lake of lava in the Plane of Fire.  It would be five hundred years before he could return to Norrath again.  Streams of lava rolled down his red cheeks.  He had been betrayed.</p>

      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2004-01-15T13:28:50+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 44: Deepest Guk</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001061.html</link>
      <description>Loral&apos;s head swam with the clues and rumors he had heard as he and his traveling companions walked through the...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1061@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Loral's head swam with the clues and rumors he had heard as he and his traveling companions walked through the upper caverns of the Froglok city of Guk.  He had heard of a curse of ancient evil and of the Grozmok stone but his pondering became circular as they walked.  Llyan the ranger was in front with Stonehewer the dwarven paladin, Juror the barbarian shaman, Loral the elven cleric, Kaylessa the elven enchantress, and Criket the Vah Shir beastlord in the rear.  Criket's warder, a five hundred pound striped cat, followed behind to make sure no beasts would take them by surprise.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="./images/guk_undead_frog.jpg"><img src="./images/guk_undead_frog_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Undead Guktan" /></a>
    </div>

<p>Loral's thoughts of these rumors ceased when he came to the boarded passage that led to the deepest caverns of Guk.  It had been blocked by the Frogloks themselves after their scouting parties came screaming back out or did not come back at all. Stonehewer turned to the rest of the party, smiled, and kicked in the boarded up cavern entrance.  It was a typical dwarven conclusion to the topic of whether or not they should continue.</p>

<p>A foul air rose from the passage.  Strong winds howled through the tunnels.  The scraping and cracking of the deeper tunnels unnerved the party.  Finding strength within each other, the party continued into the complex network of caverns.</p>

<p>Stonehewer's cry of surprise and the twang of Llyan's bow were Loral's first warning of danger.  He saw the sagging grey-skinned creature crawling towards them with long fingered hands and webbed feet.  Its long infected tongue lolled out, dragging on the ground behind it.  Llyan's arrow had burst one of the milky dead eyes of the beast.  Yellow liquid dripped down its grey rotted cheek like a broken egg yoke.  The smell gagged Loral, making him stop in the middle of a prayer and ruining the spell he began to cast.  Loral saw bones tearing through the dead flesh of the beast.  There was no doubt that they faced the crawling hungry dead of Deepest Guk.</p>
    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="./images/guk_undead_frog_2.jpg"><img src="./images/guk_undead_frog_2_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Undead Guktan" /></a>
    </div>
<p>Another of Llyan's arrows ripped into the beasts throat before Criket's warder roared in, tearing the beast apart with four inch claws.  The shock of the beast wore off Stonehewer. The paladin took three menacing steps forward and with a powerful overhand cut, severed the beast in two.</p>

<p>For twelve hours the party battled the undead minions of Guk, some rotting husks of recent adventurers, some ancient skeletal remains of Guk's ancestors.  Occationally a ghastly figure would form through the walls, spirits of the tormented dead of Guk, and rake at the party with ethereal claws.  Crossing into a large cavern of vine covered stone and green pools of bacteria, the party felt something else.</p>
    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="./images/guk_eye.jpg"><img src="./images/guk_eye_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Oculous" /></a>
    </div>
<p>A hissing vibration filled the room.  The party felt it in their teeth and lower parts of their mind, the parts that will pull a hand out of a fire without thinking.  The hiss got louder and one of the strangest beast they had seen rounded one of the caverns corners.  It floated in the air about four feet off the ground.  It had a spherical bony shell surrounding a huge eye that stared angrily at them.  Tentacles, some ending in hideous mouths with needle-like teeth, others ending with sharp jagged blades, wiggled angrily at the party.  The hiss lowered its pitch and began to shake the party's nerves, paralyzing them.</p>

<p>The creature floated calmly over to the elven maiden, Kaylessa, preparing three of the vile mouths to tear into her soft skin.  With his remaining stamina, Llyan broke from the paralyzing grip of the eye's mental attack, drew his thin blade, and stabbed it in the most likely of targets, dead center in the huge eye.  The Oculus burst, spraying the party with fluid.  An inhuman primal scream filled their mind, reaching pitches beyond the capabilities of the mind to comprehend.  They fell to the ground in agony but as the thrashes of the eye began to slow, the pain went away.  Soon, it was dead and the party stood staring at horrifying creature with Llyan's blade protruding from its black pupal.</p>

<p>Oblivious to the battles above him the lich-priest, Bhotea, sat huddled over a web shrouded tome.  For the better part of a year he had researched this dark work.  Its words and runes twisted and reformed the more he read.  His body had begun to decay since reading the dark book, feeding its evil, but the priest no longer cared.  His longtime traveling companion, once a Guktan Paladin of Mithanial Marr, lay on a stone alter dissected and disemboweled.  He was a small sacrifice in the pursuit of power, thought Bhotea.</p>
    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="./images/guk_eye_2.jpg"><img src="./images/guk_eye_2.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Ocluous" /></a>
    </div>
<p>A blazing flash of light in the corridor ahead of him tore the lich's attention from his beloved book.  He did not expect to see what he saw.  A dwarf, armored in shining blue plate armor, was stained with the black blood of the undead minions that shared this cavern with the lich.  His skin was ashen from the ethereal wounds of dozens of ghastly spectres but his eyes burned with a blazing life the lich no longer knew.</p>

<p>Stonehewer charged in holding his twin-bladed sword high.  The undead priest raised his hand and a blast of magical energy sent Stonehewer crashing to the ground.  Two arrows from Llyan's bow streaked in but a wave of the lich's hand turned them into dust before they reached him.  Juror blew a small wisp of dust from his hand.  The cloud grew into millions of tiny insects that roared around the lich.  The lich chanted three words and black tentacles burst from the floor around the barbarian, tearing into his legs and dragging him to the ground.  Criket and her warder both rushed in but were repelled by the same barrier that stopped Llyan's arrows.  The lich-priest grasped out with his clawed hand and made a fist in the air.  Criket came off the ground, crushed within a huge invisible hand.  Loral heard Criket's bones snapping as she floated in the air a few feet from the lich.</p>
    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="./images/guk_lich_battle.jpg"><img src="./images/guk_lich_battle_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Lich Priest" /></a>
    </div>
<p>Kaylessa chanted her own spell.  A tiny black ball formed in her hand. It flew from the elven enchantress and smashed into the lich's invisible barrier with the sound of shattered glass.  Criket collapsed into a heap on the ground.  Stonehewer, understanding the significance of what happened, rose and approached the small undead wizard.  He cut powerfully and the lich's decomposing head flew into the air followed by a gyser of black sour blood.</p>

<p>Two days later the party sat outside the Wayfarer's Southern Ro camp.  Criket, now fully healed, sent her cat after Llyan who ran merrily in wolf form.  Juror and Kaylessa were speaking with one of the Wayfarers while Stonehewer tried with frustration to polish off the black acidic blood of the lich from his silver blade.  Loral, a small black-skinned journal in his hand, wrote of their adventure and his thoughts.</p>

<p>"I do not know what the Wayfarer's want, but I know that no evil such as the liches of Deepest Guk should remain."  Loral penned carefully.  "While their motivations are unknown the Wayfarer's instruction has aided the forces of good.  Perhaps I was wrong about them."</p>

      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-12-29T00:05:22+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loral&apos;s Statistics and Equipment</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001055.html</link>
      <description> Level 65 High Elf Cleric of Tunare All current statistics and equipment are being tracked on Loral&apos;s Allakhazam Character...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1055@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<img alt="Loral Ciriclight" height="520" width="300" src="./images/loral_in_gold.jpg" class="imageset1" /> 
      <h2>Level 65 High Elf Cleric of Tunare</h2>
<p>All current statistics and equipment are being tracked on <a href="http://everquest.allakhazam.com/profile.html?44568">Loral's Allakhazam Character Sheet</a></p>
<!-- 
      <h2>Statistics</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>Hitpoints: 2533 (4388 self buffed)</li>
        <li>Armor Class: 1059 (1165 self buffed)</li>
        <li>Attack: 799</li>
        <li>Strength: 133</li>
        <li>Stamina: 152</li>
        <li>Agility: 161</li>
        <li>Dexterity: 167</li>
        <li>Wisdom: 340</li>
        <li>Intelligence: 160</li>
        <li>Charisma: 140</li>
        <li>Save Vs. Poison: 74</li>
        <li>Save Vs. Magic: 118</li>
        <li>Save Vs. Disease: 76</li>
        <li>Save Vs. Fire: 79</li>
        <li>Save Vs. Cold: 129</li>
      </ul>
      <h2>Focus, Effects, and Flowing Thought</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>15% Spell Duration Decrease</li>
        <li>1% to 20% Direct Healing Increase</li>
        <li>1% to 23% Direct Damage Increase</li>
        <li>10% Mana Cost Decrease</li>
        <li>Ultravision</li>
        <li>See Invisible</li>
        <li>Flowing Thought 15</li>
        <li>22% Melee Haste</li>
      </ul>
      <h2>Equipment</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>Ear: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Earring+of+the+Solstice">Earring of the Solstice</a> (Flowing Thought 1)</li>
        <li>Neck: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Choker+of+the+Wretched">Choker of the Wretched</a> (Flowing Thought 1)</li>
        <li>Face: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Tobrin+Mystical+Eyepatch">Tobrin's Mystical Eyepatch</a> with Chilling Orb of Dark Sight (See Invisible / Ultravision)</li>
        <li>Head: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Coil+of+Twisted+Platinum+Wire">Coil of Twisted Platinum Wire</a> (Flowing Thought 2)</li>
        <li>Ear: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Earring+of+Purity">Earring of Purity</a> (Clickable Cure Poison)</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li>Finger: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Ring+of+Ice+Oddities">Ring of Ice Oddities</a> with Gleaming Prism of Destruction (Anger of Druzzil, 1% to 23% direct spell damage increase)</li>
        <li>Wrist: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Wristplates+of+Vengeful+Fury">Wristplates of Vengeful Fury</a> (Flowing Thought 2)</li>
        <li>Arms: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Akkirus'+Vambraces+of+the+Risen">Akkirus' Vambraces of the Risen</a></li>
        <li>Gloves: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Silver+Chitin+Hand+Wraps">Silver Chitin Hand Wraps</a> (22% melee haste)</li>
        <li>Wrist: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Wristplates+of+Vengeful+Fury">Wristplates of Vengeful Fury</a> (Flowing Thought 2)</li>
        <li>Finger: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Cloudy+Ring+of+Pneumatic+Force">Cloudy Ring of Pneumatic Force</a></li>
        <li>Alternate Finger: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Knotted+Turtlebone+Ring">Knotted Turtlebone Ring</a> (Enduring Breath)</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li>Shoulders: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Shining+Crimson+Shawl">Shining Crimson Shawl</a> (Mana Preservation 4, 10% less mana on all spells)</li>
        <li>Chest: <a href="http://everquest.allakhazam.com/db/item.html?item=23603">Malevolent Breastplate of Suffering</a> with Brilliant Enchanted Prism (Flowing Thought 2)</li>
        <li>Back: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Gleamscale+Cape">Gleamscale Cape</a> (Healing Improvement 4, 1% to 20% direct healing increase)</li>
        <li>Waist: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Belt+of+Thunderous+Auras">Belt of Thunderous Auras</a> (Flowing Thought 2)</li>
        <li>Legs: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Akkirus'+Greaves+of+the+Risen">Akkirus' Greaves of the Risen</a> (clickable Word of Healing, 100 point group heal)</li>
        <li>Feet: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Boots+of+Flowing+Slime">Boots of Flowing Slime</a> (Flowing Thought 3)</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li>Primary Hand (Raid / Casting): <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Water+Sprinkler+of+Nem+Ankh">Water Sprinkler of Nem Ankh</a> (Clickable Reviviscense, Resurrection with 96% experience restoration)</li>
        <li>Primary Hand (Melee): <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Hammer+of+Damnation">Hammer of Damnation</a> (Proc: Wrath of the Gods)</li>
        <li>Secondary Hand: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=Circular+Shield+of+the+Blaze">Circular Shield of the Blaze</a> (Haste of Solusek, 10% spellhaste for direct damage spells)</li>
        <li>Ranged: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/item.html?id=29037">Ceramic Totem of Xegony</a> (Spell Haste, 20% decrease in casting time)</li>
        <li>Ammo: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/itemlist.html?searchtext=White+Rope+Bridle">White Rope Bridle</a> (Summon Mount, the white horse Illumina)</li>
        <li>Charm: <a href="http://lucy.fnord.net/item.html?id=35008">Intricate Wooden Figurine</a> with Adventurer's Stone</li>
      </ul>
      <h2>Cash</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>45,000 Platinum</li>
      </ul>
      <h2>Alternate Advancement Abilities (196 total points)</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>+3 Strength</li>
        <li>Run Speed 3</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li>Spell Casting Mastery 3</li>
        <li>Spell Casting Fury 3</li>
        <li>Healing Adapt 3</li>
        <li>Healing Gift 3</li>
        <li>Spell Casting Reinforcement 3</li>
        <li>Mental Clarity 3</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li>Celestial Regeneration</li>
        <li>Divine Resurrection</li>
        <li>Mass Group Buff</li>
        <li>Spell Casting Reinforcement Mastery</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li>Planar Power 3</li>
        <li>Innate Enlightenment 5</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li>Advanced Healing Gift 3</li>
        <li>Advanced Healing Adapt 3</li>
        <li>Celestial Renewel 2</li>
        <li>Divine Arbitration 3</li>
        <li>Fury of Magic 3</li>
        <li>Radiant Cure 3</li>
      </ul>
      <h2>Flags</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>All PoP flags including Plane of Time, only one Justice Trial</li>
        <li>Sebilis, Howling Stones, Sleepers Tomb</li>
        <li>No Vex Thal, No Veeshan's Peaks</li>
      </ul>
-->
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-12-01T19:31:16+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 43: The Wayfarers</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001052.html</link>
      <description>The two elves glanced nervously about the crowded inn. They did not much enjoy leaving their fair wood of the...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1052@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>The two elves glanced nervously about the crowded inn.  They did not much enjoy leaving their fair wood of the Faydark but their most recent employment demanded it.  Leaving the wood was bad enough but traveling through the Spires to the moon of Luclin was even more disturbing.</p>

<p>Talamiin, the older of the two and a seasoned warrior, spoke little as he sat hunched over his untouched ale.  He glanced at the adventurers entering the tavern, hoping to finish this job and be done with it.</p>

<p>"Have you met him before?" Silvian, the younger and far more eager elf, asked.  Talamiin shook his head.  "The guards of Felwithe speak of him."  Silvian continued, not noticing his companion's disinterest.  "He is a high priest with both Exarch and Archon titles of the church," Silvian continued. "He has been in the wilds since the discovery of Kunark.  He only returns to resupply himself and report to the church.  He is usually back out within twelve hours.  The loose lipped acolytes say that every promotion or title has been an attempt to bring him back.  Most priests his age have either returned to Felwithe or left the church.  But he won't come back and he won't leave."</p>

<p>"There are darker rumors as well."  Silvian lowered his voice. "Some say he consorts with demons and other dark powers.  He has traveled with ogres, trolls, even Tier'dal, at one time or another.  But he is still an agent of the Church, probably one of their best it is said."</p>

<p>"He is a murderer and a monster," the older elf spoke suddenly.  "Three years ago he killed a fellow cleric who interrupted one of his dark rituals.  The church says he was under a curse, but I think they still needed him rather than have him beheaded as he should have been.  It doesn't matter.  Here he is."</p>

<p>Silvian looked to the door and saw the cloaked figure enter.  He was tall and stood straight.  From under his hood he beheld the room through a pair of multi-colored spectacles.  Behind the curious spectacles, Silvian saw his cold blue eyes, eyes that seemed to stare beyond the walls of the room.  Silvian saw Loral's golden armor under his cloak, tarnished with weeks of travel.  Loral's eyes locked onto the two elves as he approached their table.  Silvian nodded to the priest and raised two fingers to his chest in a sign of blessing to the Mother of All, Tunare.  Loral casually returned the gesture.  Talamiin did nothing.</p>

<p>"I hear you have information for me."  Loral's voice sent shivers through Silvian.  He became aware that he was looking at the same high elf that had faced the rulers of Kunark, had battled against the devils of the outer planes,   had defeated the avatars of no less than twelve gods, four of them elder gods, and had faced and returned from the trials of the dragons of the Claws.</p>

<p>Talamiin kicked Silvian's chair and Silvian jumped.  Talamiin nodded to him to give their information.  Silvian was aware of Talamiin's dislike of the priest and he was aware that Loral was aware.  It seemed not to concern Loral, and Silvian began his tale.</p>

<p>"The Wayfarers have agents in every known city of Norrath.  They do not attempt to hide their presence but their popularity gives them access to a vast amount of information.  They have wizards and telepaths to share information among their agents and their camps."  Silvian paused for a moment.  "In three months the Wayfarers have become the most well informed, well connected, well financed, and with their mercenary force of adventurers, the most powerful organization of Norrath."</p>

<p>Loral looked down to the table for a moment, considering the words.  Then he spoke again.</p>

<p>"Where do they come from?"</p>

<p>"Their leader is a barbarian rogue named Mordin Rasp.  He and some adventurer friends of his formed the core of the Wayfarers.  They seem to have a limitless supply of magical artifacts which they reward to adventurers who work for them.  Their job seems honorable enough."  Silvian paused again, carefully considering his next words.  "Felwithe has supported their cause."</p>

<p>Loral's eyes shot up, locking hard onto Silvian's.  Silvian stiffened, not expecting such a quick and powerful reaction to his subtle implication.  He was not accusing Loral of subversion, but why would the priest hire them to look into a situation Felwithe had already dismissed.</p>

<p>"A group shows up out of nowhere.  In two months its agents infiltrate every city.  Their camps become small towns visited by the most powerful hunters of our world.  They are rich, powerful, and better connected than any other organization.  As soon as they appear, dens of some of the worst evil we have ever seen suddenly appear.  We do not know where they come from, we do not know what they want, and no one questions their appearance.  Felwithe may not be worried, but I am."</p>

<p>Loral reached under his cloak and dropped a bag onto the table.  Silvian sat with his mouth agape as Loral stood and left.  He looked to his companion and saw a smile on Talamiin's face.</p>

<p>"I may have been wrong about him after all."</p>

      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-11-27T23:12:44+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 42: Aviatis</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001044.html</link>
      <description> Loral sat in a dwarven tavern outside of the city of Kaladim. He drank the thick liquid of dwarven...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1044@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>Loral sat in a dwarven tavern outside of the city of Kaladim. He drank the thick liquid of dwarven ale, the sweetest and weakest the bartender had available but still far too thick for Loral's taste. He spent very little time in this area nowadays, but rumors of the Wayfarers had him looking for information. This band of treasure-seekers seemed to appear out of nowhere, quickly building camps across Norrath. Rumors spoke of the treasures they promised to any who explored newly discovered dens of evil. Having heard of the location of the Wayfarer camp from a drunken dwarf just before passing out, Loral closed his leather-bound journal, returned it to a pouch at his side, and left for the camp.</p>

    <p>On reaching the Wayfarer's camp, he was immediately shocked by the sheer volume and excitement of the people around it. Hundreds of adventurers milled about.   Some were young and inexperienced and others were obviously seasoned and powerful. The Wayfarers themselves were as diverse as those who sought them out. Dark elves and wood elves chatted together while barbiarians and trolls toasted each other with giant flagons of mead.  It pleased Loral to see such diversity.  This breaking of racial barriers hadn't been seen on Norrath since the fall of the Combine empire.</p>

    <p>Joining the Wayfarers was not difficult and Loral was quickly given a task to perform. Loral traveled to an exhumed graveyard in the cursed forest of Lesser Faydark where a network of caverns had been found under a lost cemetery. One of the graves had broken into a pit leading into the caverns below.  Many adventurers gathered around the excavation and the remains of dozens of bodies were scattered about. The whole hill smelled of death.  Loral looked with trepidation into the pit.</p>

    <p>A strong clap on Loral's back gave him a jolt and the stout dwarf Stonehewer laughed at the expression of shock on Loral's face. Juror the shaman smiled behind the dwarf with two of his bladeswingers, Llyan and Vamcill by his side. Kaylessa, one of Felwithe's adventuring enchanters and friend to the guild of Healers, approached as well. Their party was ready. With one last prayer to Tunare, Loral and his companions dropped into the pit.</p>

    <p>Thick liquids of tainted life and mists of tormented souls seeped into the broken earth, filling the rats, bats, and spiders inside with a lust for blood and fearsome strength. Jointed legs covered in coarse hair dragged the bulk of huge spiders through the caverns. The white sightless eyes of giant rats turned towards the party and lines of diseased drool spattered to the ground. As soon as the mutated beasts sensed the adventuring party, they attacked.</p>

    <p>The party fought the masses of tainted beasts for hours. Powerful magics broke open the shells of the huge spiders. Thick lumps of black gore fell onto the ground. Llyan pierced the boated bodies of the giant rats, pinning them squealing to the earth. The chanting of the party's spellcasters was almost continuous as wave after wave of the creatures vomited forth from the infected caverns. As grotesque as these creatures were, the party soon faced a far more dangerous foe.</p>

    <p>Standing calmly, the slight female figure could easily have been mistaken for an elf except for the sickly pale skin. She stood and beheld them calmly, her eyes gleaming silver in the torch light. Her grey lips twisted into a smile, revealing long fangs. She attacked with unnatural speed and went right for Loral's throat. Were it not for Stonehewer's quick movements she would have torn it open.</p>

    <p>Stonehewer cleaved his firey blade towards her back. She twisted quickly avoiding the blade and swiped a claw at the dwarven knight, tearing four deep gashes into his face. Loral sealed the deep wounds with a prayer to Tunare. Juror cupped his hands and a roar of tiny insects engulfed the vampiress. Vamcill's red-runed scimitar cut down hard, splitting her open from her shoulder down to her hip.</p>

    <p>Two caverns away, Aviatis opened his own silver eyes, his telepathic bond to the Scion broken. He turned and fixed his eyes on his two black-robed advisors. They nodded silently and stepped out into the cavern entrance.</p>

    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="./images/mistmoore_trueborn.jpg"><img src="./images/mistmoore_trueborn_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Trueborn" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>As much as the Scion Caretaker's attack had shaken the party, the two Trueborn's were far more sinister. They were a head taller than the party's biggest member and covered in thick black robes deeply embroidered in red and gold. Their gaunt faces peered out from under the deep hoods with sunken cheeks and dead eyes. One raised his palms towards the party and waves of flames roared onto the party. The other drew a wicked blade engraved with skulls and coated with his own black blood.  Stonehewer cut at blade wielder but the Trueborn sidestepped faster than the dwarf could see.</p>

    <p>Stonehewer grunted, pulled his blade back, and stabbed deep into the vampire's stomach. The vampire smiled, gripped Stonehewer's wrist, and with inhuman strength forced the blade out of his body. Blue waves flowed from the second Trueborn's hands and the mortal wound sealed.</p>

    <p>Stonehewer grunted again at this bad turn of luck. With one Trueborn healing the other, they would outlast the party's attacks. Stonehewer fixed the solution in typical dwarven style by smashing the spellcasting vampire in the mouth with his armored fist. The Trueborn reeled, his jaw broken. Black blood and jagged teeth spattered to the ground. Stonehewer looked down to his stained fist and grunted a third time.</p>

    <p>"I'll never get this stuff off," he said shaking the dark blood from his fist. With a half turn and powerful swing, Stonehewer swung his two handed sword again. The pale head of the first Trueborn fell into the dirt.</p>

    <p>Loral locked eyes with the second Trueborn who held his broken jaw with fingers covered in dark blood. Loral raised his hand and chanted to Tunare. A beam of white light bored into the vampire's chest and ripped out the tormented spirit. The dead corpse fell to the ground in a smoking heap.</p>

    <p>While they had vanquished the minions of Aviatis, the lord himself was beyond their estimations. Aviatis had climbed the ranks of the Trueborns for centuries and he did not do it by being either stupid or weak. They saw him standing alone in the center of his inner sanctum. He was even taller than the Trueborns they had faced before. Vamcill strode forward without a word, but they were not prepared for the reaction.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="./images/mistmoore_aviatis.jpg"><img src="./images/mistmoore_aviatis_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Trueborn" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>Loral felt his blood become thick. His heart slowed and he became instantly weak. His head throbbed in pain that blurred his vision on every pulse. He was faintly aware that the others were clutching at their chests and falling to their knees. Juror's spear clattered to the ground. Within merely the presence of the vampire lord, they had already lost.</p>

    <p>Loral heard the voice within his mind. The demon Xuzl spoke to him, told him to use the power within the shield on his arm. The horrible effect of the vampire's spell lifted and Loral found himself able to concentrate. He rose in front of the surprised vampire lord and with a quick swing, smashed the lord in the knee with his spiritual hammer, Daninulaer. A burst of white fire exploded over the vampire lord.</p>

    <p>Aviatis howled with rage and pain. His spell had broken. The others returned to their feet, quickly preparing their most powerful magics or most devastating attacks. Llyan fired arrow after arrow into the vampire. Many skipped harmlessly over the vampire lord's protective spells but some burrowed deep into the vampire's dead skin. A black tendril rolled off of Juror's palm and burrowed deep into the vampire's skin. The skin cracked and oozed black blood. Stonehewer strode in.</p>

    <p>The vampire's head snapped up and he punched out. A huge spiritual fist followed the move and blasted Stonehewer back against the rocky wall, crushing the wind out of him and knocking him unconscious. Aviatis whirled again and shards of ice ripped through the party. Clinching his jaw against the pain, Juror strode forward and rammed his spear deep into the lord's chest, piercing its black heart. The vampire and Juror locked eyes with each other. Juror ripped out the spear and the vampire fell dead to the ground.</p>

    <p>They had taken what trinkets they had found along the way back to the Wayfarers. Among the treasures of the vampire lord was a worn leather book. It had deep engravings in the thick cover, a cover of some skin Loral preferred not to think about, and on its back was a strange symbol or glyph. The language was old and it would take him much time to translate. He did not yet know that its message held the fate of Norrath within it.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-10-22T20:47:47+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 41: Banishment</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000199.html</link>
      <description> It had been seven years since Loral had retired from his days of adventure, but he had one last...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">199@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>It had been seven years since Loral had retired from his days of adventure, but he had one last job to do.  Loral walked slowly around the cavern, carefully inspecting every detail of the large room. Any flaw in its construction could spell disaster for those within, and eventually all of Norrath. Two large ballistae, huge crossbows with bolts two meters long, were bolted to the floor corners of the room. Seeing these siege weapons in such a small room would make no sense to any outside observer, but to Loral, they were critically important. Loral checked the chains that ran across the floor ending at two huge stone wheels on the far end.  Loral looked to the two armored barbarians that stood to the sides of the large wheels, iron hammers slung over their shoulders.  He turned and looked to the two elves that manned the giant crossbows.  The resolve of these warriors would be more critical than the flawless engineering of the room and its furnishings. They were about to see something few mortals ever did, and fewer still ever lived to talk about it.</p>

    <p>Loral took out a black gem from a pouch on his belt. A single word activated the priceless gem, and once activated it could never be deactivated.  The huge crossbows, the unbreakable chains, and the strength of the warriors would all fail if the gem was not activated properly. Each was a piece of a large puzzle, each had to be put in at just the right time or they would all die.  Loral took a deep breath.  It was time to release Xuzl. Loral took the battered shield off of his back and set it in the center of the floor.</p>

    <p>"Awaken Xuzl. You are free."</p>

    <p>A vibration filled the room, rattling the chains on the floor and drawing concerned looks from the guards. The edge of the shield began to glow and then burst into flame. The circle expanded outward forming a large pool of fire. A sudden blast of hot air filled the room as the portal to the Plane of Fire opened.</p>

    <p>A red claw reached out of the pool and gripped the stone floor. Another claw followed the first and the two heaved up the rest of the demon's bulk from the pit. Xuzl's green eyes beheld the small priest.  The foolish priest had kept his word.  Xuzl was free.</p>

    <p>Upon blackened hooves, Xuzl stood above the fiery pit.  He stretched his full fifteen feet height expanding his wings to the edges of the room.  He beheld the priest again with his burning green eyes, he hissing laughter filling Loral's mind.</p>

    <p>"Ganthalrom"</p>

    <p>The word of command activated the black gem. The shine from Loral's earrings and rings faded.  Two magical gems that lit the room darkened immediately but the four torches of the room stayed lit.  The demon felt the shell of invisible protection surrounding his huge frame disappear. He called upon a column of lava to incinerate the priest but no fire came. All of his magical powers were gone along with all other magic in the room.  All magic within one hundred feet of the black gem ceased to exist.</p>

    <p>It mattered little to Xuzl. Even without his powerful magic, the demon was stronger than a the Ice Giants of Permafrost. He could crush all five of these pitiful creatures with a single stone. That was when he noticed the ballistae.</p>

    <p>"Fire"</p>

    <p>Two huge bolts, each a six foot steel rod tipped with a black barbed tip, tore through Xuzl's arms. The huge chains, attached to the end of the bolts, raced up the ground and criss crossed Xuzl's massive chest. Xuzl roared and the guardians felt their knees grow week. One of the elves manning the ballistae fell to the ground, his hands covering his head.</p>

    <p>The two barbarians bashed out two logs that held the stone wheels in place with their hammers. Behind the wall, a four ton stone weight fell. A network of levers and pulleys behind the wall pulled the chains tight around the beast. Four huge chains wrapped the demon around the chest, crushing the bones of the beast's wings.  Three more wrapped around its legs.  Xuzl was pinned to the wall, the chains held tight by the huge stone weight.  The strength of twenty frost giants could not break their bond.</p>

    <p>Loral had spent years studying the powers of extraplanar creatures and in almost all cases they had three powerful weapons; physical strength, magical abilities, and psionics . Two of the demon's three weapons had been removed.  Only one remained.</p>

    <p>While magical energies were drawn from the outer planes or their gods, even from one plane to another, the psychic abilities of outer planar demons came from a different source.  Unlike magical energy which would be stopped by the black gem, psychic energy worked on the internal powers of the mind and would be unaffected. Sometimes these psychic effects were subtle. Xuzl's was not.</p>

    <p>The elf that manned the left ballistae screamed, a scream so violent that his throat ripped itself apart from the strain. Blood flowed from his eyes and ears, running rivers down his cheeks. Loral felt his stomach heave when he heard a small pop and the elf fell dead to the stone floor, his brain crushed under the might of Xuzl's powers.</p>

    <p>The barbarian to the beast's left took out a large black shining helm he had hanging on his back. The helm cost almost as much as the black gem, its shape forged from instructions over five thousand years old. It was built from a material known to block the mental intrusions of the Shissar and was used as armor by the ogres of Old Norrath. The ogres used the armor to keep psychic intrusion out, but this helm was designed to keep it in. Most importantly, the power of the helm to block psychic abilities was not magical but natural.  It would work within the stones antimagic shell.</p>

<p>The ogre put the helm over Xuzl's huge head, the form fitting perfectly around the demon's black horns and covered the green burning eyes of the demon with smooth black metal. A latch clamped the helm shut, tight against the creature's head.  Loral let out a sigh of relief.  Had the helm not fit, they would have all died as their elven companion had.</p>

    <p>Xuzl felt his senses crash down. He could no longer hear the thoughts and emotions of the attackers. He could not send out his psychic tendrils into their minds. He could not summon his powers to call forth waves of lava or reopen a gateway back to his home world.  He could not even see.  For the first time in fifty thousand years of life, the arch-demon Xuzl was afraid.</p>

    <p>Loral watched the chest muscles of the huge beast flex against the strain of the giant chains. He saw the black claw clench into a fist and extend as if reach for something, anything. The chains pinned the creature completely to the wall, his arms wrapped around him in some obscene embrace.  Xuzl's roar got softer and softer, turning into an inhuman whimper as the chains tightened around his chest. Loral could not see Xuzl's eyes under the black helm, but the whimper was one that brought no hatred into Loral's mind.</p>

    <p>For the first time since contemplating the trapping of this unholy beast, Loral had doubt. He would have thought this feeling was one of Xuzl's psychic tricks, but with the black helm in place he knew such a trick was impossible. Who was he to trap so mighty a creature? He had orchestrated and carried out a plan to trap this beast forever within this tomb. What right did he have to do so?</p>

    <p>Another vision filled Loral's head. One of the beast Xuzl plucking an armored female elf off of a hill far away in the lands of Tunaria. The beast flew high, crushing the screaming paladin in an immortally strong grip. With a smile and a chuckle, the demon bit off her screaming head and swallowed it whole.</p>

    <p>Loral's vision snapped back to the trapped beast, faceless under the black helm. To remove such a creature from the world of Norrath was necessary. To have such a power free in the mortal world or even the planes was against all that was good.</p>

    <p>Loral and his remaining companions left the chamber, sealing the door behind them. After a few hours, the torches burned themselves out and the room was black.  The only sound was the forced breathing of the demon, his chest too constrict to scream or even speak.</p>

    <p>Loral walked past the illusionary treasure room filled with a king's ransom in platinum and magical items. Two stone guardians, built and enchanted by gnomish arch-mages stood motionless, protecting the room from intrusion forever. Should any adventurers get this far, an almost impossible feat, they would think the treasure room to be the final victory.  None would suspect the giant rock on the opposite wall to contain the unholy beast Xuzl, and his eternal tomb.</p>

<p>Thoughts of the demon flowed out of Loral as the thick liquid of the potion of forgetfulness flowed down his throat. In moments, he and his three remaining companions would forget the entire experience. It was the only way to ensure their secret remained so. All three stepped out of the maze-like catacombs and into the inner chambers of the Church of Tunare. Soon all three were walking through the streets of Felwithe, the encounter and its location already forgotten.</p>

    <p>None of them remembered that a few hundred feet below the streets of the elven city of Felwithe, chained to the wall and bathed in pitch blackness, hissed the eternal breath of Xuzl the demon. The demon, however, would never forget.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-09-30T20:27:59+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 40: Shades of Grey</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/001028.html</link>
      <description>For six years I have served the Emerald Guardians. I was proud to wear their leaf on my cloak and...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1028@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p><em>For six years I have served the Emerald Guardians.  I was proud to wear their leaf on my cloak and eager to serve the people who had felt such torment at the fall of Takish Hiz.  It was a joy to travel to the far reaches of Tunaria as an agent of the Guardians.  It may now be my greatest pain.</em></p>

<p><em>Scores of orcs have fallen to my arrows.  The goblin witch, Teshtuzu, spit out her last curse when my blade crossed her throat.  I traveled to Diren's Hold and defeated the great bear, Trapmaw.  But then my duties changed.  I was sent west to find a Tier'Dal Enchanter and his prisoner, an elven maiden whose mind had been broken with his poisoned words.  I found them at an inn in Highbourne.  The Tier'Dal's wicked magics ceased when I cut off his hands and then his head.  A stab of my guardian's blade ended the screams of the mind-warped elven maiden.  It wasn't until her hand reached out to her dead lover that the truth reached me.  Charmed vessels do not cry over fallen masters.</em></p>

<p><em>Troubled, I followed new instructions to head south through the desert of Ro to recover an artifact of the church of Tunare stolen by a fallen priestess.  It took me weeks to find her, deep in the swamps of Guk on a ruined pyramid of an old, dark god.  She was in prayer to whatever dark god she now served when my first arrow tore into her side.  A wolf-shaped demon attacked me from the shadows.  The elven enchantments of my blades ripped into its ghostly form and it burst into smoke.  Tesarin Moonstrider clutched the chalice to her breast, her prayers never ceasing, even when I plunged my thin scimitar through her chest to the hilt.  It was difficult to understand the prayers she whispered as life left her.  One thing rang clear.  They were prayers to Tunare.</em></p>

<p><em>For six years I have been an agent of the Fayspires.  Through bureaucratic double-talk and false patriotism they have turned me into a weapon.  I believed I was a ranger of Tunaria, serving the will of the Mother.  Tunare has left Tunaria and left behind the salted earth of a once-great elven empire.  Ranger is not the right word for what I am.  The world is not black and white.  I am Tarlin the Grey.</em></p>
<p><em>I am an assassin.</em></p>
<p>- From the journals of Tarlin of Tunaria</p>

<p>Loral pushed the worn leather journal across the table, knocking over his glass and spilling his red wine on the table.  The words hit him like a hammer.  It shattered a fog that had surrounded him since the days he left for Kunark.  Their missions had never been to rescue the elf maiden, Fironia Vie, but to fill the treasure-rich lands of Kunark with those who served their interests.  It had all been a lie.</p>

<p>For decades Loral had followed the church's orders, traveling throughout Kunark, Velious, Luclin, and now the outer planes.  Their motives or goals were never clear.  Loral had never asked for justification. He was trained to follow the will of the church.  Now images of his past flashed into his mind as the words of his father, written five hundred years earlier, rang in his ears.  The death of the Overking Bathezid, the death of Venril Sather himself, the vampyre Xalgoz, General V'Ghera, Trakanon, Nagafen, Lady Vox, King Tormax, Innoruuk, Cazic Thule, Terris Thule, Bertoxxulous, Rallos Zek and his sons, all of them had been slain with Loral's assistance.  Hundreds had been slain to further the goals of the council of Felwithe, expanding their lands, their influence, and their coffers.</p>

<p>Loral had been their weapon.</p>

<p>He left the city of Tanaan at once and traveled to Felwithe with only one thought in his mind.  He must face Yeolarn.</p>

<p>The stone door slid open, splashing the room with harsh light.  Loral walked in, silouetted black against the white light of day behind him.  His explosive entrance sent the guards' hands to the hilts of their blades.  They softened when they recognized Loral, not because they no longer thought he was a threat, but because there was little they could do about it if he was.</p>

<p>Allia Moondancer smiled when she recognized Loral under the hood of his cloak but the smile dropped when she saw the fury in his blue eyes.  As unthinkable as it was, Allia saw the truth of this visit.  If this conversation did not go well, elven blood would spill in the church of Tunare.</p>

<p>"How long have I been an assassin of the church, Yeolarn?"  Loral roared.  "How long have you built me into the dagger of Felwithe?  How long did it take you to decide to feed me to the Shissar?  How surprised were you when I returned?"</p>

<p>Loral stopped dangerously close to the platform where Yeolarn stood.  The Tunarian priests had the words of their battlemagic on their lips, but few had great expectations for their success.  They foresaw their magics flowing off of Loral's enchanted armor like water.  They saw his ethereal hammer swing out impossibly fast, crushing the steel helmets of the guards along with the skulls inside.  They saw his magic, a chaotic magic fueled by a demon some had whispered, rip through them like thousands of blades.  All of the priests stood tense and ready.  All but Yeolarn, who leaned heavily on his staff as if Loral's questions added weight to his shoulders.</p>

<p>"We sent you to Ssraeshza because we could not send an army.  We sent you because you ARE an army.  How long have we battled Crushbone?  How long have we kept the orcs in check when you alone could kill every orc in Crushbone in two hours?  We do not send you to Crushbone because the orcs are necessary for the stability of Felwithe.  You are an agent of the church.  We send you to the far reaches of the land.  We send you into the pits of hell and we send you alone."</p>

<p>The scarred shield burned on Loral's arm.  Deep in his mind he heard the whispers of Xuzl.  <em>THEY HAVE BETRAYED YOU, ELF, AS THEY DID YOUR FATHER.  RAISE YOUR HAND AND SHOW THEM WHAT THEY HAVE DONE.  GIVE THEM THE JUSTICE THEY DESERVE.</em>.</p>

<p>"Felwithe is no single entity, it has no single mind," Yeolarn continued.  "The motivations of each council member is as different as we are from the Tier'Dal.  Some sent you to Luclin to see if Felwithe was in danger.  Others sent you to die.  We have many agents in the lands, each acting independently.  Some are killed.  Some break under the strain and turn against the Mother herself.  But you return.  You always have."</p>

<p>Loral felt his skin set fire from within.  <em>RELEASE ME.  RELEASE ME AND I WILL GIVE YOU VENGEANCE.  YOU CAN WALK AWAY WHILE THE CORRUPTION OF FELWITHE BURNS BEHIND YOU.  DESTROY THIS CITY THAT SO INSULTS THE NATURE OF TUNARE.</em>  Loral clenched his fists Yeolarn continued.</p>

<p>"Fironia Vie's name was a banner for our interests in Kunark.  Venril Sather needed to die, whether a threat to Felwithe or not.  Emperor Ssraeshza needed to die, whether he would have left his temple or not.  We send you because there is evil that must be destroyed.  It is not about the safety of Felwithe, it is about good and evil.  It is about the will of Tunare."</p>

<p>Loral's head swam.  Behind his eyes Xuzl screamed for release.  Visions filled Lorals mind of Xuzl exploding from the church and burning all of Felwithe in a great ball of fire.</p>

<p>"You knew the truth before you walked in that door.  You act in the interests of Tunare, in the interests of good.  You have done so before and you will do so again."</p>

<p>Yeolarn handed Loral a scroll sealed in wax.</p>

<p>"Takish Hiz has been found."</p>

<p>Silence filled Loral's mind as both he and the demon within his cursed shield considered this news.  Then the voice of Xuzl screamed again in a tongue thousands of years older than the elves.  Loral silenced him with a single thought, a single promise.</p>

<p>He would release Xuzl in Felwithe.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-09-01T03:20:21+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 39: Torment</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000204.html</link>
      <description>From the worn leather-bound journal of Loral Ciriclight buried on a shelf of infinite books in New Tanaan It was...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">204@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>From the worn leather-bound journal of Loral Ciriclight buried on a shelf of infinite books in New Tanaan</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="./images/torment_landscape.jpg"><img src="./images/torment_landscape_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Plane of Torment" /></a>
    </div>

<p>It was 3168 in the Age of Turmoil.  Only a few months earlier we found that all of Norrath's lands had been folded closer, connected to they planar city of New Tanaan in the Plane of Knowledge.  I remember how strange and wonderful it was traveling a short twelve steps between Felwithe and Halas, a trip that took six weeks by foot and boat.  Now these portals have entrenched themselves into every aspect of our society, changing a thousand years of culture and economics by the removal of geographical boundaries.  How quickly we have accepted these planar gateways and now treat them as a dirt path through the woods or an oak wheel on a cart.  They are commonplace to us now and few of us can ever recall the world without them.</p>

<p>Now powerful adventurers have entered the Plane of Time.  What changes will we find as hunters and treasure seekers begin tugging on the strings that tie together our past and future?  The swing of an enchanted blade may sever the chain our very existence or release horrors beyond imagination.  How can we possibly understand the ramifications of our actions?  The life of a quarter of a million Erudites could be snuffed out like the flame of a candle.</p>

<p>Why do we go?  I find myself asking this question often.  Is it the will of Tunare?  In the great balance of the outer planes, her realm and the hells of nightmare and disease cannot threaten each other.  Is it the will of the church and the safety of Felwithe?  I doubt the demons of these deep planes could comprehend such an intrusion.  We cannot be sure the demonkind could survive in our world at all.  The pollen of a flower may be as toxic to them as Trakanon's breath is to us.  Is it the thrill of adventure that pushes us to these outer worlds?  After seeing the darkness within some of these terrible places, one must question the sanity of such a motivation.</p>

    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="./images/torment_building.jpg"><img src="./images/torment_building_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Plane of Torment" /></a>
    </div>

<p>Few questions in life have simple answers.  Many variables drive our actions.  I cannot say why my friends and I entered the Plane of Torment but whatever the reasons, there we were.</p>

<p>I had seen the world of the banished in a vision some months previous, but I was unprepared for the feeling of sheer hopelessness as we beheld the horrible world.  There are very real dangers in this prison world but it is the mental terror that is the most dangerous.  Were it not for my stout friends, Stonehewer, Semidil, Kabbal, Juror, Vuldar, and Norque, I would have fled as soon as my eyes beheld the blood red sky and black sea.</p>

<p>The air in torment was thick and hot.  Though breathable, our bodies revolted with each forced breath, rejecting the smell and taste of blood and decay.  Faint screams, moans, and unsettling laughter rolled across the black water.  The cells of Torment, rooms suspended from chains that led up into the red haze of the infinite sky, held beasts older than Norrath.  Demons who spend their days within their own insanity, hating all life itself and wishing for the destruction of all life including their own.  With trepidation our party took our first steps onto the first of hundreds of suspended walkways.</p>

<p>The deafening scream of the bloodravens was our first welcome to this hell.  The psychic attack drowned out any ability to call upon our magical powers.  The beasts flew on oily black wings.  They stared at us with bloody eye-less sockets and filled our minds with visions of endless terror.  They ripped into our skin with a power and ferocity far beyond their size.  While our magical powers were limited, the blades of Stonehewer, Kabbal, and Semidil quickly cut down the demonic birds, their screaming fading along with whatever life force they had.</p>

<p>Within the mental screams of the eyeless bloodravens I heard the laughter of Xuzl.  The demonic entity trapped in my shield showed me just how unprepared we mortals were to even think we could understand what we were seeing.  The demon projected his feelings of elation woven into the thicker fabric of horror.  Even with his tauntings, his protections saved my life.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="./images/torment_demon.jpg"><img src="./images/torment_demon_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The battle of the Kaniz Hunter" /></a>
    </div>
		
<p>The Kaniz Hunter and Boruk Ravager made up for their lack of subtlety with pure physical power.  Like most creatures of the outer planes, their crude language was intermixed with telepathic visions of their intent to rip off our limbs and feast on our blood.  To feel the pleasure these unholy beasts felt at the thought or our own torture is a mental paradox beyond what mortal minds should face.  To see ones self as so alien a being is terrible indeed.</p>

<p>Thank Tunare that their physical forms were natural enough for blades and spells to combat.  Kabbal's great axe cut into the hoof of one, breaking the bone at an odd angle above its twisted backwards knee.  Far from defeated, the beast sunk its claws deep into Kabbal's thigh ripping into flesh and muscle.  My own prayers to Tunare sealed the mortal wound and Stonehewer's blazing greatsword beheaded the demon.</p>

    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="./images/torment_pig_demon.jpg"><img src="./images/torment_pig_demon_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="kabbal versus the Boruk Ravager" /></a>
    </div>

<p>With the finest elven swordsmanship, Semidil plunged his blades into the second demon's chest to the hilt.  Semidil stared at the blazing red eyes of the demon, expecting the massive creature to fall over dead.  The Boruk Ravager laughed and punched the warrior in the face, sending him skidding across the stone walkway.  A barrage of magic assaulted the creature, waves of poisons, disease, and clouds of darkness engulfed it as both Juror and Norque chanted.  The red eyes went white as blindness took over the demon.  Stonehewer promptly beheaded the second beast, seeming to prefer this method of dispatching the demons of Torment.</p>

<p>We traveled for four days along the suspended walkways of the prison world.  Succumbing to curiosity, I ventured close to one of these buildings and what I saw made me wish I had not.  I do not know how demons come to exist, whether simply created by their god or perhaps the manifestation of imperfections in our own world.  I do know that no natural force could have created the Constructs.  The beast was a mass of pulsating veiny flesh.  It dragged its weight with a number of swollen tentacles, each ending in a mouth lined with needle-like teeth.  It had no visible eyes, but three of the larger tentacles turned my way and I heard a gurgling hiss.  With uncanny speed for such an unwieldy beast the hideous creation attacked and it wasn't alone.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="./images/torment_constructs.jpg"><img src="./images/torment_constructs_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Constructs" /></a>
    </div>

<p>Kabbal severed three of the hideous mouthed tentacles from the beast with a swing of his axe.  Daninulaer, my summoned hammer, smashed in the skull of another wolf-headed demon.  A third, seeing it was out numbered, grabbed Semidil by his chain tunic and in a flash of black light, the two disappeared.  Two more demons roared in and with the tentacle Construct still quite alive, our luck had run out.</p>

<p>Our astral lines snapped tight as the claws ripped into us.  The lines dragged our spiritual projections back into the Plane of Tranquility.  There was a moment of panic until we saw Semidil unconscious next to us.  Mentally exhausted but safe, we ended our exploration into Torment the only way we could have, defeated. Other adventurers had been trapped, doomed to an eternity of pain and misery. We did return, however, with a tale to tell and a little smarter for the experience.</p>

<p>Two years ago the Shissar gave me the greatest gift I had ever been given and then ripped it out of my mind like a barbed arrow.  For two days they injected sixty years of a life I had never lived into me.  I fell in love with and married a woman who has never existed.  Sometimes in that place between sleep and consciousness I can still feel her next to me, her hand draped across my chest.  Then I awaken further and remember that she was nothing but a dark electricity burned into my mind and I weep.  Sometimes I hear my son's laugh in the streets of the bazaar and I turn with a smile before my mind reminds me that he was never born.  For two years I have had to struggle with the acceptance that none of it was real.</p>

<p>Sometimes I wonder if I have left the ancient laboratories of the Shissar warlocks at all.  I wonder if I am still living my own life or living the sixty year lie they wrapped around me.  One thing convinces me that the life I live now is real; I never questioned the one the Shissar fed to me.  I enter the Planes for a few reasons, but there is one strong one I do not wish to admit.  I go to the Planes because it is the only place that feels real.  The surrealism of the outer planes wraps around me like the embrace of a mother and for just a moment I remember the feel of Elandra's hand in mine.  That is usually just before the demons come.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-08-08T12:47:32+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 38: Xuzl</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000145.html</link>
      <description> The room was small, no more than twelve feet across, with a desk, a rug, and a bed. On...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">145@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>The room was small, no more than twelve feet across, with a desk, a rug, and a bed. On a chair opposite the door was the artifact, covered with a black cloth. Loral's eyes never left the object as he closed and bolted the door. Loral couldn't help but wonder if it was the last time he would ever see the outside world again.</p>
    <p>With a small knife, Loral carved runes of protection into the wood of the door and into the supporting beams. He used the dust of crushed peridots and globes of summoned water to make a shimmering paste that he filled into the carved runes. A prayer to his goddess and a wave of his hand made the runes shine with an internal light. Loral prayed again, this time surrounding his body with a magical shell of protection from both physical, mental, and elemental attacks. He did not know what he might face in this encounter, it was best to be prepared. With his protection spells in place, Loral was ready.</p>
    <p>Loral pulled back the cloth and revealed the circular shield. It appeared dull and scarred from thousands of battles. It was an artifact of the Plane of Fire, a shield that held magical powers beyond the understanding of mortals. It had been forged before the existence of man or elf, a weapon of power in a war long past. There was something deeper, however. During its last battle the shield had captured a piece of the spirit it once protected. Loral closed his eyes and began to speak.</p>
    <p>"Awaken, Xuzl." Loral felt a flash of heat as the shield came alive. Loral imagined the shield expanding into a gateway, its oily surface appearing as a black liquid. A red claw extended out. A blast of hot sulphuric air blew Loral's hair back. He could feel the beast enter the room, over two thousand pounds of muscled hatred and fire.</p>
    <p>Loral heard the thud of Xuzl's hoof hitting the wooden floor. He felt the mass of the beast all around him. The floor seemed to sink under the demon's weight. Loral heard leather wings unfold around him, filling the entire room. He could smell the beast's burning breath beating down on him. Through his closed eye lids he could see the burning green eyes of Solusek's guardian. In a basement of a bar in Felwithe Loral sat in front of one of the most dangerous creatures ever to step foot upon Norrath.</p>
    <p>Xuzl's voice boomed. "At last we speak, elf. I wondered when this moment would occur." Xuzl laughed, a sound mixed of screaming children and steel scratching on stone. Loral could feel Xuzl's mind probing into Loral's, seeking control.</p>
    <p>"Stand down, Xuzl." Loral spoke, putting as much strength into his voice as he could. "I know what you are and I have seen your powers before. You shall not have control over me." Loral held his hand up revealing the black oval scar on his palm - a scar it the shape of an eye. "I have been possessed before, demon. I have tasted the breath of evil from my own mouth and I shall not taste it again."</p>
    <p>Xuzl considered the scar for a moment. "A beast of Innoruuk gave you this," the demon spoke with a voice both deep and gratingly sharp. "The Prince of Hate never had much patience. Your resistance to me is no concern. In time, priest, you will feel the strength I can give to you and perhaps you will see things differently."</p>
    <p>"Perhaps I should toss you into the pits of Lavastorm."</p>
    <p>Xuzl laughed. "Perhaps some red-skinned goblin would find me there. Perhaps his mind would not be as strong as your own and perhaps I would be released faster than I thought." Loral felt his heart sink at the demon's logic.</p>
    <p>"I am a patient one, priest." Xuzl continued, "I have many powers to give and many tales to tell. I will not lie to you as Innoruuk's fiend did. It is far more entertaining to watch you burn by your own twisted truth."</p>
    <p>"And what truth is that?"</p>
    <p>"The truth that you do more to damage your world than you do to protect it. Do you think you've saved Norrath by killing Fennin Ro? Do you think no one will take the throne? Can you not see the great imbalance you have created? The Planes are a scale, pasty elf, and you just took all of the weight off of one side. It is only a matter of time before the world crumbles around you." Again came the steel-scraping laugh.</p>
    <p>"I have tasted the blood of your grandfather, elf." Xuzl's heat grew as he spoke. "I heard him scream out to a goddess that would not listen when I ripped him in half and crushed his skull in my teeth. A thousand of your kind I have killed, but your own self destruction may be the most entertaining death I have seen."</p>
    <p>"Perhaps, demon. But for now you will serve the will of Tunare. You will serve as my hand, as I serve as hers. And when your time of service is up, I will return you to your fiery pits with the other vermin that infest your world."</p>
    <p>Loral opened his eyes. The room felt no different than it had when he first entered. The demon was gone. The scarred shield sat quietly across from him. Loral picked it up and slipped it onto his arm, feeling its warmth.</p>
    <p>Loral considered the danger of such an item.  To have the voice of one so versed in the ways of the outer planes was a benefit beyond measure, even if the voice was so foul as Xuzl's. If the will of Tunare is served and the protection of the elves is sound, the methods may not be questioned. It would not be the first time Loral had fought next to the hand of darkness in order to serve the greater good and it would not be the last.</p>
    <p>Loral climbed up the steps of the bar's basement and into the city of Felwithe. The demon sat comfortably on his arm.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-07-07T14:30:39+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>


  </channel>
</rss>

