<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/</link>
<description>Everquest news, editorials, and commentary.</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<copyright>Copyright 2004</copyright>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2004 13:46:06 -0500</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2004 07:53:23 -0500</pubDate>
<generator>http://www.movabletype.org/?v=3.01D</generator>
<docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs> 

<item>
<title>The Calm Before the Storm</title>
<description>Today we deliver another gathering of news from across the lands and across the ethereal worlds of the net.  We look at some new changes to test, some discussions of new LDON raids, and the continuing class issue updates.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000026.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000026.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2004 13:46:06 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The New Mobhunter</title>
<description>This week we release a new version of Mobhunter for our faithful readers to poke with sharp pointy sticks.  Come take a look!
</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000025.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000025.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2004 20:45:33 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Swapping, Selling, and Soloing</title>
<description>This week we take a look at the most recent patch, some updates to the test server, and some interesting discussions happening around the community. Oh yes, we also overthrow the aristocracy of the uberguild and give power to the people...oh wait, thats next week.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000024.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000024.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sat, 24 Jul 2004 21:17:26 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Advantages of Point-based Loot</title>
<description>This week&apos;s Mobhunter discusses the advantages of a point-based loot system. While Everquest primarily uses random drops to reward players with equipment, Lost Dungeons of Norrath showed us a new, fair, and powerful loot system. It is my hope that we see systems like this used more in the future.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000022.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000022.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2004 12:58:53 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Summit Changes Round 2</title>
<description>An upcoming patch this week includes many new changes and improvements for the live servers. This week&apos;s article discusses changes to the tribute system, safe augment removal, LDON adventure point refunds, two new LDON raiding zones, the Veeshan&apos;s Peak revamp, and a few other changes.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000021.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000021.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2004 12:43:06 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Progression in Everquest</title>
<description>In this week&apos;s editorial we look at how progression works in Everquest. We discuss what progression is, where it runs free, where it gets blocked up, where it is strong, and where it needs to improve.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000020.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000020.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2004 04:32:02 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Book of Gunthak</title>
<description>Today&apos;s article covers this week&apos;s patch including the new Gunthak stone, changes to Time, updates for the PvP servers, strange new slash commands, and a few other updates.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000019.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000019.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2004 14:59:06 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Return to the Sewers</title>
<description>This week&apos;s news roundup discusses the new Gunthak portal, Time changes, high-cost LDON gear, a new raid instance, augment swapping, LDON item refunds, and Loral&apos;s latest sewer disaster. We at Mobhunter get killed by gnats so you don&apos;t have to!</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000018.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000018.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2004 19:42:51 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Guild Summit Report</title>
<description>This weekend&apos;s guild summit revealed a lot of history and a lot of the future of Everquest. Read Loral&apos;s report on the state of the game.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000017.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000017.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Tue, 08 Jun 2004 04:32:54 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda</title>
<description>Next week SOE is hosting a visit for guild leaders and community representatives to talk about the state of the Everquest and get feedback. This article outlines the evil agenda I plan to bring to San Diego and hand to the Everquest developers.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000016.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000016.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2004 21:11:35 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Caves of the Kobold Slavers</title>
<description>A new patch today brought us a new tutorial, some fixes to the Plane of Knowledge crashes, and some other stuff. We also look at the Gates revamp and Sony&apos;s new pricing plans.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000015.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000015.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2004 05:10:57 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Something New</title>
<description>As our faithful readers already know, change is slow to come here at Mobhunter. The look, the functionality, and the Planes of Power ad have all been constants you&apos;ve been able to count on for years. But it&apos;s time that we add something new.

Read on to discover our latest addition... </description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000023.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000023.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 May 2004 07:54:08 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Whispers of War</title>
<description>We received a lot of big news last week. Today we discuss the Omens of War and the Gates of Discord retune. Enjoy!</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000014.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000014.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2004 18:46:18 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The End May Be Nigh Someday!</title>
<description>Today we discuss Everquest 2&apos;s beta registration, this week&apos;s patch and its results, the death of Afterlife, and a special report on Gates of Discord retuning.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000013.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000013.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2004 18:46:45 -0500</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Found: More Lost Dungeons</title>
<description>Patch day today. We look at some of the new features of the patch including new LDON zones, the free Plane of Knowledge, the new &quot;Hot Spots&quot;, and cover a few bits of news from last week.</description>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/new/000012.html</link>
<guid>http://mobhunter.com/new/000012.html</guid>
<category></category>
<pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2004 18:47:08 -0500</pubDate>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>