<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://mikeshea.net/rss.css" type="text/css"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
    xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

  <channel>
    <title>LoralCiriclight.com</title>
    <link>http://loralciriclight.com/</link>
    <description>Tales and adventures of Loral Ciriclight in the online role playing game, Everquest.</description>
    <dc:language>en-us</dc:language>
    <dc:creator>mike@mikeshea.net</dc:creator>
    <dc:rights>Copyright 2003</dc:rights>
    <dc:date>2003-03-20T04:08:17+00:00</dc:date>
    <admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.movabletype.org/?v=2.62" />
    <admin:errorReportsTo rdf:resource="mailto:mike@mikeshea.net"/>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>

    <item>
      <title>Chapter 36: Solusek Ro</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000142.html</link>
      <description> The final day of the elven city of Fayspires was approaching. The ancient trees of Telethin burned like giant...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">142@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <p>The final day of the elven city of Fayspires was approaching. The ancient trees of Telethin burned like giant torches, filling the sky with black smoke. Outside of the city, the armies of Tunaria battled the demons of Ro. Inside, the last sages of Fayspires concentrated their powers on the large blue shell that encompassed the city.</p>

    <p>Waves of fire and bolts of electricity bounced off of the protective shell. Then Rizlona entered the wizards guild and all was lost. Once known as a bard with songs that soothed the most troubled heart, the elven woman had been in seclusion for weeks before the gates of Fire had opened. For weeks Solusek Ro whispered to the bard, tempting her with powers and riches beyond any Rizlona had ever known. When she awoke this morning she found a white multi-faceted gem in the center of her floor. The last dark words of her dream rang in her ears. "Take the Dresolik to the wizards."</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="images/solro_rizlona.jpg"><img src="images/solro_rizlona_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Rizlona the Traitor" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>The eyes of the wizards snapped open when they felt the burning artifact enter their room.Before they could react, the gem flashed and a guardian of Fire appeared in the middle of the wizards' circle. The demon was black faced with red burning eyes and held a double-bladed glyphed axe.Elven magic exploded and blood sprayed on the white marble walls as the last defenses of Fayspires collapsed.</p>

    <p>Rizlona was given a place as a guardian of Solusek Ro in his black tower deep within the Plane of Fire. For five hundred years, her powers grew within her dark chamber. It was within that chamber that she now faced the vengeance of the elves. It was within that chamber that she faced the vengeance of the elves. She was reminded of the last days of Fayspires when she heard the roars of battle just outside her door.</p>

    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="images/solro_grezou.jpg"><img src="images/solro_grezou_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Grezou" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>Few had ever seen a horror greater than that of the demon Grezou. Older than the mountains of Kunark, he attacked with a ferocity of pure hatred. Beams of energy shot from his emerald eyes and claws ripped through enchanted armor like paper. The blades of the warriors of the Cult cut deep but the beast was relentless. Calling upon the powers of his home plane of Fire, Grezou reached his arms high. His chanting was interrupted by a blast of absolute cold that tore through the massive chest of the greater demon. Loral turned to see an icy glimmer in Azile's eyes before they returned to normal. Loral shuddered.</p>

    <p>Covered in ash and soot, the raiding party entered Rizlona's chambers. Loral was shocked to see the elven woman armored in gold. His surprise intensified as his companions attacked the woman and she showed her true form.</p>

    <p>Solusek Ro had given many gifts to Rizlona for her part in the destruction of Fayspires. None was more powerful than her new body. Rizlona fell to her hands and knees. Her back arched and elongated. Claws sprang from her finger tips as she grew many times her size. Her armor fell away revealing a thick gold hide of scales. The cracking of bones refitting and reforming made Loral shiver. Huge batlike wings spread above the raiding force. When she raised her head again, Loral stared in shock at the head of a huge golden dragon.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="images/solro_rizlona_2.jpg"><img src="images/solro_rizlona_2_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Rizlona Revealed" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>Rizlona breathed and a huge column of lava engulfed the front lines of the raiders. Blue rings of protective magic kept the party alive if not unharmed. The party attacked. Powerfully enchanted blades and waves of magical powers ripped into the dragon. Though it felt as if it lasted for days, the battle lasted only a few minutes before the betrayer of Fayspires fell dead.</p>

    <p>Each of the five guardians of Solusek Ro had been defeated. A silence fell over the tower. Bubbling lava and creaking steal were the only sounds as the war party stood in front of the pillar of flame, the gateway to Solusek's antechamber.</p>

    <p>Solusek Ro stood on the raised platform of his throne room. His remaining minions stood with him, horribly powerful protectors feared by Norrath's eldest dragons.</p>

    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="images/solro_throneroom.jpg"><img src="images/solro_throneroom_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Throneroom of Solusek Ro" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>Loral thought back to the stories of the exodus of Tunaria. He remembered the cold eyes of his father when Tarlin retold the sad tale. Thousands of elves had died, many of starvation and exposure to the harsh ocean of Tears. While the strongest of the elven armies died upon the fields of Northern Tunaria, many of the sick, the elderly, and the children of the elves died in travel to Faydwer. So weakened were the elves that they had been threatened with extinction at the hands of the Crushbone orcs.</p>

    <p>It was the jealousy and greed of this spoiled child of Fire that taught the elves the meaning of true sadness. The vengeance of Tunaria fed every elf who ever picked up a sword or cast a spell. On this day, vengeance was sated. Solusek Ro, the Burning Prince, was killed within his own lair. Across the Plane of Fire, one last flash of brilliant light from the top of the needle spire of his tower could be seen.</p>

    <p>Loral stood staring at the smoldering corpse of Ro. His hammer, Daninulaer, still hummed in his hand. An unintelligible voice whispered within his mind. The weight of his actions began to sink in. Rallos Zek the Warlord had been killed, protecting Growth from the assault of the frost giants of Kael Drakkal. Solusek Ro, destroyer of Tunaria, had been destroyed, avenging the death of thousands. All across the outer planes, gods, demigods, and their armies had been hunted and killed.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="images/solro_solusek.jpg"><img src="images/solro_solusek_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Burning Prince" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>Somewhere within the chambers of Ro, a gnome of the raiding party found a lever opening a pit of burning lava. Darkweb the wizard recognized it as a gateway, perhaps deeper into the Plane of Fire.</p>

    <p>Loral stared into the burning pit. He could return to Felwithe this day. He could spend every day from now on in peace, knowing Felwithe was safe. Loral looked deeper into the gateway. There was no logical reason to continue. He had served Tunare more than any had ever expected. There was no need to face further unknown horrors. A single prayer and the powers of the Faithstone of Nature would return him home. Entering the gate would send him to dangers beyond any known by mortals. The laughter of Xuzl the demon echoed in the back of Loral's mind.</p>

    <p>Loral jumped into the pit of Fire.</p>
  
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-03-20T04:08:17+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 35: The Tower of Ro</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000129.html</link>
      <description>It was three hundred and fifty years before the Age of Wonder and Tunaria burned. Tarlin and his band of...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">129@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>It was three hundred and fifty years before the Age of Wonder and Tunaria burned.  Tarlin and his band of fifty rangers marched solemnly but quickly through Kithicor on their way north to Telethin.  They could already see the red smoke in the sky.  Fayspires was on fire.  They stepped out onto what was once rich and grassy lands but now was lifeless rock and ash.  It was on these burnt lands that the elves faced Solusek's demons.</p>

<p>They felt the ground rumble under their feet and the air filled with waves of heat as a massive form approached.  Grezou came upon them on twenty foot wings, his body rippling with muscles and smoking with an internal flame.  He opened his clawed hand and a cone of fire incinerated two of Tarlin's companions.  Holding their ground, the other rangers raised their bows and fired waves of arrows enchanted with ice.  Steam rose from a dozen wounds but the red demon was not finished.</p>

<p>Sixteen more companions were killed before the beast was sent back to the Plane of Fire.  While the troops regrouped and mended their horrible burns, Tarlin stood on a charred hill overlooking the valley that had once been Telethin.  He brushed away a dirty lock of blonde hair that stuck to the grime and sweat of his brow.  Large red shapes dotted the once lush countryside that was now a wasteland of ash.  Tarlin's heart sank. Two hundred more demons remained.  It was Takish Hiz all over again.</p>
  <div class="imageset1">
    <a href="images/solro_walkway.jpg"><img src="images/solro_walkway_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The platforms of Ro" /></a>
  </div>
<p>The Planes were alien to Loral in every way.  For a year he had traveled the planes and he felt himself changing mentally and physically.  His armor had shifted around him changing hue from deep blue to gold.  His summoned hammer, Daninulaer the Wraithsbane, pulsed with life in his hand.  Loral felt his grasp on the physical laws of nature slip the further he traveled into the Planes.  His time in the Tower of Solusek Ro was no exception.</p>

<p>Giant stone walkways stood suspended over huge chasms of lava.  Hallways forged from thousands of tons of iron twisted and turned throughout the demonic lair.  Teleportation crystals sent the Norrathian adventurers deeper into the tower, removing all sense of bearing and navigation.  There was nowhere to travel but up, further into the hands of the Burning Prince.  Loral caught a glimpse through a crack in the wall of the outside world.  He became dizzy when he saw the ocean of lava that surrounded the black tower for hundreds of miles.  His mind cleared when he heard the attack of the first of Solusek Ro's guardians.</p>
  <div class="imageset2">
    <a href="images/solro_guardian.jpg"><img src="images/solro_guardian_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The A Guardian of Ro" /></a>
  </div>
<p>The demon Xuzl sat within his black hall and waited. For six hundred years, he had remained within the giant iron tower of Solusek Ro, rising like a black needle in the center of the Plane of Fire.  After six hundred years, he remembered the taste of mortals. Although he would now face mortals again, it was not on their land.  It was on his own.</p>

<p>Xuzl stood to his full twenty four foot height and stretched his giant wings to the edges of his hall.  Outside he could hear his minions in battle.  The clash of steel and the blasts of flame flashed through his doorway.  Soon the intruders entered.  He recognized their races from his short stay on Norrath.  All the races were represented, it seemed, armed and armored with great treasures to fill his vaults and arm his own troops.  Xuzl was not a stupid creature, however.  He knew that no ordinary mortals could penetrate this deep into the 
tower of the elder god, Solusek Ro. He knew the strength of the guardians 
these adventurers had defeated.</p>
  <div class="imageset1">
    <a href="images/solro_xuzl.jpg"><img src="images/solro_xuzl_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Xuzl" /></a>
  </div>
<p>Two green eyes suspended in blackness were the first signs of this 
mighty foe the mortals glimpsed.  Then the room exploded into orange light as walls of fire roared to life.  Xuzl raised his claw into the air sending waves of fire through the war party.  Only the protective magics of their druids saved them from the searing heat.  Loral ducked behind his shield and felt the enchanted steel melt under the waves of flame.  The adventurers returned the attack firing dozens of enchanted arrows and magical spears of ice onto the beast.  Xuzl's own protective magics stopped many of the attacks, but some pierced his thick hide.</p>

<p>Any conversations among the minions of Solusek Ro's tower ceased when they heard the roar of Xuzl.  A demon among demons, none dared to challenge the creature. He was one of the five guardians of the Burning Prince himself and kept company only with those he commanded.  To hear the beast's cry of agony and rage put fear into the mightiest of Solusek's guardians.</p>
  <div class="imageset2">
    <a href="images/solro_xuzl_2.jpg"><img src="images/solro_xuzl_2_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Xuzl" /></a>
  </div>
<p>The smouldering corpse of Xuzl lay on the stone platform of his lair.  His mouth was twisted in agony and anger, bearing horrible fangs.  Loral eyes were fixed on the slain demon.  Many such creatures remained but for a party of mortals to enter the realm of Solusek himself and defeat such a foe was incredible.  Loral felt a twinge of doubt and trouble within the back of his mind.</p>

<p>Binedina stepped forward and handed Loral a round silver shield found in the demon's treasures.  Loral dropped his own ruined shield and slipped this new one onto his arm.  The roar of Xuzl's final death echoed within Loral's ears and the circular shield blazed with fire and then grew still.  A powerful item indeed, Loral thought, and bowed to thank Binedina for her generosity.  She smiled in return and the war party moved on.</p>

<p>Within the highest spire of the tower, at the tip of the spike within the world of lava, Solusek Ro stood.  There was a threat within his home.  His demonic sentinel had been killed. Solusek Ro summoned his remaining guardians close and ordered the remaining four sentinels to stand ready. Solusek, the Burning Prince, felt a sensation he hadn't felt for a thousand years - Fear.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-03-18T13:30:03+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Make Everquest Look Better</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000139.html</link>
      <description>Everquest is a beautiful game. Every frame, every view gives us thousands of bits of information, from what armor someone...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">139@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Everquest is a beautiful game.  Every frame, every view gives us thousands of bits of information, from what armor someone is wearing to how many nasty fire beetles are outside the gates of Qeynos.  Our view into Norrath is the primary sensory output of EQ.  Everything else our computer has ends up leading to the picture.  We need to make that picture look as good as it possibly can get.</p>

<p>  This article describes ten ways to make Everquest look better and give you a better gaming experience.  The following settings will dramatically improve the look of the game, however it is mainly for newer systems with over 512 megs of ram and either Geforce2 or Radeon video cards.</p>

<h2>Set initial Options</h2>

<p><strong>Who should do this:</strong>  Everyone.  Proper optional settings will make the game look better for everyone.</p>

<p>When clicking "Options" on the initial Everquest menu you will first be prompted to pick your video card.  Pick the one that matches your best video card, often the only selection.  The next menu is for detailed character models.  Choose as many as you can, ideally all of them on a system with 512 megs of ram or better.  The last menu is the Luclin Engine Settings menu.  Check "sound", "mip mapping", "Social Animations", "Dynamic Lighting" and "Texture Compression" to "on".  "Texture Caching" should be set to "off".  "Resolution" should be as high as you can go, 1280 by 1024 on 17" monitors and 1600x1200 on 19" and 21" monitors.  "Texture Quality" should be set to "high".</p>

<p>The detailed character models with Shadows of Luclin have greatly improved the realism of other players.  On a system with 512 megs of ram or higher you can set all models to the new ones including horses.  It is important that the use of high resolution models doesn't drop your frame rate to a crawl.  Frame rate is just as important as resolution for a realistic environment.</p>

<p>Properly setting these settings will dramatically improve the realism of Norrath from the detail of other players to the realism of the buildings and streets of the cities.</p>

<h2>Enable Mip Mapping</h2>

<p><strong>Who should do this:</strong>  Everyone with a 32 bit color video card including Nvidia Geforce or Radeon video cards.</p>

<p>Mip Mapping is a way to blur textures as they get farther away.  Having this enabled will mean that objects appear smoother as they get farther away.  If this is not working, you will see things shimmer as they get farther away.  This breaks the solid feel of the game and reminds us that we're just looking at a stupid monitor, not a world.  Mip mapping helps create a solid world.</p>

<p><strong>How to do this:</strong> The mip map setting under the initial "Options" set above is currently broken.  There is only one way to make sure mip mapping is working.  Open your "eqclient.ini" file in the everquest directory with Notepad.  Look for a line called "MipMapping=TRUE" and replace "TRUE" with "1" so the line reads "MipMapping=1" without the quotes.  Now restart Everquest.  Note:  Every time you change your display options you will have to redo this change in the eqclient.ini file.</p>

<h2>Set proper resolution, bit depth, and refresh rate settings</h2>

<p><strong>Who should do this:</strong>  Everyone.  While settings will vary depending on system, everyone should tune resolution to its optimal level.</p>

<p>Every pixel is telling you something.  Every dot on the screen is a bit of information.  The more bits of information you have, the more information your brain can process.  The higher the resolution, the more realistic the game is.  Bump your resolution to the highest possible resolution you can with your current monitor and video card setting.  On 19" and 21" monitors with high end systems, you should be playing at 1600 by 1200 resolution.  On 17" monitors you should be playing at 1280 by 1024.  Try different settings out until you can find the highest one.</p>

<p>Like resolution, the higher the refresh rate the better.  Set a refresh rate at 75Hz or higher when possible.  This will make your screen refresh faster which will reduce the amount of flicker.  While 60 frames a second is very fast, 75 is much better.</p>

<p>Bit depth is one of the smallest changes that will drastically improve your picture.  Setting a bit depth of 32 bit will remove saw-tooths at the bottom of buildings and remove a lot of strange effects at the bottom of rocks or statues.</p>

<p><strong>How to do this:</strong> There are two places to change this.  One is in the initial "Options" screen.  The other is in game with the Options menu.  Press "ALT-O" for options.  Press the "Display" tab.  Press "Video Modes".  Select the proper resolution for your monitor.  Select "75hz" refresh.  Select "32bit" bit depth.  Click "accept".  When your picture comes back, click "yes" to save those settings.  Should you pick a setting too high for your monitor, it will revert back to the original.</p>

<p>Icons and text will appear much smaller when you switch.  Use "/chatfontsize 5" to bump your chat text up.  The other windows will be smaller but you will get used to them in time.  Smaller user interface windows mean you get to see more of the world.  Remember that you are looking at a world, not a user interface.  Get the user interface out of the picture as much as possible.</p>

<h2>Clean your monitor</h2>

<p><strong>Who should do this:</strong>  Everyone.</p>

<p>A little Windex can go a long way.  Removing smudges and dust can give you a much nicer picture.  Remember that your monitor is your window into another world.  Keep the window clean.</p>

<h2>Calibrate your monitor</h2>

<p><strong>Who should do this:</strong>  Everyone.  Properly tuning a monitor costs no money and does not effect performance at all.</p>

<p>When a game artist designs textures they have their monitors set at something called "NTSC standard" a specific set of color, brightness, and contrast settings.  Your monitor should be calibrated as close as you can to NTSC standards.  Each monitor setting is different but you want your color to be set as close as possible to "normal". <a href="http://www.zonezero.com/calibration/english.html">This tutorial can help you calibrate your monitor.</a>.  If you have a monitor with professional settings, the color temperature should be set to 6500K.  Proper monitor calibration will make colors appear richer, deeper, less washed out, and more vibrant.</p>

<h2>Set anti-aliasing level</h2>

<p><strong>Who should do this:</strong>  Those systems running over 2ghz processors with over 512 megs of ram and either a Geforce 4 or Radeon 9700 video card.</p>

<p>Anti-aliasing is a feature of newer video cards but is often ignored.  With high-end systems, anti-aliasing can be set with little or no performance loss.  On most newer systems a level of 2x is appropriate.  With a very powerful system, 4x will improve it further.  Anti-aliasing will remove jagged lines  from objects up close and far away such as the edge of a sword or the brim of a helmet.  It gives a much sharper and more realistic picture.</p>
<p><strong>How to do this:</strong>  Different video cards will do this differently but most follow this basic instruction.  From your windows desktop right click on the background and click "display".  In the tabbed window click "settings" and then the "advanced" box.  From this advanced window click the "Direct 3D" tab.  This window should have some form of "anti-alias" setting.  Try either "none" or "2x" for most systems.  Very powerful systems can try "4x".  Framerates will vary.</p>


      </body>

      <dc:subject>Article</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-03-16T16:09:07+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 34: The Warlord</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000122.html</link>
      <description>Jalen had been guarding the gates of Felwithe longer than any human had lived. His blade had seen no fewer...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">122@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Jalen had been guarding the gates of Felwithe longer than any human had lived. His blade had seen no fewer than five hundred orc necks in his two hundred years of service. He had been guarding the Koada'dal city since it had been founded.  As 
unexpected as it was, he died as he had always hoped, defending the 
city of the elves.</p>

    <p>The guardian of Felwithe never felt the ethereal blade cut through his steel armor and sink into his back. The Daiku Hendin, Gandulak, let the blade slip free as the body of the high elf fell to the ground. Gandulak's face betrayed no emotion as he looked with white pupil-less eyes towards the gates of Felwithe. The ogre pulled his cloak tighter around his large frame and faded back into the darkness. The assassin peered out from under the black hood, his tattooed face hardly visible. In a few hours, the king of Felwithe would be returning from Kelethin. Then Gandulak would strike. The king would be well guarded but none upon the mortal world had seen the skills of a Hendin, a master assassin of Zek. He had no doubt that he would be able to dispose of any guards who might stand in his way. He had no doubt that the king of Felwithe would die this day.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="images/drundor_war_wraith.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_war_wraith_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The War Wraith" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>Loral's vision of the demonic assassin shattered as a War Wraith tore into the priest's party. The cowl on the beast's face made Loral wonder what horror was being hidden that could possibly be worse than the rest of the demon's body. Loral was shocked back into the present when a swing of Moegid's axe 
severed the beast's head from its body with machine-like precision. A shower of thick black blood sprayed against the wall as the corpse fell to the stone floor. The ring of the steel axe echoed down the corridors of Drundor.</p>

    <p>At the top of a large stone staircase, the war party engaged the Daiku 
Hendin Shadowmasters. Armed and armored in black metal forged from the 
mountains of the Plane of War, the Hendin attacked with the power of 
the giants of Kael who lived deep within Kael and also with the dexterity 
and accuracy of the finest elven swordmasters. Each swing led into three more, each feint led to a riposte that had their opponents clutching at their open bellies or slashed throats. Their white eyes burned with the thrill of combat but they never succumbed to the rage of a typical warrior.  Only with the solid coordination of powerful warriors and the combined efforts of many spellwielders were the powerful guardians destroyed.</p>

    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="images/drundor_elite.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_elite_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Hendin Shadowmaster" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>The adventurers were ragged when he struck.Some leaned heavily on their blades while others sat against the walls. A chill was felt throughout the party. An elven ranger narrowed his eyes and turned towards the dark hallway as a wind flowed past. A black blade burst through his chest. The blade pulled out and cut across, severing the ranger in half to the horror of his companions. Behind the cloud of blood was the grinning face of Vallon Zek, the master of assassins. A bombardment of arrows raced towards the god but before they landed, his visage split into five. Each acting independently, the shades of Vallon cut through the adventurers.</p>

    <p>Loral watched in horror as powerful warriors were carved into pieces before his healing light could keep them alive. In a well coordinated feint, the adventurers focused their attacks on each shade in turn while the others were led down the dark corridors by quickfooted druids. One by one the shades were cut down by the raiding party. Finally, with teeth clenched in vengeance, another ranger of Tunare fired two arrows into the eyes of the son of Zek. The god fell to his knees and then face down onto the stone floor.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="images/drundor_tallon_zek.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_tallon_zek_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Tallon Zek" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>A great roar of anger rumbled through the fortress, numbing the bones of the adventurers and rattling their teeth. The mightiest warriors' knees went weak, hearing the immortal voice of war.</p>

    <p>From deep within the center of the fortress was the first arena ever created. A den of combat, only the best warriors had ever been tested there and few of these ever stepped out. The raiders floated down onto the sandy floor with spells of levitation. The stench of centuries of decay tainted the air and the roaring flame of Rallos Zek's axe lit the arena. The warriors of the Cult stepped 
forward - Dachunker, Grongl, Slivereyes, Torray, and Tera - all representatives 
of different cultures but all the mightiest warriors of Norrath.</p>

    <p>Bright red eyes of hate flared from within the black helm. His body was built from the blood of armies. His burning axe had been forged from the combined rage of one hundred thousand battles. Time slowed down for Loral as Zek's black boots cracked the stone under the sandy floor. With a huge throw, the burning axe soared. With a ring of steel on steel, the head of a human paladin tumbled through the air, a pinwheel of blood in its wake. Loral began chanting in time with six other clerics. A steady stream of healing energy filled the warriors, closing wounds that the horrible axe opened.</p>

    <div class="imageset2">
      <a href="images/drundor_rallos_zek.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_rallos_zek_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Rallos Zek The Warlord" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>Loral gained confidence as the battle raged on. While the black armor turned almost every attack, many hit home. The healing waves of Loral and the other clerics flowed, keeping the attacking warriors alive. The sizzling blasts of fire and ice pelted the God of War. The battle was in their favor, until the dead returned to life.</p>

    <p>Loral felt the ground under his feet break open. A rotting claw wrapped in a tarnished silver gauntlet reached out of the ground. All around the arena beasts tore free from the ground around them. Giant boars armored in gold burst through the rear lines of the war party. A score of the winged beasts they had battled earlier dove in, claws tearing into flesh. Quickly the creatures were rallied, taunted, and led astray by the arrows and spells of a rear guard. The slayer of Vallon Zek fired arrow after arrow, piercing the thick hide of a boar and tearing holes in the wings of the war wraiths.</p>

    <div class="imageset1">
      <a href="images/drundor_beasts_of_zek.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_beasts_of_zek_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The beasts of Zek" /></a>
    </div>

    <p>The burning axe spun in the air around the God of War. The blades of the warriors cut deep under his armor. Black blood flowed from a thousand wounds. The female troll, Dachunker, crushed Rallos Zek's knee with a skull headed heavily enchanted mace. He came down hard on one leg and the keen blade of Slivereyes's sword found the edge of a plate and plunged deep into the Warlord's skull. The fortress went silent. The risen beasts stopped their assault and turned towards their master. The impossible had happened. Slivereyes pulled his blade free from the helm and cut again at the God's neck almost severing the head from its shoulders. The red eyes flashed one last time and then went out. The burning axe, still spinning in the air, plunged into the ground 
with a crack of thunder.Rallos Zek the Warlord had been killed.</p>

    <p>Gandulak felt a psychic scream split his mind. Only his thousand years of training kept him from crying out. Something horribly wrong had happened. Twenty other Hendin, all poised outside of Norrath's cities, heard the same cry. Thousands of miles away the giant priests of Zek fell dead, blood streaming from their ears. Gandulak's skin grew cold. Something horrible had occurred within his home world. He drew a small ruby from within the folds of his cloak. He crushed the gem and blew the fragments into the air. A tear in the fabric of space created a doorway back to the Plane of War. Gandulak stepped into the rift and it snapped shut behind him. A minute later King Thearsis Thex came back from his meeting with the council of Kelethin, completely oblivious to the danger that had once stood only a few feet away.</p>

    <p>Loral awoke just before dawn in the inn of New Tanaan. The fragments of his dream slipped away as his eyes took in the room's furnishings. He pulled the thick blanket tighter around him and let his eyes close. The king of Felwithe was safe as were the other leaders of Norrath's people. Rallos Zek had been slain and his assassins had retreated. Loral could afford another hour of sleep.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-02-17T04:26:04+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 33: Drundor</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000113.html</link>
      <description> &quot;The warriors of Zek are not finished with you. The fires of War are eternal. I shall return.&quot; The...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">113@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>"The warriors of Zek are not finished with you. The fires of War are eternal. I shall return."</p>

  <p>The words from King Tormax echoed through Loral's head as he watched the frost giant lord die in the icy caverns of Kael Drakkal. For four years he had fought the giants of Kael. Loral had battled the frost giant general, Narandi, during the war of Thurgadin. He had destroyed the guardian of the church of Zek, Derakor the Vindicator. A hundred giants had fallen to Loral's companions. Still the spirit of war did not leave this powerful enemy. The Kromzek leader had fought a war on three fronts, battling Thurgadin, Skyshrine, and the Plane of Growth within the same year. Loral was no tactician but even his priestly mind knew how difficult such a campaign would be. All three enemies of the Kromzek continued to feel the sting of the giants' spears. Scores of Coldain were killed on the river banks of the Great Divide during Narandi's battle. Corpses of young dragons littered the Western Wastes, slain by the mercenaries of Kael. Loral had even found a spy deep within the inner halls of Skyshrine, cloaked and masked by the magic of the Kromzek priests.</p>

  <p>King Tormax lay dead but the sense of dread did not leave Loral. Outside stood the war machines of Kael aimed at the Plane of Growth. The war would be delayed but Loral doubted it had been stopped completely. The priests of Zek were powerful and the giant king would return to his dragon-skull throne. Only one path remained for Loral to follow. There was only one way to protect Tunare. He must remove Kael's resolve to fight. He must remove the source of their murderous spirit. He must face Rallos Zek.</p>

  <div class="imageset1">
    <a href="images/drundor_tanaan.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_tanaan_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="New Tanaan" /></a>
  </div>

  <p>Ten years had passed since the battles of Kael. Loral sat at a small table in an inn of New Tanaan. Across from him sat a beautiful human female wrapped in red robes. Starkin the ranger walked into the bar and saw the venerable priest in his green robes speaking to her. She soon rose and walked out the door, smiling at Starkin as she left.</p>

  <p>"Who was the woman?" Starkin said as he sat down at Loral's table. "I do not recognize her."</p>

  <p>"Nor will you ever." Loral said with a smile. "I have met her perhaps a dozen times and each time she appears different. You could pass her again on your way out and not even know it."</p>

  <p>"One of the spies of your vast network?" Starkin said teasingly. "Certainly the church would not approve."</p>

  <p>"The Tier'Dal incorporate spies, my friend, I simply have contacts." Loral smiled and took a sip of wine from the crystal glass on his table. "Well informed contacts."</p>

  <p>His demeanor changed though when he remembered the tale of his friend, the enchantress. "The kingdom of Felwithe sent me here to locate threats to the elven nations," he spoke sternly. "The tools I use to fulfill that role are not of their concern. Perhaps the Church would not approve of my methods but they have not seen the dangers I have seen."</p>

  <p>Loral took two rolled parchments from his worn leather pouch. One held the wax seal of the Church of Tunare, the other the symbol of Healers United.</p>

  <div class="imageset2">
    <a href="images/drundor_hall.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_hall_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Fortress of Drundor" /></a>
  </div>

  <p>"Zek has commissioned the construction of war machines from the gnomish tinkerers of Innovation. He already has an army of warriors and with these new machines he plans to invade Norrath. The model of the metal beast in Innovation was destroyed four days ago but I do not think that will dissuade Zek from his attack on our world. The priests of Kael will open a doorway to Drundor, the Fortress of Zek, and his army will march across Norrath."</p>

  <p>Starkin grew cold. He had seen one of his warriors, a Daiku it was called, in the desert of Storm. It took twelve adventurers to defeat the murderous beast. The creature appeared to be an ogre but with a speed, power, and sturdiness he had never seen in a mortal.</p>

  <p>"A portal has been opened to Drundor from the caves of Tranquility and a raiding party plans to infiltrate the fortress," Loral continued. "I plan on entering with them." Loral handed the two parchments to Starkin. "Please deliver the first to Yeolarn of the Church of Felwithe. The other should go to Juror." Loral rose and embraced his noble friend. "I will return with news soon." Starkin looked at Loral for the truth of that statement. Himself a veteran planewalker, Starkin the Warder knew that Drundor would offer little chance of escape.</p>

  <p>Two days later, Loral entered the Fortress of Zek.</p>

  <p>Norrath was a world of balance. Each element helped to off-set another. The outer planes had no such balance. Stepping foot into Drundor sent a feeling of murderous dread through Loral's skin. Rough stone floors fed into the metal plates of the walls. Steel torches burned harshly, blackening the walls around them. The clashing of steel upon steel, the howl of wild animals bred for war, the roars of triumph, and screams of pain all echoed throughout the halls. Though fifty members strong, the raiding party Loral accompanied felt small. There was no doubt in Loral's mind that he had entered a hall of death. There was no purpose for Drundor other than war.</p>

  <div class="imageset1">
    <a href="images/drundor_guards.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_guards_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Guards of Drundor" /></a>
  </div>

  <p>Two guards of the fortress, over 20 feet high and armored in steel stained with dirt and blood, saw the approaching raiding party. Without hesitation or nervousness, they drew shining blades from their scabbards and roared as they swung at the front lines, hoping to sever them in half. Thus began the many battles the adventurers faced in the Fortress of Zek.</p>

  <p>All throughout the fortress, the party met the forces of Zek's army. Every guardian of Zek was covered in scars and each fought with the experiences of centuries of combat. Loral imagined the devastation that would face the cities of Norrath as hundreds of these icons of battle stormed through, mercilessly cutting down everything in their path. For these warriors there had never been peace. There was no concept of love or happiness. There was only the smell of blood and the rush of victory.</p>

  <div class="imageset2">
    <a href="images/drundor_tallon_zek.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_tallon_zek_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Tallon Zek" /></a>
  </div>

  <p>The party soon entered a large hall deep within the fortress. The torches burned low and Loral became aware that all had become quiet around them. A powerful warrior of the raiding party stepped in and drew his blade. From the quiet darkness soared a screaming arrow of flame. It struck the warrior and sent him flying through the air, slamming him against the back wall of the room. From the shadows stepped Tallon Zek, nocking another arrow into his ancient bow.</p>

  <p>The raiding party charged in to meet the demi-god. Tallon's 15 foot bow creaked and he let another arrow fly, this one blazing with ice. A mage caught the huge arrow in the chest and immediately fell dead, the four foot arrow still smoking in his chest. Steel rang against the god's armor as the party hacked at the diety of battle. Overwhelmed, Tallon spoke a word of command and fired another barbed arrow. The arrow split into three dozen smaller ones, each finding the mark of one of his attackers. Those hit by the barbed arrows flew back and were pinned to the walls of the hall. The shouts of battle became the cries of the dying as arrow after arrow left Tallon's unholy bow. But the attackers were filled with resolve.</p>

  <p>The healing energy of Tunare flowed from Loral's hands, mending the gaping holes of the evil arrows. Calling upon the strength of the Mother, Loral raised his hands and a shower of blue lights quietly embraced the raiding force. The light enveloped the adventurers near him, mending their wounds and renewing their spirit. The party regrouped and attacked again. This time Tallon Zek fell to their blades.</p>

  <div class="imageset1">
    <a href="images/drundor_loral_hall.jpg"><img src="images/drundor_loral_hall_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Loral travels deeper into the halls of Drundor" /></a>
  </div>

  <p>Loral stood over the body of the son of Zek. Many of the party tended to the injured and to those fallen in the battle. Others sorted through the treasures found in the hall. Loral could only look at the corpse at his feet and wonder when this would end. The fortress around them continued to bustle with activity. Zek's army was far from defeated. Loral felt old. How far he had gone in the name of Felwithe. How many enemies had he uncovered. How distant he was from his home.</p>

  <p>Leaning heavily on his silver-headed hammer, Loral walked forward. His armor felt heavier than before, pressing deeply in permanent creases on his shoulders. The memories of Coldain blood staining the snow of Velious returned to him as he headed back into the depths of Drundor.</p>

      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-01-24T04:18:11+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 32: Lxanvom</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000103.html</link>
      <description>It is with a quivering hand that I write my last words. At my feet lies my lord, the thirteenth...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">103@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p><em>It is with a quivering hand that I write my last words. At my feet lies my lord, the thirteenth Adan, king of our lands. My blade is buried in his back. His blood stains the hand that writes these words. It was the promise of great strength, whispered sweetly and softly to my ears over the years that has caused this to happen. Whispers of dreams and power realized. The dreams spoke of a ritual, glyphs and runes I have inscribed upon the floor of this place, the Kings Rest. It is irony that I am now hearing whispers of truth. I have betrayed my king and my people, the voice says, not as a revelation but as torment. I hear the hissing laughter of my new lord, the dark lord, the Plaguebringer. I hear his voice, tears falling from my betraying eyes as they look at the green portal that has opened. The voice grows louder. I have a new master now, it says. He is coming...</em></p>
      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/lxanvom_azile_the_scorcher.jpg"><img src="images/lxanvom_azile_the_scorcher_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Azile the Scorcher" /></a>
      </div>
<p>A large candle dripped wax onto an oak table while Loral read the ancient tome. The words had been written over four thousand years earlier, only having recently been translated by the scribes of Tanaan. Loral began studying the fall of Lxanvom, the King's Rest, after his adventures took him to its door in the Plane of Disease. He read of Bertoxxulous, the god of disease. For weeks he had been reading the texts, carefully turning the yellowed pages. Nothing took his attention away from the words of a culture long dead. The room grew hot. Loral looked up and saw the scribes of the library step back and out of the way as a small figure in red robes approached.</p>

<p>The room was illuminated by a red glow. Flames danced in Azile's black eyes behind the shadows of her hood. In her hand she held the Staff of the Four, an eternal flame burning at its top. Loral noticed for the first time that in their century of adventures together Azile hadn't aged a day. Azile would be almost one hundred and thirty, Loral calculated, though she looked hardly older than forty. Her eyes spoke of anything but youth. Her power had grown beyond any Loral had ever seen. He had watched her rip open rifts to the depths of the outer worlds and bring forth flames hotter than any known in the mortal world. She was no longer the simple traveler Loral had once known.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/lxanvom_deathknights.jpg"><img src="images/lxanvom_deathknights_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Deathknights of Lxanvom" /></a>
      </div>
<p>An unpleasant vision filled Loral's mind. He dreamed of the elder gods dead within their own worlds.  He saw armies of adventurers slaying the immortals of the outer planes and storming timeless keeps and castles. Visions of Fennin Ro's smouldering corpse lying upon the charred ground of Fire sending a column of black smoke into the air flashed in his mind. Above the corpse, floating upon a cloud of flame rose the new goddess of Fire - Azile the Scorcher.</p>

<p>Azile walked up to the table and sat down next to Loral. She smiled, pulled a small package from her pack, and put it down on the table. The smell of warm cake filled the air around him. Perhaps he was wrong. The vision must have been a trick of the light when she had entered. Too much reading of dramatic old texts, he thought.</p>

<p>"The Lotus has breached the Crypt of Decay," she stated. Loral looked at her unblinking eyes and beheld again the fiery vision.</p>
      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/lxanvom_adon_1.jpg"><img src="images/lxanvom_adon_1_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Adon of King's Rest" /></a>
      </div>
<p>Despite the cold darkness of the tomb, Loral felt sweat drip down his face. His eyes closed in silent meditation to Tunare, but the rhythmic chanting of the undead summoners could not be blocked out. For three days they had fought the undead of Lxanvom. Decayed husks of old priests and knights attacked with cracked lips pulled back over rotten jagged teeth. They had cut through the minions of the upper floors with little trouble, but when they entered the lower depths of the crypt they found a greater evil.</p>

<p>The summoners, undead priests of a lost age, called fourth the remains of the kings of Lxanvom. Torn from their rest and twisted into hideous forms, the kings attacked with strength and fury. They attacked with bloated fists and the pincers of enormous spiders. The sounds of thunder and the smells of burning flesh filled the crypt that had gone untouched for so many centuries. The blades of the Cult ripped into the kings and their minions, cutting through the material world and into the world of the tormented souls. One by one the evil forms of once great rulers fell.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/lxanvom_bertox.jpg"><img src="images/lxanvom_bertox_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Bertoxxulous the Plaguebringer" /></a>
      </div>
<p>All was quiet. The chanting of the undead priests became screams of death as they sacrificed themselves for a final summoning. The air became foul and cold. The group was silent as the Plaguebringer approached. His green burning eyes beheld them, the defilers of his temple. He reached towards them with a long thin arm ending in a claw with too many joints. The horror of the apparition in front of them held the adventurers as still as death.</p>

<p>A roar of fire broke the trance. The warriors screamed and charged in, blades held high. The clash of steel on hardened bone was deafening. Loral closed his eyes, calling upon the healing and protective magic of the Mother but Bertoxxulous had magic of his own. A dark grey mist flowed from the outstretched hands of the elder God. Loral felt his skin crack open. Sores began to appear and oozed a black liquid. All around him adventurers fell to their knees, their life energy being sapped out of them by the curse of Bertoxxulous.</p>
      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/lxanvom_bertox_dead.jpg"><img src="images/lxanvom_bertox_dead.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The death of Bertoxxulous" /></a>
      </div>
<p>A millennia earlier in lands long forgotten, the children of Veeshan created a weapon of incredible power. Using the skills of the greater wyrms, they forged a spear of prismatic energies capable of stabbing through the thickest scales the dragons had. It had been forged as a weapon for mortals to one day battle the Sleeper, Kerafyrm. Centuries later it had been discovered by an unlikely elf and on this day, it saved her from an unlikely enemy. With milky eyes and sunken cheeks, the rogue Annalyze reared back and threw the ancient spear into the back of Bertoxxulous's skull. With a deafening crack, the Plaguebringer's skull split and he crashed down to the ground.</p>

<p>A week later Loral was back in Tanaan, carefully turning another page from the tome that sat on the table. He took a bite from Azile's cake, feeling a warmth flow down his body. Though grey lines still crossed his face, the scars of Bertoxxulous's curse had almost completely healed. A deeper wound remained open however... a wounding of purpose. For a year, Loral had battled the beings of the planes, fighting for the safety of Faydwer and in the name of Tunare, but to what end? How far would he delve into these realms of uncertainty? For now, Loral could only ponder...and enjoy another piece of cake.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-01-05T16:56:01+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 31: Nightmare</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000093.html</link>
      <description>Breath burned through Loral&apos;s lungs as he raced across the land of Nightmares. He could hear the pursuing hobgoblins getting...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">93@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Breath burned through Loral's lungs as he raced across the land of Nightmares. He could hear the pursuing hobgoblins getting closer as their claws tore up the ground behind him. Purple luminescent clouds raced across the eternally black sky and the elongated fingers of long dead trees reached for Loral, whipping past him as he ran. Loral tripped on a stone as eager for his death as the pursuing demons. He was up with a flash, his blood pumping through his veins. The hobgoblins licked their lips in anticipation of the feast... for nothing was as sweet as the blood of a mortal. The leader of the pursuing demons leapt forward and clawed at Loral's back. Two of the 12-inch claws were turned away by Loral's draconian armor but the third ripped across the back of his neck down to the bone.</p>
      <p>Loral's vision blurred from shock but his legs did not stop. Ahead he saw the gates of Thule. Towering over 15 feet tall, the skeletal guardians of the gate would easily finish the job the hobgoblins started. Their eyes blazed and they smiled a grin of a thousand needle-like teeth when they saw Loral coming. Loral had one more trick. A word to Tunare surrounded him with an impenetrable shield of force. The claws of the mighty guardians skimmed off of the shield and Loral ran through the gates into the lair of Terris Thule.</p>
      <p>Loral collapsed to the ground, blood flowing from the wound on his neck. A warmth traveled over the wound, closing it and sending waves of relief into Loral's body. He looked up into the smiling face of Axen, dwarf priest of Brell and cleric of Lotus Cult. Loral realized he was surrounded by the hunters of the Cult. Loral was lifted to his feet by the strong hand of the troll warlord, Grongl, who grinned at him with yellow teeth.</p>
      <p>"On behalf of the church of Tunare and the adventurers of Healers United, I offer my services to you for this exploration," Loral stuttered.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/nightmare_deathknight.jpg"><img src="images/nightmare_deathknight_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Protector of Nightmares" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>"Exploration? BAH!" roared Grongl at the priest. "This is an execution! You wish to help? Keep me alive." Grongl walked off laughing. Loral turned to meet the calm gaze of Binedina, the barbarian priestess and leader of the guild. Holding her fur cloaks tight around her, she nodded to Loral and smiled. Beside her, Loral met the cool gaze of a dark elf dressed in soft black leather from head to foot. Her master of assassins, Loral guessed, although the assassin's form seemed to change each time they met. Loral had known Gnix for years but could never guess what race he truly was. The assassin smiled.</p>
      <p>There was little time for further greetings. The raiding party was divided into groups, each member protecting the others with spell, prayer, or steel. Blades came free from their sheaths and scouts were sent out into the valleys of the Nightmare Queen. For a few brief moments, the only sound was the howling wind that blew through the canyons. Soon the scouts returned. They were not alone.</p>
      <p>Built from the tormented souls of mighty heros, heros who betrayed their kings, the Protectors of Nightmares learned obedience from the clenched fist of Terris Thule. Possessing a power greater than most armies, the giant skeletal demons fought with a fury unseen in mortal worlds. A sweep of their powerful arms sent men and women of legend crashing into the walls. Fire burst around them from the magics of the raiding sorcerers. Blades cut deep into the black armor of the minions, chipping at the bones beneath. With a final howl of damnation, the Protectors of Nightmares fell.</p>
      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/nightmare_crypt.jpg"><img src="images/nightmare_crypt_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The keep of Thule" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>For two days, the raiding party traveled through the canyons. They met with only a few of Terris Thule's guardians but each one fought with the rage of eternal torment. The raiding party planned well for these encounters, mixing powerful magics and combat tactics to defeat the mounted riders. It was on their third day that the party found the inner sanctum of the Queen of Nightmares.</p>
      <p>For years, Terris Thule, the Dream Scorcher, had seen the paths of mortals through their twisted dreams. Deep in her keep she closed her eyes and envisioned the coming army, secure in her powers and her defenses. An arcane whisper brought spheres of protection around her skin, protection from both blade and spell. She looked around the hall, insuring all was in place. She waited. Soon the attackers entered.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/nightmare_terris.jpg"><img src="images/nightmare_terris_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Terris Thule, The Dream Scorcher" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>Grongl stepped forward into the hall, the rest of the party moving in a half circle around him. He drew his swords, Bloodfrenzy and the Blade of Carnage. A single shout from the troll warlord sent the raid into action. Spellcasters began their incantations while a rain of arrows fell upon the demi-goddess. The arrows exploded into energy around her, though none hit home. Waves of ice and flame rushed over Terris Thule, blocked by her wards of protection. With another command, the swordsmen attacked. Rushing in with blades drawn they cut into the energy shields surrounding the goddess. The Dream Scorcher laughed.</p>
      <p>A wave of her hand sent the attackers to their knees. Visions of unthinkable terror flowed into their minds, shattering their resolve. With no warning, spectral guardians of the nightmare queen rose to slay the paralyzed army. But strength found its way back into the attackers. They broke into groups, each battling the specters while another force remained upon the daughter of Cazic. Soon the specters were cut down and the attackers reunited on the goddess, filled once again with the fury of battle.</p>
      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/nightmare_stone_demons.jpg"><img src="images/nightmare_stone_demons_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Stone Demons" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>Terris Thule's protections began to weaken. The blades and spells of the Cult cut deeper into her defenses. But the queen had one last defense. Far above her, the last guardians of the Dream Scorcher came to life. Stone demons crashed to the floor and stood, their thirty foot wings spreading out to the sky. The roars of the demons deafened the attackers. The demons crashed into the flanks of the attacking party, cutting into the groups of spellcasters like knives through paper. Dachunker, a powerful female troll warlord of the Cult, smashed the knee of one of the great beasts with two skull-headed maces. But another demon stabbed its claws through her back and out the front of her stomach. Blood poured from the warrior's mouth and she fell to the ground dead.</p>
      <p>Loral rushed forward to restore life to the fallen heroine but the hand of Maylay the Necromancer stopped him. With a smile to the Tunarian priest, he knelt down and touched the forehead of the troll. Dachunker's eyes grew dark but her body stirred. Dachunker stood, her wound still pouring forth lifeblood and gore. Terris Thule sent another wave of nightmarish visions into the walking corpse but they had no effect. Nightmares, it seemed, did little to deter the dead. The zombie dropped the twin maces she had been fighting with and from her back drew a sword Loral had last seen in a Shadowhaven bar - the Sword of Ssraeshza. Piercing through any remaining spells of protection, the troll stabbed hard and slammed it through Terris Thule's chest. Black blood poured to the floor as the goddess fell. The 5000 year old golden-runed sword had once again earned the name Godslayer.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/torment_alone.jpg"><img src="images/torment_alone_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Plane of Torment" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>A powerful blow sent Loral sliding across the ground as the last of Terris Thule's guardians sought revenge. Loral attempted to call forth the protective prayers of Tunare but the last word caught in his throat as the fist of the demon slammed into him.</p>
      <p>Loral woke. A weight seemed to press down upon him as he sat upright. His eyes were filled with a red fog. He looked down to see he wore the yellow robes of a Tunarian acolyte. Standing upright took much effort but the vision surrounding him nearly sent him back to the ground. The world had changed. The red fog of his vision surrounded everything. Across a sea of blackness he could make out a floating island, a keep, suspended from an unknown ceiling by an enormous chain. For months Loral had studied the outer planes and he knew he was no longer in the Plane of Nightmares. If ever there was a place darker and more terrible, it was here - The Plane of Torment.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-01-05T14:22:28+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 30: Disease</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000092.html</link>
      <description>Loral looked with revulsion into the pit that led into the Plane of Disease and the giant pipe that eternally...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">92@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Loral looked with revulsion into the pit that led into the Plane of Disease and the giant pipe that eternally poured forth the black liquid inside. The stench of the pit overwhelmed him, burning the inside of his nose and causing his lungs to constrict. The tainted fountain was a dark contrast to the beauty of the land that surrounded it. The Plane of Tranquility promised an eternal peace. It was the land Loral always dreamed of - a land of green grass, clear waters, and quiet solitude. Like the curled demonic finger of an ancient beast protruding through the ground, the spout of disease-ridden fluid reminded Loral of his task. He would have to enter this infested portal. Loral slipped on his turtle-bone ring and breathed in the clean air that flowed from the ring's innate mystical power. With a final look around, he dove into the tainted pit.</p>
      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/disease_pipe.jpg"><img src="images/disease_pipe_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>A great splash of the vile liquid deposited the cleric into the Plane of Disease. Loral landed hard on one knee, gritting his teeth. One hand clutched the Symbol of Tunare around his neck and the other gripped an ethereal hammer. If the smell of the sewer in Tranquility was revolting, the smell of this new world was unimaginable. Loral gagged at first, even with the aid of his magical ring. A fog rolled over the stone slab where Loral found himself. A great green lake, foul and thick, surrounded the slab on three sides while a wall of rotting flesh reached into the grey sky above.</p>
      <p>A clap on his shoulder shot Loral upright, sending a wave of nervous energy down into his fingertips. When he turned, he saw the grin of two hundred teeth and the emerald eyes of Rasthik the beastlord. If Loral found himself assaulted by the odor of this place, he could not imagine how Rasthik was managing to survive. The lizard-man could smell the blood of a dead Vampyre from a quarter mile away. Loral heard another splash and Warrick the barbarian shaman fell from the portal to the slab. Loral noticed that Warrick had taken the less subtle approach of sticking two twisted rags into his nostrils to avoid the stench. Loral smiled but his smile quickly faded when he remembered where he and his friends had come.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/disease_landscape.jpg"><img src="images/disease_landscape_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>Loral had spent weeks in the Library of New Tanaan upon arriving in the Plane of Knowledge. He had been sent by the Church of Tunare to investigate the new portals manifesting themselves as books on pedestals all over Norrath's great cities. While the ethereal nature of the planes reminded Loral how different they were from Norrath, it was in the old tomes and dusty parchments of the great library that he fully lost himself. For Loral they were a king's treasure, rivaling that of Lord Nagafen the red dragon. For weeks he buried himself in the precious documents, filled with ancient legends written by hands dead for centuries. Large candles burned down to their bases as he passed the days and nights reading the histories of civilizations and gods long forgotten. It was in those magnificent volumes, covered by millennia of dirt, mold, and cobwebs, that he discovered the tales of Lxanvom, the King's Rest, and its exile into the Plane of Disease.</p>
      <p>Two wolves ran up the rotten flesh bank of the festering lake. Their paws floated over the surface, seeming to move half the speed of the great distance they traveled. When they arrived, the wolves shifted form into two elven rangers of the Healers, Taey and Brooken. Another splash from the invisible portal dropped Isos the Paladin onto the great slab. Together the companions began their trek over the putrid lands of the Bertoxxulous, the Plaguebringer.</p>
      <p>Loral remembered hearing Ciric and Azile talk about the outer Planes. He always found his mind had trouble wrapping around their concept. Ciric explained it best once when comparing it to a scale, with Norrath at the center. Norrath was a balance between good and evil. Many lands and many people, both good and evil, existed all in one world. The further out of the scale you went, the less balance things had. While the Plane of Sky, Growth, and Tranquility were on one side; Fear, Hate, and Nightmare were on the other. There was little balance in many of these planes; they were either good or evil. Nowhere was this clearer than in the Plane of Disease.</p>
      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/disease_malarian.jpg"><img src="images/disease_malarian_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>Taey's blade severed two of the spined legs of a gigantic insect-like Malarian. The creature returned the attack by spitting an acidic liquid on the ranger through its elongated stinger. Taey recoiled and retched as the acid ate away at her armor and skin. Two of Brooken's crackling arrows slammed into the bloated abdomen of the winged beast as it took flight. A quick prayer from Loral sent a wave of blue energy from his hand to the wounded ranger neutralizing the acid and soothing Taey's wounds. The creature twisted and stared with giant compound eyes upon the meddling cleric, its remaining legs clicking with agitation.</p>
      <p>Telepathic visions flooded into Loral's mind - images of the violent insect ripping Loral's arms off and burrowing its extended maw into his chest. Loral breathed deeply, canceling the horrific images from his mind. He raised a hand and a burning red energy of condemnation crushed the beast's exoskeleton. The creature fell to the ground, breaking into a cloud of noxious gasses. The party jumped back from the infectious cloud but then cheered at each other. The victory was short lived, however, when they saw the spiders, diseased rats and beetles, flowing ooze, and deformed humanoids waiting for them across the fleshy hills.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/disease_crypt.jpg"><img src="images/disease_crypt_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>For two days Loral traveled across the vile lands. While some adventurers left and others joined, the party crossed streams of sickly bile and walls of scabbed flesh and exposed bone. The world around them appeared to be a single living thing that simply grew into chaos. Soon they came to a large set of what appeared to be vertebrae and beyond it was the first mortal constructed structure they had seen since the stone slab - The Crypt of Decay.</p>
      <p>It was at this ancient structure that Loral witnessed the first sentient beings of this world, the Magi of Bertoxxulous. Empty eye sockets of the Deathbone Magi stared blankly at the party, their rotten chapped lips whispering arcane spells of ancient times. Great fires erupted around the adventurers, but they were quick to retaliate and defeat the plagued wizards.</p>
      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/disease_gryme.jpg"><img src="images/disease_gryme_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>With trepidation the party carefully made their way into the crypt, having now expanded into two dozen adventurers. It was as they reached the balcony of the great hall that Gryme, the Crypt Guardian, attacked. Gryme was enormous, as wide as a hill giant is tall. His body was covered with exposed bone wrapped in folds of decaying flesh. His chain-wrapped fists slammed into the front-line attackers of the raiding force, sending them sliding across the stone floor or hurling them into the air.</p>
      <p>A mighty battle ensued. Dozens of arrows bore deep into the back of the giant but seemed to harm it little. Wizards, both Gnomish and Erudite, called forth huge shards of ice and burning rocks upon the beast. The raiders rushed in, cutting deep into the thick festering flesh of the creature. With a great heaving breath, Gryme vomited a cloud of poisonous gas, sending the attackers to their knees. Loral and the other priests of the raiding force sent wave after wave of healing energy into those who had been caught within the cloud. Soon Loral felt the last amount of Tunare's energy leave him. With little left to do, he drew forth his magical hammer of Judgment and rushed in. Gryme's iron clad knuckles smashed into Loral. The blow shattered his nose and knocked him instantly unconscious.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/gryme_dead.jpg"><img src="images/gryme_dead_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>The crack of his nose being pushed back into place jolted Loral awake but before the wave of pain drove him back to unconsciousness he felt a warmth of energy flow through him, soothing and mending the bone. He sat upright, once again gagging as the smell of the accursed land flooded into his nostrils. The mound of the decaying corpse of Gryme and the recovering raiding party was nearby. Many had fallen to the horrid breath of the rotting crypt guardian and many others had been crushed by his heavily-armored fists.</p>
      <p>One of the raiders with the stomach strong enough to approach the corpse of Gryme, a powerful human warrior named Zarcharius, found a tiny key attached to a rope around the beast's engorged neck. The grim warrior looked up towards the stairway that led deeper into the crypt. It was clear that a good part of him wished he never had found the key, just as many of his fellow adventurers wish they hadn't stepped foot into this diseased world. But a gleam in his eye, one of adventure and discovery, drove him forward. He drew his gleaming black-runed blade and walked up the ancient staircase of the crypt. Everyone else followed.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-01-05T14:21:54+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 29: The Godslayer</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000091.html</link>
      <description>Since the dawn of Norrath, pain, torment, and horror all paid homage to the Plane of Fear. Dark demons and...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">91@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>Since the dawn of Norrath, pain, torment, and horror all paid homage to the Plane of Fear. Dark demons and foul spellcrafters delighted in the terror of mortals, reveling in their power as servants to one of the most powerful gods of Norrath, Cazic Thule. The Faceless, as he was sometimes called, had the largest number of followers in all the lands and there had never been a threat to his reign as the Lord of Fear. This day, however, he faced the worst danger he ever knew.</p>
<div class="imageset1"><a href="images/fear_stones.jpg"><img src="images/fear_stones_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Plane of Fear" /></a></div>
<p>The fiends watched in curiosity as the rifts opened. Large tears in the fabric of their world sucked foul air into Norrath on the other side of the rifts. The scouts came first, recognized as Iksar by the minions of Fear. One such demon, a bat-winged fiend known as Gamblazan, glided forward towards a scout, planning to tear open the small lizard for its intrusion. But the lean Iksar struck first, stabbing through the naturally armored chest of the red beast with his ethereal tipped spear. Gamblazan stared down at the mortal and fell dead to the tainted earth.</p>

<p>With a rhythmic rumble, five hundred Iksar poured through two dozen rifts into the Plane of Fear. Alraza Thule, the Bloodqueen, looked over to Dread, another of Thule's demi-gods, and shrugged in confusion. This confusion soon disappeared when behind the Iksar army slithered 
in the Shissar.</p>

<p>A war greater than one ever seen upon Norrath filled the Plane of Fear. Waves of roaring magma turned scores of screaming Iksar into ash. More were tossed into the air only to come crashing down, bursting into gore. The destruction of their slave army did little to discourage the Shissar Warmasters. While their well equipped fodder distracted the minions of Thule, the Shissar struck at Cazic Thule's children, the demi-gods of Fear.</p>

<p>Twelve great sorcerers hurled great beams of pure energy at the hulking wolf-headed beast, Gromhazik the Chaosfiend. His pitch black skin split and charred, burning down to the bone. Arunz the Amygdalan King carved through dozens of the Iksar soldiers when the telekinetic grasp of five Shissar channelers took hold. Arunz screamed loud enough to turn every head, mortal and immortal, until a power greater than the combined strength of every giant of Norrath ripped him to pieces.</p>
<div class="imageset2"><a href="images/emperor_ssraeshza_3.jpg"><img src="images/emperor_ssraeshza_3_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Lord Ssraeshza" /></a></div>
<p>Watching from a nearby hill, the Bloodqueen began a great incantation when a powerful blow from behind stole the words from her lips. She looked down to the golden-runed blade protruding from her chest. Twisting around she beheld her slayer, the Shissar King Ssraeshza. With a sneer, the Shissar lord pushed the dead demi-goddess off of his blade and wiped the black blood on her rotten mantle.</p>

<p>Seeing three of his children die in as many minutes told Cazic Thule of the danger he faced. Beckoning for one of his alchemists, he roared instructions to the quivering beast. They had only one chance, releasing the Greenmist.</p>

<p>A great cloud of green fog flowed out of the Amygdalan temple and wafted through the confused combatants, both demonic and Iksar alike. Not until he saw four of his generals fall over dead amidst healthy troops did the threat become clear to the Shissar King. Looking over at the great form of The Faceless, he cursed, and along with his remaining generals, the lord of the Shissar left the Plane of Fear through one of the remaining rifts back to Norrath.</p>
<div class="imageset1"><a href="images/emperor_guardian_battle.jpg"><img src="images/emperor_guardian_battle_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="" /></a></div>
<p>But the Greenmist followed and five thousand years later the Emperor of the Shissar could still feel its weight on his shoulders. He felt too the sickening feeling that Cazic Thule must have felt when the Lord of Fear saw true danger at the hands of mortals. The lord of the Shissar, Emperor Ssraeshza, had seen his generals slain, his oldest and most trusted advisors cut down, and his personal guard neutralized. His greatest creation, the Blood Golem, a construct built from the lifeblood of five hundred generations of Iksar and protected under the greatest spells of protection his priests could provide, had been cut down in his own inner sanctum.</p>

<p>Now he stood and looked into the eyes of his slayer. The mortal adventurer stood in front of him, cutting deep with blades forged to pierce his impenetrable scales and bathed in a beam of energy fed by a dozen high priests of a dozen different gods. For each mortal cut the emperor inflicted on this warrior, the wound closed as soon as the ancient blade had finished the stroke. The air burst around him into fire, ice, and electricity. Four dozen other blades cut into his scaled skin but this avatar of a dozen gods took all of his attention. This warrior had become a vehicle of revenge for all the gods 
perverted by word and deed of the ancient Shissar emperor and could not 
die.  With a final cut, the most devastating ruler to ever walk Norrath 
was 
killed."</p>
<div class="imageset2"><a href="images/emperor_ssraeshza_4.jpg"><img src="images/emperor_ssraeshza_4.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Emperor Ssraeshza" /></a></div>
<p>It had been two weeks since Loral returned from the Temple of Ssraeshza. He sat at the end of the bar of the inn of Shadowhaven where he had spent many of his nights in luclin. At one table sat three trolls, one sharing the tale of the death of the Shissar emperor with his disbelieving companions. The golden-runed blade strapped to his back spoke a greater truth than the trolls loud voice. When Loral looked too long at the wicked blade he felt a hiss in his mind and was reminded of the treachery he felt under the terrible powers of the Shissar interrogator. What tales that blade could tell, he thought, and wondered whether it might ever find the chest of a mighty or terrible god again.</p>

<p>At the other side of the bar stood a young elven paladin.  She looked with disdain upon the troll discussion, turning quickly into a table-breaking bar brawl. The bartender did nothing to intervene, knowing the purses of the trolls to be as large as their mighty ale-filled bellies. Loral watched the fiery-haired Paladin glare at the troll and turn away to finish her champagne cocktail. How much he was reminded of his early days after leaving Felwithe. The paladin had no idea of the horror that troll may have saved Norrath from. Possibly neither did the troll, thinking the Emperor was but another big game hunt. For the young knight of Tunare, the troll was but an annoying disturbance in a normally quiet bar.</p>

<p>The purple and red cross clasped to the paladin's cloak sent Loral's thoughts down a different stream.  For eighty of his 100 years of adventure, Loral had been a member of Healers United.  Unlike the highly political climate between Felwithe's rulership and the Church of Tunare, Loral found a network crossing many faiths, cities, races, and experiences.  It was a large shift from the stereotypical views Felwithe had given the young priest.  Loral was shocked to find the band led by a dark elf priestess of Innoruuk, but after one meeting with Dahlea, Loral saw the kindness behind her sharp gaze and knew he found the right group.  Soon the barbarian oracle, Juror, led the group with his strict adherence to the balance of the Tribunal.  Loral had countless adventures with the members of the Healers and assisted in the protection of young adventurers on their first hunts.  While Loral had found a wonderful tool to help in his travels and a wonderful group of friends to share those travels with, learning of the small differences between the races of Norrath was the lesson that helped Loral the most.  He was richer for the experiences and knowledge of his friends, whatever their race or beliefs.  He suddenly realized just how much Ciric's teachings of balance had helped him.  Without those insights he may never have accepted the Healers or many of the friends he met along his journeys.</p>
<div class="imageset1"><a href="images/emperor_gate.jpg"><img src="images/emperor_gate_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Emperor Gate" /></a></div>
<p>Loral remembered stories of the Erudite's first adventures in Norrath. Travelers hardly ever left the safety of their cities.  In those days, transportation was by foot or boat.  The magic of teleportation had yet to be discovered. Beasts ruled the lands between the walled cities and much of the magic and artifacts were buried in hidden tombs of long forgotten empires.  With the discovery of teleportation and of the Nexus, new gateways between far off lands became possible and and with the erosion of geographical 
boundaries, the separation of the races became thin as well.</p>

<p>The world had changed in the hundred years Loral had traveled in the service of Tunare. But in many ways he had changed while the world had not. Loral looked at the trolls, once sworn enemies of the elves. The troll storyteller returned his gaze.  Loral raised his glass to the storyteller and smiled.  The troll smiled a toothy grin and returned the toast. Many of these changes were good indeed.</p>

<p>Three weeks later, the Plane Wars began.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-01-05T14:21:30+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 28: Light</title>
      <link>http://loralciriclight.com/000090.html</link>
      <description>&quot;And what of the heroic paladin lost to the Shissar? What ever happened to him?&quot; Loral had told his son...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">90@http://loralciriclight.com/</guid>
      <body xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>"And what of the heroic paladin lost to the Shissar? What ever happened to him?"</p>

      <p>Loral had told his son the tale of his rescue in Ssraeshza many times but this was the first time Darlan had asked this question. Loral found it puzzling, not just the question but something else. A burning sensation in his hand interrupted his train of thought but a voice in the nearby woods took back his attention.</p>

      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/faydark.jpg" title="Greater Faydark"><img src="images/faydark_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Greater Faydark" /></a>
      </div>

      <p>"Aye, old friend, what ever did happen to that broken down old knight."  Stepping out of the brush to the grassy hill where Loral and Darlan sat with their picnic came Jolain Goldenleaf dressed in the traditional silver and gold armor of the Felwithe paladins. Resting over one shoulder was his legendary blade, Nature's Defender, and a green cloak fell lazily over the other. He held his golden helmet next to his hip.  A lock of his jet black hair had come free from his neat pony tail and fell across his scarred face. Loral stood and embraced his old friend.</p>

      <p>For an hour the two traded tales of their adventures. While Loral and Darlan had been traveling across Antonica, Jolain had been training Felwithe's newest recruits. This day his students traveled through the forest of the Faydark, keeping a watchful eye for orc invaders who, even two hundred years later, continued to pour forth from Crushbone.</p>

      <p>Their tales shifted to their partnership during the plane wars, entertaining young Darlan with visions of the golden armies of elves and stout dwarves standing strong against giant and powerful demons never meant to walk Norrath. For ten years Loral and Darius had served together, fighting the unnatural horrors of the outer planes and pushing them back to and finally through the rifts to their own planes. Although highly entertained with such marvelous tales, Darlan's original question returned.</p>

      <p>"How was Sir Goldenleaf returned from Ssraeshza?"</p>

      <p>"Aye, friend, I have little recollection of the event. What ever did become of the vile Shissar?" Both Jolain and Darlan looked to Loral. The burning became stronger in Loral's hand, breaking his concentration on the question. Images of the Shissar flashed into his mind, jolting him suddenly and ringing his ears, but Jolain's questions continued.</p>

      <p>"Did the elves know of the tunnels below? Were the cities of Norrath planning an assault? What of Katta Castellum or Sanctus Seru? What did those cities know of the threat of the Shissar?" Jolain's questions pounded inside his head. Gone was the sweet sound of birds chirping and crickets seeking their mates. Gone was the sound of the water passing down the rocky stream. All he heard was the hissing questions and all he felt was the white hot burning sensation in the center of his left palm.</p>

      <p>Then it all became clear. Loral looked into the eyes of Jolain and raised his palm towards the knight. A beam of pure white light burst forth, turning the armored elf into ash. The beam continued, searing through the forest like paper and seeming to crack the very fabric of the world in half. The scene around him shattered like a rock being thrown through a mirror. Loral found himself in darkness.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/taskmaster.jpg" title="The Shissar Taskmaster"><img src="images/taskmaster.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="The Shissar Taskmaster" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>Immediate was the pain he felt all throughout him. He screamed when he tried to move. His one eye opened, the other swollen shut, and beheld the great glyphed Shissar before him. To his right he saw the great golem pinning him to the walls of the dark temple with giant clay hands. Not a muscle in his body or a nerve in his head was free from the electrical energies the Shissar spells pumped through him. With a mouth capable of swallowing his hole head, the glyphed serpent hissed at him, exposing great fangs as long as Loral's forearm. The ancient beast reached forward, preparing to tear out the troublesome elf's heart when the room went silent.</p>

      <p>Visions of battle and fire filled Loral's head. The glyphed serpent turned towards another smaller Shissar and hissed an intricate throaty command. The smaller snake replied and the two turned and slithered towards the great door at the other end of the large room.</p>

      <p>A moment later, the great golem that pinned Loral's arms to the wall stepped away and Loral fell to the floor in a crumpled ball of agony. It thundered quickly out the door leaving Loral alone in the large room.</p>

      <p>It took all of Loral's energy to remember how to breathe.  His one open eye spotted a golden glimmer a short distance away. His left arm broken above the elbow, Loral shifted to his right side and inched across the floor, each move bringing waves of pain and blackness. Twelve feet and an eternity later, Loral found the source of the golden glimmer, a small idol of Tunare poking out of his five large packs. That golden glimmer turned into a glimmer of hope. Loral snaked his good arm through the straps of his worn leather packs and drew out the Faithstone of Nature. He whispered his prayers to Tunare and held the stone close. Thirty seconds later, the room flashed away and he was lying on the marble floors of the Church of Felwithe hearing the gasps of Yeolarn and the priests of the Mother.</p>

      <div class="imageset1">
        <a href="images/dog_in_growth.jpg" title="Dog"><img src="images/dog_in_growth_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Dog" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>Dog raised his large head from the thick grass as the voice of Mother filled his mind. As always, a great feeling of love and warmth filled him when he heard it, even if he knew it meant having to leave his games with Rex or his meals to help her. Dog trotted through the large woods, past the great tree where Mother stayed and past the walking trees that guarded her. He ran through the blue stream taking joy in the great splash and the feeling of water soaking into his thick fur. Soon he came upon four large pillars and an open marble floor. In the center was a small one, dressed in a light yellow robe. Dog had been asked to help before, mostly to show the small ones who appeared towards the great tree, but sometimes not.</p>

<p>Today, Dog had to point the small one away, back to the glowing tunnel that stood to the side of the large platform. Dog licked the small one's face rolling it over onto its back. Dog turned his head to the side and perked up his ears hearing the faint beat within the small one's chest. Another great lick and the small one bolted upright. Dog could smell the fear in the small one, but felt it leave when the small one looked into Dog's eyes. With his great muzzle, Dog pushed the small one onto its feet and pushed it back into the tunnel from where it came. When the small one had left, Dog trotted back to his original resting place, assured that he had done well and salivating at the smell of his sixth meal of the day waiting for him.</p>

      <p>"It was as real as the life I have lived until now."  Loral sat with Juror in the small bar of Shadowhaven and recounted his tale four weeks after his return to the temple. "Two hundred years I had lived, all illusions of the Shissar trying to tear open my mind."  The large barbarian, much wiser than his great size imparted, sat and listened to the cleric's tale. It wasn't until the end of Loral's story, detailing a life that had never been lived, that Juror shared a piece of information that explained Loral's chance for escape.</p>
      <div class="imageset2">
        <a href="images/shadowhaven.jpg" title="Shadowhaven"><img src="images/shadowhaven_t.jpg" height="225" width="300" alt="Shadowhaven" /></a>
      </div>
      <p>"Lotus Cult killed the Glyphed Covered Serpent shortly after you left," Juror's deep voice said calmly.  Loral looked at the barbarian for a long time.  Although his head still swam with the false-life the Shissar had implanted, the relief of knowing the vile creature that fed it to him was killed took a great weight off of his shoulders.  He looked to his friend again and became aware of the large barbarian's greying hair and lined face.  How long the two of them had served their deities.  How long they had worked together within the great network of Healers that spanned so many races and so many societies.  While Loral had certainly aged less physically in his 110 years of service, he felt no younger than his friend looked.</p>

      <p>Later that night Loral rested in the darkness, staring up at the ceiling of the small stone room of the inn in Shadowhaven. In two days he would be traveling to Katta Castellum to look into an unknown undead menace that could possibly be in the area. The church had sent word of the discovery and Juror gave Loral information to further the claim. Fellow members of Healers United would meet him in the dark city, and they would investigate and deal with the threat.</p>

      <p>The unknown threat was not on his mind, however. Loral knew the Healers would be able to deal with such a menace, whatever it turned out to be. Instead Loral's mind went back through a life he never lived, mourning the death of a wife he never had. A tear fell across his cheek before he fell into a deep sleep.</p>
      </body>

      <dc:subject>Story</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2003-01-05T14:21:02+00:00</dc:date>
    </item>


  </channel>
</rss>

