<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>I betcha they&apos;ll come out with a new fancy box of all expansions in one, including this one, ju</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I betcha they&apos;ll come out with a new fancy box of all expansions in one, including this one, just in time for xmas.

-Bolas</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>My only hope is with this being for 1-75 they actually get this out in the mainstream media &amp; ge</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>My only hope is with this being for 1-75 they actually get this out in the mainstream media &amp; get it some hype, &amp; get a push for new players rolling.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Level from 1-75 in the new zones sounds like nice marketing spin. What about spells?  Can I get my 5</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Level from 1-75 in the new zones sounds like nice marketing spin. What about spells?  Can I get my 50-70 spells without going to Kunark, Velious, Luclin, PoP, OoW zones?  It&apos;s supposed to be stand-alone right (well, with original EQ)?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Also fairly recent news is one the progression servers the uberguilds have killed the triggers neede</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Also fairly recent news is one the progression servers the uberguilds have killed the triggers needed for opening kunark.  Bad news is SOE is not ready to open kunark for at least a couple more weeks...</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>from sony boards..

Where is Kunark?

The Combine has completed all of the necessary steps to open t</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>from sony boards..

Where is Kunark?

The Combine has completed all of the necessary steps to open the Ruins of Kunark expansion but, as you know, the continent is still not open. The fact of the matter is that you have hit our minimum timer. We are going to let the timer run out as initially planned which means that the Kunark expansion will open just about on July 28th...</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;explain to them how &apos;awsome&apos; it is to put all your spare time into a virtual world c</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;explain to them how &apos;awsome&apos; it is to put all your spare time into a virtual world cartoon character building it up while all the while you know one day eq will be shutdown and the data erased.&quot;

Yeah, unlike our accomplishments in real life, which will endure for all eternity.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>New char models darnit!

&quot;The problems are one and the same.  EQ&apos;s new graphics engine is </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>New char models darnit!

&quot;The problems are one and the same.  EQ&apos;s new graphics engine is very modern and very efficient, but the Luclin character models are not and when you get a lot of them into one area, it bogs things down.  If we were able to replace all the old character models with updated ones made under the new systems, you&apos;d likely see a significant peformance increase even though the graphical quality would be much high</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Grief wrote: PS: News of the new Serpent Spine being digital download ONLY is disturbing. Is SOE giv</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Grief wrote: PS: News of the new Serpent Spine being digital download ONLY is disturbing. Is SOE giving up on EQ1?&quot;

they are going to only digitally distribute this expansion but they plan for their next fully encompassed expansion box to be distributed by retail so sometime in december you should expect to see a box with everything upto Prophecy of Ro. then you digital download Serpent spine.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Man.. I want box goodies! Really, they need to release it in stores and get it out there. They NEEEE</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Man.. I want box goodies! Really, they need to release it in stores and get it out there. They NEEEEEEEEEEEEEEED to do Loral&apos;s &quot;AOL disk&quot; idea with EQ. Make up nice boxes of like 30 free unlimited trial zone disks and have them on the counter of every gamestop, eb games, software etc. best buy etc. etc. etc. etc. so every person who goes to buy a PC game grabs it.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>If Serpent&apos;s Spine is download only, it instantly goes from &quot;The expansion that tries to d</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>If Serpent&apos;s Spine is download only, it instantly goes from &quot;The expansion that tries to draw in new players with a new race and newbie areas that are up to modern graphical standards&quot; to &quot;The expansion that tries to keep current players busy playing alts.&quot; SOE needs to release a box with base EQ AND Serpent&apos;s Spine (and ideally all the other expansions). I think they know that, but they may not announce it for a whi</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>With all the work that has gone into old zones recently with putting old mobs onto the new system, I</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>With all the work that has gone into old zones recently with putting old mobs onto the new system, I think we can expect a big push for new players from SoE.

Exactly how they&apos;ll do that remains to be seen, but a multi pronged approach would work best, but the key factor will be opening up the market, they learned from seeing how WoW suceeded that there is a big market untapped out there.

Boxed complete up to Serpent&apos;s Spine on shelves</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Teremar wrote:
If Serpent&apos;s Spine is download only, it instantly goes from &quot;The expansion </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Teremar wrote:
If Serpent&apos;s Spine is download only, it instantly goes from &quot;The expansion that tries to draw in new players with a new race and newbie areas that are up to modern graphical standards&quot; to &quot;The expansion that tries to keep current players busy playing alts.&quot;

Aye, QFT right there. I don&apos;t see the point of creating 1-75 content + new race, if your not pushing for new players with a retail box. Someone in</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&gt;&gt;&gt; Level from 1-75 in the new zones sounds like nice marketing spin. What about spells? Ca</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&gt;&gt;&gt; Level from 1-75 in the new zones sounds like nice marketing spin. What about spells? Can I get my 50-70 spells without going to Kunark, Velious, Luclin, PoP, OoW zones? 

You can already do that, at least with Kunark, Velious, Luclin and PoP spells.  You can research most, if not all of them.  They should have the research components of the appropriate level dropping in the new zones (something I&apos;ll keep an eye out for.)


</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I am actually disappointed they didnt take the cap to lvl 80 like they eluded to.  lvl 75 is already</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I am actually disappointed they didnt take the cap to lvl 80 like they eluded to.  lvl 75 is already going to reivialize alot of content but at least going to lvl 80 it allows SOE to take a nice big step in difficulty and make some really big encounters to accomodate the 80 cap.

The other question is will the stat caps increase?  Most people are capped at 365+ on stats already.  But will thre cap go beyond the +5 per level you get when you ding?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Posted by Greif
Be that as it may, the new race Drakkin can be monks; so I will be playing a new mon</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Posted by Greif
Be that as it may, the new race Drakkin can be monks; so I will be playing a new monk with all the twink items (Fungi FTW) that I have stocked up over the years. 

Do we know for a fact what classes the new race can/will be?  I have searched and can find no info at all - also, do we know base stats, or special abilities?</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>