<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Mobhunter</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/" />
  <modified>2006-02-08T04:09:45Z</modified>
  <tagline></tagline>
  <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7</id>
  <generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="3.01D">Movable Type</generator>
  <copyright>Copyright (c) 2006, Loral</copyright>
  <entry>
    <title>Prophecy of Ro: In-Depth Preview</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001460.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-08T04:09:45Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-02-05T17:42:14-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1460</id>
    <created>2006-02-05T22:42:14Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">With the release of Prophecy of Ro only three weeks away, Loral Ciriclight spends some time digging into some exclusive details of this new expansion.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>In two weeks, Sony Online Entertainment will release the eleventh expansion for Everquest: Prophecy of Ro.  Three days ago I had the opportunity to walk across the new lands offered in this expansion and discuss its new features with Everquest's lead designer, Travis McGeathy, also known as Rashere.</p>

<p>The release of Prophecy of Ro includes the largest single release of rebuilt old-world zones.  All of Freeport and the entire Desert of Ro will be redone in the style of later expansions using newer graphical techniques.  Previously seamed polygonal landscapes now become rolling dunes of sand and rock.</p>

<p>The rebuild of Freeport not only updates the appearance and layout but also shows how the city has grown over the years.  The factions that split the city have become even more aggravated.  The alleys of East Freeport grow darker while high walls and armed guards protect the sanctity of the Temple of Marr in the west.  The Tower of the Arcane rises high above the wooden buildings around it.  SOE paid attention to both the vast scope of the city and the intricate details found in every corner.</p>

<p>The content available in Freeport and Ro is still the same.  The level ranges of the zones have not changed.  New quests have been added, including a new faction quest in Freeport that, when earned, lets players walk freely through both sides of Freeport without harassment.  While the difficulty of this quest is not yet known, it will not be as severe as a "collect 10,000 cloth caps" quest.</p>

<p>SOE will release these four zones, replacing six old-world zones, to all players regardless of whether they purchase the expansion or not.  While the new missions in these zones are only available to purchasers of Prophecy of Ro, some new quests in these zones will be available to everyone.</p>

<p>The new zones of Prophecy of Ro are split into three sets: Takish Hiz, Plane of Magic, and Plane of Rage.  Each of these sets includes two large static zones as well as individual missions.  This does not include a final unique zone, the Theater of Blood, discussed later.</p>

<p>An overarching storyline connects the players through these new zones.  Mayong Mistmoore has become a demi-god and now threatens the pantheon.  Druzzil Ro, goddess of Magic, is unable to directly interfere with these plans but is able to call upon the adventurers of Norrath to help thwart Mistmoore's plans.  She opens gateways to the Plane of Magic, the Plane of Rage, and with the help of Tunare and Karana, sends adventurers back into the glory days of the elven cities of Tunaria.</p>

<p>The winds of Karana have uncovered the ruins of Takish Hiz.  Players will remember exploring some of this city in Lost Dungeons of Norrath, but that prepares them little for what they face now.  In the first of the three zone sets, adventurers will explore the ruins of Takish Hiz and transport back to the time before the fall of Elddar Forest.</p>

<p>The ruined city of Takish Hiz is a large static hunting zone tuned for level 50 to level 65 characters. Players will face creatures lost under the sands for centuries.  Deeper within the zone, adventurers will find access through Druzzil's magic to the forest of Elddar.</p>

<p>The second zone in each zone-set is tuned for higher levels than the first.  Elddar Forest is tuned for level 70s at roughly the same difficulty as the Hive.  Powerful treants, huge intelligent forest giants, and other great beasts roam the massive trees of the elven city.  The city layout of Takish Hiz remains consistent across both the Elddar and Ruins of Takish Hiz zone, showing adventurers how the city has changed.</p>

<p>The Plane of Magic is home to the creations of Druzzil Ro.  It consists of two zones, Arcstone and Relic.  Arcstone represents the more chaotic and natural aspects of Druzzil's magic.  Powerful spirits rule over the land and the landscape itself changes drastically depending on which spirit controls the area.  A camp of lost travelers gives new adventurers a place to ground themselves as they explore the strange land.  Arcstone is tuned for level 60 to level 70 at around the same difficulty as the Muramite Proving Grounds.</p>

<p>Relic represents the antithesis of Arcstone.  Relic is itself a vast artifact of great power, huge both physically and in planar strength.  A great spire, the Skylance, pins Arcstone and Relic together like a spindle between two platforms.  Looking up the spire in either of the two zones shows you the surface of the other.  Gravity pulls outward in both zones like a sphere instead of down as we are used to, so the surfaces of the two lands face each other instead of being stacked on top of one another, with the Skylance holding them together.</p>

<p>Relic is much more orderly than Arcstone.  Druzzil Ro's minions wander the strange metallic platforms and walkways in strange, twisted, and sometimes horrifying shapes.  Walkways lead far up into the higher platforms where large bowls of elemental magic fuel the great artifact.  Huge dragons of fire, storm, and water act as guardians of these sources for the vast engine of magic.</p>

<p>The Plane of Rage makes up the final set of base zones for Prophecy of Ro, with Devastation and the Stronghold of Rage.  Devastation is a land in constant conflict.  Nine armies endlessly war against one another in an attempt to control the Stronghold of Rage in the center of the land.  A wall of twisted and agonized creatures rings the battlefield.  Those who commit murder out of anger find themselves trapped in the wall after their death.  Only after centuries fighting through the other murderous beings on the wall do they earn the right to fight for Sullon Zek and possession of the Stronghold.</p>

<p>Devastation is tuned for levels 60 to 70 and includes much of the destructible terrain mentioned in the Prophecy press release.  Players can crush walls, catapults, doors, and ballistae down to rubble.  The armies continually war with one another and the results of these wars lead to that army controlling the Stronghold.  During our tour, powerful drachnids held the center of this chaotic world while roving bands of orcs, kobolds, armored skeletal knights, and werewolves prowled the landscape.</p>

<p>Death in Devastation is different than death anywhere else.  Death results in a respawn in Devastation with equipment intact and an unequipped body at the site of the death.  There is no way out of Devastation save those of magical means.  Even death does not allow escape from this world.</p>

<p>The Stronghold of Rage is a fortress built by the Bolvirk, the oldest natives of the Plane of Rage who appear as strange runed giants.  The zone is tuned for high-end level 70 players and consists of the wartorn inner sanctum of the Stronghold.</p>

<p>Upon achieving greater power, Mayong Mistmoore captured his own world and twisted it towards his own evil will.  This resulted in the Theater of Blood, the dark world of the vampire demi-god.  This plane is designed for the highest power single group adventurers.  There is no zone connection to this world.  Only by following the path throughout the other lands will players find themselves here.  This zone was modeled after the Plane of Fear back in the old days of Norrath.  It is very dangerous and very difficult but with powerful rewards.  Non-raiders will find themselves hunting in groups of two or three against the denizens of this world while high-end raiders will find challenges deeper in. Mistmoore's Tower, Deathknell, spears up from the center of this dark land.</p>

<p>These descriptions do not include the wide array of missions, monster missions, quests, and raids available in Prophecy of Ro.  Prophecy of Ro includes over thirty missions with a dozen monster missions, the first ever monster raid, many single-group overland quests such as the spirit hunter missions in Arcstone, and six missions for level 45+ in the new Freeport.</p>

<p>Within the focus on level 50 and above, Prophecy of Ro has a lot to offer players of almost any play style.  Level 50 to 60 players receive six new missions in Freeport and can hunt in the Takish Hiz overland zone.  60 to 70 players receive more missions and at least three huntable static zones.  High-end level 70 players will find hunting in all six of the primary zones and, given enough effort, should find it possible to hunt in the Theater of Blood.  The new monster missions in Prophecy of Ro are available to all players of all levels assuming they can reach the mission itself.</p>

<p>Prophecy includes a lot of raid content across all of the new zones.  Each of the zones includes at least one Anguish level raid with two raid-instances similar to the Demiplane of Blood.  Prophecy also includes events for 18 to 36 Time-level raiders as well.</p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro takes a different path than Depths of Darkhollow or Dragons of Norrath.  Prophecy focuses more on static content than instanced dynamic content.  Competition will return, for good or for ill, on some of this content.  The return to a large static Plane of Fear style zone might show us how accurate our nostalgia really is for the days of old.  We will know in a few months how well this works.</p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro also includes an array of new features.  Players can now block certain buffs from ever landing on them, freeing up slots for the buff they desire most.   Some classes will receive traps that let them blast attacking creatures with a variety of effects.  Areas of influence, including player auras and zone-specific storms of magic, alter how battles are fought. Every class will receive either a trap or an aura.  Some will receive both.</p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro looks to be a large expansion mixing elements of many previous expansions.  The planar focus of the zones and the storyline follow much of the same lines as Planes of Power.  The focus of static hunting zones follows much of the success of Omens of War.  Prophecy adds new missions and monster missions in the manner of Dragons of Norrath and Depths of Darkhollow.</p>

<p>How good will this expansion be? It often takes a month or two after release to say for sure.  All of the right pieces are here, although we will have to see how players respond to more static content after the previous two heavily-instanced expansions.  Much of the success also depends on the rewards.  Players always follow the greatest reward for their time spent.</p>

<p>With some excellent visuals, nice features, and a lot of strong static huntable content, Prophecy of Ro has all of the requirements for a very strong expansion.  In a short three weeks, the adventurers of Norrath will, once again, find themselves in strange and exciting new worlds.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
6 February 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Rollback of January 2006</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001458.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-08T13:11:44Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-01-22T21:31:20-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1458</id>
    <created>2006-01-23T02:31:20Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Last week Everquest faced one of the most dramatic events in Norrath&apos;s history.  Today, Loral Ciriclight, cuts through the rumors and speculation to dig into the truth of the Great Rollback of January 2006.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>On Wednesday, 18 January 2006, the Everquest servers went down for a routine four hour patch. They came back online at 11:42 AM EST with few game changes except one - a new vendor in the Plane of Knowledge selling expensive to priceless tradeskill items for next to nothing. The Everquest developers, Sony Online Entertainment, designed these vendors for the recent betatesting of Prophecy of Ro, the eleventh Everquest expansion due for release mid February 2006. These vendors let betatesters test new tradeskill recipes with items that exist on the live servers only in much more rare quantities.</p>

<p>The results were quick and catastrophic. Players flooded to these new vendors, buying as many of these rare components as they could hold from the unlimited supply of the rogue vendor. Many players know that an event like this is a temporary situation so they hope to make out with what they can as long as they can. Knowing a character rollback may be likely, these players quickly transfer items to alternate characters, friends, or through their own shared bank. Players, hoping to keep their profits, might launder these rogue items through dozens of trades. Prices in the bazaar fell quickly as these new items flooded the market. All of this happened within two hours.</p>

<p>SOE quickly became aware of the situation and removed the rogue vendors. Yet the damage was done. Thousands of rare tradeskill items, some of them so rare that only a thousand exist across all servers, had now entered the market. While the economy of the server might balance out the error over time, many players who had never acquired a single rare tradeskill item, now might have hundreds of them. SOE made the decision to begin rolling back the characters who purchased items from the vendors and all of those who had traded with them down the line.</p>

<p>One can imagine the web of transactions between those who originally traded with a rogue vendor and any of those who had contact with them and so on down the line. Imagine a single piece of platinum coated with a poison that spreads to whoever holds it and anything they possess. Whenever any infected coin or item changes hands, another character and all of their possessions become infected. When it reaches the bazaar, it can flood hundreds more.</p>

<p>SOE contained the spread of the rogue items and all of the affected players forty eight hours after the servers originally came up. Every character touched by anyone or anything that could be traced back to the original vendors was rolled back to their last save point before the patch.</p>

<p>Rolling back certain characters resulted in strange lapses in the state between one character and another. One character hands an item to another character. The second character is rolled back to a previous state but the first character, having given an item and not received one, is not rolled back. This results in the loss of the original item.</p>

<p>Erana, an enchanter on Quellious, was one such victim. Erana, her bazaar vendor, and some friends transferred some equipment including a Manastone, an item of great power that no longer drops anywhere in Everquest. While most of these characters were rolled back including the new possesser of the Manastone, the original holder of the Manastone was not. This resulted in the Manastone becoming lost in the void between mismatched rollbacks. Like thousands of others, Erana began the painful process of navigating a complex petition form to contact customer service in the hopes of recovering her Manastone. She cares little for other items lost over the two day rollback, she can always replace those, but the Manastone is irreplaceable.</p>

<p>Though this example is extremely rare and most likely the exception, Erana's tale is not unique and some stories are worse. Some players lost entire corpses full of their most valuable possessions due to the paradoxical states between rollbacks. A player dies and leaves a body behind before the patch. After the patch they recover the body but become poisoned by a tainted transaction. The rollback leaves them in a state before they had recovered their body but now with no body to recover.</p>

<p>While these lost corpses are very rare, they are paralyzing and dismaying to those affected. A lost corpse can mean the end of a character. SOE's customer service almost always returns the body to the victim but it can take a long time for a response, a time when the player nearly convinces himself or herself that all is lost.</p>

<p>Most frustrating is the fact that many of the players rolled back did nothing out of the ordinary. They did not try to get rich quick on low-priced ultra-rare tradeskill items. They did not try to exploit a bug in the game. They might have accepted some coin for a buff or bought some emeralds in the bazaar. They might have transferred some gear from one character to another and lost nearly everything of value. Even if they didn't lose a body or gear, many lost all of the progress made in two days worth of play time. One player, returning to Everquest with Everquest Titanium, a $20 package including the base game and ten expansions, wrote of his confusion at losing levels and equipment for something he didn't even understand.</p>

<p>From the time of the initial discovery of the rogue merchants the Everquest forums exploded with posts of rage, frustration, arguments, and threats. It becomes nearly impossible to uncover the truth as angry players post rumors, assumed statistics, threats, vague details, and overdramatic outcries. One full thread of posts discussed the impact of another rogue vendor who gave out alternate advanced points when players handed them a single platinum piece. SOE developers spent time away from the real issues to dig into every script that could possibly result in a situation like this only to find out that it had never happened. No such vendor existed on the live servers, the beta servers, or anywhere else. Other players reported the losses of millions of platinum pieces, hundreds of alternate advanced points, tens of levels, and entire suits of new equipment - far greater results than any player can earn in a two-day period.</p>

<p>These exaggerations took much away from the real stories of those directly affected. High-end raiders lost two nights worth of victories in difficult raid zones, bazaar traders and tradeskillers lost two days worth of profits, mid-level hunters lost levels earned over two days of hunting.</p>

<p>At midnight on 20 January 2006, Chris Lena, the Everquest Producer, wrote a letter of apology and explained the direct results of the error and the effects. Chris stated that less than 1% of existing Everquest character were effected by the rollbacks and that customer service would help with lost corpses and guild membership status but not with lost items. Later, SOE announced that it would help with the recovery of lost epic items or epic quest pieces as well as offering a double experience bonus starting Saturday morning on 21 January and ending the following Monday. Due to some technical difficulties Saturday morning, the double experience weekend was extended until Tuesday morning.</p>

<p>The decision to roll back certain characters over a 48 hour period meant that many players unaffected by the poisoned transactions saw little change at all. It did, however, let the transactions continue to spread as the players rolled back. Taking down the servers and rolling back every character, affected or not, might have had many of the same problems faced already but with less of the paradoxical state for the lost 48 hours. Only SOE has the data to truly determine which method would lead to the best outcome.</p>

<p>Many posts questioned the 1% affected rate stated in Chris Lena's letter. It seems everyone knew someone, often more than one who was rolled back and lost time, items, money, or all three. Some entire guilds were affected as guild bankers became tainted and spread the poison out to every guild member who touched the bank. Again, no one outside of SOE knows exactly the number affected, but those who play most often, those with the widest social circles, were the most likely to become affected.</p>

<p>Yet the numbers matter little to those who lost much during a rollback. To the player who loses a corpse full of their hard-earned equipment or another player who loses a priceless artifact from a quick trade in the bazaar, the results are all that matter.</p>

<p>Now is as good a time as any for SOE to consider re-looking at their choice for equipment loss on death. At the Everquest Summit in September 2005, Craig Knapp begain the discussion of Everquest's death system. With recent games choosing alternate penalties for death instead of equipment loss, SOE should consider a new death system that lets players respawn with gear and receive another penalty - a "death effect" perhaps - to off-set the benefit of returning fully equipped.</p>

<p>While the psychological advantage of returning fully equipped is strong, situations like these recent rollbacks build a much stronger case. Players don't ever want to lose equipment. In today's new world of massive online games, equipment loss is too strong a penalty that effects the wrong set of players - the lower and middle level players who have few tools for corpse recovery and a smaller network of friends to assist.</p>

<p>If you are one of these player, what can you do? Be patient and persistant. Be polite and understanding. If you've lost a body or irreplacable gear, keep working with CS to try to recover it. Don't accept no for an answer but don't hurt your case with rudeness.</p>

<p>With a letter of apology and a weekend of double experience, SOE hopes to put the event back into the pages of history. While the situation will no doubt fade over time as the CS teams recover all that can be recovered and the rest of us move on with our adventures, the week of the Great Rollback will not likely become forgotten.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
21 January 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>

<p>Update:  Erana, the enchanter in the article above, received her manastone back on 30 January 2005.  Many reports came in from those who lost items in the rollback and eventually had them recovered by SOE's Customer Service staff.</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Further Prophecies and the Everquest Expansion Release Cycle</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001456.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-08T13:11:12Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-01-16T19:44:47-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1456</id>
    <created>2006-01-17T00:44:47Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">In today&apos;s article Loral talks about the recent Everquest and Prophecy of Ro news and then digs in to a popular and controvercial topic: the Everquest expansion release cycle.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>First, a look at the news:</p>

<p>The beta for the new expansion <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&amp;message.id=161906">began last week</a>, with beta requests succeeding sporatically as players hit the site.  Those invited into the beta are sworn to secrecy, not only on what wonders they see but even their attendance within the beta itself.  Silence itself becomes a clue.</p>

<p>SOE posted some new information to the Prophecy of Ro website including <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50053">two videos</a>.  One video shows the rebuild of Freeport including all new Freeport militia barracks, <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/expansions/prophecyofro/images/prophecyofro4.jpg">a new dock</a>, and the new temple of Marr.  The second video shows off some of the new zones in Prophecy.  The zones definitely look other-worldly.  SOE also announced a rebuild of both Freeport and the Desert of Ro released to everyone, whether you purchase Prophecy or not.</p>

<p>Contrary to the premature complaints on the forums, Prophecy of Ro will include both high-end and mid-level content.  The newly revamped Desert of Ro and Freeport zones will offer some new content for lower and mid-level folks while higher-end raiders will find new challenges as well.</p>

<p>Raging Fury was the <a href="http://www.lavanet.no/rf/">first to defeat Mistmoore</a> and later, SOE's Kytherea posted an <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50052">interview with the guild</a>.  In response to raid-tuning criticism, Prathun, the designer of the Demiplane of Blood and many of the high-end raids since Gates, <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&amp;message.id=161910#M161910">talked about the tuning of the Demiplane</a>:</p>

<p>"The Demi-Plane of Blood was completed, start to finish, without any retuning.  That's nine end-game raids in three tiers that didn't need developer spying, gradually reducing the toughness, or removing hard features.  Guilds that beat Redfang, Zi-Thuuli, Hatchet, Sisters, Devlin, Tris, Roley, the Performer, and Mayong killed version 1.0.  Every time."</p>

<p>The guild Assent <a href="http://eq.nitrous.org/eq/media/">released a video</a> of their journey through the Depths of Darkhollow including a couple of clips of Mayong Mistmoore, the official end-boss of Depths.  Mayong's death resulted in a <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50054">new bit of lore</a> leading to the Prophecy of Ro.  </p>

<p>Chris Lena, producer of Everquest, recently <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50059">gave an interview</a> on EQPlayers.  Along with his Neil-Gaiman-like picture, Chris gave an excellent Kurt-Vonniguty answer to the question "How did you choose [Raghnell's] name?"</p>

<p>"I didn't – it was fated since before the dawn of humankind. So it is written and so it shall be."</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B000CPSHFS/">Everquest Titanium</a>, the $20 Everquest package including the base game, all ten expansions, and a 30 day subscription, has been released.  This is the easiest it's ever been to get into EQ.</p>

<p>Now on to our hot topic of the day:  The Everquest Expansion Release Cycle.</p>

<p>Ever since the release of Planes of Power, a massive expansion with nearly a year-long development cycle, SOE released expansions every six months.  Only once, after the release of Gates of Discord, was an expansion delayed, and then it was only for a month.  Every other expansion; Ykesha, LDON, Omens, Dragons, Depths, and now Prophecy; has come out or will come out every six months.</p>

<p>Every time a new expansion is released the boards light up with angry posts.  Most of these are from the "fix bugs" category (don't worry, I don't plan to gloss over this one so easily) but some dig into other thoughts and ideas.</p>

<p>Here are a few reasons people get upset about the six-month development cycle:  bugs from the previous expansion, class balance issues, haven't finished a lot of the content in previous expansion yet, one's raiding guild hasn't defeated the last boss yet, $30 every six months on top of $15 a month is a lot of money, the next expansion will come out buggy, one just got to a certain power level and doesn't want to have to get to a next one.  All of these are valid issues and all deserve a deeper look.</p>

<p>I have often dismissed the "fix bugs" reason mostly because those bringing it up don't follow through with a list of the bugs they want fixed.  Often the bugs turn out to be class balance problems - not real bugs, but there ARE real bugs that need to be addressed.  The best thing we can do is articulate this list and bring it up when we can instead of using a more generic call for bug fixing.</p>

<p>Whether or not these bugs would be fixed with a different release cycle is unknown.  We can assume, from the outside, that by delaying an expansion SOE could fix bugs instead of building new content, but given the unknown economic model, we can't say whether or not they'd have to cut back on the number of people on the developers team to make up for the lack of expansion money coming in.  Those bugs might last just as long whether there is a new expansion every six months or every year.  That doesn't mean bugs shouldn't be fixed, though.  It means we need to do our best to bring them to the attention of the developers and watch their progress ourselves.</p>

<p>Content progression is another big argument against the six-month development cycle.  A lot of raiders aren't able to finish the raid content in a new expansion before the next expansion comes out.  There is a careful balance between too much and too little raid content, it seems, and while some powerful guilds will have farmed the top encounters for months - others struggle to get past raid encounters from expansions long past.</p>

<p>The situation doesn't improve for single-group hunters.  There's often a lot of content unused by single-group hunters.  Some go immediately to newer and more rewarding content in newer expansions while some stay in the older hunting areas where they know exactly what to expect.  Many players who rely on pickup groups for progression have to move where the bulk of the players go - whether it is to new expansions or staying in old ones.</p>

<p>Can there be too much content?  Can't groups simply pick the areas they want to go, picking through the vast quantities of possibilities in search of the most fun and rewarding ones?  A lot of these problems require a different train of thought.  Everquest isn't a game with an ending (one of the reasons I hate the term "end-game").  Very very few ever hit every single major encounter in the game.  Accepting that many of us will never exhaust an expansion would help us more enjoy the content we do face.  At that point it becomes a question of whether or not we get our money's worth from each expansion.</p>

<p>Is $30 every six months for a new expansion worth it? It's up to each of us to decide.  No one forces us to buy a new expansion, though the drive of the other players makes the desire for new expansions different from single-player game expansions.  Ultimately, however, we vote with our dollar.  If the features and content aren't enough to interest us, we shouldn't buy it.  Most of the time, however, the features and content are enough to get us interested.  Compared to the $50 to $60 for single-player games, $30 for an expansion in which we may spend hundreds of hours is not a bad deal.  It's always important to remember that our true power in this game is our wallets.  If it's not what we want or we don't want it yet because we haven't finished the last one, we shouldn't buy it.</p>

<p>World of Warcraft changed the face of massive online games in many ways.  One element that may have led to its success is the sheer amount of polish.  It plays well and it plays clean.  There are bugs but they're hard to find and while other games may have one struggling to move around an interface, Warcraft builds a seamless world around you.  Blizzard is also spending up to two years of development time on their first new expansion.  Likely it will be as polished as the initial game.  Already they have people betatesting it, over six months from the release.  There is something to be said for taking that sort of time to clean up a product.</p>

<p>Is six months too short?  That's a hard question to answer.  We cannot say for sure that we would receive better products or better support if the cycle increased.  We simply do not know the full economics of SOE's business to say for sure how things will come out.  Before the days of Planes of Power they had much longer development cycles but bugs still existed.  They aren't worse today than they were back then.  Content still had to be tuned and retuned.</p>

<p>Personally, I always look forward to the newer expansions. I love seeing this world grow.  I like having vast amounts of content from which to pick and choose.  I like growing in power and seeing new places.  I always fondly remember my first days in a new expansion.  There are no expansions where I feel like I didn't get my $30 worth.  Sure, I get vexed when I think about Dragons and realize that most of my time there was in Creator missions.  Sure, I'm mad at the sheer amount of difficult or locked content in Gates.  I still spent many many hours, hours where I was highly entertained, in those expansions.</p>

<p>This topic has many facets and many of them, the business ones, are unknown to us.  As players we can do our best to tell SOE what we want, what we want fixed, show them what we are willing to pay for, and show them what we are not.  It isn't our responsibility to tell them how to run their business. It is our job to tell them and show them what we desire.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
16 January 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Expansion Announcement: Prophecy of Ro</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001454.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-01-03T20:19:34-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1454</id>
    <created>2006-01-04T01:19:34Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today SOE announces the eleventh Everquest expansion: Prophecy of Ro.  In this article we look at the announced features, some juicy screenshots, and ponder the future with what little information we have.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Today Sonly Online Entertainment <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=254">announced the coming release</a> of Everquest's eleventh expansion, <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/expansions/prophecyofro/">Prophecy of Ro</a>.</p>

<p>The Press Release focused mainly on the new features of the expansion including breakable objects, traps, and Spheres of Influence.  The press release is vague on detail so we can only speculate on what these features mean.</p>

<p>It will be hard to get excited over breakable objects.  We saw them in EQ2 and once you've picked up a table and thrown it through a window in Half Life 2, smashing open a barrel just isn't the same.  Larger scale breakable objects, like castles falling out of the sky or orc-laden bridges collapsing into the depths of a cavern would add a lot of excitement.  Currently, however, details on the exact meaning are slim.</p>

<p>The same can be said for the two other features.  Spheres of Influence are described as localized areas where the rules of the game can change to aid allies or thwart enemies.  For example, sandstorms may be called down to blind anyone who enters an area.  Both player created and environmentally created spheres may drastically alter the battlefield.  How these spheres will effect player versus player combat is also unknown.</p>

<p>Traps should also effect the battleground before combat begins.  We can only speculate that these traps will be similar to the hunter's traps in World of Warcraft.  Players set the traps, lure the mobs into them, and hit them with nasty effects.  These traps will not be rogue-only, but rogues will have more versatility with them than other classes.  Players will also face some devious traps in their adventures.</p>

<p>Again, the press release is vague on the details of these three features so hopefully we will learn more about them soon.</p>

<p>Other minor features are more specific and sound quite useful.  Buff filters will let players select which buffs they want to avoid.  This mainly effects high-end players who hit the limit of buffs quickly.  Eight new bank slots add a total of ninety six new available slots.  That should help tradeskillers quite a bit.  New spells, tradeskills, tasks (solo quests I assume), and disciplines are also mentioned but not AAs.  We might see some Dragons-style AAs won over the course of missions or quests but I don't think we'll see entire new banks of AAs like we saw in Depths of Darkhollow.</p>

<p>Digging into the content, Prophecy of Ro will contain seven static zones and thirty missions, including monster missions.  The press release also mentions six small instances but I expect those are the zones used for the thirty missions.  The expansion will include new monster missions but overall we will not see as many missions as we did in Depths of Darkhollow.</p>

<p>The scaled difficulty of the expansion is also mostly unknown although raids will be scoped for Demiplane of Blood and Anguish-level guilds.  Smaller events will likely start at Time / Elemental level and go up from there.  The number of these events and raids is, you guessed it, currently unknown.</p>

<p>More interesting than the press release itself was the press kit I received later.  The following nine screenshots were included and released for publication:</p>

<p style="text-align: center"><a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Arcstone1.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Arcstone1_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Arcstone4.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Arcstone4_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Dissonance1.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Dissonance1_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Dissonance6.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Dissonance6_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport15.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport15_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport2.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport2_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport22.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport22_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/FreeportSewer2.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/FreeportSewer2_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Relic1.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Relic1_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a></p>

<p>The names of the images are nearly as interesting as the images themselves:  Dissonance, Relic, Arcstone, and Freeport.  I don't think we have to guess very hard to figure out which old-world zone is getting a makeover.  This discovery alone brings up many new questions.  Will Freeport be a new hub?  Is SOE planning on revamping other major cities?  How will SOE get more players to spend time there when newer city zones like Abysmal Sea go mostly unused?</p>

<p>The story behind Prophecy seems to focus back on our time with the gods in Planes of Power.  A new diety seems to be causing catastrophic events to unwind and only the adventurers of Norrath can help.  From the screenshots above, it appears new Planes may be in our future.</p>

<p>Like most details, we do not know how SOE will handle loot in Prophecy of Ro.  The point system of Dragons led to bottomfeeding at the easiest missions to acquire loot.  Depth of Darkhollow's one-time loot resulted in a lot of nice gear from a variety of missions but only for a few slots. It isn't uncommon to walk away from Depths of Darkhollow with five different neck items or four shoulder items.  This resulted in a lot of wasted loot.</p>

<p>Neither of these two previous systems seem ideal but they did have advantages.  With those systems, players did not compete for items against other group items.  Random drops off of rare mobs was not the only way to earn gear anymore.  Hopefully new hybrid systems can help players earn appropriate rewards for appropriate challenges and reward them for facing a variety of challenges instead of the same one over and over again.</p>

<p>It's hard to follow an expansion like Depths of Darkhollow.  Monster missions added a unique and powerful feature to Everquest - one that has already changed how people think and play the game.  Breakable environments, traps, and spheres of influence just aren't as exciting.  Likewise, including half of the missions contained in Depths of Darkhollow makes it clearly sound like a smaller expansion than Depths both in powerful features and in pure content.  Yet the price is the same.</p>

<p>Granted, the time spent in Everquest expansions far exceeds the time spent on more expensive games with less content, but when one considers players paid the same amount for huge expansions like Planes of Power, one comes to expect more for our dollar than what we expect from other games.</p>

<p>This announcement also comes amid lengthy discussions on the Everquest expansion release schedule, a topic of heated debate since the rumors of Prophecy started nearly three weeks ago.  I will take a deeper look into this topic in a future article to see exactly where these frustrations come from.</p>

<p>The full scope of this expansion is still not known to us.  Until more information becomes available, we can only work with speculation and conjecture.  More details will surely come soon.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 January 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Titanium Prophecies</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001445.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-12-19T14:26:59-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1445</id>
    <created>2005-12-19T19:26:59Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we discuss the release of EQ Players, the leak of Prophecy of Ro, the announcement of Everquest Titanium, the most recent Everquest patch, the progress of Depths of Darkhollow, and John Smedley&apos;s interview on the state of massive online games.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>We've had a couple of busy weeks so let's dive right in.</p>

<p>A new producer takes the helm at the Everquest Live development team.  As Craig Knapp moves off to a new project, Chris Lena takes over as the Everquest Producer.  Chris introduced himself in his first Everquest Producer's letter after attending the <a href="http://eq.stratics.com/content/hoclogs/20051214.php">most recent Everquest Developer's chat</a> over at Stratics.  The <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&amp;message.id=151681">players congratulated Chris</a> on his promotion and Caster's Realm posted an <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=10010">interview with the new producer</a>.</p>

<p>I found this quote interesting:</p>

<p>"One of the issues is that many people feel a little intimidated by the sheer amount of content – it can be daunting. We are working on some things to address that as well but I can't say anything else on that at this time."</p>

<p>Here's another quote to stick in your scrapbook and come back to in five years:</p>

<p>"EverQuest will definitely be around a lot longer than 5 years."</p>

<p>Last week an accidental slip on the forum list revealed what is most likely the name of the next Everquest expansion, Prophecy of Ro.  While no SOE represenative validated the name, none worked to quell the rumors either.  Like every expansion since LDON, some players were very excited at the new prospect while others gave the same complaints we have heard for four years: "no new expansions, fix bugs!"</p>

<p>Everquest expansions have come out every six months since Planes of Power.  The days of the yearly Everquest expansion are over.  SOE stated at previous summits that they regularly see a drop off at the five to six month mark in any expansion release with a clear jump in subscriptions shortly after an expansion's release.</p>

<p>Six month expansions are the pulse of a healthy game.  They regularly improve and add upon the existing game, giving players new content and features that go well beyond typical class reenvisionment issues or bug fixes.</p>

<p>Bugs need to be fixed.  None of us have any doubt about this, but holding up expansions for smaller bug fixes will not help the health of the game.  Players don't return to EQ because the boats started working again, they return to see features like monster missions, single group adventures, and new high-end raid content.</p>

<p>I expect we will hear more about the new expansion in January with a release probably in February or March of 2006.</p>

<p>On Thursday, 15 December 2006, SOE released <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/">EQ Players</a>, a website that ties into Everquest more than any other website before.  The EQ Players website closely matches the EQ2 Players website of Everquest 2 and includes features such as a live character page, character rankings, guild listings, leader boards, image galleries, item data, and spell data.  While systems like Magelo helped players keep track of their fancy gear so they could drool over it while pretending to work, the EQ Players site automatically updates itself as your character improves.  So now you can see exactly what <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/character_profile.vm?characterId=536870914344">Loral is truly like</a>.  Oops, I forgot to take off my Turtlebone ring!</p>

<p>The site's release was not without controversy.  Eighteen of the twenty webservers used to host the site did not work correctly resulting in lousy performance for the first couple of days.  Connecting EQ Players to the live game also created some problems resulting in two or three patches within a 24 hour period.  One of Chris Lena's first public jobs was to <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&amp;message.id=247">apologise for the issues</a>.</p>

<p>Other players were <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=eqplayers&message.id=1029">concerned about privacy</a>.  While the site allows characters to remove or restrict their listings and rankings, doing so requires active participation.  Some feel that the privacy of those who do not yet know or understand the site is missing.  Frankly, I think the site would be a lot less fun if it only had forty or fifty showoffs while the rest of the world hid in indifference.  No real private data is revealed, there are no account titles or personal information.  If players are really concerned that people will find out what hat they wear, they can always remove their listing.</p>

<p>Earlier this week SOE also announced the Everquest Titanium pack for release in January 2006.  This pack will contain the base game, a free 30 day subscription, and all ten expansion packs including Depths of Darkhollow for $20.  This is the first time a new player can buy the entire game for this low a cost.  Unfortunately, the pack's release misses the holiday rush, and within one to two months of its release, a new expansion will also be released upping the total cost of Everquest to $50.  Still, considering the cost of $80 to $100 before, this is a much better deal.</p>

<p>This holiday season, SOE also offered up a 21 day free account reactiviation for old players.  If you no longer play EQ but want to see how the world has changed, now is a good time to go see.  Unfortunately, reactivated players won't be able to try out some of the new features like Monster Missions or Spirit Shrouds, but at least they can poke their heads around and see what is new.</p>

<p>A patch on 7 December 2005 added a few new changes.  A change to the monster missions now requires every member to enter the mission and receive a crystal in order to earn experience.  This was included to prevent players earning experience without ever even attending the mission.  Though a fair change that does little to increase the difficulty of monster missions, some players hiding under the flag of "Casual gamer" claimed that this change hurt their ability to match high-end hunters.  No element of the game should ever reward experience with no effort.  Earning up to an AA of experience without moving reveals a broken system.  That system is now fixed.</p>

<p>A new Arena also finally made it from Stormhammer to the live servers.</p>

<p>Speaking of Stormhammer, it appears the elite server will soon close its doors.  The high monthly cost for negligible improvement resulted in very few players on the server.  While some felt that SOE could have done more to make the server attractive, it was unlikely that SOE could spare the resources for such a gamble.  Closing the server and moving the players seemed the only reasonable choice.  When I saw the numbers of active players on Stormhammer in comparison to other servers at the last Summit, it was clear to me that this was the only choice.</p>

<p>The difficulty of Overlord Mata Muram came up during the last Developer's Chat.  A player asked if the end-boss of Omens of War would have his difficulty reduced considering the small number of guilds guilds able to defeat him.  Rashere stated that while probably too difficult, OMM would remain at his current difficulty as a sign of guild power.  Within 24 hours of his statement, two new guilds defeated Overlord Mata Muram bringing the total number to twenty.  OMM still remains undefeated on some servers including my home server of Quellious.</p>

<p>The second tier of the Demiplane of Blood, the most powerful raiding zone in Everquest, has been entered.  Many adventurers whisper rumors of the identity of the final encounter in the zone.  <a href="http://www.lavanet.no/rf/">Raging Fury</a> has some excellent descriptions of the latest high-end raiding encounters.</p>

<p>If you are more of a single-group hunter, like myself, you may find <a href="http://samanna.net/gen.info/prog.dod.shtml">Samanna's Guide to Depths of Darkhollow Missions</a> useful.  This single-page guide has every mission, reward, and progression tree for over fifty Depths of Darkhollow non-monster missions.</p>

<p>Pontificating about massive online games became a new past time of mine since writing for Mobhunter.  I found the website <a href="http://terranova.blogs.com/">Terra Nova</a> to be a very interesting academic look at massive online games.  Richard Bartle, the programmer of the world's first multiuser dungeon, writes for them on topics ranging from <a href="http://terranova.blogs.com/terra_nova/2005/12/nytimes_tracks_.html">economics</a> to <a href="http://terranova.blogs.com/terra_nova/2005/12/the_transparent.html">reward systems</a>.  It's a great read.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.gamespot.com/pages/news/story.php?sid=6141213">Gamespot's interview with John Smedley</a> had some interesting things to say about the recent Star Wars Galaxies changes.  A recent Wired article titled <a href="http://www.wired.com/news/print/0,1294,69816,00.html">Star Wars Fans Flee Net Galaxy</a> discussed the exodus of older players due to a more action-based feel.  In the interview, Smedley discusses the failure of sandbox games (the Sims, Second Life) compared to goal-oriented games (Everquest, Warcraft).  He also talks about a lot of interesting topics including cross platform gaming on any device, massive online games on the PSO, and players in South Korea being unable to put down cigarettes to use the keyboard.  It's a great read.</p>

<p>Here's another quote to add to your scrap book:</p>

<p>"People within the company feel so much pride in this game that they want it to beat the crap out of World of Warcraft."</p>

<p>With <a href="http://www.blizzard.com/press/051028-burningcrusade.shtml">four and a half million players</a>, <a href="http://worldofwarcraft.com/burningcrusade/">a new expansion on the way</a>, and being the <a href="http://ve3d.ign.com/articles/676/676865p1.html">number five best selling game a year after release</a>, World of Warcraft has a pretty big ass to kick.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
19 December 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Interview with Prathun on Everquest Raids</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001443.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-12-05T15:36:48-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1443</id>
    <created>2005-12-05T20:36:48Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we have a Mobhunter Exclusive interview with Prathun, the lead Everquest raid designer and most experienced raid designer in the world for massive online games.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>On my first guild summit nearly two years ago I met a designer and bent his ear as I bent so many with my gushing praise for LDON and my desires for an LDON 2.  The kind man nodded and smiled enthusiastically, mentioning their own feelings with the release of LDON and their own desires for a system like that in the future (what became today's mission system). Little did I know I was speaking to the legendary Prathun, Johnathan Caraker, the main raid designer for Everquest since the days of Gates of Discord.</p>

<p>Prathun is the most experienced raid designer in the Massive Online Gaming industry.  His Everquest resume includes most of the Epic 1.5 and 2.0 raids, all of the single group and raid trials of the Muramite Proving Grounds, all of the dragon raids in Dragons of Norrath, the design of Dreadspire, and all of the raid encounters in the current peak of high-end raiding, the Demiplane of Blood.</p>

<p>Today we give you a Mobhunter exclusive interview with Prathun on the past, present, and future of raid content in Everquest.</p>

<p>Loral: What sort of decisions go into the design of a raid encounter?</p>

<p>Prathun: It might be easier to ask, "What decisions don't go into the design of raid encounters?"  We have choices to make about the lore behind the task, its complexity, the intended difficulty, loot rewards, involvement with the expansion progression, and intended time investment.  </p>

<p>While risk and reward decisions are obviously crucial to the creation of a well-balanced raid, lore is an often underestimated aspect of the design.  A well-developed character with history and roots in the story of EverQuest is more interesting to pit players against than an entity no one has heard of.</p>

<p>Loral: How have you seen raids and raid design change over the years?</p>

<p>Prathun: I've seen raid design come a long way since original EverQuest.  Looking back at the early years of the game, encounters were typically a single mob with a few spell abilities attached.  As our scripting language has matured, it's opened up the opportunity to mold some truly unique and interesting events.  Raid mobs can change their attributes over the course of the fight, react to the strategies of the players, and even exhibit artificial intelligence that feels almost human.  </p>

<p>The Proving Ground Trial of Corruption is a good example of the latter.  It pits the raid against NPCs that mimic the behavior of player characters:  the warriors can call out for assists, clerics heal those in need, wizards who root players then back away to nuke them, and monks with the ability to feign and mend themselves when brought to low health.</p>

<p>Loral: How have raiders changed in their attitudes and feedback towards raids?  How do raiders today compare to the raiders of five years ago?</p>

<p>Prathun: Experience has taught raiders how to deal with the basics of positioning, healing, and adds, so it wouldn't be possible for me to get away with the same kinds of raids that existed five years ago.  A big NPC that hits hard and has a few damage AEs isn't going to present any interesting challenge to current raiding organizations.  They've all "been there, done that" and could complete that kind of raid blindfolded.  </p>

<p>As for the attitudes and feedback part of the question - they haven't changed a bit. :)</p>

<p>Loral: There has been a recent trend since Omens to require more from each individual member of a raid.  This has spawned both positive and negative feedback.  How do you see this new style of raid design evolving in the future?</p>

<p>Prathun: Oddly enough, I would classify a fun raid versus a poorly designed one by that criteria:  does everyone on the raid have something to do?  Do all participants have a meaningful role in the event, a reason for being there, and an opportunity to affect the outcome?  I want to make sure that everyone at a raid is playing the game, not semi-afk waiting for the chance to bid on loot, so you can expect to see more raids that require attention from all attendees in the future. </p>

<p>The traditional means of accomplishing this goal is to present challenges that play to all classes' strengths.  I try to give offtanks something to offtank, crowd controllers mobs to mesmerize or charm, curing classes debuff spells to cure, and so on.  The other means of accomplishing the goal is to present generic tasks that are critical to the success of the raid but can be completed by any class.  Examples would be having to kite a cursebearer in Inktu`Ta, responding to a gaze from Mata Muram, or being in charge of the moon relic when facing Vule.</p>

<p>Loral: How do you decide what power level to design raids for in a new expansion?  When is it appropriate for Anguish or Demiplane of Blood content as opposed to Elemental or Time level content?</p>

<p>Prathun: While there's always been some overlap between expansions, we try to raise the bar and introduce new challenges every expansion, especially when the players gain a significant increase in power via levels, AAs, spells, or gear.  The power level decisions touch on raid design, itemization, and expansion progression, so they're hashed out by several key people early in the design process.  The intended difficulty of a raid is set in stone long before I ever sit down and start brainstorming the mechanics behind it.</p>

<p>Loral: Raid balancing and retuning seems common these days.  Can you explain the problems with tuning raid content before and after the release of an expansion?  Why do we always see such radical shifts in raid balance after release?</p>

<p>Prathun: We've discovered that it is near impossible to emulate the circumstances of a Live server environment on Beta.  Guilds perform differently when real loot is on the line, have better turnouts on Live than Beta, and they'll conjure up unconventional strategies that aren't attempted when a developer is watching over their shoulder.  Beta testing has been invaluable for testing the concept of a raid and ferreting out functionality bugs, but it hasn't been 100% effective in hitting the difficulty bullseye.  </p>

<p>I am fairly content with how the Demi-Plane of Blood has turned out.  While it has seen tuning changes and will certainly see more in the future, they won't be the dreaded 'radical shifts'.</p>

<p>Loral: How do you determine the number of players a raid should require?  How does this effect the design and testing of a raid?</p>

<p>Prathun: Generally speaking, the higher the difficulty level of the encounter, the more players it will require, the more complex the design, and the harder it will be to test.  Our established player count for end-game raids is 48-54, eight to nine groups.  </p>

<p>A large part of the difficulty of these end-game fights is in maintaining a roster of well-geared and reliable players that are available to tackle the encounters on a regular basis.  This doesn't translate well to single-group content.  There's no fair way to approximate the coordination of organizing a Demi-Plane raid and apply that same challenge and reward to six people. As for testing, a small event can often be tested by a hodgepodge of assorted players on the Beta server, but a full guild is needed to put an end-game raid to the test.  Anything less is a waste of time.</p>

<p>Loral: You mention tying high-end raids to the roots of Everquest history but few of the high-end raid targets are known by anyone other than those who activly raid against them.  How do you plan to bring more of the lore of high-end encounters to the rest of the players?  For example, in Depths, most any players can see the transformation of Emperor Draygun to a lich in the excellent monster mission "Fall of Illsalin".  Do you plan to continue this sort of trend?</p>

<p>Prathun: Absolutely.  I'm a big fan of introducing the antagonists early and often, and there are many ways to accomplish this.  Tirranun stormed through Lavastorm and screamed at the mortals for daring to trespass in his domain when Dragons of Norrath launched.  The major players in Velious were described in stories that were featured in the game's instruction manual.  Gorenaire and The Cragbeast Queen were figured prominently in areas where anyone could see them.  </p>

<p>The raid encounters in the Demi-Plane of Blood are described by the inhabitants of Dreadspire - you can hear the Wailing Sisters crying near the guest rooms, and the watch often catches a glimpse of Zi-Thuuli off in the distance.  The best way to bring the lore to the players is by letting them experience it firsthand, as in the Fall of Illsalin monster mission you mentioned.  To Oshran's credit, that mission arc was an amazing bit of storytelling.</p>

<p>Loral: What sorts of things can we expect to see in the future of Everquest's raid content?</p>

<p>Prathun: Without revealing too much, I'd like to point out that there's going to be some familiar faces from EverQuest history making an appearance in the near future!</p>

<p>Loral: Thank you very much for taking the time to speak with us.</p>

<p>Prathun: Thank you for the opportunity!</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Great Depths Reitemization</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001435.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-11-21T09:12:43-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1435</id>
    <created>2005-11-21T14:12:43Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week SOE updated over one thousand items in the Depths of Darkhollow expansion.  Today we discuss these changes and what they mean for Everquest overall.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last week SOE released a patch that upgraded over 1000 items in the Depths of Darkhollow expansion.  These upgrades were limited to single-group non-monster missions and drops in static zones off of random or named beasts.  This is the largest upgrade in equipment that any expansion has ever received and SOE made the intent clear:</p>

<p>"After DoD launched, we saw a lot of feedback from players that non-raid loot rewards weren't't appropriate for the difficulty of the content. Carefully evaluating the cases players brought up led us to audit the model that has been used for itemization for several expansions now."</p>

<p>"The old itemization model was based around the top end single group gear being roughly 50% of the stats of top end raid level gear. This worked fine when it was first implemented, but as stats have increased, so too has the gap between raiders and non-raiders. Since content is tuned with player power in mind, this has caused a growing gap in the difficulty of expansion zones, in turn leading to the problems players have been reporting."</p>

<p>"After a lot of evaluation on the potential impact, we decided to change the itemization model to bring single group gear closer to the level of raid attainable gear. Beyond providing more tangible upgrades in the expansion, this change should also have a number of positive effects on the game as a whole and is something we will continue to use when making items in the future."</p>

<p>You can read the full report over at <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9920">Caster's Realm</a> or <a href="http://crucible.samanna.net/viewtopic.php?t=1200">Samanna.net</a>.</p>

<p>Equipment receive an average of about 125% to 150% upgrade in statistical power, mostly in hitpoints and mana.  Few focus, combat, or regeneration effects were modified except in cases where the rewards dropped in the wrong paths.  For example, some Hive-level missions dropped Corathus-level loot.</p>

<p>The boards lit up with responses, both positive and negative as usual.  One post, <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=141471">DoD Upgrades Went Too Far</a> discusses the issue of single-group loot eclipsing raid loot in Planes of Power.  </p>

<p>To me, this clearly shows just how out of proportion the loot has been over the past four years.  Few complained very long when better Kunark single-group loot dropped than that received off of old-world dragon raids.  Few complained when Velious single group loot outperformed Kunark loot.  Only Planes of Power offered such powerful loot and at such extreme quantities; thirty six 150 to 200 hp and mana drops in a single Plane of Time raid; that players had little choice but to raid in Planes of Power even four years after the expansion's release.</p>

<p>This new loot opens up a lot of opportunity.  For one, single group players now have a clear and long line of progression in level, alternative advancement, content, and equipment without ever having to raid.  Play time is now the only factor in the advancement of single-group hunters.</p>

<p>This also offers up alternative equipment progression areas for guilds or raiding groups.  Instead of farming the same raids over and over to gear up enough people for the next step, guilds can augment their raid rewards with single group items in high end DoD hunts.  This new jump in power should be able to take guilds beyond Plane of Time and into the deeper Gates, Omens, Dragons, and Depths raids.  As individual power grows, the opportunity for pick-up raids increases as well.</p>

<p>This jump in power also opens up more content in old worlds for non-raiders such as the MPG trials and the Ikkinz expeditions.</p>

<p>Not every item received a proper upgrade.  With fifty missions, five static zones, and over one thousand items, a few slipped through without upgrades.  For example, two of the four rewards on the the Jarzarrad the Prophet missions were upgraded to 210 mana items but the other two, the rewards for the harder two missions in the set, stayed at their original 150.  I expect we will see these reported inconsistencies addressed in the next patch.</p>

<p>Some items seemed to improve a bit too much.  A humorous post by my friend, the Kyv, states that <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=141619">the Gear Gap between Raiders and Casuals has gone too far in the other direction</a>.  He cites two new augments dropping in Illsalin and Dreadspire with well over 100 hitpoints and mana.  These two single-group acquirable rewards, though currently available to single-group raid-equipped players, offer better statistics than the rewards from raid encounters in the same zone.  While closing the equipment gap between raiders and non-raiders is an admirable goal, the intent wasn't to trivialize raids within the same expansion.  I expect we will see these augments change soon.</p>

<p>As the equipment on single-group missions improved, so did the population of these areas.  Instead of most players focusing on easy monster missions to polish off a few AAs before a raid, players now hunt in difficult missions for excellent experience and nice usable loot.</p>

<p>This latest patch also tuned the difficulty of the missions in Depths of Darkhollow to offer a smoother curve of progression.  The intent is for single group hunters to have a smooth line of progression from easier missions through the harder ones.  With around fifty single group missions, the progression path and the loot will help steer players through a long range of missions and story arcs instead of focusing them on only one area like the Faerie monster mission.</p>

<p>Monster missions also received some updates.  SOE lowered the experience of easier monster missions such as Queen Noknok's Tomb and released two new monster missions, one in Paw and one in Solusek A.  Monster missions are in danger of the creator problem in Dragons of Norrath.  The Creator mission offered the best reward for the fastest mission.  Instead of trying out every mission available in Dragons, players focused on the one that offered the best reward for the smallest effort.  Even those wishing to try other missions often had to choose between hunting the Creator or not hunting at all.</p>

<p>Rashere, the lead designer, <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=TNZ&message.id=214201#M214201">wrote a note</a> on SOE's intent to offer scaling rewards based on popularity.  As certain missions grow in popularity, their experience reward lowers and those on the least popular missions increases.  This keeps players traveling across many missions instead of focusing on the same one.</p>

<p>This patch helped fix the largest problem in Depths of Darkhollow: low powered rewards.  It also did much to improve the game overall.  The power rift caused by large amounts of high powered equipment in Planes of Power has gone away.  Single group hunters now have a clear progression to excellent items and the content their new power will make available.  It also helps players gear up for higher-end raiding guilds and lessens the requirements of raiding guilds to gear up new members.  This is a great change for Everquest.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
19 November 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Interview with Maddoc on Live Events</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001434.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-11-11T09:46:53-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1434</id>
    <created>2005-11-11T14:46:53Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral interviews Jason Mash, Maddoc, a senior designer for Everquest on the topic of Everquest&apos;s Live Events.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>This week I had the opportunity to sit down (well, email) Jason Mash, senior designer for Everquest and the brain behind some of the more recent Live events including the War of Antonica event we saw recently.  Let's dig right in.</p>

<p>Loral: What is your general philosophy, doctrine, and purpose behind live events?  Why do you do them?  With what questions do you begin?</p>

<p>Maddoc: One of my most fond memories of EverQuest, especially in the early days, were the random events that would occur throughout the world in various zones. For instance, in Qeynos Hills, a skeleton army would spawn occasionally and GM's (who played some much larger, meaner skeletons) would participate in the event. I remember a feeling sense of wonder and awe that I was participating in this event, helping to rid the world of these terrible undead minions.</p>

<p>The overall purpose behind the design of live events is basically to invoke the same sense of awe and wonder. Typically, we want to create an event that the players can interact with, influence in some cases, enjoy participating in, and ultimately have a lot of fond memories of. We also want to expand on existing lore, sometimes in very subtle ways, which adds a layer of community coherence by giving them something to collectively try and figure out and discuss. For those who are interested in the lore, that's always an aspect that they enjoy, and I like to help foster that as much as possible.</p>

<p>Loral: What goes into the design of a live event?  How long does it take?</p>

<p>Maddoc: A live event goes through a number of phases, the first (and probably most important) of which is the planning stage. We figure out what our goals are for the particular event, what lore we want to present to the players, how we want them to interact with the event, how we want them to influence the event, and ultimately the sequence of events that the players will encounter as the event progresses.</p>

<p>A live event doesn't have a standard amount of time that it takes to build since it's very tightly and directly tied to the scale of the event. I (along with Prathun, Absor, and Keridon) had roughly 6 weeks to design and implement the Retake of Grobb live event. That particular event was very large scale, spanning an unprecedented 90% of the old-world EverQuest zones, which was able to be done due to the amount of time we had to work on it.</p>

<p>Loral: What sorts of things did you learn when doing the War of Antonica events leading to the retake of Grobb?</p>

<p>Maddoc: The Retake of Grobb event was a learning experience for everyone involved, giving us an opportunity to do something that had never been done in EverQuest before, while at the same time giving the player's something global to participate in and affect to a certain extent.</p>

<p>There were only a couple things that I would like to change about the event progress, the most notable of which being the presentation of some of the more subtle lore points. Some of them were a little too obscure or dependant on players being in the right place at the right time, so I'd make them a little more obvious.</p>

<p>Loral: How do live events fit into the release of a new expansion?  Tell us a little about the design and story of the Depths of Darkhollow release event.</p>

<p>Maddoc: In conjunction with the ongoing storyline in EQLive, we incorporated the events that would lead Norrathians into Darkhollow. The storyline had been planned months in advance when we first conceived of the expansion.</p>

<p>The turning point began when Lanys T'Vyl, child of the Prince of Hate, entered Neriak, the dark elf city, and demanded the help of Queen Cristanos Thex in the way of a sacrifice for the greater good of dark elves. Lanys had a plan, specifically magic knowledge, which could elevate their evil race above all in Norrath. Cristanos obliged and offered up her very own husband, King Naythox Thex, as the sacrifice for Lanys' designs.</p>

<p>By deceiving and drugging Naythox, Cristanos made her husband ready for the ritual Lanys had planned and there was a procession from the dark elf city into the nearby Nektulos Forest. There was a decision to conduct the ritual outside the city should anything go terribly wrong.</p>

<p>For many days, Cristanos' necromancers of her Dead guild chanted in a circle around Naythox Thex as they worked the magic of the curse Lanys mapped out for them. There were many interruptions as the army of the light and good in the world, Norrath's Keepers, attempted to thwart the queen's and Lens's efforts. Skirmishes took place across the forest until, one night, Lanys, the leader of the Dark Reign army, and Firiona Vie, leader of Norrath's Keepers, met on the battlefield.</p>

<p>As the battle reached a fever pitch, the curse upon Naythox was almost complete and was seemingly fed by the chaos around it. While all in the forest focused on the clashing blades of war, Cristanos saw her opportunity to withdraw her husband to act in her own scheme and teleported them both back to Neriak, the dark elf city, with the aid of her wizardly handmaiden.</p>

<p>The removal of Naythox also removed the focus of the curse and the discordant energy in the air created an explosion that few have seen before. And when the dust cleared, the armies of both sides, including their leaders and commanders, had disappeared and a passage to a dark underground world appeared the path to Darkhollow.</p>

<p>And while Norrathians discovered Darkhollow, no one yet knows where Lanys, Firiona, or their allies have gone.</p>

<p>Loral: Where do you see live events going into the future?  Do you see monster missions playing any part?</p>

<p>Maddoc: I foresee monster missions becoming more and more integral to live events in the future. On that front specifically, we've currently got a Halloween event that's in progress that makes use of the monster mission system, and it seems to be going over really well with the players. It's very likely that they'll continue to make an appearance.</p>

<p>Loral: What are some of the main complaints you hear in regards to live events and how do you address them?</p>

<p>Maddoc: The most common complaint I've heard recently is that there's sometimes not enough notice that an event is going to happen, which I think we'll work into the next event, perhaps giving a day or two warning before big events or battles.</p>

<p>Loral: What was your favorite event or piece of an event?</p>

<p>Maddoc: I'm very partial to the armies in the Retake of Grobb event (mostly because I spent a lot of time developing it for the RTG events), specifically the technology that manipulated their movement across Norrath. I'd like to develop that technology further, adding in a lot more flavor to them, such as training sessions, night-time activity, and other events of the same nature. There's so much potential for this new technology that I believe we could put to use in many other places in EverQuest besides live events.</p>

<p>How awesome would it be to see small patrols of guards gather together, fall into formation, and begin a training session in their home city? After which, they could go on a march throughout the lands, patrolling for and exterminating any immediate threats to their culture? Maybe they are occasionally given orders to escort an Emissary of the Court to another, distant city. It's all part of an interactive and dynamic world that I'd love to expand on and add into EverQuest at any chance.</p>

<p>Loral: How much did you love those most excellent Reports of the Wilds?</p>

<p>Maddoc: Reports of the Wilds? What are these mysterious relics of which you speak? All friendly jokes aside, they were very well written and I enjoyed them thoroughly. :)</p>

<p>Notes:  With luck, we will have more such interviews with other members of the Everquest Live staff.  I thank Jason for spending the time to answer these questions and hope to talk to him again soon.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
14 November 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Patch of Hallow&apos;s Eve 2005</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001433.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-29T13:22:07-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1433</id>
    <created>2005-10-29T18:22:07Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week we take a discuss the first major patch since the release of Depths, the Hanvar changes in Anguish, the Depths loot situation, the Walk of Game contest, the EQ Halloween festivities, an the most recent developer&apos;s chat.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>SOE released the first major patch since the release of Depths on Thursday.  The new user interface was one of the most noticeable changes.  This new UI was released with the Escape to Norrath Everquest demo, and finally made it to our servers this week.  Reactions to new user interfaces are pretty easy to predict.  Some folks hated it, some folks loved it.  While most of the changes were cosmetic, the new horizontal and vertical hotboxes shook some people up.  I found it a lot easier to run all four hotbox sets at once with this new layout.  I keep two above my array of chat boxes on the bottom of the screen and two along the left and right sides of the screen.</p>

<p>The new spell gems are a bit of a change.  Anyone who has used Thomas King's UIs in the past will recognize the style but they aren't quite as intuitive as the older spell gems.  SOE moved the older UI to a new "default_old" folder so traditionalists can stay with the older UI, but I imagine we'll see less support for the old UI as new features are added.  Overall, however, the new user interface gives EQ a nice fresh look, an important move for a six year old game.</p>

<p>The new audio trigger feature introduces a lot of potential.  One can set up the audio triggers to alert them when they receive tells, when buffs have worn off, when invis drops, when someone mentions their name, or even add some nice sound effects to critical blasts and critical heals.  The tool is flexible enough to use in very specific situations like the emotes in Anguish or complete heal rotation triggers.  Powerusers will most likely find the best uses for this tool, but it offers a lot of possibilities.</p>

<p>Everquest now uses the default system mouse during play.  The biggest improvement seems to be mouse cursor speed regardless of the framerate of your game.  Players can also mouse out of the EQ window in windowed mode without having to release the mouse.  This addition wasn't without bugs, however.  It appears some discrepancy between Microsoft's use of the mouse and EQ's caused the mouse to stick in the upper left corner.  Dev Rapez <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=211#M211">posted a fix</a> that requires an upgrade from Microsoft.</p>

<p>Stormhammer received a new Arena.  I heard whispers of this new Arena at the last Fan Faire and I expect we will see it on live servers in a month or so.  Stormhammer is a server in dire straights at the moment.  At nearly 1/10th the population of the other servers, players on Stormhammer find it harder and harder to progress through the content of newer expansions.  While most servers had the Nest opened up within a month or two after the release of Dragons of Norrath, Stormhammer only had it opened up recently.  Sony needs to make a decision about Stormhammer and the most likely solution is to disband the server, send the players to any other server they'd like to go, and lower their monthly rate back to the normal fee.</p>

<p>The patch message mentioned power improvements to spirit shrouds.  We have yet to see how much more powerful these shrouds will be.  My "Shroud the Creator" contest is still going on.  Send me a screenshot of six spirit shrouded characters defeating the Creator and win a new copy of God of War for the Playstation 2.  The screenshot must show six shrouded players, a /who to show the levels and races, and the dead creator all in one shot.</p>

<p>This patch also included this year's Halloween events.  Keep an eye out in Kithicor woods for some strange activities including a trick-or-treat scavenger hunt, an undead attack in East Commonlands, a high level quest in Hate, and what appears to be a monster mission of divine proportions.  There is also an excellent <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=TNZ&message.id=210505">spoiler thread</a> on the EQLive forums for weaker souls.</p>

<p>We didn't see any improvements to Depths of Darkhollow's loot in this patch, but we can expect it for the next one.  A few developers commented on the loot balancing process and while the exact statistics of these new improvements aren't yet known, we can expect some nice upgrades.</p>

<p>The patch did include a new quest NPC in Undershore who rewards players for finishing Depths of Darkhollow mission sets.  The rewards for these quests appear to be items with a clickable +50 resist buff, one for each of the five resists and a final one for all five at once.  From the quest's text, it appears to open up some event as well but details are not yet known.</p>

<p>The developers joined EQ Stratics on Thursday night for another developer's chat.  Aside from pompous egotistical pasty jerks hogging all of the questions, the chat went well.  We learned that SOE is as excited about the success of Monster Missions as many players.  Zorillius mentioned the release of one or more new monster missions before the end of the year.</p>

<p>Prathun, the force behind the creation of the Demi-Plane of Blood, the top raid zone in the game said that he felt progress through raid content in Depths is about where he expected or "slightly behind par".</p>

<p>The raiders of Anguish learned that during the last patch, the raid mob Hanvar grew in strength.  This nerf appeared to fix an outstanding bug from the previous designer that fell through the cracks.  While many raiders are upset about the nerf, the most common complaint seems to be about the time it took to fix it.  Raiders have already defeated the encounter and it is unlikely to severely block those seeking the epic 2.0 spheres that Hanvar drops.  </p>

<p>While the Hanvar nerf may seem like a very big deal to those currently working on epic 2.0s, it is unlikely to stay a big deal for long.  Player power continues to go up so any upgrade to difficulty will simply keep Hanvar from turning into the next Qvic M'Shas. In a couple of months, people won't know the difference.  How many people still complain about the Vulak nerf?  From all accounts, Hanvar was bugged and finally got fixed.</p>

<p>Everquest is <a href="http://www.walkofgame.com/">up for a star at the Walk of Games</a> at the Sony Meteron in San Francisco.  These stars celebrate the most influential games of our time.  While Everquest no doubt often faces criticism, I can think of no other game I have played for this long and one that has had the most impact on my life.  I can't think of a more influential game on that list.</p>

<p>Time to go trick or treating!</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
29 October 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Two Contests and the Lost Files of Moorgard</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001431.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-17T08:10:55-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1431</id>
    <created>2005-10-17T13:10:55Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we officially announce two Mobhunter contests and the great finding of the Lost Files of Moorgard.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last week, in order to test a theory and add a bit of fun, I announced the official Mobhunter Spirit Shroud contest.  Here are the details:</p>

<p>Mobhunter's Spirit Shroud Contest!</p>

<p>Take yourself and five friends, switch to level 70 spirit shrouds of any type, and go defeat the Creator Dragons of Norrath mission.  Send me a single screenshot of you and your five friends in spirit shroud form, an inventory window to show me your level, a /who in your chatbox to show me the level, class, and race of your group's shrouds, and the body of the dead creator.  This should all be in a single screenshot.  Email the screenshot to loral@loralciriclight.com in jpg format.</p>

<p>If you are the first to send me this screenshot, you will win a brand new copy of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B0002XL3BA/">God of War</a> for the Playstation 2, this year's best action / adventure game.</p>

<p>Now on to the second contest:</p>

<p>Mobhunter's Red Cross iPod Shuffle Giveaway!</p>

<p>Support for those affected by Hurricane Katrina is still greatly needed.  Visit the <a href="http://www.redcross.org/">Red Cross homepage</a> and donate $20 or more to the Katrina relief effort.  Forward me a copy of your Red Cross donation receipt and your name will go into a raffle for a 1gb iPod Shuffle player.  The shuffle is slightly used but in fine working order. On November 15th 2005, I will have someone draw a name out of a hat filled with all of the $20 or more Red Cross receipts to find a winner for the 1GB iPod Shuffle player.  You may only submit one donation per name and address.</p>

<p>So donate today.  Help those who need our aid and perhaps win a fine mp3 player at the same time.</p>

<p>Now for our last bit of news, the Lost Scrolls of Moorgard!</p>

<p>In the late hours of the evening, when the blackness of of night was absolute, I found myself hunched over my writing table scrawling out this article on sheets of parchment with a large  quill.  A whisper brought my head up from my words, slipping through the ancient halls of Castle Mobhunter.  I picked up my candelabra dripping hot red wax onto the oak table, gathered my monk's robes about me, and with trepidation, followed the strange whisper.</p>

<p>The whisper led deep into the lower vaults of the castle, revealing halls and rooms I had never before seen, halls lost to the current residents of the castle.  The whisper traveled further until it led to a huge oak door banded with steel and marked with a great M.  I pushed on the door and felt an ancient latch break free.  The door swung open.</p>

<p>A room filled with dust and cobwebs held nine large pots.  I lifted the heavy lid off of one of these pots and felt old stale air escape for the first time in centuries.  Inside were sheaves of lambskin bound and tied in thick covers of leather.  I untied it, feeling the twine turn to dust under my fingers, and read the first page.  Suddenly understanding dawned on me.  I had found the <a href="http://mobhunter.com/moorgard/">Lost Scrolls of Moorgard</a>!</p>

<p>From September 25th, 2000 until August 16th 2003, Moorgard wrote over four hundred articles for Mobhunter.  These articles entertained and informed thousands over the years.  They helped steer Everquest into a new age.  Now these articles, once thought lost forever, have been found.</p>

<p>These articles document the history of Everquest from the times of Kunark to the times of the Planes of Power.  Follow Everquest back through its history from the eyes of Everquest's best editorial writer.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
17 October 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sinkholes in the Depths</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001425.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-08T11:52:50-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1425</id>
    <created>2005-10-08T16:52:50Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Depths of Darkhollow opened up some of the most exciting and innovative features we have seen in any massive online game.  No expansion is perfect, however.  This article looks at three of the largest problems in Depths of Darkhollow: disappointing rewards, unbalanced missions, and low powered high level spirit shrouds.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Depths of Darkhollow included some of the most innovative features in any of the ten previous Everquest expansions.  The creativity of this expansion shows us how far this game has come and how far it can go in the future.  With monster missions and spirit shrouds, Depths offers the most content to the widest range of players since Lost Dungeons of Norrath.</p>

<p>Yet no expansion is perfect.  This article outlines the three biggest problems in Depths of Darkhollow and offers recommendations to help fix these problems.  Let us begin.</p>

<p>Problem 1: Disappointing Rewards</p>

<p>The mission system in Depths of Darkhollow moves away from the point system found in LDON and Dragons of Norrath to a new mix of both dropped rewards and rewards earned for the completion of a mission.  Unfortunately, the loot on many of the non-monster missions is well below the power of equipment required to defeat the mission.  Those who need the loot cannot defeat the mission and those who can defeat the mission often have equipment far better than the reward.  Here's an example:</p>

<p>The third mission from Kelliad in Stoneroot falls, "Building a Disguise", sends you off to kill 10 Witherans, 25 drachnids, 10 more drachnids, and a final boss.  While the base mobs themselves are not very difficult to defeat, the boss hits for over 3,000, harder than most of the gods in Planes of Power.</p>

<p>What was our reward for defeating this magnificent foe?  </p>

<p>Rippled Cape<br />
AC: +11 Str: +12 Dex: +6 Wis: +12 Int: +12 Agi: +6 Fire Resist: +20 Cold Resist: +20 Magic Resist: +20 HP: +120 Mana: +130</p>

<p>This mission was harder than any other fight I have ever faced in Everquest.  The reward, however, was less powerful than the rewards found six expansions and three years ago.  Here is a cloak I picked up as rot loot in Plane of Time over two years ago:</p>

<p>Cloak of Ferocity<br />
AC: +25 Str: +18 Sta: +20 Wis: +18 Int: +18 Agi: +20 Fire Resist: +15 Disease Resist: +15 Cold Resist: +15 Magic Resist: +15 Poison Resist: +15 HP: +145 Mana: +145<br />
Vengeance III<br />
Fury of Druzzil</p>

<p>From Dragons of Norrath I can purchase this cloak doing any of the missions in the expansion.  This takes a lot less work than the battle against the Chamber Guardian:</p>

<p>Cloak of the Red Dawn Augmented with a Glittering Demantoid Stone<br />
AC: +16 Dex: +11 Sta: +11 Cha: +10 Wis: +9 Int: +9 Fire Resist: +13 Disease Resist: +12 Magic Resist: +13 HP: +115 Mana: +135 End: +135<br />
Strikethrough: +2%</p>

<p>This is only one example of many.  In-game chats and forum postings all complain about lackluster loot rewarded for exciting and difficult missions.</p>

<p>How can SOE fix this?  Improve the loot drops from the non-monster missions in Depths of Darkhollow.  It is time that single-group players meeting an appropriate challenge can have access to the type of loot found six expansions back in Planes of Power.  Single group hunters require this gear to progress through the Illsalin missions and to hunt in places like The Nest, the MPG trials, and Riftseekers in older expansions.  Replace 120 hitpoint and mana drops with 150 hitpoint and mana drops and add focus and combat effects.</p>

<p>Problem 2: Unbalanced Difficulties on Missions</p>

<p>While many of the new missions in Depths of Darkhollow offer exciting and appropriate challenges for those who seek them, some of the missions found in Depths are far harder than many groups are able to defeat.  Let's go back to our previous example, the Chamber Guardian of the "Building the Disguise" mission.</p>

<p>The Chamber Guardian is a powerful drachnid with an AE knockback snare that steadily grows in power as his hitpoints go down.  In the final 10% of the fight he can hit for more than 3000 in a single hit.  Our Time-geared fighter died in one round.  We defeated him our second time through, after an hour of clearing back to him, only when I used Staunch Recovery, the veteran reward ability that fully regenerates mana.  It took me over 13,000 mana to keep our tank alive during this fight.</p>

<p>What content was this tuned around?  What non-raider could ever be expected to burn 13,000 mana?  What would have happened if I had a DON-equipped paladin instead of a Time-geared warrior? </p>

<p>This is a mission in the middle of the expansion.  It isn't a final mission and the end reward for this and the four other missions in the series is a level 68 spell.  No level 68 player can withstand the Chamber Guardian's power.</p>

<p>Again this is only one example.  In the "Preemptive Strike" mission on "Normal" difficulty the party faces post Riftseeker level trash mobs and ten shades that hit above 2000.  Had I not done this mission with a Qvic-geared tank, I don't think I would have completed it.</p>

<p>Monster missions face some of the same problems in both directions.  Some monster missions, like the original Griffin mission, ended up being too easy to finish.  Others, like the "Defending the Grove" monster mission seem impossible.  No doubt there should be a range of difficulties but the difficulty seems to shift from trivial to impossible very quickly.</p>

<p>This problem can be fixed with better and more accurate testing.  Single group "normal" difficulty missions, and those missions with no difficulty should be tuned around players with single-group acquired equipment.  "Hard" missions and some of the more powerful missions in Dreadspire should be tuned around those with Time+ raid gear.</p>

<p>Problem 3: Spirit Shroud Power, Progression, and Experience Gain</p>

<p>Shrouds above level 60 have a very difficult time coming anywhere even near the power of a regular level 60 or above player.  With the high difficulty of content in newer expansions, shrouds cannot meet the needs of any high level player.</p>

<p>I had hoped that shrouds could be used to switch from one archetype to another in case the group could not find that one last required class type.  However, in nearly all cases, one is better off playing one's main character even if one isn't of a desired class type.  For example, as a level 70 cleric I am much more suited to tanking than a level 70 shrouded warrior.</p>

<p>This problem shows off the much larger problem of the power spread across the highest level.  This has been a problem for some time but as our power grows overall, the gap becomes wider.  As long as that gap remains as wide or wider than it is now, things like spirit shrouds will never meet the needs of anyone at high levels.</p>

<p>Shroud progress is also very slow.  After an entire LDON as a level 50 rogue shroud, I earned less than 10% towards the next unlocked shroud.  Add this to the very low experience I earned for my main and Monster Missions end up looking like a much better way to hunt with my friends.</p>

<p>These problems can be fixed in a few ways.  First, increase the amount of experience earned while in a shroud.  Second, speed up shroud progression.  Three, increase shroud power at level 70 and begin to take a longer look at how to narrow the power gap at level 70.</p>

<p>Last week I announced my Mobhunter Spirit Shroud Contest.  Send me a screenshot showing that six level 70 players using only spirit shrouds defeated the Creator mission on Dragons of Norrath and you win a free unopened copy of "God of War" for Playstation 2.  The screenshot must show six spirit shrouded players, a "/who" statement or inventory screen to show levels, and a dead Creator corpse.  Send this screenshot to loral@loralciriclight.com.</p>

<p>The problems above do not fully describe every problem in Depths of Darkhollow but from a content focus, they are the three biggest.  These problems are solvable.  Better mission testing, balancing the difficulty of "normal" missions, increasing mission rewards, and increasing rewards while using spirit shrouds would go a long way to help improve this expansion.  The shroud power problem is much more difficult to solve since it is only a manifestation of the larger power gap problem at the high levels.</p>

<p>All of these issues came up at the last EQ community summit and I have faith that we will see them addressed in the near future.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
8 October 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Summit Report, September 2005</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001424.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-03T16:39:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1424</id>
    <created>2005-10-03T21:39:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Loral returns from the west with tales of the September 2005 Everquest Summit.  Read on for details on the summit discussions, some editorial fluff, and exclusive juicy details on a new and most excellent feature soon to be released.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Still groggy from a late-night level 50 Lost Dungeon hunt and a later-night scramble to pack up my books, notebooks, and fancy fountain pens, I woke up Thursday morning and began my trek west to the steel towers of SOE and all the worlds held within.</p>

<p>I had the advantage at this summit of knowing or at least recognizing most of the other EQ community representatives from previous summits and fan faires and rode the bus to the hotel with Samanna of the Spirit Realm.</p>

<p>Thursday night we met with Rashere, Brenlo, Kytherea, and Ashlanne for dinner.  Most of our discussions revolved around Gemdiver's pre-Summit State of the Game article where he accidentally dubbed the term "Age of Rashere".  We had a lot of fun with that.  We discussed monster missions, mission progression in Depths, Everquest's past, and the future.</p>

<p>We learned at the dinner that the Depths of Darkhollow expansion was the number two best selling PC game during the week of its release behind the latest Sims expansion.  The dev team was very excited and proud of this news.</p>

<p>Friday was mainly a day of recreation.  We visited San Diego's excellent yet hilly zoo.  Friday evening we met with the SOE developers for dinner and challenges of Dance Dance Revolution and Street Fighter 2 (I still owe Prathun a rematch after our 1 to 1 ending scores but at least I pwn3d Zajeer).  My ideas of tying Dance Dance Revolution to the Overlord Mata Muram encounter continues to fall on deaf ears (Overlord Mata Muram says "You! Cleric 01246, DANCE!").</p>

<p>Saturday morning after breakfast we headed to SOE for our day of official discussions.  It was here I began to blanket the lands with my twenty two printed copies of "Loral's Evil Agenda".  Knowing some would no doubt be destroyed in horrible ways, I made sure to bring many extra copies.  Little did I know that lord Brenlo would go so far as to literally eat one on the bus ride to SOE.</p>

<p>Our first meeting brought up the topic of EQ's marketing.  With the recent release of Escape to Norrath, SOE began a new way to market EQ.  There were a lot of suggestions and feedback on the release and availability of Depths of Darkhollow.  Whatever people thought about the clockwork boar, a lot of people in the room bought the box just for that rather than download it.</p>

<p>While Escape to Norrath offers an excellent window into EQ, the 300 meg download can be heavy.  Some of us suggested that SOE offer this on CDs like AOL does, no doubt a costly proposal, or as a bundle with PC-Gamer.</p>

<p>Our second session was titled "Everquest, level 1 to Uber" and focused on player progression from the lowest levels of the game to the highest.  I mentioned improving the 20 to 50 game on my Evil Agenda and suggested that SOE consider more progressive missions and quests for these levels to show mid-level players the benefits we see in expansions like Dragons and Depths.  Armor and class weapon quests do a lot to drive players to fun content but currently most players buy weapons in the bazaar.</p>

<p>I also brought up reevaluating the costs of LDON items, especially below level 65.  Zajeer explained his intention to look at these points and make sure that players are no longer leveling faster than they can buy items in LDON.</p>

<p>Rashere began a discussion about SOE's interest in reducing downtime, especially with combat endurance.  Right now EQ doesn't have an in-combat and out-of-combat state system to ensure that players are no longer locked in combat.  Such a system would let players regenerate hitpoints, mana, and endurance faster than when they are in combat.  Use of a monster's agro list can help but it isn't the ideal solution.</p>

<p>We discussed one topic in which I have been interested for some time, the identification of player power at level 70.  Frodlin, the warrior corrispondant and an excellent debate partner of mine, joked about an Everquest 2 style "Level 70 double up arrow", an idea I liked a lot.  With alternate abilities and gear now far more powerful than ever before, an in-game identifier of player power would help SOE properly tune encounters.</p>

<p>Gemdiver had my third favorite quote of the weekend when he asked "Since there are two other wizards here, I will stay away from wizard problems, but what is the state of class re-envisioning things like druid stances and rogue vs. wizard dps."  Even when he's trying he can't let go of wizard issues.  The answer was that about 70% of the outlined re-envisioning took place so far with good results and other things, like the druid stances, take a bit more time to program in.</p>

<p>Our third meeting discussed Depths of Darkhollow.  Craig Knapp mentioned Gemdiver's recent "State of the Game" paraphrasing "Depths of Darkhollow could be the greatest EQ expansion if the loot didn't suck."  Gemdiver's actual quote wasn't quite this strong: "If Zajeer and SOE upgrade the DoDH mission drops to a Qvic level of gear, they will have pulled off the greatest expansion this great game has ever seen."</p>

<p>Depths loot quickly became a hot topic.  Zajeer, the item designer, explained that loot was based on drops from previous zones of comparable difficulty including Noble's Causeway, Muramite Proving Grounds, and Riftseekers.  Loot on Monster Missions was much harder to gauge since monster mission difficulty is independent from character power.</p>

<p>Zajeer and the other designers have seen the complaints about the loot quality in Depths.  Zajeer himself plans to spend the next couple of weeks looking at the difficulty of missions and the loot dropping within to make sure the risk vs. the reward is appropriate.</p>

<p>I suggested a few things on this topic including a set of class or archetype armor built for level 70 single-group hunters or perhaps more evolving items so that while the first item drop may not be excellent, it could grow into something quite nice.  On the topic of class armors, Zajeer was apprehensive saying that he received a lot of negative feedback on previous class armor sets (I believe he was talking about high-end raiding armor feedback, not group armor).  On the topic of evolving items, he gave me my second favorite quote of the trip: "That's not too bad of an idea."</p>

<p>I look forward to Zajeer's rebalance of Depths loot over the next couple of weeks.</p>

<p>The topics of progression for shrouds and evolving items both came up.  Rytan stated that shroud progression was slower than he had intended.  Evolving item progression is about where Zajeer intended it but it is important to note that evolving items only progress when mobs are killed solo or in a group.  Quests, task experience, mission rewarded experience, and raids do not give experience to evolving items.</p>

<p>The last official discussion of the day was an open discussion.  Craig Knapp began the discussion by asking about Everquest's current death system.  Currently EQ handles death much different than competing MMOs and while many of the designers feel that death continues to erode into a meaningless disadvantage in EQ, the topic is still hotly debated internally.</p>

<p>There are many ways death can be handled.  Everyone agreed that death still requires some penalty but it is likewise clear that those facing the stiffest death penalties are those in the middle of the game, not at the end.  High-end hunters have the easiest time finding resurrections, regaining experience, and recovering equipment.  Those in the middle often do not have anyone who can help them and if they find a cleric able to res at their level, they recover significantly less experience than those with 96% resurrections available.</p>

<p>Cheating and Macroquest came up during this discussion as well.  Grumbuk, the assistant lead programmer on Everquest, has worked hard to defeat many of the cheats and exploits found in EQ.  He described his philosophy on cheating, saying that EQ has no desire to lose business based on false detection of a non-cheating player and that the strongest countermeasures for cheats and exploits are when the cheater knows what SOE does but still cannot defeat it.  It is clear that the EQ programmers pay a lot of attention to cheats and exploits and are developing both systems and techniques for dealing with this problem.</p>

<p>A lot of the information gleaned from this summit came from the spaces in-between the official events.  Here are some interesting bits:</p>

<p>This weekend was the first time I had heard discussion about the Demi-Plane of Blood, the final raid zone in Depths of Darkhollow. Prathun told me a little of the types of challenges faced in this new raid zone and they sound like an excellent departure from standard statistical-based raids and more like some of the things we saw in MPG trials and with Mata Muram himself.</p>

<p>I heard about a few monster missions I haven't yet experienced or heard of including a recreation of the release of the Green Mist in Overthere.</p>

<p>The EQ mouse pointer will soon be based on the windows mouse.  This means you can simply mouse out of an EQ window instead of the strange "SHIFT ALT R" mouse release.  This may also speed up mouse precision quite a bit in game since the mouse and the framerate of the display will be independent.</p>

<p>Now we come to the most interesting bit of information I heard at the Summit.  SOE will release a new audio queue system added to test soon and to live soon after.  This audio system lets players assign audio clips to chat window events.  For example, if I receive a tell, I can get a little chime.  However, this system is far more flexible than simple tell chimes.  Players can base audio samples to any string of text displayed in any chat window.  For example, if one receives a tell from his or her guild leader, he or she will hear a different chime.  If a particular item comes up in the auction channel that one has been waiting for he or she can hear a cash register.  If a cleric's turn comes up in the CH rotation, the cleric can hear a bell ring.</p>

<p>The sound system will be completely skinnable with new sounds and allows you to assign these sounds to any string of text that comes up in any of your chat boxes.  Add a big boom to critical blasts or hear a warning bell when a Conviction fades.</p>

<p>The ten million dollar "Loral's Evil Agenda - Submit To It" campaign worked quite well.  I saw copies of the evil agenda floating all over the place.  At one surrealistic moment, someone folded one into a paper airplane, threw it across a resteraunt, and nearly put out the eye of an unsuspecting Moorgard, the first and most excellent Mobhunter writer, a couple of tables away.  What a strange chain of events that would have been.</p>

<p>For each Evil Agenda burned in the hotel fire pits, I saw another read by developers during some infrequent downtime.</p>

<p>This was a difficult time for a Summit.  The Everquest developers currently spend their time fixing issues that come up in Depths of Darkhollow.  The expansion is too new to say for sure what SOE needs to fix, although we certainly had suggestions.  It is too early to say whether monster missions will remain popular although I suspect they will as long as SOE releases new ones.  It is far too early for SOE to say anything about any future expansion.</p>

<p>However, this summit stood as a perfect point for developers and summit attendees to step back and look at the whole game.  Discussions on the death penalty, mid-level content, LDON point costs, and reducing downtime are all important to the health of this game.  The benefit, however, comes not when we talk but when we begin to see SOE implement changes based on this feedback.  Sometimes these changes take a while, but we have seen some of the best changes to Everquest within the last year and I see no sign of that slowing down.</p>

<p>I have met the SOE developers a few times in the past at fan faires and community summits.  It never ceases to amaze me how hard they work and how enthusiastic they are about their game.  These are not 9 to 5 employees.  They work all the time.  They put in ten to twelve hour days every day of the week.  They know their product very well.  Some of them are no doubt stubborn but they believe in what they do.  They rarely cave under the pressure of biased criticism and if you want to convince them, you have to bring both data and show them how a change helps the entire game. These developers love their game.</p>

<p>It was especially a pleasure to meet the other community reps again and I will leave you with a variety of other summit reports and pictures:</p>

<p><a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=11491">EQ Vault: Report 1</a><br />
<a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=11494">EQ Vault: Report 2</a><br />
<a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=11495">EQ Vault: Report 3</a><br />
<a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=11511">EQ Vault: Final report</a><br />
<a href="http://www.eqclerics.org/forums/showthread.php?t=20678">Boanerges's Report</a><br />
<a href="http://crucible.samanna.net/viewtopic.php?t=908">Samanna's Report</a><br />
<a href="http://applets.crgaming.com/images/DDR2-vi.jpg">Pic</a>. (left to right) Gemdiver of Caster's Realm, me, and Rashere the lead designer watching Merloc and Glorianna play Dance Dance</a>.<br />
<a href="http://www.eqinterface.com/Summit05/">Nolrog's Tons o' Pics</a>.<br />
<a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/1068040/">Nolrog's Pics in a Flickr Set</a></p>

<p>I will link more reports as I receive them.  Please send a comment if you find one I haven't linked yet.</p>

<p>I thank SOE for the opportunity and the excellent event.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 October 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda, September 2005</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001420.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-09-24T09:24:14-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1420</id>
    <created>2005-09-24T14:24:14Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">With the recent release of Depths of Darkhollow and a new Everquest community summit coming up this week, now is the perfect time for Loral to once again outline his evil plans.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>With the announcement of SOE's latest Everquest Community Summit it was time once again to sit back and ponder the best possible future direction for Everquest.  Previous evil agenda covered everything from encounter variety to mentor systems and many of these items are now addressed.  With the latest expansion released only two weeks ago, it becomes difficult to say for sure where the future should head.</p>

<p>We begin this Evil Agenda start with four larger areas for improvement and then include a list of a few smaller areas or areas already discussed previously (often at great length).  Let us begin.</p>

<h2>1. Further Improve Monster Missions.</h2>

<p>Monster missions added a whole new gamestyle to this six year old game and it has become a favored style of play for many since its release.  Add 18 and 24 person monster raids to give any group of 18 to 24 players a chance to try out the raid style so popular with many higher level players.  Offer missions for groups with three players.  Continue to use monster missions as a way to experience lore by tying them to old moments in Norrath history.</p>

<h2>2.  Continue to Tie Future Expansions to Old World Lore.</h2>

<p>Many nostalgic players talk about the great days of Kunark and Velious.  By making these two older expansions part of the core base of the game, SOE can then base instanced dungeons, monster missions, and even entire expansions off of these older lands.  Many players now off in other lands may return if they see "Everquest: Ruins of Kunark II" on the shelf.</p>

<h2>3.  Improve the Dynamics of Combat.</h2>

<p>New AAs like Gift of Mana show a new style of combat where random elements can change player behavior during combat.  This leads to new and unique battles instead of typical "Step 1: complete heal, step 2: see step 1".  Consider the heroic opportunities from EQ2.  Work on encounters that increase difficulty without simply upping the creature's damage.</p>

<h2>4.  Improve the 20 to 50 Game.</h2>

<p>These past six months we have seen a new tutorial, new 10 to 20 missions, and two rebuilt newbie zones.  New 20 to 50 missions and tasks will help players grow from these new additions to the later content found in Omens of War, Dragons of Norrath, and Depths of Darkhollow.  New mid-level missions, more quests, new armor quests, or even an "epic-lite" quest would greatly improve the 20 to 50 game.</p>

<p>With those four major Evil Agenda points behind us, lets look at a few additional changes that would continue to improve the game:</p>

<ul>

<p>    <li>Continue to tune spirit shrouds to ensure usefulness above level 55.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Find solutions to the limitations of the global model file.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Rebuild Plane of Knowledge to reduce lag, add features, and improve cultural bonding (like "Halastown").</li></p>

<p>    <li>Add an sound effect as an option when receiving a tell.</li></p>

<p><li>Find a way to make new player models a possibility.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Add a separate con color for mobs within five levels of the player.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Improve the point-rewards for LDON gear from 20 to 65 to make LDON viable for gear progression again.</li></p>

<p>    <li>Make "/" work for cross server and cross game tells instead of ";" and "[".</li></p>

<p>    <li>Further consolidate and simplify the user interface. Combine like windows.</li><br />
</ul></p>

<p>I look forward to the future of Everquest.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
24 September 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Onward into the Depths</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001419.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-09-20T13:07:59-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1419</id>
    <created>2005-09-20T18:07:59Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we look at some of the initial issues of Depths of Darkhollow and begin to prepare for a new EQ community summit.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last Tuesday we found ourselves falling into the Depths of Darkhollow and seeing Everquest in an entirely new light.  The message forums exploded with new information and strange new lingo.  A lot of excited posts talked about the new monster missions and began decoding some of the longer quests.</p>

<p>Within all of this, SOE announced a new Community Summit focused on EQ in the Past, Present, and Future.  I think that means "we want to talk about big issues and not get bogged down with class problems right now".</p>

<p>So here is the plan for the next couple of weeks.  I planned to give Depths about two or three weeks before writing up a "Potholes of Depths of Darkhollow" article outlining some of the problems faced in this expansion but the new EQ Community Summit popped up and I have to write an Evil Agenda for that.</p>

<p>So this weekend I will publish a "Loral's Evil Agenda, September 2005" article.  A week after that I will write up the results of the summit article and a week later I will write up the Potholes of Depths article.</p>

<p>The response to the new expansion has been generally positive.  People seem to really like the monster missions and after the dozen of them I've done, I am still really excited about it as a new style of play.  Future monster missions and some added features will no doubt make its way into this month's evil agenda.</p>

<p>One thing I found interesting about the monster missions is that the rewards received are pretty good at level 70, somewhere around Wall of Slaughter and Muramite Provingground level.  These monster missions may be a good way for underequipped level 70 players to gear up to at least a 120 hp / mana baseline.</p>

<p>Depths departs from the mission center hub that we saw in Dragons of Norrath and that makes mission progression a bit more difficult to understand, discover, and conquer.</p>

<p>Each of the five main hunting zones; Corathus, Undershore, Stoneroot, Hive, and Illsalin; are of a set difficulty.  The missions off of these zones are slightly harder than the difficutly of the hub zone.  So Corathus missions should be easier than Ilislan missions.</p>

<p>The Mission NPCs, however, can be anywhere.  So Hive missions are acquired in Corathus, while Illsalin missions are acquired in Undershore.  Even more difficult is the ease with which players find Illsalin missions compared to the elusive Corathus Creep missions.  One hopes that SOE can make the easier missions as easy to find as the harder missions.</p>

<p>My friends Gemdiver and Nanyea of Caster's Realm released an excellent <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9584">Depths of Darkhollow Mission System</a> that captures much of the known Depths missions and plans to include even more as they get more information.</p>

<p>Difficulty compared to the rewards received is a large topic right now. Personally I found the Illsalin missions to be very difficult even on "normal" and from what I heard, the loot rewards were low considering the power required to defeat it.  This seems to be a common problem even for the "hard" missions.  A lot of other players with whom I often debate on equipment gap issues agree that these missions should be dropping loot more on par with MPG trials and Qvic armor instead of low elemental quality.  Hopefully we will see greater equipment rewards and lowered difficulties for "normal" missions.</p>

<p>Shroud progression came up as a problem as well.  Players report having to kill up to two thousand NPCs to acquire the next shroud.  Progression this slow is far more frustrating than it is rewarding so hopefully we will see this improved as well.</p>

<p>Other players have the opposite problem with some of the monster missions.  Monster missions such as "Shadowmane Invasion", an excellent battle between two rival werewolf tribes, offer a far greater reward than most traditional hunting zones. In some cases players earned 2.5 AAs for about 20 minutes of work.  Already I was beginning to get flashbacks to the dark days of constant Creator missions when I heard "this mission offers twice the reward, why would we do anything else?".  No doubt a nerf is already in progress.  I didn't buy this game to play one mission over and over. Each mission should offer an equal reward compared to the risk and effort.</p>

<p>Monster missions revealed another problem as well.  Since players of any level can group together for a monster mission, the loot scales itself based on the level of your main character.  However, one cannot learn what the actual power of that gear will be until one already loots it and leaves the mission.  A quick change added the highest power of the rewarded item to that artifact's description so at least level 70 people know what they will receive, but it is still unclear to lower level players what they might win.</p>

<p>An ugly bug poked out its head with missions in general.  Players who either zoned or went linkdead during the success of a mission found themselves unrewarded for the mission and locked out with a 56 day lockout timer.  This problem seems common and the developers have already acknowledged it and are working on a solution.   Hopefully this gets fixed soon.</p>

<p>I offer the following list of recommendations to SOE for initial improvement to Depths of Darkhollow:</p>

<p>- Lower the difficulty of the "normal" missions so pre-RS level 70 hunters can accomplish them.</p>

<p>- Fix the 56 day lockout bug.</p>

<p>- Continually monitor and ensure that mission rewards meet an appropriate balance.  We don't want another creator.</p>

<p>- Offer appropriate rewards for the difficulty on normal missions. Gear rewards should be better than the gear required to defeat a mission.</p>

<p>- Make it easier to find Corathus Creep missions.  Easier missions should be easier to find.</p>

<p>- Lower the requirements for shroud progression.</p>

<p>This weekend I will write up my fifth Evil Agenda to outline possible large-scale improvements to Everquest.  This time, however, I am at a bit of a loss to come up with critical improvements to the game that haven't been answered in the past.</p>

<p>So this is your chance.  If you have a large issue that you think needs to be handed to the developers, either send me a note or post your idea here.  I will not take every request and you must convince me that this request is a game-wide issue not already addressed.  Class issues are, of course, not going to be addressed here; seek your class representative to champion your cause.</p>

<p>Good hunting.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
20 September 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Depths of Darkhollow: In-depth Preview</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001416.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-09-09T20:04:22-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1416</id>
    <created>2005-09-10T01:04:22Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">With the release of Depths of Darkhollow early next week and a release of the beta non-disclosure agreement, Loral now brings you an in-depth preview of Depths of Darkhollow.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Nearly a year has passed since the release of Worlds of Warcraft and Everquest 2.  With such fierce competition, many worried that Everquest was finally on the downward spiral.  We worried that these new games would have features and functions impossible in a game like Everquest and that the EQ development team would be hard pressed to add anything unique or interesting to Everquest that hadn't been done before.</p>

<p>We should not have worried.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow is Sony Online Entertainment's tenth Everquest expansion in six years.  It is, by far, the most bold and innovative expansion ever released.  While other games struggle to keep up with features like LDON adventures and the Mission System, Depths of Darkhollow adds unique, useful, and fun features never seen in any other massive online game.</p>

<p>Since the difficult release and lackluster response of Gates of Discord, SOE has improved Everquest with every expansion.  Every expansion improved upon the strengths of the previous and Depths of Darkhollow appears no different.</p>

<p>One would assume that a tenth expansion in any game would have difficulty improving upon the original game and nine previous expansions, but Depths of Darkhollow shows once again how far this six year old game can go.</p>

<p>Let's dig in.  We start with the basic content found in most expansions and end this preview by looking at the more radical features: spirit shrouds, monster missions, and evolving items.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow includes six new large static zones including The Undershore, Stoneroot Falls, The Ruins of Illsalin, Corathus Creep, The Hive, Dreadspire Keep.  The release of Depths of Darkhollow also included a rebuilt Nektulos forest for all EQ players including those not purchasing the expansion.  These zones scale from level 45 to level 70 with three zones tuned for level 68 to 70 hunters.  Dreadspire Keep should give a good challenge to those bored of Riftseekers.</p>

<p>These static zones include a wide range of design from huge statues and torch-lit tent cities to huge suspended stone bridges crisscrossing huge chasms.  The EQ artists found an excellent balance between the hyperrealism of Everquest 2 and the epic, but cartoony feel of World of Warcraft.  The design and architecture of Depths includes a lot of detail without sacrificing the feeling of epic fantasy.</p>

<p>Dreadspire Keep, the end-zone of Depths of Darkhollow, is not locked by a raid like the end-zones in most previous expansions but instead by a single group event.  Dreadspire is an entirely different style of zone, one of such strangeness that it must be seen and heard to be believed.  You will travel through the depths of shadowy hell only to find yourself walking into the set for Masterpiece Theater with a pale-skinned butler handing you a warm glass of brandy.</p>

<p>Since Lost Dungeons of Norrath, every Everquest expansion has included instanced single group hunting areas.  Dragons of Norrath included the Mission system and Depths further capitalizes on Missions by adding over forty single group missions from level 55 to 70.  Depths of Darkhollow changes the path towards mission progression from the ways of Dragons.</p>

<p>Depths mission progression consists of a set of missions in each of the static zones.  You are rewarded for each mission accomplished and again when you complete a set of missions in each of the zones.  There will be random rewards for those who do a mission more than once, but unlike Dragons, you will be rewarded for completing a variety of different missions rather than completing the same mission over and over.</p>

<p>Here is an example. You and your ragged band of adventurers meets an important figure in the Depths of Darkhollow who sends you on a mission.  You go on the mission, fight a big horrible creature and its minions.  When the boss is defeated, your group is rewarded with a dropped item you may divvy up as you choose.  If this is the first time you or any of the others have done this particular mission, you will receive a one-time reward that may be a piece of gear or some other tasty treasure.  Future battles against this mission will still drop a piece of gear off of the boss, but future one-time rewards must be received from different dungeons you have not yet defeated.</p>

<p>One important note and change that may frustrate some players.  Mission entrances are sometimes very deep in hostile zones.  Getting TO a mission can become as difficult as the mission itself.  These missions are tuned to include the time it takes to arrive as well as the time it takes to complete so they shouldn't become much longer to complete than missions in previous expansions.  It can be frustrating, however, to accept a mission and not actually begin it until after an hour of traveling.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow also includes some single group events (I heard them referred to as single group raids, a term that made my head spin but my heart soar) that are triggered by a group but take place in open zones.  These are a mixture of instanced missions and regular overland killing but the idea is unique.  This fits well with my previous request for more interesting single group content than static hunting and boring boss monsters.</p>

<p>Many Anguish-level raiders found the high-end raids in Dragons of Norrath to be too easy and not rewarding enough to hold their interest.  Once Overlord Mata Muram was defeated in the Citadel of Anguish more than a few times, these raiders had little to do.  Depths attempts to pacify and perhaps humble these high-end raiders.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow includes two dozen events and raids ranging from 24 person elemental level events to 54 person Anguish and post-Anguish level raids. Anguish raiders can expect over a dozen 54 person high-end raids.  This will hopefully give high-end raiders more than enough challenge and also offer further parallel progression paths for lower-end raiders to reach more powerful challenges and greater rewards.</p>

<p>While not a level-cap increasing expansion, Depths offers a bit of character progression.  Depths includes about a dozen new AAs for each character class for a total of perhaps 200 points of further AA progression.  Depths includes one new discipline for melee and even a new discipline for hybrids, something they have requested for some time.</p>

<p>Spell casters will see two or three new spells for each caster class in the level 65 to 70 range.  New forms of spell research will allow players to research previously dropped spells from older expansions including the elusive 69 and 70 runes from Omens of War.  The exact details of this research is still unknown but acquiring these spells should be less frustrating than in the past.  [Update 9/12/2005: I found out today that these researched spells will only be up to level 65, not up to 70, however my understanding is that there will be greater access to Omens 69 and 70 spells within Depths of Darkhollow.]</p>

<p>Now we will look at some of the unique features of this expansion.</p>

<p>One of the greatest challenges and frustrations of a massive online game comes when two friends both play the same game but one quickly outstrips the other due to longer play times.  Soon these two friends, who used to hunt together often, cannot hunt together at all due to such a wide level range.  A <a href="http://www.penny-arcade.com/view.php?date=2004-12-31&res=l">Penny Arcade parody of Worlds of Warcraft</a> covers it well.</p>

<p>Other games have found ways to solve this problem.  City of Heroes included the sidekick system that raised the level of one player to meet the other.  Everquest 2 included the Mentor system that let one player lower his or her level to that of a friend.  Everquest added a big twist on this mentor system with Spirit Shrouds.</p>

<p>Spirit shrouds allow players to polymorph into a monster of their level or below in increments of 5.  These monsters are broken up into archetypes called "templates".  Each template includes a set of skills that meet a typical character archetype such as melee, spellcaster, healer, utility, or tank.  There are eight sets of spirit shrouds with over twenty different monster models and over thirty different shrouds total.</p>

<p>My good friend Nanyea wrote a <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9515">detailed look at spirit shrouds</a> and I recently wrote an <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9550">instructional guide to spirit shrouds</a>.  I also wrote a previous article called <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=9103">What Will Play as a Monster Mean for EQ</a> feature.</p>

<p>The primary purpose for spirit shrouds is to allow higher level players an opportunity to effectively hunt with lower level friends.  It meets this job very well. Shrouds also let players try out templates vastly different from their own. If you spent most of your time playing a pasty cleric, you can now try out playing as a melee, spellcaster, or tank.</p>

<p>At higher levels, shrouded monsters become less powerful than characters of the same level.  Much of this is based on the large equipment and Alternate Advancement power increases at higher levels.  Shrouds should allow players to switch to a needed archetype if a group is missing one core member, but they will not be able to hunt in the most powerful areas.  A group of three primary characters and three shrouded characters should to be able to hunt in places like Wall of Slaughter and the lower Dragon missions.</p>

<p>However, if a group cannot find one core class for a hunt, they might consider monster missions instead.</p>

<p>When I first heard about Depths of Darkhollow I was most excited about spirit shrouds.  After my first Nagafen monster mission, I changed my mind.</p>

<p>Monster Missions are the best feature of Depths of Darkhollow.  Monster missions let any group of four to six players of any level and any class face a challenge as monsters in an instanced scenario.  Monster missions open the door to entire new possibilities for challenging encounters.  They are self-contained events under perfectly controlled environments and power levels.  They are easily balanced and not affected by any outside influence.  They are the most fun I've had in EQ in a long time.</p>

<p>There are twenty such monster missions in Depths of Darkhollow.  About half of these are in the depths itself while ten go back to old world zones to let players face some old world challenges.  Imagine invading Freeport as a band of pirates.  Imagine fighting off the undead hoards as froglok paladins in lower guk.  Imagine breathing waves of fire upon sniveling raiders who invade in an attempt to steal your Cloak of Flames.  The possibilities are endless.  My only hope is that we continue to see new monster missions added in the future.</p>

<p>Depths offers a new form of equipment known as "evolving items".  These items grow in power the more you use them.  They may start off as weaker pieces of equipment but the more you use them, the stronger they get.  There are several dozen such items in Depths of Darkhollow.  Intelligent items are a rare subset of these.  These items will actually communicate to the player through emotes and possibly tells.  Though these items will be quite rare and unique, they will be available to single group hunters as well as high-end raiders.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow is the first expansion to offer a box prize so useful that I will suffer the traffic of Washington DC to buy my copy retail rather than download it from SOE directly.  Those who purchase the retail version of Depths of Darkhollow will receive an in-game clockwork boar mount.  This mount is comparable to the 10k plat horse and drogmar mounts but with a unique model and look.  Rewards like these offer an incentive to retail outlets to carry this expansion and it is these boxes on the shelf that bring new players to Everquest.  Unfortunately, poor retail systems between the US and other countries make it nearly impossible for non-US players to receive such a reward.</p>

<p>Depths of Darkhollow shows how far Everquest can evolve.  While many questioned how long a game like EQ can survive, we only have to look at the ingenuity in expansions such as this one to see how far Everquest can continue to go.  Depths of Darkhollow offers all of the strongest features of a good solid expansion along with two of the most radical concepts I have seen in any roleplaying game.  Considering the hours and hours of content this expansion contains, it is easily worth the $30 price tag.  While time will tell for sure, Depths has all of the signs to be the best Everquest expansion ever released.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
9 September 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>

</feed>