<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- generator="FeedCreator 1.7.2" -->
<rss version="0.91">
    <channel>
        <title>Powered by Mambo 4.5.2</title>
        <description>Mambo site syndication</description>
        <link>http://www.illuminationguild.com/Mambo</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 May 2006 17:29:22 +0100</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>FeedCreator 1.7.2</generator>
        <image>
            <url>http://www.illuminationguild.com/Mambo/images/M_images/mambo_rss.png</url>
            <title>Powered by Mambo 4.5.2</title>
            <link>http://www.illuminationguild.com/Mambo</link>
            <description>Mambo site syndication</description>
        </image>
        <item>
            <title>The History of Ainmer the Bixie</title>
            <link>http://www.illuminationguild.com/Mambo/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=55&amp;Itemid=2</link>
            <description>WARNING: AINMER ALERT 




It&amp;rsquo;s common knowledge that one of the secrets
behind Enlightenment&amp;rsquo;s success is our use of Teamspeak as a raid tool.
While it can be disruptive at times &amp;ndash; for the majority of the time it&amp;rsquo;s
effectiveness is, by far, a major asset, especially when one considers
the times we simply did not &amp;ldquo;have the numbers&amp;rdquo; to pull an encounter
off, but did so regardless.</description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Mission: Roley</title>
            <link>http://www.illuminationguild.com/Mambo/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=54&amp;Itemid=2</link>
            <description>  In 2006, an Enlightenment kill-squad unit was sent to prison by a Militia court for a crime they didn't commit. These men and woman promptly escaped from a maximum-security Freeport prison to the Antonican underground. Today, still wanted by the Militia, they survive as soldiers of fortune. If you have a problem, if no one else can help, and if you can find them, maybe you can hire the A-Team. </description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Redfang = Deadfang</title>
            <link>http://www.illuminationguild.com/Mambo/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=53&amp;Itemid=2</link>
            <description>(There will be definitely more to come in the next day or so as my
creative juices get flowing - but I wanted to get this update at least
started to get our monks off my back.  So.. for you monk team -
here you go!)





</description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>We ain't scared of no ghosts!</title>
            <link>http://www.illuminationguild.com/Mambo/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=52&amp;Itemid=2</link>
            <description>The last few weeks have seemed such a whirlwind - so this morning I sat
down and actually began to reflect on them.  I'm sure those of you
who visit our sight are well aware of where we've come from and how
we've progressed over the last ten months or so.  Never in all my
dreams back then of where this guild would go did I expect to be where
I was last night - on the cutting edge of content.  And what fun
it is.


</description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Tower of Sullon Zek!</title>
            <link>http://www.illuminationguild.com/Mambo/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=51&amp;Itemid=2</link>
            <description>That's right, folks.  Look what we did!

This update is short and sweet on the worlds and displays a few pictures of this zone 
we've stumbled across.  Huge, huge kudo's to my guildmates for all their work figuring out
and deciphering clues.  What a great accomplishment guys!
</description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
