<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Mobhunter</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/" />
  <modified>2006-06-14T03:56:00Z</modified>
  <tagline></tagline>
  <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7</id>
  <generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="3.01D">Movable Type</generator>
  <copyright>Copyright (c) 2006, Loral</copyright>
  <entry>
    <title>A Moss Snake Kicks You for 4 ^H^H^H^H^H</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001480.html" />
    <modified>2006-06-14T03:56:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-06-13T22:37:30-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1480</id>
    <created>2006-06-14T03:37:30Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we look at the most recent patch of Everquest, pontificate more on the Combine server, and mourn the loss of Everquest&apos;s greatest bug.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Much of the Everquest community's attention still lies on the Progression Server, now named "The Combine". SOE currently plans to release this server at the end of June. A lot of players are returning to the long forgotten lands of Norrath to remember the first days adventurers walked the lands. Whether or not they stay is a question yet answered.</p>

<p>Today brings the release of the largest patch since the release of Prophecy of Ro. While it contained few of the much needed content changes to Prophecy of Ro, it did contain a plethora of feature fixes.</p>

<p>Two improvements in particular may seem mundane to experienced players but do much to make Everquest a more accessible game for new players.  Players can now see group members on the in-game map, helping them locate their fellows when they get lost. I can't even fathom the amount of time I would earn back if this feature had been implemented six years ago. The next feature is the inclusion of the Guild Lobby into the core game. The ability for players to summon their body regardless of whether they purchased Dragons of Norrath is a huge improvement for lower and mid-level players who have neither the tools nor the experience to find corpses lost in the less forgiving pits of the older worlds. </p>

<p>These two improvements help bring Everquest closer to the industry standards for massive online role playing games. While many may shout, stamp their feet, and wave their fists saying that it is just the further "dumbing down" of Everquest - we will see how long they play on the Combine server suffering through eight hour corpse runs in Fear or sixteen-zone runs to get back their bronze armor. Long behind me are the days of horrifying corpse recovery - recovery that directly adversely affected my real life - and good riddance.</p>

<p>This patch also included the implementation of a new chat service back-end. While advertised as "transparent to the user", the service did have a few bugs.  Using a semicolon to send a cross-server tell no longer works and chatting in channels from EQIM also no longer works. No doubt this change helped SOE consolidate resources, but it would have been nice to ensure a truly transparent shift before implementation.</p>

<p>SOE modified experience gain for evolving items, intelligent items, and shrouds. In all three cases, experience gain has improved and now follows the same modifiers that regular experience follows when grouping. As players join others in groups, each player earns a higher percentage of experience than they would alone. Now experience earned by items and when transformed through shrouds includes the same bonuses.</p>

<p>Along with this change, SOE increased the amount of required experience for the single most popular evolving item, the cloak of the spirit tracker. This increase in total experience gain means that players who may have been 40% into the item's progression are now down to 10%. This change may be off-set by the overall increase in item experience, but again, only time will tell if the balance was met.</p>

<p>Today, SOE released one of the long awaited changes to the Everquest death system. Along with the full release of the guild lobby to all players, players will now begin losing experience and leaving equipped corpses starting at level 6. A corpse summoner in the tutorial will teach players how to recover their body using the summoners. While this doesn't meet the ideal circumstance of returning to a bind point fully equipped on death, it does help show players how to handle the death system in Everquest when they might be used to the systems in newer games.</p>

<p>This patch also released a new and much improved Nektulos forest. The previous version of Nektulos, released with the release of Depths of Darkhollow, often received complaints that it broke the realism of a forest. Instead of individual trees, that version had large single-sided objects painted with the texture of trees. This gave it the feel of a movie-set instead of a forest. The new Nektulos matches much of the layout of the original Nektulos but with a much improved look.</p>

<p>In the greatest retroactive nerf to the original Everquest legacy, no longer will moss-snakes kick. All animals not able to actually kick can no longer do so. While this change makes sense, it seems to be an extreme change to a piece of long lasting Everquest mythology. The elusive kicking moss snake will be forever missed.</p>

<p>Times are quiet in the lands of Norrath. The high-end raiders seek the beasts at the end of Deathknell and the treasures they hold. Others look to the history captured in the Combine. For those of us in between, we stare across the voids left in Ro's Prophecy and think to the days of adventure long past and far into the future.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
13 June 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Dangers of Progression, The Serpent&apos;s Spine, SOE&apos;s Vanguard</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001478.html" />
    <modified>2006-06-14T03:49:57Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-05-16T21:46:34-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1478</id>
    <created>2006-05-17T02:46:34Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week Loral takes a look at the news surrounding the Progression server, the rumored name of the next expansion, and SOE&apos;s co-publication of Vanguard.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The Antonican bards lean against their trees, leather bags empty. Little news from the lands of Norrath crosses the desks of the fifty gnomish editors of Mobhunter, so we focus this article on what little news we hear.</p>

<h2>The Progression Server</h2>

<p>Many players paid much attention to the Progression server, coming in June. SOE sent out a press release containing previously reported details and announcing a release in June 2006. The server will be named "The Combine".</p>

<p>I worry that both players and Everquest developers place too much anticipation on the progression server. We still do not know how popular the server will be when players realize the tedium involved in things such as travel and corpse recovery. While many players complained about the Knowledge stones and feel the corpse altar removed the thrill of danger in EQ, we do not know if these same players will actually play instead of talk about it on the forums.</p>

<p>I for one still remember the tedium involved with long-term travel. I remember how awful corpse recovery was from failed Vox raids. I remember camping to chat and buffing each member of a raid at a time. I remember dying in some unknown area at a low level and having no idea how I would recover my equipment. I don't want to return to those days.</p>

<p>I wrote an article for Caster's Realm late last year called "<a href="http://loralciriclight.com/001450.html">Why a Classic Server is a Bad Idea</a>" and I feel that many of the points are still valid.</p>

<p>SOE has spent six years coming out with improvements to Everquest. While not every improvement has been positive, many of those that were will be locked on the progressive server. All of those positive features, all of those improvements, will not be available for some time.</p>

<p>Time will tell whether the progression server is popular or not. I will keep a keen eye on it and, for the effort spent developing it, I hope it succeeds in its goal to draw more players back to EQ.</p>

<h2>The Serpent's Spine</h2>

<p>Rumors on the EQ Live forums and some investigative work by those with far too much time on their hands, has revealed the likely title for the next expansion: The Serpent's Spine. No other new information has been revealed except that SOE designers stated that while level 80 is not entirely out of the question, it is much more likely to increase the level range to 75. Given the difficulty in creating new items, disciplines, spells, and AAs at each level, and the great amount of new content discussed in the new expansion, we are very likely to see the cap at level 75, not higher.</p>

<h2>Vanguard co-published by Sony Online Entertainment</h2>

<p>In surprising news and resulting in a great gnashing of many sets of cynical teeth, SOE and Sigil Games Online announced that the two companies would co-produce Brad McQuaid's Vanguard: Saga of Heroes massive online role playing game.</p>

<p>While this stirred up great controversy, the outcome is likely not nearly as exciting.</p>

<p>Since Everquest, Sony Online Entertainment has acted as a sort of service provider for other massive online games. By consolidating resources such as technical support centers, data centers, backup and recovery, network connectivity, and in-game support, SOE can support a wider range of games much cheaper than any single company could on its own. We saw this recently with Matrix Online, added to SOE's extensive collection of MMOs including Everquest Online Adventures, Everquest 2, and Planetside.</p>

<p>Moving Vanguard to SOE makes sense if any game hopes to have any longevity. By running many games off of the same resources, SOE can afford to keep games alive much longer than a company producing only a single game. Expect to see more massive online games falling to one or two MMO service provider companies.</p>

<p>None of this speaks to any change in the direction of Vanguard or Everquest. The development teams are still separate and exclusive in their focus and direction.</p>

<p>Such ends the news for this period of slow news. Our spies will keep their ears open for any vibrations in Mobhunter's great web of information and pass along any such vibrations to you, our dear readers.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
16 May 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Five Recommended Improvements to Prophecy of Ro</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001477.html" />
    <modified>2006-06-14T03:50:35Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-04-30T18:10:26-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1477</id>
    <created>2006-04-30T23:10:26Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral Ciriclight looks at five ways to improve the latest Everquest expansion, Prophecy of Ro.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The release of Prophecy of Ro is now three months past. Many players focus their attention on the soon-to-come Progression Server. However, while many look to these two interesting glimpses into the future, the Prophecy of Ro lays unfulfilled. </p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro requires improvement. While some areas of this expansion have proved very popular such as Arcstone, the Spirit quests, the relic quests, and the Thurgadin monster missions; these features alone do not justify the cost of the expansion. This article outlines five areas for improvement in Prophecy of Ro.</p>

<p>1. Increase Spirit Mark drops.</p>

<p>The spirit marks, currently dropping only off of named mobs in Arcstone, help non-raiders increase their equipment to reach higher-end content such as the Depths of Darkhollow spell progression missions and the Omens of War Muramite Proving ground trials. Unfortunately, these marks only drop in Arcstone and drop rarely off of rare spawning named beasts. While it would be easy to increase the drop rate, instead SOE should add these drops to named creatures in Elddar, Relic, and Devastation to help bring players to these underused zones.</p>

<p>2. Improve Relic, Devastation, Elddar, and Stronghold of Rage.</p>

<p>Increasing loot rewards is only one factor in improving the usefulness of the Prophecy of Ro static zones. Currently only Arcstone sees a significant number of hunters. Devastation may see occasional groups for the saga skin mission, but with less frequency than Arcstone's spirit hunter missions. All four of these zones need to be improved to make them more huntable and more desirable. Increasing experience rewards, decreasing mob density, increasing random loot rewards, and decreasing mob damage output may help make these zones more desirable to those who purchased Prophecy of Ro.</p>

<p>3. Bridge the required-equipment gap between Dragons of Norrath and the Depths of Darkhollow and Muramite Proving Ground Trials.</p>

<p>There remains a constant wringing of hands and gnashing of teeth when it comes to discussions about the Creator mission in Dragons of Norrath. What these discussions often omit is that players spend a lot of time in content of this style. Creator offers nice rewards for a low investment of time. Rather than complain that creator is too easy, consider that many players want clear, consistent rewards for their time.</p>

<p>4. Scale more content to the level of difficulty and time investment of Creator. </p>

<p>Offer rewards that help single-group-equipped characters improve to the point where they can reasonably face the challenges of high-end spell-progression missions in Depths of Darkhollow, the Skylance missions in Prophecy of Ro, and the Muramite Proving Ground trials in Omens of War. Help bridge the required equipment gap between lower-powered Arcstone and Dragons of Norrath content and the higher-end single group content in Depths of Darkhollow and Prophecy of Ro.</p>

<p>5. Add more Spirit Hunter style missions.</p>

<p>Arcstone added five more "single-group raid" encounters to Everquest along with the Seeker event in Depths of Darkhollow. These events show single-group hunters the style of encounters that high-end raiders have seen for years. These events are fun, challenging, and rewarding. A great many players are able to face them, defeat them, and earn nice rewards for doing so.</p>

<p>Add more events of this nature to Prophecy of Ro. Add a series of legacy creatures to the new Desert of Ro including a Lich to the spectre tower, an ancient ancestor of Lockjaw, an ancient mummy lord, a sand giant lord, and the swashbuckler king of the waterboys. Add in a new quest to reward those willing to face these five new foes.</p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro has the potential to pull players out of instanced single-group content and back into large static zones. As it stands, however, Prophecy of Ro needs improvement in order to match the excellent content found in older expansions such as Depths of Darkhollow and Omens of War. With these five improvements discussed above, Prophecy of Ro could become one of the greatest of Everquest expansions.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
30 April 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Spring 2006 Summit and Fan Faire Final Report</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001474.html" />
    <modified>2006-06-14T03:50:50Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-04-11T21:22:30-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1474</id>
    <created>2006-04-12T02:22:30Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today Loral reviews and organizes all of the news gathered in Atlanta Georgia at the Everquest Spring 2006 Summit and Fan Faire.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>We return from the towers of the south, leatherbound notebooks laden with rumors and gossip. Today we summarize the knowledge captured at the April 2006 Everquest Community Summit and Fan Faire.</p>

<h2>The Twelfth Expansion</h2>

<p>During the first Everquest Summit panel, SOE revealed some details on the yet-unnamed twelfth Everquest expansion.  This expansion will focus on all levels from level 1 to the max level, likely level 75 - a level cap increase over the current level 70. The expansion will attempt to bring new players to the game by offering entire new lines of content and progression from the very first levels all the way through to the end.</p>

<p>The twelfth expansion will include quests and missions for all levels and will mostly focus on large zones over the smaller instanced missions of expansions like Dragons of Norrath and Depths of Darkhollow. With this focus on larger un-instanced zones, there will be more base content than the last few expansions but with no lack of quests. The intent with this focus is to get more players playing together in the same area rather than separating players out into groups of six and isolating them from other groups.</p>

<p>This expansion will include a full copy of the base Everquest game so with this single purchase alone, a player can begin the game at level one and progress all the way to level 75. The intent of the progression in this new expansion is to even allow this player a chance to reach the highest power and most challenging content of high-end raids. All of this resides in a single package.</p>

<p>The new expansion will also include a new starting city, although no details were available.</p>

<p>This expansion will also include new high-end raid content at and above the current high-end raid zones of Deathknell and Demiplane of Blood. Players of all levels will likely have new hunting areas available to them, regardless of their level.</p>

<p>As mentioned, the new expansion will likely increase the level cap to level 75. This will give high-end players a reason to hunt regularly for experience and will also increase the base power level of all high-end players above current level 70 limits. Content once inaccessible except by those in raid gear will become easier as players increase their base power by leveling to 75.</p>

<p>The expansion will also likely include new sets of Alternate Advancement points to further increase a high-level players power. Because of the abundance of high experience rewarding zones and the ease at which AAs can be earned at higher levels, the costs for these new abilities will likely be higher than previous expansions. One can remember the backlash against the high cost of AAs in Gate of Discord, but Norrath was a different place back then and with AAs coming at nearly one every fifteen minutes in instanced hunting zones like the Nest and the Hive, players will have little lack of places to earn them.</p>

<h2>The Progression Server</h2>

<p>For the past few months and even years, some players have asked SOE to return them to the older world of Everquest, a world without the Plane of Knowledge and without instances, a world where the economy wasn't flooded with powerful items for low costs. SOE answered this request with a new upcoming "Progression" server.</p>

<p>This server will begin with all expansions disabled. Only the base game will be active, although any changes to the base game such as zone revamps and class changes will stay in place thus making this a "progression" server and not a "classic" server. As groups of players activate certain triggers, such as killing boss mobs in the old world, each expansion will become unlocked. For example, supposing that Nagafen and Vox are the trigger mobs for opening up Kunark, when groups of players kill these two dragons, Kunark will be unlocked.  When they kill Venril Sather and Trakanon, Velious may become unlocked.</p>

<p>SOE hopes that this server will give players a new starting ground on even territory. No character transfers will be allowed. Players will earn the low-end items earned seven years ago and be forced to defeat encounters with much lower power than currently available on normal Everquest servers with all eleven current expansions.</p>

<p>It is not yet known whether this server will be popular or not. Even the developers within SOE differ as to how this new server should operate. Will players play in a game with limited transportation and long corpse recoveries? Will veteran players ignore their high-powered characters on normal servers for lower powered characters who fight for days to earn lower powered rewards? Only time will tell.</p>

<h2>The Death Penalty</h2>

<p>Currently, players who die leave behind corpses wearing all of the character's gear. Resurrections and corpse recovery vendors in the Guild Lobby can help players recover their equipment, but newer players who do not understand these systems or have access to clerics able to resurrect have a harder time with corpse recovery than high end raiders who simply wait for a resurrection or spend a very small percentage of their money for a corpse summon.</p>

<p>SOE plans to look further into this system and possibly develop a new way to handle death in Everquest. Possible changes include optional respawning with full equipment but leaving behind a naked corpse that must still be resurrected for experience, or waiting on a respawn to let a group or raid member resurrect a player without forcing a zone. Details of a new death system are still unknown but expect more information soon.</p>

<h2>Downtime</h2>

<p>In relation to other current MMOs, Everquest has a large problem with player downtime. Characters who run out of mana or endurance at all levels of the game often have to sit for long periods of time to recuperate. Current games like Everquest 2 and World of Warcraft include a "combat state" system that understands when a player is in or out of combat.</p>

<p>SOE plans to build such a "combat state" system in Everquest. With this system in place, the game could see when a player has left combat and increase that character's regeneration of hitpoints, mana, and endurance to reduce the downtime a player faces when hunting at all levels of play.</p>

<h2>Other Topics</h2>

<p>SOE revealed more news of note and items of interest throughout the four day event. </p>

<p>With Rytan's departure as the spell guru, Prathun, the SOE designer known for designing high-end raid content, will take over spell development.  Oshran, the designer behind Arcstone and the 70 spell missions in Depths of Darkhollow, will focus on new alternate advancement abilities as Rashere focuses on the overall design of Everquest.</p>

<p>Lead programmer Jamey Ryan is working on a dynamic reward system that will help solve the problem of players focusing on only the most rewarding content for experience or shards. As players focus their attention on one particular piece of content, the rewards will lower while the rewards on unused content will increase. This will help push players to try a variety of content rather than focus on only the most rewarding content for the lowest effort.</p>

<p>SOE revealed a new more traditional revamp to Nektulos Forest. Many complained that the existing revamp of Nektulos was too rigid in design, looking more like a movie prop than a forest. The new Nektulos follows the philosophy that a zone revamp should look much like the original. It includes real trees and the same general layout as the original Nektulos zone.</p>

<p>SOE sees the introduction of destructible objects, traps, and auras as the beginning of a more dynamic and interactive world in Everquest. Like the features released in previous expansions, expect to see these features used to create more dynamic and interactive environments, quests, and storylines.</p>

<p>The performance problems found in Elddar forest are due to strange effects of trees. SOE plans to look into these problems and perhaps fix them with a programming change.</p>

<p>Spell Research will likely be further improved to include spells from older expansions such as LDON and Omens of War.</p>

<p>The EQ Players website will likely include many more features. These features include guild roster lists in XML, a better system for guild websites and guild websites for EQ Live, and a new skinnable character page. Other more ambitious efforts were described as well but are likely to come out later as these features require in-game development and further discussions between the EQ Players developers and the EQ Live team.</p>

<p>Throughout the long weekend I sat with many of Everquest's current designers and programmers. They stayed up late and talked openly with their fans about all aspects of the game from large topics such as the new upcoming expansion to small ones such as spell balance between druids and wizards. Once again it was clear how much the SOE development team cares about their game. The Everquest development team continues to make bold and sometimes dangerous moves as it evolves over the years. The mission system, instancing, monster missions, spirit shrouds, the upcoming Progression server, and a new expansion built for players of all levels, all show how far the design team is willing to go to keep this venerable game fresh in the minds of both new and old players.</p>

<p>We have many new adventures ahead of us.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
11 April 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Notes from the Spring 2006 Summit and Fan Faire</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001473.html" />
    <modified>2006-04-29T16:11:49Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-04-06T07:18:30-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1473</id>
    <created>2006-04-06T12:18:30Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Loral begins his living journal with notes from the Everquest Spring 2006 Summit and Fan Faire.  Watch often for frequent updates.  Update: first details of the next expansion, newso on a new &quot;non-classic&quot; classic server, discussions of death and downtime.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>This article will act as my living journal of the Everquest Spring 2006 Community Summit and Fan Faire.  Continue to watch this article throughout the event for recent updates and news.  I will also post new pictures of the event to a Flickr set called <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/72057594100206856/">Everquest   Spring 2006 Summit and Fan Faire Pictures</a>.  I will note when I have taken more picture.</p>

<p>Thursday, 6 April 2006, 7:25am:</p>

<p>It was a long day yesterday. Many of the Summit attendees arrived at 4pm to the Atlanta airport including a handfull of developers. There were a lot of familiar faces and conversations immediately fell to Everquest. The Summit is for both Everquest and Everquest 2 so we had some interesting discussions on the differences between the two games at this particular slice in time. I have let my EQ2 subscription lapse for nearly a year now. There simply isn't time enough for more than two games.</p>

<p>I had a chance to chat with Grumbuk on the shuttle about Everquest and Prophecy of Ro. Grumbuk is the mind behind many of the analytical tools that help catch cheaters including many Macroquest players. Gemdiver mentioned that a pile of characters on Fennin Ro were recently simultaneously banned due to macroquesting.  Grumbuk's eventual goal is to have a system in place that can actively monitor the population for such cheats and act upon these data but at the moment he worries that even a system with 99% accuracy might still ban legitimate characters due to strange bugs so he simply compiles the data and gives it to CS to act upon it.</p>

<p>The Marriott is a beautiful hotel, a 40 story concrete monster with a hollow center.  From the 27th floor, I can look down through the inside of the building but doing so makes me a bit dizzy.  The internet runs a steep $13 a day but I'd pay anything for my dear readers.</p>

<p>After checking in I injected myself into a planned dinner with some of the developers.  I had about five minutes from check in until I had to be back down in the lobby.  A nerd might have run up and had his or her laptop set up within that five minutes, skipping other unnecessary behaviors like brushing teeth or putting on some fresh deodorant.  Only a true renaissance nerd, however, has to load his fountain pen full of ink from a bottle.  Fountain pens don't fly well, you see, so a small canister of black Noodler's permanent fountain pen ink always travels with me along with my three favorite fountain pens: a Pilot Vanishing Point, a Lamy 2000, and the pen of the gods, a massive Pelikan M-1000.  I'll likely only use the Vanishing point but I like having the other two handy.</p>

<p>We spent most of dinner chatting on a variety of topics. Oblivion came up often throughout the night. Many of the developers including Rashere and Zajeer are playing Oblivion on Xbox 360. I have the PC version but the framerate drops so low that it is an exercise in frustration every time I play.  The conversations once again reinforced that the development team are gamers first and foremost. Designing games pays their bills but they also do it because they love it.</p>

<p>I didn't recognize Chris Lena, the Everquest producer, until I heard him speak. I had met him once before but he radically changed his appearance from his <a href="http://images5.theimagehosting.com/clena.JPG">Neil Gaimanesque look</a> to something like the main character in Jarhead. I haven't had a chance yet to sit and pick his brain, but the visit is still young.</p>

<p>I had a great conversation in what I hope is a string of conversations with Kwill of EQ Vault on what it means to be an Everquest journalist.  We shared a few emails and in-game chats about a recent rash of articles bashing professional game journalism as strictly fluff pieces with inflated ratings. Having been often accused of the same thing, it brings up many questions on our roles and responsibilities as  non-professional game journalists (a snobby term, indeed). I could write a whole article about it but I don't know that there is much interest so I will save it for now.</p>

<p>Breakfast is at 9am with a full day of discussions planned including "Session 1: Growing the Game - Making EverQuest attractive to new players and still remain appealing to current players" in the morning and "Session 2: Prophecy of Ro - A look at the last expansion; what went right, what went wrong, and what we can learn from it.".  I have a lot of material to discuss at both meetings. The <a href="http://mobhunter.com/001468.html">Evil Agenda</a> should fit nicely into the first discussion and my recent <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=10449">Successes and Failures of Prophecy of Ro</a> article on Caster's Realm should fit the latter.</p>

<p>I will take copious notes and pictures and will post throughout the day.</p>

<p>Thursday, 6 April 2006, 5:15pm:</p>

<h2>New Expansion Details, New "Progression" server opening.</h2>

<p>Wow, do I have some interesting news.  I droned on a lot this morning so I'll cut into some of the more interesting stuff right away.</p>

<p>There will soon be a "not a classic server" server.  This server will begin with only the original game unlocked at first.  As groups or guilds defeat certain triggered encounters, new expansions will become unlocked. It will be a no-transfer server so everyone is starting off at the beginning of the game. All the new non-expansion features will be there like chat channels, LFG, and new UIs, but features such as Plane of Knowledge won't be active until that expansion is unlocked.  All of those who have screamed on the forums for months about a "classic server" will now get their chance to put their money where their mouth is. It sounds pretty interesting and SOE is expecting it to be popular. With some core features removed that we take for granted these days like the Guild Lobby, Nexus, Knowledge, Bazaar, and LDON Magi, it will be interesting to see how much old-world people are willing to take.</p>

<p>Second, SOE threw out some hints at the next expansion.  The expansion will be a full level-range expansion from level 1 to 70.  They intend to build a new focused set of content for players of all levels and plan to sell the expansion as a stand-alone game as well as an expansion for us old-time players.  There is no word on a price, but I expect it to remain at $30. There will be content of all types including solo content, small group content, six-person group content, instances, quests, and other things that we expect at the high-end.  There will not likely be low level raids since balancing such things and making them worth the effort is hard when gaining five levels will reap much better benefits.  There will be overarching quest lines that will go through a series of levels and even at least one that will go all the way from level 1 to 70. The intent is to make content at those levels that is fun enough that people aren't worried as much about leveling and gearing up to 70 as fast as they can (although I expect we will either see a level increase or a large jump in AAs - likely both).</p>

<p>Rashere mentioned two big areas they will be working on over the next few months: death and downtime.  Various ideas for a new death system were discussed (as they were at the last summit) including choices to respawn with gear, a flat 90% res at all levels rather than lower resses at lower levels which doesn't properly scale since life should be harder at the higher levels than it is at the lower. There was no mention of any sort of death effect but the development team is still interested in making death matter.</p>

<p>Downtime will lead to some sort of combat state system so that the EQ system knows players are out of combat and will up the reneration to compensate. This poses problems when players can leave combat, regen, and enter it again when they weren't intended. It's a complicated issue but SOE plans to focus their attention on it.</p>

<p>There will be a new Nektulos revamp that is much more traditional and less Hollywood-set-like.  This one has real trees and a real forest. It is much more like the desert of Ro revamp in that the layout is much the same as the original layout.  We were able to zoom around it a bit and it looked good.</p>

<p>You learn something every day and today I learned that there is a fellow in the Plane of Knowledge that describes the location for every monster mission. He is apparently available on "find".</p>

<p>With Rytan's recent departure and Rashere no longer working on AAs, two existing developers will now be handling those topics. In strange irony, Prathun will now be the new spell guy. Prathun is very well liked as a high-end raid developer, not to mention being a very easy guy to talk to even though his Street Fighter 2 skills are slightly lacking, so it will be interesting to see how people work with him. Typically spell issues were always hotly debated leading to strong feelings towards the developer in charge. Oshran, the designer of my favorite static zone in POR, Arcstone, will be taking over on AAs. There is no new announcement on a new item guy to take over for Zajeer who is also moving off of items to focus on other content.</p>

<p>Our second session covered Prophecy of Ro, though it quickly fell into other general topics as well.  The discussions started around destructible items and how this, traps, and auras lead to a new way to interact with the environment. Many ideas were thrown around including missions, events, raids, and encounters based on destroying or defending various destructible structures. The development team seems continually interested in focusing on features that work well in future expansions as well as the one introduced such as the mission system, monster missions, and now auras, traps, and destructible items. While destructible items was mainly focused in Devastation, the developers plan to use it elsewhere.</p>

<p>The problems with Elddar were known and the programming team is looking for a way to fix the lag in this zone.</p>

<p>That's the word for now. I will post again later tonight or early tomorrow.  I added a whole new pile of pictures to the <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/72057594100206856/">Everquest Spring 2006 Summit Flickr set</a>.  I will label a few of these as I remember the names.</p>

<p>Thursday, 6 April 2006, 9:58pm:</p>

<p>We just got back from dinner. I spent much of it grilling a very responsive and patient Chris Lena on all things from the  raid / single-group equipment gap to a word-by-word analysis of his quotes on the dev chat a few weeks ago. I did glean a few pieces of info, however.</p>

<p>The new yet-unnamed expansion will likely continue the same release schedule so I expect to hear more official details in a month.  The release itself will likely be September.</p>

<p>Feedback on POR has been quiet. Based on the discussions today, there aren't any glaring overall problems like there were with Gates or Depths of Darkhollow. There isn't a big content-changing patch expected anytime soon.  I would argue that the problems brought up in my Prophecy report still needed to be addressed but as players grow in power, more of that content previously locked by difficulties will become more available.  There's nothing like a level increase to increase overall player power.</p>

<p>SOE currently has no plans to rebuild a Plane of Knowledge and other than a secretly whispered special project of which SOE cannot comment, there are no plans for new player models.  SOE did create a new terrain editor that helps with the rebuilding of old zones which was used for the new desert of Ro and the upcoming Nektulos 3.0.</p>

<p>I was corrected on my terminology for the new non-classic classic server which is known, officially, as a "Progression" server.  SOE doesn't have exact details on what will open up new expansions, but the mechanics of the unlocking will basically be like unlocking the expansions as if you paid for them. If you are a player who only owns the original game, much of the newer content is cut off. The Progression Server simply treats every player as though they didn't play. Certain free features like POK will still have to be shut off manually. </p>

<p>The exact methods to unlock new expansions is not yet known, but the intention is for more than a single group or guild to do it. The mind quickly falls back to Nagafen raids with individual buffs and camping to chat.  For players who do not desire such challenges, expansions will unlock as groups unlock them just as though a new expansion was released.  There is a lot of interesting potential, though whether players can really live through the old style again remains to be seen.</p>

<p>More news tomorrow, I'm off to bed.</p>

<p>Friday, 7 April 2006, 8:27am:</p>

<p>My friend Boanerges over at EQClerics posted <a href="http://eqclerics.org/forums/showthread.php?t=20920">his notes from yesterday's Summit meetings</a>.  He had a lot of good info.  Also, my other friend Nanyea posted some <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&amp;message.id=213346">additional information from the Summit meetings</a> on the EQLive boards.</p>

<p>Some vanity news: there's a <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&amp;message.id=209271&amp;view=by_date_ascending&amp;page=1">great post about the Everquest Raiding Game</a> on the EQLive forums that used my <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=10406">Caster's Realm article on the topic</a> as a base.  </p>

<p>There's also an interesting thread about the difficulty of <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&amp;message.id=212009&amp;view=by_date_ascending&amp;page=1">Theater of Blood</a>. Every time I ask about the intention of this zone, I get a different answer. Personally I think it could have been designed for more players by having less flagging requirements and lowering the DPS and overall damage output a little, but having not hunted there invalidates much of my opinion. Right now I think the value of this zone for a non-raider is to bottomfeed off of the drops that high-end raiders don't want when they tear a line to a huge ubermob. I think it could be more than this.</p>

<p>7 April 2006, 2:40pm</p>

<p>I posted more pictures to the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/72057594100206856/">Spring 2006 Summit flickr site</a>.</p>

<p>Baelish gave a very interesting presentation on many of the upcoming changes to EQ Players. Much of it was qualified under a great cloak of secrecy (why you would tell a bunch of press geeks that they can't talk about something, I'll never understand) but much of it sounds interesting.  A few things we CAN talk about includes a fully CSS implementation of player profiles that other websites can skin.  Your guild's website can post character profiles with any look or layout that they wish.</p>

<p>Guild rosters can be pulled directly from EQ Players in XML, letting guilds reformat, sort, and display rosters any way they wish.</p>

<p>Other whispers and rumors include an in-game tournament system, an in-game tie to Comic Book Creator, dream profiles with gear you WISH you had, automatic paperdoll uploading, automatic screenshot uploading, an automated DKP system, and an in-game browser to tie to many of these services.  A lot of these features are still under discussion and planning so we'll have to see what happens.</p>

<h2>More Breaking Future Expansion News: "Likely" Level Increase to Level 75, New Starting City</h2>

<p>I got a "most likely" confirmation on a level increase to level 75 in the upcoming unnamed fall expansion. That should help a lot of players increase their power enough to handle content previously out of reach such as the MPG Trials and the harder DODH missions.</p>

<p>There will "probably" be raid content above Deathknell as well so it sounds like players of all levels have a good reason to head into this one.</p>

<p>The goal of the expansion is for players to be able to go from level 1 to level 75 and all the way through the post-Deathknell raid content in this single expansion alone. It will likely be far more efficient for players to go back to previous expansions at various points in their growth, but the intent is for the expansion is to be a new starting point for new Everquest players including a new starting city.</p>

<p>Friday 7 April 2006, 11:09pm</p>

<p>While most of the Fan Faire attendees and developers headed over for karoke and live music, I spent some time sitting with the bard correspondent, the lead programmer, and senior programmer for Everquest.  We had a great conversation surrounding everything we heard so far including the Progression server, the new look at the death penalty, the low level game, atlas changes, improvements in the hotzone system, further use for environmental effects such as breakable items, and a lot of other things. It is always great to see how much these guys love their game and love talking to players about it.</p>

<p>Here are a few more notes from the panel.</p>

<p>There was discussion surrounding the Atlas and additional information one might be able to see.  Coloring certain zones to represent current population was the best suggestion I heard so that players can see where current popular zones are located and find groups a little easier.</p>

<p>I spoke more to Grumbuk and Jamey Ryan about how pathing works and asked the pathing bug questions that came up in the comments earlier.  The 20k fall off of the horse while using an aura has been fixed on test.  Much of the pathing information requires more information on the specific zones, mobs, and any other data. They are working on pathing issues and discussed the difference between the pathing meshes used in old world zones to their new "Path Volume System" that lets them mark out possible paths with wide geometric boxes instead of simple lines. They talked about the pathing problems with Arcstone and pulling mobs above a certain Z axis and hope to have a fix soon.</p>

<p>This afternoon was the tradeskill and lore discussions. I don't follow tradeskills much so I cannot comment on much of it. Vahlar mentioned that they are planning to compile the lore behind the previous eleven expansions and post it so players can get a feeling for what has happened over the years.</p>

<p>I also forgot to mention something that Boanerges mentioned in his report: new AA sets are likely to cost a lot more AAs than previous sets. This caused a big stir back in Gates of Discord, but AAs are much easier to get now both in the higher experience rewards in zones and with the fact that AAs get easier to earn once you reach higher levels.  The AA for a level 50 costs exactly the same experience that an AA costs at level 70 but level 70s get much more experience per kill. The answer to the age old question of "should I level or should I get AAs" should always slant towards level.</p>

<p>Tomorrow will be the meat of the EQ panels so expect more notes tomorrow afternoon.  I also posted more pictures to the <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mikeshea/sets/72057594100206856/">Spring 2006 Summit and Fan Faire Flickr Page</a></p>

<p>Saturday, 8 April 2006, 8:32am</p>

<p>Kwill has two excellent fan faire reports posted including <a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=16474">the EQ Vault Community Summit Report</a> and <a href="http://eqvault.ign.com/fullstory.php?id=16475"> 	Pakse's Community Summmit Report</a>.</p>

<h2>A brief Discussion of Alternate Advancement</h2>

<p>Yesterday I briefly mentioned some of the discussions surrounding Alternate Abilities without going too far in depth.  Here is a bit more discussion.</p>

<p>The level increase to 75 in the next expansion will likely include a new set of AAs to upgrade basic class-specific AA skills such as durability, healing improvement, magic damage improvement, lightning reflexes, and other class-defining abilities.  These skills will require base AA improvements just as spells require improvements when a class goes from level 70 to 75. Like the level increase, these AA increases will improve the baseline power of high-end characters in Everquest regardless of whether they raid or hunt in single-groups.</p>

<p>At higher levels, AAs are much easier to acquire than they are at lower levels. For older players, AAs are much easier to acquire now than they were back in the days of Luclin and Planes of Power. As levels increase, so do the experience point rewards of defeated creatures. Yet the cost for a single AA remains the same - roughly the same cost as going from level 50 to level 51. This means that AAs designed for levels 71 through 75 should cost much more than baseline level 50 AAs and likely will.  For example, there may be a new set of Healing Adapt AAs  that go from 1% to 10% but cost 10 AAs per percent or 100 AAs for the whole set. That may seem daunting at lower levels but at level 70, one can earn an AA per hour doing monster missions alone. This rate is much higher in certain high-experience-reward areas such as the Nest and Hive missions.</p>

<p>Players of Everquest above level 50 are of two minds when it comes to AAs.  Older players who hunt often and earn vast quantities of AAs rather quickly constantly require new AAs in order to have a reason to hunt. Raiders especially rarely earn any equipment in single-group hunts that they desire. Their only reason to hunt in single groups is to earn experience, but if they are maxed out on AAs, they don't even have that.</p>

<p>The other type of player, newer players attempting to reach higher levels and higher-end content, see that 400 AAs might be required to earn all of their baseline abilities expected from a high end player and fall into despair.  It may take them two hours to earn a single AA at level 55 or above.  Earning 400 such AAs would take far longer than most players have the time to spend.</p>

<p>SOE discussed various ways this might be approached. Some mentioned baseline quests that would reward players with a set of AAs on a given line. Complete a set of four missions and earn the entire bank of Healing Adapt 1, 2, and 3 AAs for example. Complete another set and earn all of the Healing Gift line. This would speed up the progression of a newer character through lines of their baseline AAs.</p>

<p>Whether we see such quests in the future is unknown. However, it is clear that earning AAs today is much easier than earning AAs in the past. Every expansion opens up newer high-experience areas where players can quickly earn new skills.</p>

<p>As a new player grows, they should seek out new levels before worrying about new AAs.  While some baseline AAs, perhaps 24 or so, should be spent on critical effects, divine arbitration for example, most AAs should not be worried about until a class hits the highest levels and earns the most experience per kill that they can.</p>

<p>Saturday, 8 April 2006, 6:26pm</p>

<h2>Possible Level Increase to Level 80?? Madness!</h2>

<p>At one of the four EQ sessions today, Rashere said they were tossing around the idea of a level increase to 75 or 80. A level increase to 80 is unlikely given that SOE has never done it in the past and that the extra levels would require tons of extra content, spells, disciplines, and equipment. A level increase to 80 would also radically alter the difficulty of old-world content. Still, it is fun to lean back and imagine what would happen with a level increase to 80.</p>

<p>There were four EQ related sessions today including Items and Spells, The Future of Everquest, Prophecy of Ro, and Class Balance. Most of the discussions focused around very specific things including particular items or spells or the way auras work in POR. There was little general news beyond the red herring level 80 drop.</p>

<p>I had a chance to meet my old friend Ben, the editor of Mobhunter's articles, and introduce him to all the developers. </p>

<p>We spent some time talking to <a href="http://www.larryelmore.com/index.htm">Larry Elmore</a> (<a href="http://flickr.com/photo_zoom.gne?id=124784836&amp;context=set-72057594100206856&amp;size=o">pic</a>), the artist who does all of the covers for Everquest's expansions. He's a great no BS guy who will tell you stories about the fantasy industry back for thirty years. Every old cover of Dragonlance or Forgotten Realms that dragged you into the world of fantasy role playing was likely done by him. He's a wealth of information and a very personable guy. If you ever get to a Fan Faire or you happen to be at this one, visit his booth and say hello. You won't regret it.</p>

<p>Sunday, 9 April 2006, 5:24pm</p>

<p>I return home after three days of madness and excitement. I learned little else of major note, but no doubt a few details will return to me.</p>

<p>I did learn that when the crystal form of experience arrived in monster missions that the pirate monster mission will offer up more experience for each crystal recovered beyond the base 20. This is one of my favorite fun monster missions so I can't wait to try it out further. I also heard more about the many progression and story lines that will follow new players from level 1 to "max level" in the new expansion.  Progressive storylines will follow players along as they progress through the lore. Also, characters will be able to submit lore books to a central library where others can come learn about the lore of the lands in this new expansion.</p>

<p>I had a clarification on some of the EQ Players functions mentioned a few days ago. After talking to some of the EQ Live developers, it was clear that little discussion between the EQ Live developers and the platform developers has occurred. I wouldn't expect many of the features mentioned in the EQ Players presentation to go live anytime soon for EQ1.</p>

<p>I will write up a full summary of the weekend's activities in a few days.</p>

<p>Thank you for reading!</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
9 April 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Loral&apos;s Evil Agenda, Spring 2006</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001468.html" />
    <modified>2006-04-13T12:06:43Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-04-01T09:11:11-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1468</id>
    <created>2006-04-01T14:11:11Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">With an Everquest Community Summit and Fan Faire just a week away, Loral takes a look at the full scope of the game to pick out the five improvements that may have the greatest impact to Everquest.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>With every SOE Fan Faire and every Everquest Community Summit, it is important to take a look over the entirety of the game to see what areas currently need the most attention. This season we look at the five issues facing Everquest after the release of Prophecy of Ro. Let us begin our recommendations to SOE's Everquest development team.</p>

<h2>Add New Player Models.</h2>

<p>With the release of more and more new massive online RPGs, the EQ models continue to look clunky and dated. Half-finished animations, strange clipping issues, and poor performance plague the Luclin models. Senior executives at SOE should consider allocating the money needed to build new player models in Everquest. With the excellent look of new zones and creatures since Omens of War, new player models would give an entirely fresh look to Everquest.</p>

<h2>Rebuild Plane of Knowledge.</h2>

<p>Since the release of Planes of Power, the Plane of Knowledge continues to act as a hub for players of all levels and play-styles.  The layout and graphics of the Plane of Knowledge do not show Everquest's best face, nor does it include features to help players find groups. A rebuilt Plane of Knowledge with new quests, missions, monster missions, new graphic enhancements, and a layout designed for performance would help players find groups faster and begin having fun. While every other city should represent their original races and cultures, New Tanaan should be the city of the adventurers.</p>

<h2>Add Quests and Missions for level 20 to 60.</h2>

<p>Since Dragons of Norrath, new quests and missions have helped high level players focus on instanced group adventures with one to two hour goals. However, little has been done to enhance the mid-level game using these new tools and techniques. SOE should reevaluate the entire game from level 20 to 60 focusing on a clearer progression path, offering progressive rewards, and helping new players feel the same sense of adventure they felt in the tutorial and high level players feel in the Dragons of Norrath, Depths of Darkhollow, and Prophecy of Ro missions. Use newly discovered storytelling and gameplay techniques to make the game as good at level 20 as it is for level 70.</p>

<h2>Add cross-server missions, monster missions, and pickup-raids.</h2>

<p>A cross-server grouping feature would help Everquest capitalize on the vast number of players across all servers. Players could go to a set location in Norrath, such as a new tavern in the rebuilt Plane of Knowledge, and find players seeking groups on other servers. Groups would be transported to a mission, monster mission, or even a small 18 to 24 person raid instance. By disabling player to player trading, economies would remain unaffected. Players would go from a few dozen LFG players to a few hundred.</p>

<h2>Remove Equipment Loss on Death.</h2>

<p>With recent MMOs avoiding full equipment loss on death, it no longer makes sense for Everquest to hang on to this archaic practice. Equipment loss on death does not make the game any more difficult but instead creates the perception of great loss for new and inexperienced players. Further, bugs still threaten players' equipment as corpses disappear in crashed instances or under the world, forcing a player to wait until customer service representatives can reimburse his or her equipment. Replace equipment loss on death with a new "death effect" that reduces movement to 75% until the player receives a resurrection or 15 minutes pass. This evens out the detriment to character death for players at all levels. Removing this outdated feature also fulfills the longstanding request for a "loot all" button and removes exploits based on leaving equipment on corpses.</p>

<h2>A Few Other Good Ideas.</h2>

<p>- Add large experience rewards for doing missions the first time to reinforce a variety of missions.</p>

<p>- Help close the equipment and damage output gap between non-raiders and raiders in relation to single-group content.</p>

<p>- Add more instanced rewarding content between Creator and monster missions and MPG Trial, DODH missions, and POR missions.</p>

<p>- Add more three-person or non-ideal group instances.</p>

<p>In its seventh year, Everquest continues to show its strength compared to all massive online games.  SOE can reinforce this strength by adding new player models, rebuilding the Plane of Knowledge, reworking the content for level 20 to 60, adding cross-server content, and removing equipment loss on death.  These changes will help Everquest continue to be competitive, challenging, and fun.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
1 April 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Evil Agenda Report Card</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001467.html" />
    <modified>2006-04-13T12:05:48Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-03-20T08:15:26-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1467</id>
    <created>2006-03-20T13:15:26Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">With the April 2006 Fan Faire soon arriving, so too comes a new Evil Agenda.  Before we lay out this season&apos;s recommendations, Mobhunter takes a look at the Evil Agendas of the past and grades SOE on the changes it has made so far.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>For every Everquest Fan Faire or guild summit I have attended, I have written up an Evil Agenda; a list of recommendations to SOE to help them improve Everquest.  In today's article, we take a look back at the items of previous evil agendas to see where SOE has shined and where they have fallen away from the path.  Using this, we can begin to formulate a new Spring 2006 Evil Agenda for the <a href="http://events.station.sony.com/fanfaire/">April 2006 Fan Faire</a>.  Please note, redundant evil agenda items were removed from this list.</p>

<p>Let us begin.</p>

<h2><a href="http://mobhunter.com/001329.html">31 May 2004: Loral's Evil Agenda</a></h2>

<h3>Focus on single-group content. Grade: A</h3>

<p>Since LDON, SOE has continued to add new single group content from levels 65 and above.  Levels 20 to 50 have little other than LDON and Monster missions, however, taking the grade down to a B.</p>

<h3>Offer easier corpse recovery in old world and GoD zones. Grade: A</h3>

<p>The Dragons Guild Lobby corpse alters took care of this problem. Horrible corpse recovery is now mostly a dark memory.</p>

<h3>Offer quest, adventure-point, or vendor alternatives for level 65 and GoD spells. Grade: C</h3>

<p>Level 66+ spells have dropped in DoDH with increasing frequency, but I am not convinced that non-raiders have more access to spells. The quests and missions for spells in DON, DODH, and POR also help, but not for base class spells from 66 to 70.</p>

<h3>Offer progressive content in 30 minutes or less. Grade: B</h3>

<p>Monster missions offered great low time commitment content.  The abstraction from actual play-characters, however, hurts their overall effectiveness.  SOE should find a way to offer the same high-speed groups for actual play-characters.</p>

<h3>Add higher-end equipment to LDON adventure merchants. Grade: D</h3>

<p>We never saw any improvements to LDON gear and DON gear never reached the goals needed for single group hunters to progress.  Gear situations improve every expansion but SOE continues to make single-group gear too low powered compared to the content that single group hunters can face.</p>

<h3>Add more Lost Dungeon content including zones, adventure types, and rewards. Grade: A</h3>

<p>DON, DODH, and POR all added some excellent single group missions with changing goals, good rewards, and new game play elements.  The mission system lets Everquest lead the pack in group-friendly massive online RPGs.</p>

<h2><a href="http://mobhunter.com/001349.html">21 October 2004: Evil Halloween Agenda</a></h2>

<h3>Add and Improve Quests. Grade: B</h3>

<p>The expansion of the mission system and the task system since DON has added some excellent rewarding quests.  The four arcstone quests are examples of excellent new quest content.  The only thing lacking are sets of progressive quests for primary-slot armor which continues to only be randomly dropped.  Using missions and monster missions as progressive quests also has a lot of potential.</p>

<h3>Improve Grouping Options. Grade: B</h3>

<p>The LFG tool, mission systems, monster missions, and global channels helps people find groups quickly but more could be done to centralize LFG areas.  Why not have a huge cozy tavern where people can seek others for groups?</p>

<h3>Focus on 90 minute events. Grade: B</h3>

<p>Most missions and raids can be accomplished in under 90 minutes.  Many monster missions can be done in under an hour.  A few missions like the Cicero's Notebook mission and the Chamber Guardian mission seem to take far longer than they should for non-raiders with lower damage output.</p>

<h3>Improve Encounter Variety. Grade: A</h3>

<p>Some of the monsters in DODH show how encounters can vary for single-group hunters.  POR took this further by adding unique game play elements to even basic zone population mobs.  For example, the fire demons in arcstone will summon miniature versions of themselves to harass healers and the tangleroots will continually chain cast root spells that must be handled in order to defeat them.  Encounter variety shakes up traditional button pushing and forces groups to change tactics depending on the mobs.  Encounters like the five Spirit mobs in Arcstone give single-group hunters the feeling that raiders get facing big, powerful, and complicated beasts.</p>

<h3>Make the Game Easier for New Players. Grade: B</h3>

<p>The new tutorial, redefined interface, and Knowledge quests do a great job bringing players from level 1 to 10.  From 11 on, however, corpse recovery is still complicated and hard to understand, groups are hard to find, and no clear progression path exists.  Level 11 characters are released into a huge world without any clear idea where to go, who to meet, or what to do.</p>

<h2><a href="http://mobhunter.com/001365.html">17 March 2005: Loral's Evil Agenda Spring 2005</a></h2>

<h3>Add new quests, tasks, missions, and mission vendors for levels 10 to 50. Grade: C</h3>

<p>While scores of new missions exist for levels 65 and above, very few interesting or progressive missions have been added from levels 10 to 50.  A clear line of missions from 10 to 50 with clear beneficial rewards help new players reach the higher levels without getting lost.</p>

<h3>Add a tiered mission vendor loot system. Grade: C</h3>

<p>SOE has tried a half dozen different loot systems and hasn't found the perfect sweet spot yet.  DODH offered a wide variety of high-end items but only for a few slots.  DON offered items for all slots but of limited power and with a system that reinforced bottom feeding off of the easiest mission.  In POR, SOE goes back to the original loot systems from which the point systems originally broke away.  SOE went full circle instead of evolving into a new system that offers all of the advantages of the older ones.</p>

<h3>Continue to improve the Plane of Knowledge. Grade: D</h3>

<p>The Plane of Knowledge grows older every day with no new improvements since its original release.  It's time for Plane of Knowledge to be rebuilt in the style of the new Freeport.</p>

<h2><a href="http://mobhunter.com/001373.html">1 June 2005: Evil Agenda, Las Vegas Summer 2005</a></h2>

<h3>Add a Mentor System. Grade: A</h3>

<p>Spirit Shrouds and Monster Missions let players play together regardless of level, class, or equipment power.  Characters earn experience and equipment based on the base level of their play character.  While some worry that abstracting a player from their play-character could be dangerous, the base intent was met very well.  Monster missions can bring friends together quickly, easily, and without concern for level, class, or equipment.</p>

<h2><a href="http://mobhunter.com/001420.html">24 September 2005: Loral's Evil Agenda, September 2005</a></h2>

<h3>Further Improve Monster Missions. Grade: A</h3>

<p>Prophecy of Ro introduced a new set of monster missions including the first monster raid and a progressive series of monster missions with an excellent augment as a reward.</p>

<h3>Continue to Tie Future Expansions to Old World Lore. Grade: A</h3>

<p>The uncovering and ascent of Mistmoore takes us back to the lore of the original expansions.  Prophecy of Ro feels far more like Everquest than the far away lands in Gates of Discord and Omens of War.</p>

<h3>Improve the Dynamics of Combat. Grade: A</h3>

<p>Traps, spheres of influence, breakable objects, unique monster missions, unique scenarios inside regular instanced missions, and the newer creature abilities found in Prophecy of Ro all push to change combat styles from one encounter to the next.</p>

<h3>Improve the 20 to 50 Game. Grade: D</h3>

<p>While we have seen great changes in the game from level 60 and above, the 20 to 50 game continues to lag behind.  Players seek out the fastest experience paths to reach the high levels and SOE does little to change that path.  New missions, new evolving items, new quests, and greater experience rewards from group-based encounters could help build a progressive track for new players to follow.  Right now, players are released into a wide open world with no clear idea where one should go to progress.  Lower level groups are difficult to find and solo content is lacking at the lower levels.</p>

<h2>Overall Evaluation</h2>

<p>While many games offer expansions that simply introduce new content.  SOE redefines itself with the release of each expansion.  Entirely new gameplay options not only offer new variety into an old game but change the way the whole game is played.  Players from the original, Kunark, Velious, and Luclin days would not recognize Everquest today.  Missions and monster missions in particular have focused Everquest towards the important goal of getting players together, giving them a fun solid adventure, and rewarding them for their efforts.</p>

<p>The game is not perfect, however.  Reviewing the recommendations from past years, we can clearly see a few gaps.  The Plane of Knowledge, the hub of travel in Norrath, clearly shows its age.  The existing player models are now almost five years old.  Clunky, broken, and poorly performing; it is time SOE took another serious look at upgrading them.  The level 10 to 60 game also needs serious work.  While tracks of progression are clearly laid out from level 65 and above, newer players have no clear path for progression.  They simply go where the experience flows best and grind until they get to the highest levels.</p>

<p>All of these things are fixable, although some; like new player models; are very expensive.  As it has over the past two years, SOE can continue to redefine Everquest into a competitive and highly entertaining massive online game.</p>

<p>Prepare for next week we outline the Spring 2006 Evil Agenda.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
20 March 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Rise of Ro and the Fall of Stormhammer</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001464.html" />
    <modified>2006-04-13T12:06:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-03-06T20:51:53-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1464</id>
    <created>2006-03-07T01:51:53Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This week we look at the parlay on the test server, the post-release Prophecy whispers, and the long-awaited discussion of the fall of Stormhammer.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Once again we find ourselves with a new unknown corner of the world to explore.  While many originally labeled Prophecy of Ro the "Ykesha" expansion, anyone to reasonably do so now clearly doesn't see what it contains.  Besides increased bank space, the expansion is no comparison to the mid-level mini-expansion, Legacy of Ykesha.</p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro contains a wide range of raid targets, many of them in open zones.  SOme claim that these high-end targets, like the three dragons of Relic, drop gear far more powerful than they should.  Veteran raiders of Demiplane of Blood were quick to jump on this topic, claiming that the high-end rewards from open-zone mobs removed any reason for them to hunt in Demiplane of Blood.</p>

<p>Back about the time the single-group gear in Depths of Darkhollow received an upgrade, the raiders began to bring forward similar complaints about the raiding gear in Demiplane of Blood.  Initially SOE responded to the complaints about high-end raid targets leading to the Demiplane by saying that flagging mobs generally don't have the gear to which a raiding guild would upgrade.  The real upgraded gear was in the Demiplane of Blood itself.</p>

<p>This wasn't the case.  The raid gear they received in Demiplane of Blood was an upgrade to previous Omens and Dragons high-end raid gear but not powerful enough to motivate raiders to use their votes, DKP points, or other loot distribution credit to purchase this equipment.</p>

<p>Likely the cause for this feeling came from the fact that few items were tuned to specific classes.  Unlike the class armor in Anguish, the armor dropping in Depths was tuned for a wide range of classes.  It would not likely have the same dedicated power for any one class that a class-specific piece contains.</p>

<p>Now, high-end raiders complain that the gear dropping in open zones is too close to this gear they didn't like already.  They don't like the gear they receive in Demiplane but they don't want others to have anything close.</p>

<p>That is obviously a biased and simplistic view of the problem, but there are important points to consider.  This gear is not as good as Demiplane gear.  This gear drops on non-instanced raid targets.  Few guilds below Anguish level will have the ability to defeat these mobs and receive these items.  While a guild can have a dedicated shot at clearing their own versions of Tacvi, Anguish, the Dragons of Norrath, and Demiplane of Blood without any worry that someone else will take these areas, other guilds will compete for the static mobs in Arcstone, Relic, Devastation, and Stronghold of Rage.  Guilds will not be able to gear up on these mobs as effectivly as instanced raid zones.  Also, once guilds begin to enter Deathknell, they will receive even higher-end rewards in a dedicated instanced zone.  As always, the paths to glory shift in new directions.</p>

<p>SOE recently scheduled a town hall to discuss how best to change the Test server.  Likely they do not wish to alienate the community that now resides on the test server but also want to change the test server into a server that is actually able to test new content.  The test server, like any of the specialized servers, goes through the process of losing so many players that it becomes nearly deserted but those who do stay fight tooth and nail to maintain their community as much as they can.</p>

<p>The town hall is now scheduled for 5pm PST on 8 March 2006.</p>

<p>The changing communities on specialized servers is not a new topic in recent days.  A while back I said that I would discuss the closing of Stormhammer and some posters have requested it.  While it is now somewhat old news, it still is an important topic for the future of other specialized servers.</p>

<p>At the September 2005 Everquest summit, the attendees had a chance to walk through the SOE operations center.  On one board they had all of the existing players on each of the servers.  Most of the numbers were close to the others except for three: Zek, Firiona Vie, and Stormhammer.  While Zek and Firiona Vie had roughly half the number of players of other main servers at that specific slice of time, Stormhammer had under 10%.</p>

<p>At the Summer 2005 Las Vegas Fan Faire I had lunch with some community representatives who played on Stormhammer and talked about the situation.  For them, nearly four months after the release of Dragons of Norrath, the Nest had yet to be opened.  While GMs worked with players to schedule server-wide raiding events, the power could not be mustered to defeat high-end raid targets.  Grouping was very hard at the high-end and grouping at lower levels was all but impossible.</p>

<p>While the community members I talked with had some ideas to re-invigorate the server's numbers, it was clear to me that there would be little SOE could reasonably do to increase the server's population.  There was only one clear answer.  Close the server.</p>

<p>On the first of February 2006, SOE closed Stormhammer.  Characters were allowed to move to any server of their choice except, perhaps, Firiona Vie.</p>

<p>One of the louder complaints came from those who used Stormhammer as a way to farm characters from one server to another.  When the announcement went live in mid January, all transfers back to Stormhammer were shut down.  Some players had characters on other live servers they intended to move to Stormhammer and then to another server.  Now, doing so costs $75.</p>

<p>I never expected Stormhammer's costs to allow players to use Stormhammer as a stable of characters to move wherever they wished whenever they wished.  While I never like to see any community crumble, I have a hard time sympathizing with those who didn't get a chance to shuffle characters around one last time.  That isn't a community problem.</p>

<p>The closing of Stormhammer was sad for many involved, but it was clear it had to happen.  Stormhammer ran for months with far fewer players than any other server.  Because of its specialized nature and higher price tag, any sort of server merger was out of the question, although Stormhammer players voted not to have Stormhammer turned into a normal server and merged with another.</p>

<p>Like Test and Stormhammer, all specialized servers will one day face this same choice.  Firiona Vie and Zek cannot hold their numbers forever and because of their specialized rules, they cannot simply be merged with other existing servers.  I expect we will hear more about these servers within a year.</p>

<p>Last week Ryan Barker, Rytan the Spell Tzar of Everquest, <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&message.id=194433">announced he was moving</a> to a secret project (likely SOE's competition to <a href="http://www.sanriotown.com/onlinegame/index.php?s=introduction">Hello Kitty Online World</a>).  I met Rytan at the first Everquest summit and again at many of the fan faires.  One thing was made very clear to every player who ever approached him to complain about a spell: Ryan knew his subject.  Never have I seen someone able to so clearly describe the relationships and details of so complicated a system.  While often the target of recklass hate, Ryan always faced his critics with even temperment and dry British-style humor.  He will be missed.</p>

<p>At great personal risk to himself, my friend Nanyea from Caster's Realm posted the <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=10354">checklist for access to Theater of Blood</a>.  The checklist outlines the seven to eight missions one must undertake to gain access to the newest Plane of Fear style high-end hunting and reward zone.  The items from this zone have also begin to filter out through Lucy and Caster's Realms's new monster database.</p>

<p>Last week I had the great privilege of <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50096">being in the EQ Players community spotlight</a>.  This gave me the chance to talk about why I enjoy this game as much as I do and even gave me a bit of room to stretch out my own evil agenda a little bit more. I give thanks to Kytherea for the opportunity.</p>

<p>Having only one week in Prophecy of Ro, it is too early to give a full review of the expansion.  I will likely write a full review once we have a wider view of how this expansion changes Everquest.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
6 March 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>As the Prophecy Unfolds</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001462.html" />
    <modified>2006-04-13T12:06:19Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-02-20T14:12:38-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1462</id>
    <created>2006-02-20T19:12:38Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">With the dawn of the Prophecy of Ro at hand, Loral takes a look at Prophecy single-group quest to reach the Theater of Blood and also looks at some of the armor rewards from the 11th Everquest expansion.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow, 21 February 2006, SOE will release the Prophecy of Ro expansion for Everquest.  Last week SOE released the Non-disclosure Agreement, allowing those who betatested the expansion to spread wild rumors at their hearts' content.</p>

<p>There's a lot of content in this expansion but two things have me anticipating a good long run through Prophecy of Ro: the Theater of Blood access quest and the new class armor sets.</p>

<p>I had heard many whispers and rumors about the Theater of Blood access quest but late last week I had a chance to speak to Keridon, the designer in charge of putting the quest together.  What I learned follows.</p>

<p>The Theater of Blood access quest takes players through all of the six new zones in Prophecy of Ro: Elddar Forest, Takish Hiz, Arcstone, Relic, Devastation, and the Stronghold of Rage.  The quest consists of both instanced and non-instanced content throughout these zones.  The quest introduces players to all of the main plot points of the Prophecy of Ro storyline, explaining what is happening and who is responsible.  While the end-game raids will follow more of the consequential storyline of the expansion, the single-group Theater of Blood access quest introduces the actors playing the roles throughout the new areas.</p>

<p>While the length of the quest is not yet known, it is expected to be quite a bit longer than the Dreadspire access quest in Depths of Darkhollow.  The overall quest difficulty scales up to Dreadspire difficulty, requiring that single-group hunters must be well equipped in order to finish the quest.  This quest is designed to be accomplished by players with no raid equipment at all but they must be well equipped to defeat the quest.  The quest is designed to give access to the Theater of Blood to those who enjoy single group hunts.</p>

<p>The Theater of Blood itself is a zone built on the philosophies of the original Plane of Fear and Plane of Hate.  It is intended to be a very dangerous zone filled with the powerful and unrelenting minions of the new demi-god, Mayong Mistmoore.  Groups of twelve to eighteen players should be able to hunt the lower minions of the Theater while larger groups may battle the larger wandering creatures of the zone.  Six high-end beasts control access to the final raid zone of the expansion, Deathknell.</p>

<p>With this much content in one zone, the Theater of Blood may soon be a very popular place.  Non-raiders might group up in two or three groups to hunt the outer beasts of the zone while larger groups of high-end non-raiders or mid-tier raiding guilds will battle the named beasts of the outer areas.  High-end raiding guilds of 54 members will battle the six keyholders to Deathknell.  Since the Theater of Blood is not instanced, all of this will happen in one zone on each server.</p>

<p>This design is not without risk.  Already representatives from high-end raiding guilds question the logic of non-instanced keyholders.  They bring up painful memories of Planes of Power where one guild might kill a mob critical to the progression of another guild.  One difference, however, is that the final zone IS instanced.  While one guild might attempt to block the progression of another, they would not be doing it to preserve their own hunting ground.  However many guilds gain access to Deathknell, each will have their own copy in which to hunt.</p>

<p>How will competition for non-instanced content work for single group hunters or the loose bands of groups hunting in Theater of Blood?  That is yet to be seen.  The progression quest to Theater of Blood will require killing specific un-instanced mobs in the six open zones.  It is possible that these static beasts will become a bottleneck for those seeking access to the Theater of Blood.  Much depends on the spawn rate of these mobs and whether any alternative paths exist.</p>

<p>What if no one cares?  Why worry about access to the Theater of Blood when we have excellent instances in Depths of Darkhollow that offer excellent experience and fine loot?  What will drive players through a long single-group quest and push them to face the horrors unseen since the days of Fear and Hate?</p>

<p>Class armor.</p>

<p>Rewards drive players to new content.  Risk versus reward sits over Norrath like a map of mountains and valleys.  Players gravitate to the valleys where the rewards are highest for their effort.  Mountains, which might have some excellent content and high adventure, stand mostly abandoned.  Players seek tangible rewards and it is these tangible rewards, new class armor, that will drive players to the content in Prophecy of Ro.</p>

<p>There will likely be two sets of class-specific armor in Prophecy of Ro: one for single-groupers and one for the hunters of Theater of Blood.  The lower power class specific armor will drop from three or four of the six static zones including Devastation, Relic, and likely Elddar and Arcstone.  Named mobs in these zones will drop molds similar to the ornate armor molds in Planes of Power.  These molds can be combined with other more easily accessible items to form a new piece of class armor.</p>

<p>The power of this armor is not fully known, but I expect it to be about 150 hitpoints and mana including focus effects, combat effects, defensive effects, or regeneration effects.  This would place the armor above the armor available in Planes of Power, the tier 1 Omens armor, and the Dragons of Norrath vendor armor.</p>

<p>This armor would mix well with the off-slot armor abundantly rewarded in Depths of Darkhollow.  The Depths single-group missions offered seven items per group on every successful mission but most of these items were for non-primary-armor slots such as neck, face, back, shoulder, waist, and some rings and earrings.  Primary slot items for chests, legs, hands, wrists, heads, and feet were more rare and not tuned for specific classes.  This new set of class armor in Prophecy will fill those slots.</p>

<p>These are not the only class armor pieces available in Prophecy, however.  True to the original model of Hate and Fear, the Theater of Blood will drop high-end class armor of a much higher power.  Again, this exact power is unknown, but 200 hitpoint and mana armor with focus, combat, regeneration, and defensive effects are likely.  Armor of this power would match the highest power off-slot items in Depths of Darkhollow and give players a very good reason to fight their way to the Theater of Blood.</p>

<p>Many questions still exist with these new pieces of content.  Will the quest to reach the Theater be too difficult?  Will too many players try to do it at the same time and create a huge bottleneck?  Will the power of the rewards be too low?  Will the mix of high-end raiders, mid-level guilds, and three-group hunting parties be too much for one static zone to handle?  There are a lot of risks with this most recent design, but if well tuned and done correctly, it could bring a lot of new excitement back into Everquest.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
20 February 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com<br />
</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Prophecy of Ro: In-Depth Preview</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001460.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-27T07:17:24Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-02-05T17:42:14-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1460</id>
    <created>2006-02-05T22:42:14Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">With the release of Prophecy of Ro only three weeks away, Loral Ciriclight spends some time digging into some exclusive details of this new expansion.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>In two weeks, Sony Online Entertainment will release the eleventh expansion for Everquest: Prophecy of Ro.  Three days ago I had the opportunity to walk across the new lands offered in this expansion and discuss its new features with Everquest's lead designer, Travis McGeathy, also known as Rashere.</p>

<p>The release of Prophecy of Ro includes the largest single release of rebuilt old-world zones.  All of Freeport and the entire Desert of Ro will be redone in the style of later expansions using newer graphical techniques.  Previously seamed polygonal landscapes now become rolling dunes of sand and rock.</p>

<p>The rebuild of Freeport not only updates the appearance and layout but also shows how the city has grown over the years.  The factions that split the city have become even more aggravated.  The alleys of East Freeport grow darker while high walls and armed guards protect the sanctity of the Temple of Marr in the west.  The Tower of the Arcane rises high above the wooden buildings around it.  SOE paid attention to both the vast scope of the city and the intricate details found in every corner.</p>

<p>The content available in Freeport and Ro is still the same.  The level ranges of the zones have not changed.  New quests have been added, including a new faction quest in Freeport that, when earned, lets players walk freely through both sides of Freeport without harassment.  While the difficulty of this quest is not yet known, it will not be as severe as a "collect 10,000 cloth caps" quest.</p>

<p>SOE will release these four zones, replacing six old-world zones, to all players regardless of whether they purchase the expansion or not.  While the new missions in these zones are only available to purchasers of Prophecy of Ro, some new quests in these zones will be available to everyone.</p>

<p>The new zones of Prophecy of Ro are split into three sets: Takish Hiz, Plane of Magic, and Plane of Rage.  Each of these sets includes two large static zones as well as individual missions.  This does not include a final unique zone, the Theater of Blood, discussed later.</p>

<p>An overarching storyline connects the players through these new zones.  Mayong Mistmoore has become a demi-god and now threatens the pantheon.  Druzzil Ro, goddess of Magic, is unable to directly interfere with these plans but is able to call upon the adventurers of Norrath to help thwart Mistmoore's plans.  She opens gateways to the Plane of Magic, the Plane of Rage, and with the help of Tunare and Karana, sends adventurers back into the glory days of the elven cities of Tunaria.</p>

<p>The winds of Karana have uncovered the ruins of Takish Hiz.  Players will remember exploring some of this city in Lost Dungeons of Norrath, but that prepares them little for what they face now.  In the first of the three zone sets, adventurers will explore the ruins of Takish Hiz and transport back to the time before the fall of Elddar Forest.</p>

<p>The ruined city of Takish Hiz is a large static hunting zone tuned for level 50 to level 65 characters. Players will face creatures lost under the sands for centuries.  Deeper within the zone, adventurers will find access through Druzzil's magic to the forest of Elddar.</p>

<p>The second zone in each zone-set is tuned for higher levels than the first.  Elddar Forest is tuned for level 70s at roughly the same difficulty as the Hive.  Powerful treants, huge intelligent forest giants, and other great beasts roam the massive trees of the elven city.  The city layout of Takish Hiz remains consistent across both the Elddar and Ruins of Takish Hiz zone, showing adventurers how the city has changed.</p>

<p>The Plane of Magic is home to the creations of Druzzil Ro.  It consists of two zones, Arcstone and Relic.  Arcstone represents the more chaotic and natural aspects of Druzzil's magic.  Powerful spirits rule over the land and the landscape itself changes drastically depending on which spirit controls the area.  A camp of lost travelers gives new adventurers a place to ground themselves as they explore the strange land.  Arcstone is tuned for level 60 to level 70 at around the same difficulty as the Muramite Proving Grounds.</p>

<p>Relic represents the antithesis of Arcstone.  Relic is itself a vast artifact of great power, huge both physically and in planar strength.  A great spire, the Skylance, pins Arcstone and Relic together like a spindle between two platforms.  Looking up the spire in either of the two zones shows you the surface of the other.  Gravity pulls outward in both zones like a sphere instead of down as we are used to, so the surfaces of the two lands face each other instead of being stacked on top of one another, with the Skylance holding them together.</p>

<p>Relic is much more orderly than Arcstone.  Druzzil Ro's minions wander the strange metallic platforms and walkways in strange, twisted, and sometimes horrifying shapes.  Walkways lead far up into the higher platforms where large bowls of elemental magic fuel the great artifact.  Huge dragons of fire, storm, and water act as guardians of these sources for the vast engine of magic.</p>

<p>The Plane of Rage makes up the final set of base zones for Prophecy of Ro, with Devastation and the Stronghold of Rage.  Devastation is a land in constant conflict.  Nine armies endlessly war against one another in an attempt to control the Stronghold of Rage in the center of the land.  A wall of twisted and agonized creatures rings the battlefield.  Those who commit murder out of anger find themselves trapped in the wall after their death.  Only after centuries fighting through the other murderous beings on the wall do they earn the right to fight for Sullon Zek and possession of the Stronghold.</p>

<p>Devastation is tuned for levels 60 to 70 and includes much of the destructible terrain mentioned in the Prophecy press release.  Players can crush walls, catapults, doors, and ballistae down to rubble.  The armies continually war with one another and the results of these wars lead to that army controlling the Stronghold.  During our tour, powerful drachnids held the center of this chaotic world while roving bands of orcs, kobolds, armored skeletal knights, and werewolves prowled the landscape.</p>

<p>Death in Devastation is different than death anywhere else.  Death results in a respawn in Devastation with equipment intact and an unequipped body at the site of the death.  There is no way out of Devastation save those of magical means.  Even death does not allow escape from this world.</p>

<p>The Stronghold of Rage is a fortress built by the Bolvirk, the oldest natives of the Plane of Rage who appear as strange runed giants.  The zone is tuned for high-end level 70 players and consists of the wartorn inner sanctum of the Stronghold.</p>

<p>Upon achieving greater power, Mayong Mistmoore captured his own world and twisted it towards his own evil will.  This resulted in the Theater of Blood, the dark world of the vampire demi-god.  This plane is designed for the highest power single group adventurers.  There is no zone connection to this world.  Only by following the path throughout the other lands will players find themselves here.  This zone was modeled after the Plane of Fear back in the old days of Norrath.  It is very dangerous and very difficult but with powerful rewards.  Non-raiders will find themselves hunting in groups of two or three against the denizens of this world while high-end raiders will find challenges deeper in. Mistmoore's Tower, Deathknell, spears up from the center of this dark land.</p>

<p>These descriptions do not include the wide array of missions, monster missions, quests, and raids available in Prophecy of Ro.  Prophecy of Ro includes over thirty missions with a dozen monster missions, the first ever monster raid, many single-group overland quests such as the spirit hunter missions in Arcstone, and six missions for level 45+ in the new Freeport.</p>

<p>Within the focus on level 50 and above, Prophecy of Ro has a lot to offer players of almost any play style.  Level 50 to 60 players receive six new missions in Freeport and can hunt in the Takish Hiz overland zone.  60 to 70 players receive more missions and at least three huntable static zones.  High-end level 70 players will find hunting in all six of the primary zones and, given enough effort, should find it possible to hunt in the Theater of Blood.  The new monster missions in Prophecy of Ro are available to all players of all levels assuming they can reach the mission itself.</p>

<p>Prophecy includes a lot of raid content across all of the new zones.  Each of the zones includes at least one Anguish level raid with two raid-instances similar to the Demiplane of Blood.  Prophecy also includes events for 18 to 36 Time-level raiders as well.</p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro takes a different path than Depths of Darkhollow or Dragons of Norrath.  Prophecy focuses more on static content than instanced dynamic content.  Competition will return, for good or for ill, on some of this content.  The return to a large static Plane of Fear style zone might show us how accurate our nostalgia really is for the days of old.  We will know in a few months how well this works.</p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro also includes an array of new features.  Players can now block certain buffs from ever landing on them, freeing up slots for the buff they desire most.   Some classes will receive traps that let them blast attacking creatures with a variety of effects.  Areas of influence, including player auras and zone-specific storms of magic, alter how battles are fought. Every class will receive either a trap or an aura.  Some will receive both.</p>

<p>Prophecy of Ro looks to be a large expansion mixing elements of many previous expansions.  The planar focus of the zones and the storyline follow much of the same lines as Planes of Power.  The focus of static hunting zones follows much of the success of Omens of War.  Prophecy adds new missions and monster missions in the manner of Dragons of Norrath and Depths of Darkhollow.</p>

<p>How good will this expansion be? It often takes a month or two after release to say for sure.  All of the right pieces are here, although we will have to see how players respond to more static content after the previous two heavily-instanced expansions.  Much of the success also depends on the rewards.  Players always follow the greatest reward for their time spent.</p>

<p>With some excellent visuals, nice features, and a lot of strong static huntable content, Prophecy of Ro has all of the requirements for a very strong expansion.  In a short three weeks, the adventurers of Norrath will, once again, find themselves in strange and exciting new worlds.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
6 February 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Rollback of January 2006</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001458.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-08T13:11:44Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-01-22T21:31:20-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1458</id>
    <created>2006-01-23T02:31:20Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Last week Everquest faced one of the most dramatic events in Norrath&apos;s history.  Today, Loral Ciriclight, cuts through the rumors and speculation to dig into the truth of the Great Rollback of January 2006.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>On Wednesday, 18 January 2006, the Everquest servers went down for a routine four hour patch. They came back online at 11:42 AM EST with few game changes except one - a new vendor in the Plane of Knowledge selling expensive to priceless tradeskill items for next to nothing. The Everquest developers, Sony Online Entertainment, designed these vendors for the recent betatesting of Prophecy of Ro, the eleventh Everquest expansion due for release mid February 2006. These vendors let betatesters test new tradeskill recipes with items that exist on the live servers only in much more rare quantities.</p>

<p>The results were quick and catastrophic. Players flooded to these new vendors, buying as many of these rare components as they could hold from the unlimited supply of the rogue vendor. Many players know that an event like this is a temporary situation so they hope to make out with what they can as long as they can. Knowing a character rollback may be likely, these players quickly transfer items to alternate characters, friends, or through their own shared bank. Players, hoping to keep their profits, might launder these rogue items through dozens of trades. Prices in the bazaar fell quickly as these new items flooded the market. All of this happened within two hours.</p>

<p>SOE quickly became aware of the situation and removed the rogue vendors. Yet the damage was done. Thousands of rare tradeskill items, some of them so rare that only a thousand exist across all servers, had now entered the market. While the economy of the server might balance out the error over time, many players who had never acquired a single rare tradeskill item, now might have hundreds of them. SOE made the decision to begin rolling back the characters who purchased items from the vendors and all of those who had traded with them down the line.</p>

<p>One can imagine the web of transactions between those who originally traded with a rogue vendor and any of those who had contact with them and so on down the line. Imagine a single piece of platinum coated with a poison that spreads to whoever holds it and anything they possess. Whenever any infected coin or item changes hands, another character and all of their possessions become infected. When it reaches the bazaar, it can flood hundreds more.</p>

<p>SOE contained the spread of the rogue items and all of the affected players forty eight hours after the servers originally came up. Every character touched by anyone or anything that could be traced back to the original vendors was rolled back to their last save point before the patch.</p>

<p>Rolling back certain characters resulted in strange lapses in the state between one character and another. One character hands an item to another character. The second character is rolled back to a previous state but the first character, having given an item and not received one, is not rolled back. This results in the loss of the original item.</p>

<p>Erana, an enchanter on Quellious, was one such victim. Erana, her bazaar vendor, and some friends transferred some equipment including a Manastone, an item of great power that no longer drops anywhere in Everquest. While most of these characters were rolled back including the new possesser of the Manastone, the original holder of the Manastone was not. This resulted in the Manastone becoming lost in the void between mismatched rollbacks. Like thousands of others, Erana began the painful process of navigating a complex petition form to contact customer service in the hopes of recovering her Manastone. She cares little for other items lost over the two day rollback, she can always replace those, but the Manastone is irreplaceable.</p>

<p>Though this example is extremely rare and most likely the exception, Erana's tale is not unique and some stories are worse. Some players lost entire corpses full of their most valuable possessions due to the paradoxical states between rollbacks. A player dies and leaves a body behind before the patch. After the patch they recover the body but become poisoned by a tainted transaction. The rollback leaves them in a state before they had recovered their body but now with no body to recover.</p>

<p>While these lost corpses are very rare, they are paralyzing and dismaying to those affected. A lost corpse can mean the end of a character. SOE's customer service almost always returns the body to the victim but it can take a long time for a response, a time when the player nearly convinces himself or herself that all is lost.</p>

<p>Most frustrating is the fact that many of the players rolled back did nothing out of the ordinary. They did not try to get rich quick on low-priced ultra-rare tradeskill items. They did not try to exploit a bug in the game. They might have accepted some coin for a buff or bought some emeralds in the bazaar. They might have transferred some gear from one character to another and lost nearly everything of value. Even if they didn't lose a body or gear, many lost all of the progress made in two days worth of play time. One player, returning to Everquest with Everquest Titanium, a $20 package including the base game and ten expansions, wrote of his confusion at losing levels and equipment for something he didn't even understand.</p>

<p>From the time of the initial discovery of the rogue merchants the Everquest forums exploded with posts of rage, frustration, arguments, and threats. It becomes nearly impossible to uncover the truth as angry players post rumors, assumed statistics, threats, vague details, and overdramatic outcries. One full thread of posts discussed the impact of another rogue vendor who gave out alternate advanced points when players handed them a single platinum piece. SOE developers spent time away from the real issues to dig into every script that could possibly result in a situation like this only to find out that it had never happened. No such vendor existed on the live servers, the beta servers, or anywhere else. Other players reported the losses of millions of platinum pieces, hundreds of alternate advanced points, tens of levels, and entire suits of new equipment - far greater results than any player can earn in a two-day period.</p>

<p>These exaggerations took much away from the real stories of those directly affected. High-end raiders lost two nights worth of victories in difficult raid zones, bazaar traders and tradeskillers lost two days worth of profits, mid-level hunters lost levels earned over two days of hunting.</p>

<p>At midnight on 20 January 2006, Chris Lena, the Everquest Producer, wrote a letter of apology and explained the direct results of the error and the effects. Chris stated that less than 1% of existing Everquest character were effected by the rollbacks and that customer service would help with lost corpses and guild membership status but not with lost items. Later, SOE announced that it would help with the recovery of lost epic items or epic quest pieces as well as offering a double experience bonus starting Saturday morning on 21 January and ending the following Monday. Due to some technical difficulties Saturday morning, the double experience weekend was extended until Tuesday morning.</p>

<p>The decision to roll back certain characters over a 48 hour period meant that many players unaffected by the poisoned transactions saw little change at all. It did, however, let the transactions continue to spread as the players rolled back. Taking down the servers and rolling back every character, affected or not, might have had many of the same problems faced already but with less of the paradoxical state for the lost 48 hours. Only SOE has the data to truly determine which method would lead to the best outcome.</p>

<p>Many posts questioned the 1% affected rate stated in Chris Lena's letter. It seems everyone knew someone, often more than one who was rolled back and lost time, items, money, or all three. Some entire guilds were affected as guild bankers became tainted and spread the poison out to every guild member who touched the bank. Again, no one outside of SOE knows exactly the number affected, but those who play most often, those with the widest social circles, were the most likely to become affected.</p>

<p>Yet the numbers matter little to those who lost much during a rollback. To the player who loses a corpse full of their hard-earned equipment or another player who loses a priceless artifact from a quick trade in the bazaar, the results are all that matter.</p>

<p>Now is as good a time as any for SOE to consider re-looking at their choice for equipment loss on death. At the Everquest Summit in September 2005, Craig Knapp begain the discussion of Everquest's death system. With recent games choosing alternate penalties for death instead of equipment loss, SOE should consider a new death system that lets players respawn with gear and receive another penalty - a "death effect" perhaps - to off-set the benefit of returning fully equipped.</p>

<p>While the psychological advantage of returning fully equipped is strong, situations like these recent rollbacks build a much stronger case. Players don't ever want to lose equipment. In today's new world of massive online games, equipment loss is too strong a penalty that effects the wrong set of players - the lower and middle level players who have few tools for corpse recovery and a smaller network of friends to assist.</p>

<p>If you are one of these player, what can you do? Be patient and persistant. Be polite and understanding. If you've lost a body or irreplacable gear, keep working with CS to try to recover it. Don't accept no for an answer but don't hurt your case with rudeness.</p>

<p>With a letter of apology and a weekend of double experience, SOE hopes to put the event back into the pages of history. While the situation will no doubt fade over time as the CS teams recover all that can be recovered and the rest of us move on with our adventures, the week of the Great Rollback will not likely become forgotten.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
21 January 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>

<p>Update:  Erana, the enchanter in the article above, received her manastone back on 30 January 2005.  Many reports came in from those who lost items in the rollback and eventually had them recovered by SOE's Customer Service staff.</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Further Prophecies and the Everquest Expansion Release Cycle</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001456.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-08T13:11:12Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-01-16T19:44:47-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1456</id>
    <created>2006-01-17T00:44:47Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">In today&apos;s article Loral talks about the recent Everquest and Prophecy of Ro news and then digs in to a popular and controvercial topic: the Everquest expansion release cycle.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>First, a look at the news:</p>

<p>The beta for the new expansion <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&amp;message.id=161906">began last week</a>, with beta requests succeeding sporatically as players hit the site.  Those invited into the beta are sworn to secrecy, not only on what wonders they see but even their attendance within the beta itself.  Silence itself becomes a clue.</p>

<p>SOE posted some new information to the Prophecy of Ro website including <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50053">two videos</a>.  One video shows the rebuild of Freeport including all new Freeport militia barracks, <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/expansions/prophecyofro/images/prophecyofro4.jpg">a new dock</a>, and the new temple of Marr.  The second video shows off some of the new zones in Prophecy.  The zones definitely look other-worldly.  SOE also announced a rebuild of both Freeport and the Desert of Ro released to everyone, whether you purchase Prophecy or not.</p>

<p>Contrary to the premature complaints on the forums, Prophecy of Ro will include both high-end and mid-level content.  The newly revamped Desert of Ro and Freeport zones will offer some new content for lower and mid-level folks while higher-end raiders will find new challenges as well.</p>

<p>Raging Fury was the <a href="http://www.lavanet.no/rf/">first to defeat Mistmoore</a> and later, SOE's Kytherea posted an <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50052">interview with the guild</a>.  In response to raid-tuning criticism, Prathun, the designer of the Demiplane of Blood and many of the high-end raids since Gates, <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&amp;message.id=161910#M161910">talked about the tuning of the Demiplane</a>:</p>

<p>"The Demi-Plane of Blood was completed, start to finish, without any retuning.  That's nine end-game raids in three tiers that didn't need developer spying, gradually reducing the toughness, or removing hard features.  Guilds that beat Redfang, Zi-Thuuli, Hatchet, Sisters, Devlin, Tris, Roley, the Performer, and Mayong killed version 1.0.  Every time."</p>

<p>The guild Assent <a href="http://eq.nitrous.org/eq/media/">released a video</a> of their journey through the Depths of Darkhollow including a couple of clips of Mayong Mistmoore, the official end-boss of Depths.  Mayong's death resulted in a <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50054">new bit of lore</a> leading to the Prophecy of Ro.  </p>

<p>Chris Lena, producer of Everquest, recently <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/news_article.vm?id=50059">gave an interview</a> on EQPlayers.  Along with his Neil-Gaiman-like picture, Chris gave an excellent Kurt-Vonniguty answer to the question "How did you choose [Raghnell's] name?"</p>

<p>"I didn't  it was fated since before the dawn of humankind. So it is written and so it shall be."</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/B000CPSHFS/">Everquest Titanium</a>, the $20 Everquest package including the base game, all ten expansions, and a 30 day subscription, has been released.  This is the easiest it's ever been to get into EQ.</p>

<p>Now on to our hot topic of the day:  The Everquest Expansion Release Cycle.</p>

<p>Ever since the release of Planes of Power, a massive expansion with nearly a year-long development cycle, SOE released expansions every six months.  Only once, after the release of Gates of Discord, was an expansion delayed, and then it was only for a month.  Every other expansion; Ykesha, LDON, Omens, Dragons, Depths, and now Prophecy; has come out or will come out every six months.</p>

<p>Every time a new expansion is released the boards light up with angry posts.  Most of these are from the "fix bugs" category (don't worry, I don't plan to gloss over this one so easily) but some dig into other thoughts and ideas.</p>

<p>Here are a few reasons people get upset about the six-month development cycle:  bugs from the previous expansion, class balance issues, haven't finished a lot of the content in previous expansion yet, one's raiding guild hasn't defeated the last boss yet, $30 every six months on top of $15 a month is a lot of money, the next expansion will come out buggy, one just got to a certain power level and doesn't want to have to get to a next one.  All of these are valid issues and all deserve a deeper look.</p>

<p>I have often dismissed the "fix bugs" reason mostly because those bringing it up don't follow through with a list of the bugs they want fixed.  Often the bugs turn out to be class balance problems - not real bugs, but there ARE real bugs that need to be addressed.  The best thing we can do is articulate this list and bring it up when we can instead of using a more generic call for bug fixing.</p>

<p>Whether or not these bugs would be fixed with a different release cycle is unknown.  We can assume, from the outside, that by delaying an expansion SOE could fix bugs instead of building new content, but given the unknown economic model, we can't say whether or not they'd have to cut back on the number of people on the developers team to make up for the lack of expansion money coming in.  Those bugs might last just as long whether there is a new expansion every six months or every year.  That doesn't mean bugs shouldn't be fixed, though.  It means we need to do our best to bring them to the attention of the developers and watch their progress ourselves.</p>

<p>Content progression is another big argument against the six-month development cycle.  A lot of raiders aren't able to finish the raid content in a new expansion before the next expansion comes out.  There is a careful balance between too much and too little raid content, it seems, and while some powerful guilds will have farmed the top encounters for months - others struggle to get past raid encounters from expansions long past.</p>

<p>The situation doesn't improve for single-group hunters.  There's often a lot of content unused by single-group hunters.  Some go immediately to newer and more rewarding content in newer expansions while some stay in the older hunting areas where they know exactly what to expect.  Many players who rely on pickup groups for progression have to move where the bulk of the players go - whether it is to new expansions or staying in old ones.</p>

<p>Can there be too much content?  Can't groups simply pick the areas they want to go, picking through the vast quantities of possibilities in search of the most fun and rewarding ones?  A lot of these problems require a different train of thought.  Everquest isn't a game with an ending (one of the reasons I hate the term "end-game").  Very very few ever hit every single major encounter in the game.  Accepting that many of us will never exhaust an expansion would help us more enjoy the content we do face.  At that point it becomes a question of whether or not we get our money's worth from each expansion.</p>

<p>Is $30 every six months for a new expansion worth it? It's up to each of us to decide.  No one forces us to buy a new expansion, though the drive of the other players makes the desire for new expansions different from single-player game expansions.  Ultimately, however, we vote with our dollar.  If the features and content aren't enough to interest us, we shouldn't buy it.  Most of the time, however, the features and content are enough to get us interested.  Compared to the $50 to $60 for single-player games, $30 for an expansion in which we may spend hundreds of hours is not a bad deal.  It's always important to remember that our true power in this game is our wallets.  If it's not what we want or we don't want it yet because we haven't finished the last one, we shouldn't buy it.</p>

<p>World of Warcraft changed the face of massive online games in many ways.  One element that may have led to its success is the sheer amount of polish.  It plays well and it plays clean.  There are bugs but they're hard to find and while other games may have one struggling to move around an interface, Warcraft builds a seamless world around you.  Blizzard is also spending up to two years of development time on their first new expansion.  Likely it will be as polished as the initial game.  Already they have people betatesting it, over six months from the release.  There is something to be said for taking that sort of time to clean up a product.</p>

<p>Is six months too short?  That's a hard question to answer.  We cannot say for sure that we would receive better products or better support if the cycle increased.  We simply do not know the full economics of SOE's business to say for sure how things will come out.  Before the days of Planes of Power they had much longer development cycles but bugs still existed.  They aren't worse today than they were back then.  Content still had to be tuned and retuned.</p>

<p>Personally, I always look forward to the newer expansions. I love seeing this world grow.  I like having vast amounts of content from which to pick and choose.  I like growing in power and seeing new places.  I always fondly remember my first days in a new expansion.  There are no expansions where I feel like I didn't get my $30 worth.  Sure, I get vexed when I think about Dragons and realize that most of my time there was in Creator missions.  Sure, I'm mad at the sheer amount of difficult or locked content in Gates.  I still spent many many hours, hours where I was highly entertained, in those expansions.</p>

<p>This topic has many facets and many of them, the business ones, are unknown to us.  As players we can do our best to tell SOE what we want, what we want fixed, show them what we are willing to pay for, and show them what we are not.  It isn't our responsibility to tell them how to run their business. It is our job to tell them and show them what we desire.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
16 January 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Expansion Announcement: Prophecy of Ro</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001454.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2006-01-03T20:19:34-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2006://7.1454</id>
    <created>2006-01-04T01:19:34Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today SOE announces the eleventh Everquest expansion: Prophecy of Ro.  In this article we look at the announced features, some juicy screenshots, and ponder the future with what little information we have.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Today Sonly Online Entertainment <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&message.id=254">announced the coming release</a> of Everquest's eleventh expansion, <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/expansions/prophecyofro/">Prophecy of Ro</a>.</p>

<p>The Press Release focused mainly on the new features of the expansion including breakable objects, traps, and Spheres of Influence.  The press release is vague on detail so we can only speculate on what these features mean.</p>

<p>It will be hard to get excited over breakable objects.  We saw them in EQ2 and once you've picked up a table and thrown it through a window in Half Life 2, smashing open a barrel just isn't the same.  Larger scale breakable objects, like castles falling out of the sky or orc-laden bridges collapsing into the depths of a cavern would add a lot of excitement.  Currently, however, details on the exact meaning are slim.</p>

<p>The same can be said for the two other features.  Spheres of Influence are described as localized areas where the rules of the game can change to aid allies or thwart enemies.  For example, sandstorms may be called down to blind anyone who enters an area.  Both player created and environmentally created spheres may drastically alter the battlefield.  How these spheres will effect player versus player combat is also unknown.</p>

<p>Traps should also effect the battleground before combat begins.  We can only speculate that these traps will be similar to the hunter's traps in World of Warcraft.  Players set the traps, lure the mobs into them, and hit them with nasty effects.  These traps will not be rogue-only, but rogues will have more versatility with them than other classes.  Players will also face some devious traps in their adventures.</p>

<p>Again, the press release is vague on the details of these three features so hopefully we will learn more about them soon.</p>

<p>Other minor features are more specific and sound quite useful.  Buff filters will let players select which buffs they want to avoid.  This mainly effects high-end players who hit the limit of buffs quickly.  Eight new bank slots add a total of ninety six new available slots.  That should help tradeskillers quite a bit.  New spells, tradeskills, tasks (solo quests I assume), and disciplines are also mentioned but not AAs.  We might see some Dragons-style AAs won over the course of missions or quests but I don't think we'll see entire new banks of AAs like we saw in Depths of Darkhollow.</p>

<p>Digging into the content, Prophecy of Ro will contain seven static zones and thirty missions, including monster missions.  The press release also mentions six small instances but I expect those are the zones used for the thirty missions.  The expansion will include new monster missions but overall we will not see as many missions as we did in Depths of Darkhollow.</p>

<p>The scaled difficulty of the expansion is also mostly unknown although raids will be scoped for Demiplane of Blood and Anguish-level guilds.  Smaller events will likely start at Time / Elemental level and go up from there.  The number of these events and raids is, you guessed it, currently unknown.</p>

<p>More interesting than the press release itself was the press kit I received later.  The following nine screenshots were included and released for publication:</p>

<p style="text-align: center"><a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Arcstone1.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Arcstone1_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Arcstone4.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Arcstone4_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Dissonance1.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Dissonance1_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Dissonance6.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Dissonance6_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport15.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport15_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport2.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport2_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport22.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Freeport22_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/FreeportSewer2.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/FreeportSewer2_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a> <a href="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Relic1.jpg"><img src="http://mobhunter.com/por_images/Relic1_t.jpg" height="150" width="200" /></a></p>

<p>The names of the images are nearly as interesting as the images themselves:  Dissonance, Relic, Arcstone, and Freeport.  I don't think we have to guess very hard to figure out which old-world zone is getting a makeover.  This discovery alone brings up many new questions.  Will Freeport be a new hub?  Is SOE planning on revamping other major cities?  How will SOE get more players to spend time there when newer city zones like Abysmal Sea go mostly unused?</p>

<p>The story behind Prophecy seems to focus back on our time with the gods in Planes of Power.  A new diety seems to be causing catastrophic events to unwind and only the adventurers of Norrath can help.  From the screenshots above, it appears new Planes may be in our future.</p>

<p>Like most details, we do not know how SOE will handle loot in Prophecy of Ro.  The point system of Dragons led to bottomfeeding at the easiest missions to acquire loot.  Depth of Darkhollow's one-time loot resulted in a lot of nice gear from a variety of missions but only for a few slots. It isn't uncommon to walk away from Depths of Darkhollow with five different neck items or four shoulder items.  This resulted in a lot of wasted loot.</p>

<p>Neither of these two previous systems seem ideal but they did have advantages.  With those systems, players did not compete for items against other group items.  Random drops off of rare mobs was not the only way to earn gear anymore.  Hopefully new hybrid systems can help players earn appropriate rewards for appropriate challenges and reward them for facing a variety of challenges instead of the same one over and over again.</p>

<p>It's hard to follow an expansion like Depths of Darkhollow.  Monster missions added a unique and powerful feature to Everquest - one that has already changed how people think and play the game.  Breakable environments, traps, and spheres of influence just aren't as exciting.  Likewise, including half of the missions contained in Depths of Darkhollow makes it clearly sound like a smaller expansion than Depths both in powerful features and in pure content.  Yet the price is the same.</p>

<p>Granted, the time spent in Everquest expansions far exceeds the time spent on more expensive games with less content, but when one considers players paid the same amount for huge expansions like Planes of Power, one comes to expect more for our dollar than what we expect from other games.</p>

<p>This announcement also comes amid lengthy discussions on the Everquest expansion release schedule, a topic of heated debate since the rumors of Prophecy started nearly three weeks ago.  I will take a deeper look into this topic in a future article to see exactly where these frustrations come from.</p>

<p>The full scope of this expansion is still not known to us.  Until more information becomes available, we can only work with speculation and conjecture.  More details will surely come soon.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
3 January 2006<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Titanium Prophecies</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001445.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-12-19T14:26:59-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1445</id>
    <created>2005-12-19T19:26:59Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we discuss the release of EQ Players, the leak of Prophecy of Ro, the announcement of Everquest Titanium, the most recent Everquest patch, the progress of Depths of Darkhollow, and John Smedley&apos;s interview on the state of massive online games.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>We've had a couple of busy weeks so let's dive right in.</p>

<p>A new producer takes the helm at the Everquest Live development team.  As Craig Knapp moves off to a new project, Chris Lena takes over as the Everquest Producer.  Chris introduced himself in his first Everquest Producer's letter after attending the <a href="http://eq.stratics.com/content/hoclogs/20051214.php">most recent Everquest Developer's chat</a> over at Stratics.  The <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Veterans&amp;message.id=151681">players congratulated Chris</a> on his promotion and Caster's Realm posted an <a href="http://eq.crgaming.com/viewarticle.asp?Article=10010">interview with the new producer</a>.</p>

<p>I found this quote interesting:</p>

<p>"One of the issues is that many people feel a little intimidated by the sheer amount of content  it can be daunting. We are working on some things to address that as well but I can't say anything else on that at this time."</p>

<p>Here's another quote to stick in your scrapbook and come back to in five years:</p>

<p>"EverQuest will definitely be around a lot longer than 5 years."</p>

<p>Last week an accidental slip on the forum list revealed what is most likely the name of the next Everquest expansion, Prophecy of Ro.  While no SOE represenative validated the name, none worked to quell the rumors either.  Like every expansion since LDON, some players were very excited at the new prospect while others gave the same complaints we have heard for four years: "no new expansions, fix bugs!"</p>

<p>Everquest expansions have come out every six months since Planes of Power.  The days of the yearly Everquest expansion are over.  SOE stated at previous summits that they regularly see a drop off at the five to six month mark in any expansion release with a clear jump in subscriptions shortly after an expansion's release.</p>

<p>Six month expansions are the pulse of a healthy game.  They regularly improve and add upon the existing game, giving players new content and features that go well beyond typical class reenvisionment issues or bug fixes.</p>

<p>Bugs need to be fixed.  None of us have any doubt about this, but holding up expansions for smaller bug fixes will not help the health of the game.  Players don't return to EQ because the boats started working again, they return to see features like monster missions, single group adventures, and new high-end raid content.</p>

<p>I expect we will hear more about the new expansion in January with a release probably in February or March of 2006.</p>

<p>On Thursday, 15 December 2006, SOE released <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/">EQ Players</a>, a website that ties into Everquest more than any other website before.  The EQ Players website closely matches the EQ2 Players website of Everquest 2 and includes features such as a live character page, character rankings, guild listings, leader boards, image galleries, item data, and spell data.  While systems like Magelo helped players keep track of their fancy gear so they could drool over it while pretending to work, the EQ Players site automatically updates itself as your character improves.  So now you can see exactly what <a href="http://eqplayers.station.sony.com/character_profile.vm?characterId=536870914344">Loral is truly like</a>.  Oops, I forgot to take off my Turtlebone ring!</p>

<p>The site's release was not without controversy.  Eighteen of the twenty webservers used to host the site did not work correctly resulting in lousy performance for the first couple of days.  Connecting EQ Players to the live game also created some problems resulting in two or three patches within a 24 hour period.  One of Chris Lena's first public jobs was to <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=Crier&amp;message.id=247">apologise for the issues</a>.</p>

<p>Other players were <a href="http://eqforums.station.sony.com/eq/board/message?board.id=eqplayers&message.id=1029">concerned about privacy</a>.  While the site allows characters to remove or restrict their listings and rankings, doing so requires active participation.  Some feel that the privacy of those who do not yet know or understand the site is missing.  Frankly, I think the site would be a lot less fun if it only had forty or fifty showoffs while the rest of the world hid in indifference.  No real private data is revealed, there are no account titles or personal information.  If players are really concerned that people will find out what hat they wear, they can always remove their listing.</p>

<p>Earlier this week SOE also announced the Everquest Titanium pack for release in January 2006.  This pack will contain the base game, a free 30 day subscription, and all ten expansion packs including Depths of Darkhollow for $20.  This is the first time a new player can buy the entire game for this low a cost.  Unfortunately, the pack's release misses the holiday rush, and within one to two months of its release, a new expansion will also be released upping the total cost of Everquest to $50.  Still, considering the cost of $80 to $100 before, this is a much better deal.</p>

<p>This holiday season, SOE also offered up a 21 day free account reactiviation for old players.  If you no longer play EQ but want to see how the world has changed, now is a good time to go see.  Unfortunately, reactivated players won't be able to try out some of the new features like Monster Missions or Spirit Shrouds, but at least they can poke their heads around and see what is new.</p>

<p>A patch on 7 December 2005 added a few new changes.  A change to the monster missions now requires every member to enter the mission and receive a crystal in order to earn experience.  This was included to prevent players earning experience without ever even attending the mission.  Though a fair change that does little to increase the difficulty of monster missions, some players hiding under the flag of "Casual gamer" claimed that this change hurt their ability to match high-end hunters.  No element of the game should ever reward experience with no effort.  Earning up to an AA of experience without moving reveals a broken system.  That system is now fixed.</p>

<p>A new Arena also finally made it from Stormhammer to the live servers.</p>

<p>Speaking of Stormhammer, it appears the elite server will soon close its doors.  The high monthly cost for negligible improvement resulted in very few players on the server.  While some felt that SOE could have done more to make the server attractive, it was unlikely that SOE could spare the resources for such a gamble.  Closing the server and moving the players seemed the only reasonable choice.  When I saw the numbers of active players on Stormhammer in comparison to other servers at the last Summit, it was clear to me that this was the only choice.</p>

<p>The difficulty of Overlord Mata Muram came up during the last Developer's Chat.  A player asked if the end-boss of Omens of War would have his difficulty reduced considering the small number of guilds guilds able to defeat him.  Rashere stated that while probably too difficult, OMM would remain at his current difficulty as a sign of guild power.  Within 24 hours of his statement, two new guilds defeated Overlord Mata Muram bringing the total number to twenty.  OMM still remains undefeated on some servers including my home server of Quellious.</p>

<p>The second tier of the Demiplane of Blood, the most powerful raiding zone in Everquest, has been entered.  Many adventurers whisper rumors of the identity of the final encounter in the zone.  <a href="http://www.lavanet.no/rf/">Raging Fury</a> has some excellent descriptions of the latest high-end raiding encounters.</p>

<p>If you are more of a single-group hunter, like myself, you may find <a href="http://samanna.net/gen.info/prog.dod.shtml">Samanna's Guide to Depths of Darkhollow Missions</a> useful.  This single-page guide has every mission, reward, and progression tree for over fifty Depths of Darkhollow non-monster missions.</p>

<p>Pontificating about massive online games became a new past time of mine since writing for Mobhunter.  I found the website <a href="http://terranova.blogs.com/">Terra Nova</a> to be a very interesting academic look at massive online games.  Richard Bartle, the programmer of the world's first multiuser dungeon, writes for them on topics ranging from <a href="http://terranova.blogs.com/terra_nova/2005/12/nytimes_tracks_.html">economics</a> to <a href="http://terranova.blogs.com/terra_nova/2005/12/the_transparent.html">reward systems</a>.  It's a great read.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.gamespot.com/pages/news/story.php?sid=6141213">Gamespot's interview with John Smedley</a> had some interesting things to say about the recent Star Wars Galaxies changes.  A recent Wired article titled <a href="http://www.wired.com/news/print/0,1294,69816,00.html">Star Wars Fans Flee Net Galaxy</a> discussed the exodus of older players due to a more action-based feel.  In the interview, Smedley discusses the failure of sandbox games (the Sims, Second Life) compared to goal-oriented games (Everquest, Warcraft).  He also talks about a lot of interesting topics including cross platform gaming on any device, massive online games on the PSO, and players in South Korea being unable to put down cigarettes to use the keyboard.  It's a great read.</p>

<p>Here's another quote to add to your scrap book:</p>

<p>"People within the company feel so much pride in this game that they want it to beat the crap out of World of Warcraft."</p>

<p>With <a href="http://www.blizzard.com/press/051028-burningcrusade.shtml">four and a half million players</a>, <a href="http://worldofwarcraft.com/burningcrusade/">a new expansion on the way</a>, and being the <a href="http://ve3d.ign.com/articles/676/676865p1.html">number five best selling game a year after release</a>, World of Warcraft has a pretty big ass to kick.</p>

<p>Loral Ciriclight<br />
19 December 2005<br />
loral@loralciriclight.com</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Interview with Prathun on Everquest Raids</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mobhunter.com/001443.html" />
    <modified>2006-02-05T22:56:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-12-05T15:36:48-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:mobhunter.com,2005://7.1443</id>
    <created>2005-12-05T20:36:48Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Today we have a Mobhunter Exclusive interview with Prathun, the lead Everquest raid designer and most experienced raid designer in the world for massive online games.</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Loral</name>
      
      <email>loral@healersunited.com</email>
    </author>
    
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://mobhunter.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>On my first guild summit nearly two years ago I met a designer and bent his ear as I bent so many with my gushing praise for LDON and my desires for an LDON 2.  The kind man nodded and smiled enthusiastically, mentioning their own feelings with the release of LDON and their own desires for a system like that in the future (what became today's mission system). Little did I know I was speaking to the legendary Prathun, Johnathan Caraker, the main raid designer for Everquest since the days of Gates of Discord.</p>

<p>Prathun is the most experienced raid designer in the Massive Online Gaming industry.  His Everquest resume includes most of the Epic 1.5 and 2.0 raids, all of the single group and raid trials of the Muramite Proving Grounds, all of the dragon raids in Dragons of Norrath, the design of Dreadspire, and all of the raid encounters in the current peak of high-end raiding, the Demiplane of Blood.</p>

<p>Today we give you a Mobhunter exclusive interview with Prathun on the past, present, and future of raid content in Everquest.</p>

<p>Loral: What sort of decisions go into the design of a raid encounter?</p>

<p>Prathun: It might be easier to ask, "What decisions don't go into the design of raid encounters?"  We have choices to make about the lore behind the task, its complexity, the intended difficulty, loot rewards, involvement with the expansion progression, and intended time investment.  </p>

<p>While risk and reward decisions are obviously crucial to the creation of a well-balanced raid, lore is an often underestimated aspect of the design.  A well-developed character with history and roots in the story of EverQuest is more interesting to pit players against than an entity no one has heard of.</p>

<p>Loral: How have you seen raids and raid design change over the years?</p>

<p>Prathun: I've seen raid design come a long way since original EverQuest.  Looking back at the early years of the game, encounters were typically a single mob with a few spell abilities attached.  As our scripting language has matured, it's opened up the opportunity to mold some truly unique and interesting events.  Raid mobs can change their attributes over the course of the fight, react to the strategies of the players, and even exhibit artificial intelligence that feels almost human.  </p>

<p>The Proving Ground Trial of Corruption is a good example of the latter.  It pits the raid against NPCs that mimic the behavior of player characters:  the warriors can call out for assists, clerics heal those in need, wizards who root players then back away to nuke them, and monks with the ability to feign and mend themselves when brought to low health.</p>

<p>Loral: How have raiders changed in their attitudes and feedback towards raids?  How do raiders today compare to the raiders of five years ago?</p>

<p>Prathun: Experience has taught raiders how to deal with the basics of positioning, healing, and adds, so it wouldn't be possible for me to get away with the same kinds of raids that existed five years ago.  A big NPC that hits hard and has a few damage AEs isn't going to present any interesting challenge to current raiding organizations.  They've all "been there, done that" and could complete that kind of raid blindfolded.  </p>

<p>As for the attitudes and feedback part of the question - they haven't changed a bit. :)</p>

<p>Loral: There has been a recent trend since Omens to require more from each individual member of a raid.  This has spawned both positive and negative feedback.  How do you see this new style of raid design evolving in the future?</p>

<p>Prathun: Oddly enough, I would classify a fun raid versus a poorly designed one by that criteria:  does everyone on the raid have something to do?  Do all participants have a meaningful role in the event, a reason for being there, and an opportunity to affect the outcome?  I want to make sure that everyone at a raid is playing the game, not semi-afk waiting for the chance to bid on loot, so you can expect to see more raids that require attention from all attendees in the future. </p>

<p>The traditional means of accomplishing this goal is to present challenges that play to all classes' strengths.  I try to give offtanks something to offtank, crowd controllers mobs to mesmerize or charm, curing classes debuff spells to cure, and so on.  The other means of accomplishing the goal is to present generic tasks that are critical to the success of the raid but can be completed by any class.  Examples would be having to kite a cursebearer in Inktu`Ta, responding to a gaze from Mata Muram, or being in charge of the moon relic when facing Vule.</p>

<p>Loral: How do you decide what power level to design raids for in a new expansion?  When is it appropriate for Anguish or Demiplane of Blood content as opposed to Elemental or Time level content?</p>

<p>Prathun: While there's always been some overlap between expansions, we try to raise the bar and introduce new challenges every expansion, especially when the players gain a significant increase in power via levels, AAs, spells, or gear.  The power level decisions touch on raid design, itemization, and expansion progression, so they're hashed out by several key people early in the design process.  The intended difficulty of a raid is set in stone long before I ever sit down and start brainstorming the mechanics behind it.</p>

<p>Loral: Raid balancing and retuning seems common these days.  Can you explain the problems with tuning raid content before and after the release of an expansion?  Why do we always see such radical shifts in raid balance after release?</p>

<p>Prathun: We've discovered that it is near impossible to emulate the circumstances of a Live server environment on Beta.  Guilds perform differently when real loot is on the line, have better turnouts on Live than Beta, and they'll conjure up unconventional strategies that aren't attempted when a developer is watching over their shoulder.  Beta testing has been invaluable for testing the concept of a raid and ferreting out functionality bugs, but it hasn't been 100% effective in hitting the difficulty bullseye.  </p>

<p>I am fairly content with how the Demi-Plane of Blood has turned out.  While it has seen tuning changes and will certainly see more in the future, they won't be the dreaded 'radical shifts'.</p>

<p>Loral: How do you determine the number of players a raid should require?  How does this effect the design and testing of a raid?</p>

<p>Prathun: Generally speaking, the higher the difficulty level of the encounter, the more players it will require, the more complex the design, and the harder it will be to test.  Our established player count for end-game raids is 48-54, eight to nine groups.  </p>

<p>A large part of the difficulty of these end-game fights is in maintaining a roster of well-geared and reliable players that are available to tackle the encounters on a regular basis.  This doesn't translate well to single-group content.  There's no fair way to approximate the coordination of organizing a Demi-Plane raid and apply that same challenge and reward to six people. As for testing, a small event can often be tested by a hodgepodge of assorted players on the Beta server, but a full guild is needed to put an end-game raid to the test.  Anything less is a waste of time.</p>

<p>Loral: You mention tying high-end raids to the roots of Everquest history but few of the high-end raid targets are known by anyone other than those who activly raid against them.  How do you plan to bring more of the lore of high-end encounters to the rest of the players?  For example, in Depths, most any players can see the transformation of Emperor Draygun to a lich in the excellent monster mission "Fall of Illsalin".  Do you plan to continue this sort of trend?</p>

<p>Prathun: Absolutely.  I'm a big fan of introducing the antagonists early and often, and there are many ways to accomplish this.  Tirranun stormed through Lavastorm and screamed at the mortals for daring to trespass in his domain when Dragons of Norrath launched.  The major players in Velious were described in stories that were featured in the game's instruction manual.  Gorenaire and The Cragbeast Queen were figured prominently in areas where anyone could see them.  </p>

<p>The raid encounters in the Demi-Plane of Blood are described by the inhabitants of Dreadspire - you can hear the Wailing Sisters crying near the guest rooms, and the watch often catches a glimpse of Zi-Thuuli off in the distance.  The best way to bring the lore to the players is by letting them experience it firsthand, as in the Fall of Illsalin monster mission you mentioned.  To Oshran's credit, that mission arc was an amazing bit of storytelling.</p>

<p>Loral: What sorts of things can we expect to see in the future of Everquest's raid content?</p>

<p>Prathun: Without revealing too much, I'd like to point out that there's going to be some familiar faces from EverQuest history making an appearance in the near future!</p>

<p>Loral: Thank you very much for taking the time to speak with us.</p>

<p>Prathun: Thank you for the opportunity!</p>]]>
      

    </content>
  </entry>

</feed>