<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>&quot;Most raiding guilds have recruitment periods in which you don&apos;t receive any loot. You sit</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;Most raiding guilds have recruitment periods in which you don&apos;t receive any loot. You sit on the sidelines, work on what you have been told to work on, watch and listen, and wait for chance to get into raid. Once in raid, you have to prove to the GL, all the officers, and the majority of the other members that you can assist, control your pet, manage your aggro, cast the correct spells, follow directions, learn the strats, etc. Make to</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Sorry, no hazing.  We don&apos;t even have a secret handshake. QQ</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Sorry, no hazing.  We don&apos;t even have a secret handshake. QQ</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>It would be a stern (and some may say wasteful) raiding guild that would let there raid loot actuall</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>It would be a stern (and some may say wasteful) raiding guild that would let there raid loot actually rot. So even your Probies will pick up some &apos;uber gear&apos; shortly before they get booted out.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Letting the loot rot (and making it well known that you will) is a great way to keep the riff-raff f</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Letting the loot rot (and making it well known that you will) is a great way to keep the riff-raff from joining in the first place.

I must say I&apos;m surprised and pleased by how much support there is for shrinking the gap between raid and non-raid gear so non-raiders can play in the high-end zones. What a refreshing change from the olden days--remember the arguments that GoD had all sorts of great gear for non-raiders and if they didn&apos;t </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;Letting the loot rot (and making it well known that you will) is a great way to keep the riff-</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;Letting the loot rot (and making it well known that you will) is a great way to keep the riff-raff from joining in the first place.&quot;

Letting items rot while newcomers are on a recruitment period is actually good policy for a raiding guild. Callous as it may sound to a non-raider, it don&apos;t hurt the recruit. Items rot because for several reasons, one of them being that its extremely common. Rikkukin BPs for instance. If they don&ap</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>At the cost of being huge elitists @$$hats</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>At the cost of being huge elitists @$$hats</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The real @$$hats are the people who think they deserve to loot any item by riding on the coattails o</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The real @$$hats are the people who think they deserve to loot any item by riding on the coattails of people who have put effort gaining access.  If you can&apos;t even put forth a fraction of that effort to participate in events for a couple weeks, don&apos;t expect 50+ people to suddenly make you &quot;uber&quot;.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>First, such equipment dropping that way is really a silly design issue more than anything. If SoE re</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>First, such equipment dropping that way is really a silly design issue more than anything. If SoE really wanted you to &quot;earn&quot; the right to use the equipment it all would be tied to quests and/or tasks.

Second, both are @$$hats, the leaches that just want to piggy ride to gear themselves, and the elitists that step over everyone just because there are a few leaches around.

But since the elitist is the one in power, they are entirely fr</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I don&apos;t see it as elitism, I see it as self defense.

I was never in a raider guild, but I was </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I don&apos;t see it as elitism, I see it as self defense.

I was never in a raider guild, but I was in a family guild that raided enough to get epics (1.0, when they were still a fairly big deal). We had several people join us for a couple months, constantly bug us to schedule raids for their epic pieces, and then move on to serious raiding guilds when they were done. Needless to say it was not appreciated and we felt very much taken advantage of</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>In that vein I&apos;ve been in Loral&apos;s guild for years, which is a family guild that is devoted</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>In that vein I&apos;ve been in Loral&apos;s guild for years, which is a family guild that is devoted to randomly buffing people and helping people out. I&apos;m remembering back to this one cleric who was in the guild for a long time and then the day after we got him his epic he left the guild and tried to join some other guild that was some sort of up and coming raiding guild type thing... This was like PoP era so i guess it was velious? I don&a</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Aarkan wrote:ANYWAY! As assholish as it might be letting loot rot in front of recruits is probably t</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Aarkan wrote:ANYWAY! As assholish as it might be letting loot rot in front of recruits is probably the best in the long run.
--
I personally find it sometimes to be a case of the officers/leadership of the guild imposeing their will upon the rest of the guild.

the easiest way to kill a guild or ensure your constantly recruiting new players is to not respect those who are in your guild and playing. telling all new recruits that you dont trust the</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The sad reality is that there are people out there that you don&apos;t want in your guild. A guild t</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>The sad reality is that there are people out there that you don&apos;t want in your guild. A guild that isn&apos;t careful about its potential members is 1) naive, 2) desperate, or 3) run by those people you don&apos;t want in your guild. Sometimes all three. The first thing I look for in a guild is that they have a process for vetting new members--including me.

Remember the Grouch Marx quote: &quot;I would not join any club that would have some</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>People who are frothing in the mouth over rotting gear just don&apos;t realize how common they are. </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>People who are frothing in the mouth over rotting gear just don&apos;t realize how common they are. A hardcore full-time guild in &quot;farming&quot; mode (completed all flags, reaping the benefits) can have a turnover of 100+ raid gear dropping per week (and thats a conservative estimate). Rot item is rot item is rot item. There are rots even the alts and twinks don&apos;t want. Loot items drop like rain once the guild has gotten all the flags a</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Well, speaking as a high-raider, I don&apos;t see this huge volume of rot loot that people are talki</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Well, speaking as a high-raider, I don&apos;t see this huge volume of rot loot that people are talking about, mostly as before a zone starts getting to the stage where almost all of the loot is unwanted the guild has already moved on to higher level farming grounds.

Zones which offer next to nothing for Raiders may get visited to twink alts or to gear up an App in a useful item, (usually out of scheduled raid days) for example a BBoB for a warri</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Skuz wrote:Well, speaking as a high-raider, I don&apos;t see this huge volume of rot loot that peopl</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Skuz wrote:Well, speaking as a high-raider, I don&apos;t see this huge volume of rot loot that people are talking about, mostly as before a zone starts getting to the stage where almost all of the loot is unwanted the guild has already moved on to higher level farming grounds.
---
so the majority of high end guilds just imagined all the rotting bard only items from Demiplane huh? ;)

I beleive demiplane is a good example of a zone where items can</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>