<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Mobhunter</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description></description>
<item>
<title>Woody still manages to do a new comic every day, even when he&apos;s doing something like moving.  =</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Woody still manages to do a new comic every day, even when he&apos;s doing something like moving.  =P</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Actually, he doesn&apos;t (always). There have been a few times when the comic has been on hiatus fo</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Actually, he doesn&apos;t (always). There have been a few times when the comic has been on hiatus for a week or two for various reasons. Besides, I&apos;m quite confident Mobhunter is not a money-maker like GUComics.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Its not about the money or GU comics, but more the prinicple (customer service) of keeping your read</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Its not about the money or GU comics, but more the prinicple (customer service) of keeping your readers informed and serviced during a long stretch of absence.  It would have been easy enough to line up a one or two guest writers to put an article or two together that engages the reader to think about the game in the non-traditional sense.

I&apos;m more concerned that Loral no longer has his heart in it, and I can&apos;t blame him after all thes</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I kind of agree with you Tharkins, but I did laugh a bit when you mentioned &quot;customer service.&</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I kind of agree with you Tharkins, but I did laugh a bit when you mentioned &quot;customer service.&quot; Don&apos;t you have to pay money to be a customer?

I don&apos;t even see any advertising (unless AdBlock is nailing it--gotta love AdBlock) so I presume no one&apos;s making any money off this site at all. Thus Loral&apos;s under no obligation to anyone to do anything. Yes, it&apos;s been on my mind to take Mobhunter off my lists of sites I </description>
</item>
<item>
<title><![CDATA[I for one loved the difficulty level of EQ in the Kunark days, and long for it to come back</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description><![CDATA[I for one loved the difficulty level of EQ in the Kunark days, and long for it to come back.

You lvl 75, 200+ AA raid types only care about getting from one raid site to another to collect the next loot drop. Adventure and exploration don't have a lot of meaning to you it seems. (judging by how I see RP'ers gettting flamed as noobs on a regular basis, I think this is a fairly accurate assesment.

Your rush to the high levels and AAs and</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>&quot;Bottom line for me, this site is losing its customer base&quot;

May I see your statistics ple</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>&quot;Bottom line for me, this site is losing its customer base&quot;

May I see your statistics please?

I actually pay money to keep Mobhunter going. I refuse to have any advertisement on the site (spam messages get through sometimes but I try to kill them as fast as I see them).

My heart is still into Everquest. I love this game. Unfortunately, the last expansion didn&apos;t give me much to do beyond the initial quests in Arcstone and Relic a</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Teremar - we&apos;re not paying customers in the sense of dollars but IMO we pay with our loyalty an</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Teremar - we&apos;re not paying customers in the sense of dollars but IMO we pay with our loyalty and our time as avid readers of the work here.  Some of us have been with this site as frequent visitors for a long time, way before Loral took over the site, that should represent something.

When the stuff is good we spread the word to other fans/friends, but when its bad or not existent.....well, we don&apos;t or voice our opinions or visit the si</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Just out of curiosity, I checked the webstats for the site. I get the same number of hits now (both </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Just out of curiosity, I checked the webstats for the site. I get the same number of hits now (both raw hits and unique visits) than I did throughout all of April and May.

Your main point, that I&apos;ve been slacking on articles, is just. The idea that I am losing customers is flawed on quite a few levels. Ironically enough, less readers would actually save me money =)

Well, since I obviously have enough time right now to sit and respond to po</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I think the combine server will tear another rift in eq. after the hype is worn off and people see i</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I think the combine server will tear another rift in eq. after the hype is worn off and people see it is still just the same old game its &quot;goose will be cooked&quot;. and then when the level is raised and the gap between casual and &quot;uber&quot; widens yet again in the super-ultimate-bestest gear yet feast another blow will be delt. the folks i know that still play eq do not want levels raised and do not even want another expansion releas</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Loral,

Wonderfully well written.  I especially liked your closing paragraph.

/cong.


</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Loral,

Wonderfully well written.  I especially liked your closing paragraph.

/cong.


</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>How can they have a true classic server without kicking snakes?!?!?!?!?!  </title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>How can they have a true classic server without kicking snakes?!?!?!?!?!  </description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Quote &quot;How can they have a true classic server without kicking snakes?!?!?!?!?! &quot;

Because</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Quote &quot;How can they have a true classic server without kicking snakes?!?!?!?!?! &quot;

Because the Progression server (Combine) is not a true classic server.</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I am truely disappointed that SOE spent resources on the combine server.  They claimed only a dev or</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I am truely disappointed that SOE spent resources on the combine server.  They claimed only a dev or two was working on the server.  Well I call bullshit on that.  Since the day combine Beta came up there have been 0 Developers and only maybe 1-2 QA on Test Server.  All this during the DX9.0c shift.  We had dozens and dozens of bugs that occured and were reported but went ignored and infixed due to the mass shift of resources from Test to Combine</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Will you bet your account on it?</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>Will you bet your account on it?</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>I came back for the Progression Server. For me it&apos;s not even really about the good old days per</title>
<link>http://mobhunter.com/</link>
<description>I came back for the Progression Server. For me it&apos;s not even really about the good old days per se.  I stopped playing after 6 years just after DoDh came out. After Anguish, I was all raided out and it just looked to get worse.  

Combine will give me a chance to start over, play through the expansions at an accelerated pace and yet not fall too far behind due do various time sinks in the game. By Velious, I&apos;m looking forward to NToV an</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>